<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Functional Ionic Liquids and Related Porous Materials for Gas Capture and Catalysis</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nchen5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Nanqing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Ionic liquids are a class of promising materials that show potential as electrolytes, solvents, and absorbents. Designing and synthesizing task-specific ionic liquids for specific purposes are required for the further development of this technology. We designed and synthesized a series of functionalized ionic liquids for applications such as gas absorption, electrolyte, and catalysis. Guanidine-derived ionic liquids were successfully synthesized as an extension of our group’s previous research. However, this ionic liquid showed no response towards CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. An amidine-functionalized ionic liquid was then designed. A new method, a modified Pinner reaction, was developed for the synthesis of amidines under basic conditions, side reactions were utterly avoided. An α-oximehydrazone zwitterion type ionic liquid was the ionic liquid that had an excellent activity towards CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. However, it suffers from a vital drawback that it decomposes during gas desorption process. Polymerized viologen-type ionic materials were discovered to have catalytic activities in selective oxidizing thioanisoles and benzoyl alcohols. The mechanism of this process is unclear so far. In this thesis, a non-ionic liquid project- &lt;i&gt;&quot;A Linear Crystalline Porous Organic Polymer&quot;&lt;/i&gt; is discussed. So far, none of a polymer was found to have linearity, crystallinity and porosity three properties at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4913</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6454&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4913</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6454</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:13:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13415009</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4913</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sheng Dai</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael D. Best, Robert M. Counce, Bin Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>