<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Global Perspectives on Peer Sex Education for College Students</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-14T11:00:18-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Oklahoma State University</institution>
<lname>Story</lname>
<fname>Chandra</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gorski</lname>
<fname>June</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;According to the World Health Organization, sexually transmitted diseases and infections continue to be a public health problem across the globe, with most infected persons being between the ages of 15 and 49. A large percentage of those affected by AIDS are 15-24 year olds, an age group which includes college students. Peer sex education is being espoused by non-governmental organizations and administrators as a viable solution to this problem. Peer education strategies and approaches to evaluation differ across programs. Some programs report increased efficacy for educators and trainees while other programs report increases in knowledge and changes in attitudes. Perceptions of peer education and resulting benefits vary based on cultural perspectives. Developers of peer education programs need to critically deconstruct current models and customize programs for particular settings, as demonstrated in several programs. Further research is needed on the effects of peer education on the educator and cultural implications.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol42/iss2/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1256&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1256</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-14T10:38:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>5581234</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol42/iss2/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>