<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spring City Kayak Launch &amp; Amenities Design Project</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:53:49-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>khz587@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Adcock</lname>
<fname>Sydney Lin</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Exemplar Engineering was requested by SETDD to perform engineering calculations and prepare contract documents in order to improve the infrastructure in Spring City, Tennessee. The SETDD has been working with Spring City in an effort to construct a public access area on a 30-acre peninsula on Watts Bar Lake. Exemplar will be responsible for designing a small park area for the town of Spring City. The construction of this park area will be separated into different phases that coincide with funding. These phases include designing and constructing underground piping and utility work, a small restroom facility, a pavilion structure, an access road and sidewalk, a greenway, and an EZ launch. The EZ launch is designed to hold small watercraft items such as kayaks, paddleboards, and canoes in order to promote lake tourism in Spring City. The phasing of this small park project included design and analysis calculations from the Civil Engineering disciplines including, geotechnical engineering, structural engineering, water resources and environmental engineering, construction engineering, and site civil engineering. The city officials of Spring City are hopeful that this project will bring tourism to their city and boost the economy since the current population is less than 2,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/engineering/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1141&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1141</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-17T18:28:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10030752</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/engineering/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Jenny Retherford</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>