<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>University of Tennessee Library Lectures, 1958-1960 (no. 10-12)</title>
<publication-date>1961-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>AR.0281</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;On April 17, 1958, Dr. Benjamin Edward Powell, Librarian of Duke University, in the tenth lecture of the series discussed Sources of Support for Libraries in American Universities. To his audience that evening and to the readers of this volume, Dr. Powell has given ample evidence of his knowledge and research of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Louis Shores, Dean of the Library School at Florida State University, was invited to deliver the eleventh lecture on April 15, 1959. The choice of his subject, The Undergraduate and His Library, and the timeliness of presentation were particularly fitting since The University of Tennessee Undergraduate Library was to be opened at the beginning of the 1959 fall quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Archie L. McNeal, Director of Libraries at the University of Miami, Coral Gables, Florida, and a member of The University of Tennessee Library Staff at the initiation of this series of lectures in the spring of 1949, was guest speaker on April 29, 1960. With characteristic ability, Dr. McNeal investigated the subject, Divisional Organization in the University Library.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libarcutlect/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;amp;context=utk_libarcutlect&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-25T07:57:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>University of Tennessee Library Lecture Series</publication-title>
<context-key>1171079</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libarcutlect/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>