<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Demography, Long Bone Growth, and Pathology of a Middle Archaic Skeletal Population From Middle Tennessee: The Anderson Site (40WM9)</title>
<publication-date>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Joerschke</lname>
<fname>Bonnie</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A biological examination of the skeletal remains from the Anderson site, 40WM9, Williamson County, Tennessee, was conducted to provide information about the nature of Middle Archaic populations from Middle Tennessee. Vital statistics were reconstructed by means of a life table assuming stable population conditions. Results of this analysis indicate a pattern of low infant/child mortality and high adult mortality. Life expectancy at birth was 23 years and the crude death rate was 43 per 1000 per annum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The health status of the Anderson population was further inferred through investigations of long bone growth and bone pathologies. The long bone growth rates of the Anderson children were evaluated by the regression model: bone length = b&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; + b&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; (age) + B&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (log&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;age). Comparison of the Anderson growth rates with those of the Arikara children revealed similar rates of growth between 0.5 and 11.9 years. Comparison of adult femur length indicated that the Anderson males were the same size as males from other skeletal populations regardless of time period, geographical location, or subsistence pattern differences. Anderson females displayed the same pattern except their mean femur length was significantly smaller than that of females from Late Mississippian populations in Tennessee. This pattern contradicts the theory that stature decreased with a shift to maize agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pathology data indicated that the most common problems which affected the Anderson people were degenerative arthritis, dental diseases, and fractures. In general, these conditions became more frequent with increasing age. Males were more frequently affected by degenerative arthritis and fractures than females.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence from this study provides complementary biological information for current archaeological research in the human ecology of the Middle Archaic period in Middle Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3961</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5448&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3961</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5448</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-14T11:47:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9120431</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3961</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Jantz, Charles H. Faulkner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>