<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Differences in Scores on Measures of Work Satsifaction, Parenting Satisfaction, Family/Work Roles Conflict and Marital Conflict Between Dual-Earner Husbands and Wives</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parrott</lname>
<fname>Michelle</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Human Resources Management</discipline>
<discipline>Training and Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Dual-earned husband and wives, the most common family style in the United States, attempt to maintain healthy relationships as they juggle work and family roles. This study examined dual-career husbands and wives on the measures of work satisfaction, parenting satisfaction, family/work roles conflict and marital conflict to determine if differences existed between the husbands and wives. The findings indicated that dual-earner husbands and wives in this sample reported remarkably similar scores on the measures of work satisfaction, parenting satisfaction, family/work roles conflict, and marital conflict. These husbands and wives were very satisfied with their jobs and their parenting skills and reported low levels of conflict in their marriages. The husbands and wives in this sample were married for over 20 years, were middle-aged and held fairly traditional beliefs and attitudes about husbands’ and wives’ roles in the family.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4807</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6299&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4807</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6299</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-18T12:25:00-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10625709</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4807</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sharon Jeffcoat Bartley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Priscilla Blanton, Lane Morris, Vicki Stout</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>