<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Survey of Gaps, Obstacles, and Technical Challenges for Hypersonic Applications</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tbarber@utsi.edu</email>
<lname>Barber</lname>
<fname>Timothy Andrew</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>hypersonic</keyword>
<keyword>high speed flow</keyword>
<keyword>propulsion</keyword>
<keyword>aerodynamics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerodynamics and Fluid Mechanics</discipline>
<discipline>Aeronautical Vehicles</discipline>
<discipline>Propulsion and Power</discipline>
<discipline>Space Vehicles</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The object of this study is to canvas the literature for the purpose of identifying and compiling a list of Gaps, Obstacles, and Technological Challenges in Hypersonic Applications (GOTCHA).  The significance of GOTCHA related deficiencies is discussed along with potential solutions, promising approaches, and feasible remedies that may be considered by engineers in pursuit of next generation hypersonic vehicle designs and optimizations.  Based on the synthesis of several modern surveys and public reports, a cohesive list is formed, consisting of widely accepted areas needing improvement and falling under several general categories.  These include: aerodynamics, propulsion, materials, analytical modeling, CFD modeling, and education in high speed flow physics.  New methods and lines of research inquiries are suggested such as the homotopy-based analysis (HAM) for the treatment of strong nonlinearities, the use of improved turbulence models and unstructured grids in numerical simulations, the need for accessible validation data, and the refinement of mission objectives for Hypersonic Air-Breathing Propulsion (HABP).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1131</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2315&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1131</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2315</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-22T20:58:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2693748</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1131</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jospeh Majdalani</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Basil Antar, Trevor Moeller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aerospace Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>