<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Changing Subsistence Strategies on the Degree of Sexual Dimorphism of Skeletons from the Southeastern United States</title>
<publication-date>1993-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grant</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examines the effects of changing subsistence strategies on the degree of sexual dimorphism for prehistoric skeletal populations from the Southeastern United States. Changes in subsistence from hunting and gathering in the Archaic Period to intensive agriculture in the Mississippian Period caused increased levels of stress that affected growth and development, as well as incidence of disease. Eight long bone measurements were taken from 17 skeletal series (6 Middle/Late Archaic, 8 Early/Middle Woodland, and 3 Late Mississippian) from Tennessee and Alabama. These measurements were subjected to a series of univariate and multivariate statistical tests to determine whether or not significant size- and shape-related changes in sexual dimorphism exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of these tests indicate that there is a decrease in size-related sexual dimorphism for Mississippian agriculturalists. This is believed to be the result of increased nutritional and disease-related stress. There is also an increase in shape-related sexual dimorphism for this group. A trend for increased size over time also exists for males and females, although Woodland Period males are slightly larger than Mississippian males. These increases are both thought to be caused by heavier workloads associated with intensive maize agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4125</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5575&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4125</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5575</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-17T12:48:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9275482</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4125</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Walter E. Klippel, Richard Jantz, Lyle W. Konigsberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1993-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1993-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>