<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A crusade for morality : status politics and Internet filtering legislation</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Plaksin</lname>
<fname>Sueanne</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis demonstrates that particular interest groups supporting the limiting and restricting of patron access on Internet tenninals in public libraries is motivated by a desire to maintain their dominant cultural hegemony. These groups, identified in this work as &quot;Crusaders&quot; are seeking to pass federal legislation that would require that public libraries install Internet filtering software on public terminals or forfeit federal funding provided through the e-rate subsidy. The importance of such a law is not its instrumental value, but its symbolic value. The sociological theory known as status politics supplies the theoretical basis for this thesis. Briefly, status politics argues that laws serve a symbolic function in society. The laws of a society not only apply order to human behavior, but also reflect the values and beliefs of societal culture. Those who have the power to establish laws also have the power to impose their ideological beliefs and values on the general public. Those who have legislative power see their status and prestige reflected in the laws they establish. By applying Kenneth Burke&#39;s five elements of dramaturgical analysis to Crusader testimony given in the Communications Decency Act of 1996, the Child Online Protection Act of 1998, and the Children&#39;s Internet Protection Act of 1999, the strategies employed on the part of Crusaders to pass such legislation are revealed. This analysis shows the techniques employed by the Crusaders to convince their audience that Internet filtering laws must be established. This thesis shows that Crusader attempts to pass Internet filtering legislation is an example of status politics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5975</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7608&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5975</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7608</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467637</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5975</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Nevin Douglas Raber</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Information Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>