<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using Meisenbach&#39;s Typology to Classify Stigma Management Strategies and their Effects</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:56:29-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>llombino@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lombino</lname>
<fname>Lia Marjorie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jshapir7@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Shapiro</lname>
<fname>Jamie</fname>
<mname>Eden</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Interpersonal and Small Group Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Jamie Shapiro &amp; Lia Lombino&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certain traits people possess that lead to stigmatization and mistreatment by others. A stigma is traditionally defined as an identity discrediting mark on someone of questionable moral status (Goffman, 1963). Despite extensive research on stigma, there is an absence of research that studies the role of communication in stigma and the impact of utilizing different communicative strategies when managing stigma. The purpose of the current study is to validate Meisenbach’s (2010) typology of stigma management communication, which is based on accepting or challenging personal and private stigma. Meisenbach proposes four different stigma management strategies: accepting the stigma, evading/reducing the offensiveness of the stigmatized trait, avoiding, and rejecting the stigma. The study also extends Meisenbach’s (2010) typology by determining the lasting effects of stigma management strategies, by investigating whether stigma management strategies correspond with people feeling better or worse following a supportive conversation. Participants (N = 203) engaged in supportive conversations about a stigmatized trait with a confederate. Two coders analyzed the conversations to determine the category of typology used. The results of this study support Meisenbach’s (2010) theory and provide practical implications, such as suggestions for identity management for someone coping with a stigmatized trait.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/communicationinformation/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1161&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1161</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-12T09:29:47-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1161/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11951343</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/communicationinformation/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Jenny L. Crowley</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>