<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mode I Fracture Behavior of Bisphenol-A Epoxy Resin</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T09:58:26-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gmcgloth@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McGlothin</lname>
<fname>Gillian Suzanne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As part of a research initiative funded by the US Navy, the Computational Mechanics and Structures group at UT is working to increase its understanding of the behaviors of composite patches that are currently being used in ship and plane repair. These composite patches are comprised of a metal base layer and a more flexible resin layer (whose purpose is to allow the patch to conform to the contours of the repaired body). By studying how the resin behaves independently of the metal, we can better understand how to properly adhere the resin to the metal and create a durable and effective repair patch for the Navy’s use. This research project specifically serves to analyze how resin samples react when subjected to a 3-point bend test. Understanding the fracture behaviors of these pieces is crucial in understanding the larger behaviors of the composite patches. The resin samples will be created by pouring liquid resin into a specially made mold, leveling off the mold for a smooth surface, water-jetting the individual samples, and cutting a notch to initiate the crack growth in each piece. Each piece will then individually be tested using a 3-point bend method and observed and analyzed for fracture behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/engineering/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1147&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1147</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-18T17:59:02-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1147/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10038785</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/engineering/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical, Aerospace, and Biomedical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Stephanie TerMaath</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>