<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Problem A: Characteristics of Marshall County Beef Producers and Their Farms; Problem B: Management Practices of Marshall County Beef Producers; Problem C: Factors Influencing Beef Management Practice Adoption by Marshall County Beef Producers</title>
<publication-date>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Brewer</lname>
<fname>Lester</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;PROBLEM A: CHARACTERISTICS OF MARSHALL COUNTY BEEF PRODUCERS AND THEIR FARMS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study was made in Marshall County, Tennessee, to determine the characteristics of Marshall County Beef producers and their farms. The study was based on a survey-type interview and reflects information for developing a county plan of action. The producers were classified into low, medium, and high groups, depending on the number of pounds of beef sold per cow in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A close analysis indicates that cattlemen interviewed in Marshall County had the following characteristics: (1) 60 percent were considered friendly toward the survey; (2) 58 percent were full-time farmers; (3) 48 percent indicated that beef was their major source of income; (4) the average educational level was 12 years; (5) over one-half were in the 45-54 age group; (6) more than one-half owned Angus cattle, and (7) the average total acreage per farm was 139.7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the high and low producers, it was found that the average high producer: (1) had 1.7 more formal years of education; (2) owned 79.9 more acres of land; (3) kept 11 more beef cows, and (4) marketed 11.6 more calves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implications were drawn from the findings concerning their relevance for the Marshall County Agricultural Extension Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PROBLEM B: MANAGEMENT PRACTICES OF MARSHALL COUNTY BEEF PRODUCERS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this Marshall County survey was to determine which recommended beef production practices were being used by cattlemen in the county. Forty beef producers were interviewed at random and comparative analyses made in reference to pounds of beef sold in 1970 per cow bred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average management ratings for all practices were computed so that further comparisons could be made. The ratings were given to each cattleman on each of 31 management practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A close analysis indicated the following regarding management practices: (1) 20 percent of the high producers kept replacement heifers, while the low producers did not keep any (2) 20 percent of the high producers had increased herd size over the previous year as compared to 10 percent for the low producers, and (3) the management level averaged by the high producers was considerably above that of the low producers. More high producers were &quot;using&quot; other recommended practices, including: (1) waiting until replacement heifers were at least 15 months of age before breeding; (2) using a systematic rotational grazing program; (3) using recommended fly control practices; and (4) using recommended procedures in castration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other comparisons showed that high producers were doing a better job than low in: (1) keeping bulls whose records met minimum requirement of the breeder&#39;s performance tested bull sale; (2) using one or more performance tested bulls; and (3) checking frequently first calf heifers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cattlemen had an average weaning percent per female bred of 88 percent; high producers reporting 86 percent; medium, 95 percent; and low, 83 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other implications from the study were drawn and educational use of the data was recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PROBLEM C: FACTORS INFLUENCING BEEF MANAGEMENT PRACTICE ADOPTION BY MARSHALL COUNTY BEEF PRODUCERS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to identify some factors influencing beef producers of Marshall County to adopt recommended practices. The forty randomly selected beef producers were interviewed and divided into high, medium, and low production groups according to pounds of beef sold in 1970, per cow bred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the things liked most about beef cattle production, the joy of watching cattle grow and the relatively low labor requirement per unit were most often mentioned. Other reasons given were: (1) the efficient use of available pasture, and (2) the relatively good return on investment. The most often mentioned dislike was the relatively slow turnover of money invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all persons from whom advice was sought, County Agents, cattle buyers and local veterinarians were most often used. Eighty-seven percent of the high producers listed County Agents as their main source of information, as compared to 60 percent for the low producers. Among other sources, farm magazines and The University of Tennessee bulletins or publications also were mentioned frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings, together with those from the two related studies, indicate a basis for development of a useful educational plan for cow-calf producers in Marshall County, Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4360</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5806&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4360</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5806</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-24T07:06:52-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9742802</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4360</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Horace C. Smith, Haley M. Jamison, Cecil E. Carter, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Problem submitted in lieu of thesis&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>