<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Influence of prednisolone on urinary calcium oxalate and struvite relative supersaturation in healthy young adult female domestic shorthaired cats</title>
<publication-date>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Geyer</lname>
<fname>N</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bartges</lname>
<fname>Joe</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Kirk</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Prednisolone (10 mg PO q24h) or placebo was administered to healthy cats for 2 weeks in a masked, placebo-controlled, crossover-design study, and 24-hour urine samples were collected. When cats received prednisolone, 24-hour urine pH was lower and 24-hour urine excretion of creatinine, magnesium, phosphate, and potassium was higher than when cats received placebo. No significant difference was found in urinary relative supersaturation for calcium oxalate (CaOx) or struvite between treatment groups. Prednisolone administration did not induce diuresis, nor was it associated with increased calcium excretion or urinary saturation for CaOx in these healthy cats. Results of this study, however, should not be extrapolated to cats that form CaOx uroliths associated with idiopathic hypercalcemia.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_smalpubs/7</coverpage-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1006</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T11:30:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Small Animal Clinical Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1284874</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_smalpubs/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>N Geyer, Joe Bartges, C A. Kirk, S Cox, A Hezel, T Moyers, and J Hayes. &quot;Influence of prednisolone on urinary calcium oxalate and struvite relative supersaturation in healthy young adult female domestic shorthaired cats&quot; Veterinary Therapeutics 8.4 (2007): 239-246.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18183542</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Veterinary Therapeutics</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>