<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Relationships on ANS function and Wellness</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-09T11:56:04-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>omaples@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Maples</lname>
<fname>Olivia M</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biological Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Cognitive Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Health Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Quantitative Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The quality of relationships and social networks plays a vital role on well-being (Feeney &amp; Collins, 2015). Social support is linked to positive biological profiles in that social support protects against the negative effects of changes in cardiovascular, neuroendocrine, and immune function. Furthermore, when exploring Autonomic Nervous System (ANS) function, higher heart rate variability has been shown to reflect a psychophysiological state compatible with social interaction (Quintana, Guastella, Outhred, Hickie, &amp; Kemp, 2012). Social support has been shown to buffer against the negative effects of life stressors (Cohen &amp; Wills, 1985), and ultimately, mortality (Holt-Lunstad, Smith, &amp; Layton, 2010). In summary, social relationships are important for both health and well-being (see review: Cohen, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, social isolation, social disconnectedness, and loneliness have been shown to have negative effects on health (Cornwell &amp; Waite, 2009) as individuals who are socially isolated display not only psychological, but also, physical consequences such as: increased risk of inflammation and hypertension (Yang et al., 2016) and greater vascular resistance, slower wound healing, and poorer sleep efficiency (Cacioppo &amp; Hawkley, 2003). In a neuroimaging study examining the effects of social exclusion on health, results show that “social pain is analogous in its neurocognitive function to physical pain” (Eisenberger, Lieberman, &amp; Williams, 2003, pp. 292).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In college students, females report more stress from romantic relationships, relationships with their parents, and quality of peer relationships when compared to their male counterparts (Darling, McWey, Howard, &amp; Olmstead, 2007). Concordantly, aspects of social well-being (i.e. need to belong) tend to have greater negative impacts on college-aged females when compared to males (Baldwin, Towler, Oliver, &amp; Datta, 2017). Moreover, the quality of such relationships have both psychological (Umberson &amp; Montez, 2010), as well as physiological (Heaphy &amp; Dutton, 2008) ramifications on health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to better understand the health and well-being of an individual, one should consider his/her relationship qualities and characteristics. Although much is known about the positive and negative consequences that relationships have on individual health such as: research is lacking regarding its connection between ANS function and domains of wellness (i.e. physical, social, emotional, spiritual, psychological, intellectual). It is critical to examine the effects of both quantity and extent of relationships in conjunction with health and wellness to truly understand the effects that relationships have on quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1221&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1221</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-09T19:45:31-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1221/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>13451460</context-key>
<withdrawn>2019-04-09</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Deborah Baldwin</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>John C. Hodges Library</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>