<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1762-The Growing Hispanic Population in Tennessee - A Potential Market Opportunity for Farmers and</title>
<publication-date>2006-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Value-Added Agriculture</keyword>
<keyword>Marketing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Marketing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Tennessee farmers are motivated by current economic trends in the farm sector to seek out valueadded and direct marketing opportunities. Niche markets, including marketing to ethnic populations, are often attractive to those seeking new market opportunities. The growing Hispanic population in the state has led some to question the market potential of this audience in Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication contains information relevant to Tennessee farmers and agri-entrepreneurs who are considering developing products and marketing to Hispanics. It provides general market research data and information important to understanding demand components, including geographic areas where potential demand may exist, the ability of the target audience to purchase products and the willingness of Hispanics to purchase products based on tastes and preferences. Results of interviews with owners and managers of retail stores marketing to Hispanic consumers are also included. Although much of the information contained in the publication is available through secondary data sources, the information has not been available in a single, affordable resource before now.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexmkt/24</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1023&amp;amp;context=utk_agexmkt&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>valueag</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-06T13:29:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Marketing, Finances and Value-Added Agriculture</publication-title>
<context-key>1263611</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexmkt/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>06-0214 PB1762-500-6/06 R12-4010-020-001-06</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>