<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Acknowledging the Horse: Ethical Considerations in Equine-Assisted Therapy</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>obrien74@msu.edu</email>
<institution>Michigan State University</institution>
<lname>O&#39;Brien</lname>
<fname>Kelly</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Social Work</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Professional Association of Therapeutic Horsemanship International (PATH Int&#39;l) and Equine Assisted Growth and Learning Association (EAGALA) are the sole entities for governing the ethical standards. However, the NASW has yet to consider ethical guidelines for equine-assisted therapy (EAT). The application of these sole EAT standards relies upon the interpretation of the association&#39;s specialists. As of yet the equine-human bond has not been greatly explored (Yorke, 2003). The horse, a highly sensitive prey animal, does not provide the unconditional acceptance of companion animals such as dogs or cats. A participant-horse relationship must foster mutual care and respect (Siporin, 2012).Thus, the requirements of the equine participants must be considered as contributing to the equine-assisted therapy session, as opposed to the horse being considered as a corollary to the therapeutic process. If the emotional, physical, and safety needs of the equine are not considered in the therapeutic setting, the positive impact of the therapy may be minimized. Using case studies and participant observation as a PATH Int&#39;l registered instructor, I examine ethical dilemmas in the setting and their unfortunate consequences in EAT practice. By examining the ethical dilemmas of using equines in therapeutic practice, we can begin to develop ethical guidelines that consider the welfare of the equine in a therapeutic setting; including the correlation and division between the NASW Code of Ethics and the stated codes of ethics of the two well-known governing bodies of equine-assisted therapy: PATH Int&#39;l and EAGALA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siporin, S. (2012). Talking horses: Equine psychotherapy and intersubjectivity. &lt;em&gt;Psychodynamic Practice, 18&lt;/em&gt;(4), 457-464.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yorke, J. (2003),&quot;The therapeutic value of the equine-human relationship in recovery from trauma: A qualitative analysis.&lt;em&gt; Theses and Dissertations (Comprehensive). &lt;/em&gt;Retrieved from: http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/168&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/23</coverpage-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1032</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-10-24T16:45:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3423706</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Kelly is a second year graduate student in Social Work and Animal Studies. Her principal research interests are the use and welfare of equines in a therapeutic setting. As a certified instructor through the Professional Association of Therapeutic Horsemanship International (PATH Int’l), she managed and trained horses at a PATH Premier Accredited Center in Nashville, TN for 3.5 years before returning to Michigan State University to pursue higher education.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Kelly O&#39;Brien&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1222 Oak Ridge Ave&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;East Lansing, MI 48823&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(231) 342-2534&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T18:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Poster: Scheduled poster session</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Ethical dilemmas in social work and animals</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>