<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Incorporating Redispersal Microsites into Myrmecochory in Eastern North American Forests</title>
<publication-date>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Kansas State University</institution>
<lname>Connell</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
<mname>Kent</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pfennigwerth</lname>
<fname>Alix</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Classen</lname>
<fname>Aimee</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kwit</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>ant seed dispersal; Aphaenogaster; directed dispersal; myrmecochore; potential enzyme activity; seed germination; soil microbes.</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Studies addressing the benefits of “directed dispersal” in ant seed dispersal systems have highlighted the beneficial soil properties of the nests of ants that disperse their seeds. No studies, however, have explored the properties of soils nearby exemplary seed-dispersing ant nests, where recent work indicates that seeds are quickly “redispersed” in eastern North America. To address this, we focused on a forested ecosystem in eastern United States where a keystone seed-dispersing ant, Aphaenogaster rudis, commonly disperses the seeds of numerous understory herbs, including Jeffersonia diphylla. We collected soil cores beneath J. diphylla, around A. rudis nests where seeds are dispersed, and from other forest locations. We analyzed the collected soils for microbial activity using potential soil enzyme activity as a proxy, as well as a number of environmental parameters. We followed this with a glasshouse experiment testing whether the soils collected from near nests, beneath J. diphylla, and from other forested areas altered seedling emergence. We found that microbial activities were higher in near-nest microsites than elsewhere. Specifically, the potential enzyme activities of a carbon-degrading enzyme (β-glucosidase), a phosphorus-acquiring enzyme (phosphatase), and a sulfur-acquiring enzyme (sulfatase) were all significantly higher in areas near ant nests than elsewhere; this same pattern, although not significant, was found for the nitrogen-acquiring enzyme NAGase. No differences were found in other environmental variables we investigated (e.g., soil temperature, soil moisture, soil pH). Our field results indicate that soil biological processes are significantly different in near-nest soils, where the seeds are ultimately dispersed. However, our glasshouse germination trials revealed no enhanced germination in near-nest soils, thereby refuting any near-term advantages of directed dispersal to near-nest locations. Future work should be directed toward addressing whether areas near ant nests provide biologically meaningful escape from seed predation and enhanced establishment, and further characterization of soil microbial communities in such settings.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/70</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1075&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>70</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1075</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-21T09:56:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>10461334</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/70</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Connell, R. Kent, Alix A. Pfennigwerth, Aimee T. Classen, and Charles Kwit, “Incorporating Redispersal Microsites into Myrmecochory in Eastern North American Forests,” Ecosphere 7, 9 (2016): e01456, https://doi.10.1002/ecs2.1456.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1002/ecs2.1456</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Ecosphere</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>