<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Roles of Self-Affirmation and Introspection in Correction for Automatic Prejudice</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kzabel1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Zabel</lname>
<fname>Kevin</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Prejudice</keyword>
<keyword>Bias correction</keyword>
<keyword>Motivation to control prejudice</keyword>
<keyword>Introspection</keyword>
<keyword>Self-Affirmation</keyword>
<keyword>Interracial interaction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Egalitarian-oriented Whites tend to employ the strategy of “liking everyone,” as opposed to correcting for their automatic prejudices, as a means of avoiding prejudiced reactions (Zabel &amp; Olson, 2014). Congruent with motivational theoretical perspectives regarding prejudice (i.e., Aversive Racism; Gaertner &amp; Dovidio), I contend that a lack of introspection into one’s automatic prejudices due to a self-image threat may be driving this tendency. In the experiment I report here, I assessed the automatic racial attitudes of egalitarian- (high Concern) and conflict avoidance-motivated (high Restraint) Whites. Then, participants were randomly assigned to introspect (or not) on their automatic racial biases, as well as to self-affirm (or not) using a values importance task. Following, participants completed an impression formation task in which they rated Black and White targets. Results indicated that egalitarian-oriented (high Concern) individuals with pro-White automatically-activated attitudes corrected for their prejudices by providing greater pro-Black trait ratings when self-affirmation preceded racial attitude introspection. This pattern of prejudice correction did not occur among high Concern participants who introspected on their racial attitudes prior to being self-affirmed, or did not introspect or self-affirm at all. Findings are congruent with previous research attesting to the utility of self-affirmation in increasing attention to otherwise self-threatening information, and provide insights as to how the strategies employed by aversive racists and their negative implications may be reduced.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3624</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5030&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3624</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5030</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-09T12:10:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7701360</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3624</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael A. Olson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lowell A. Gaertner, Garriy Shteynberg, Victor E. Ray</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Experimental Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>