<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pictorial Inscriptions</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:52:41-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jwinfiel@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Winfiele</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
<mname>w</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>egowder@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gowder</lname>
<fname>Emily</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;PICTORIAL INSCRIPTIONS is an exploration into the nature of paint graffiti and street art and its contribution to the character of the city. Art has been used as a prevalent and effective means of communicating ideas throughout human existence. As it has evolved to present day, street art has become a way to display ideas that people are passionate about, voice opinions on social and economic events or even as a canvas that pop culture has extended onto. These displays can reflect the pride, hate, love, frustration or joy that the artists have in their work. It can voice the excitement the citizens have for their city, personal passions or even display new ideas boldly in a large confrontational format. These types of street art can be found in spaces that are defined as primary, secondary and tertiary spaces. In research, it was found that the genre of content may depend on the location of the piece and whether it was a preemptively desired result. No matter the level of acceptance or permanence, street art has become an intriguing and prevalent display in each city that can serve as a meaningful legacy to the artist.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/architecturedesign/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1138&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1138</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-17T08:43:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10027646</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/architecturedesign/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Architecture and Desgin</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>A. Katherine Bambrick Ambroziak</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>