<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Personnel Training and Employment Needs of Hospital Food Services in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1969-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peay</lname>
<fname>Moiselle</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Personnel training and employment needs in 25 selected Tennessee hospitals were studied. Information from this pilot research will be used to develop methods and procedures for conducting similar studies of the food service industry in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following a preliminary survey by mail to identify the sample desired, personal interviews were scheduled with the hospital administrator and the food service manager in each of the selected hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six major categories of personnel were studied: (1) managerial, (2) supervisory, (3) clerical, (4) food preparation workers, (5) food service workers, and (6) food sanitation workers. For each category, food service managers indicated their opinion regarding the importance of selected areas of skills and knowledge assumed to be needed by personnel. Training conducted by the hospital and the responsibility for training also was indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Included in the areas of training mentioned as important most often by managers were communications and human relations for all job classifications other than food preparation and sanitation workers. For managerial personnel, management principles, human nutrition and food science, menu planning and personnel administration were considered most important. For supervisory personnel, managers agreed on the importance of principles of quantity food preparation and service, nutrition and diet therapy, sanitary and safety standards and use and care of equipment. For clerical personnel, managers indicated as most important food inventory control, stock room operation and food storage. Managers stressed the importance of quantity food preparation and service for regular and modified diets, use of standardized recipes, quality food standards, menu terminology and use and care of equipment for food preparation workers; food display and service for food service workers; and for food sanitation workers, safety and use and care of equipment. Sanitation and personal hygiene was considered important for food preparation, food service and food sanitation worker job categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little training for managerial personnel was done by hospitals. A greater number of hospitals reported training for supervisory personnel than for managerial. Training mentioned for clerical workers was limited to those areas directly concerned with food service activities. As the skill and training level decreased, more training programs were reported by hospitals, with widespread training being conducted for food preparation, food service and food sanitation personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hospitals generally considered training for managerial personnel the responsibility of an agency other than the hospital. For the majority of the remaining areas, managers indicated that training for food service personnel should be shared between the hospital and an outside agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information from the pilot study had implications for further study of food service personnel training programs. Recommendations for procedures in further studies were made.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3962</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5447&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3962</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5447</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-14T10:29:21-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9119729</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3962</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Jo Hitchcock</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Grayce E. Goertz, Douglas C. Towne</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1969-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1969-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>