<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Synthetic Turf Systems With and Without a Shock Pad on Lower Extremity Biomechanics During a 90° Cutting Movement With Differing Approach Velocities</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>telvidge@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Elvidge</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Kenneth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>biomechanics</keyword>
<keyword>cutting</keyword>
<keyword>turf</keyword>
<keyword>shock pad</keyword>
<keyword>approach speed</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biomechanics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine differences in lower extremity kinematics and kinetics on two different synthetic turf systems (turf only and turf with a shock pad) for two approach velocities (3.0 and 4.0 m/s) during a 90° cutting movement. Twelve recreational male American football and soccer players were recruited to perform five trials for each of the four conditions. A three-dimensional motion analysis system synchronized to a force platform was used to collect marker coordinate and ground reaction force (GRF) data respectively. A 2 x 2 (surface x approach velocity) ANOVA was used to analyze kinematic and kinetic variables. Across surface conditions, there was a general lack of significant differences. While there was a lack of differences for kinematics and kinetics, there might have been increased co-contractions to stabilize the lower extremity with the increased deformation on the shock pad condition, which was undetectable via the inverse dynamics. However, knee frontal-plane peak loading eccentric power was found to be greater on the shock pad condition (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.013) while knee frontal-plane peak push-off eccentric power was reduced on the shock pad condition (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.020). A surface x approach velocity interaction was detected for knee sagittal-plane peak eccentric power (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.018). Post-hoc analysis found a significant difference for approach velocity on the turf only condition. As the protocol dictated a change in performance, the largest changes were seen in peak hip extension (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.007) and knee extension (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.004) moments, suggesting that these were the major factors for determining the performance improvement. There were also increases in ankle eversion moment (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.001) and ankle inversion ROM (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.001) as approach velocity increased. These increases potentially suggest that the risk of a lateral ankle sprain injury increases as approach velocity increases. As approach velocity increased, it was found that peak push-off vertical GRF decreased (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.011) as peak push-off medial GRF increased (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.025). This suggests that as approach velocity increases, medial forces become more important than vertical forces during the push-off phase.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4738</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5767&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4738</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5767</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-21T15:08:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9726243</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4738</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Songning Zhang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Joshua T. Weinhandl, John C. Sorochan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>