<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A History of the Development of the University of Tennessee, Martin Branch</title>
<publication-date>1960-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Inman</lname>
<fname>Elmer</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The University of Tennessee, Martin Branch, has developed through four distinct states in response to educational needs in upper West Tennessee. The State failed to support education adequately and other groups organized schools in response to this failure to meet the need in education. The local Baptist Association organized and supported Hall-Moody Institute in response to this need, and the school continued to operate until 1927, when the college was consolidated with Union University at Jackson, Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time that the Junior College was established at Martin, local citizen support was strong in the General Assembly. In fact, the support was strong enough that Dr. Andrew D. Holt, in his study conducted at Columbia University, credited the combined efforts of three groups--the Martin group, the Clarksville group, and the educational forces--with the success of three aspects of educational legislation. A junior college was established at Martin; a college was established at Clarksville; and the passage of favorable school legislation was accomplished. The timing of establishment was good since a physical plant and equipment were available for immediate use by the State of Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennessee Junior College, the official title given to the newly established junior college at Martin, replaced Hall-Moody Junior College and took possession of all property, including land, buildings, and equipment, that had been owned by the former school. The development of Hall-Moody, because of its location, is an integral part of the sequence of events in the development of the Junior College and the Martin Branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predictions based upon surveys and population estimates and trends indicate that present facilities and institutions of higher education are insufficient to provide the education needs of the future. The General Assembly of the State of Tennessee has already passed legislation providing for the limitation of enrollment in State colleges of Tennessee. It is appropriate at this time an analysis of the University of Tennessee, Martin Branch, development be made. The development pattern of the past may indicate steps that need to be taken at the present time and in the future to provide adequate higher education for citizens of upper West Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2925</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4373&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2925</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4373</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-09T08:21:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6221571</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2925</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>W. W. Wyatt</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Earl M. Ramer, John W. Gilliland, Lillian W. Stimson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1960-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1960-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>