<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>“I was born full deaf.” Written language outcomes after one year of Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI)</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kwolbers@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wolbers</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Connecticut - Storrs</institution>
<lname>Dostal</lname>
<fname>Hannah</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Bowers</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>deaf education</keyword>
<keyword>deaf and hard of hearing</keyword>
<keyword>writing</keyword>
<keyword>writing instruction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nonstandard grammatical forms are often present in the writing of deaf students which are rarely, if ever, seen in the writing of hearing students. With the implementation of Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI) in previous studies, students have demonstrated significant gains in high-level writing skills (e.g., text structure) but have also made gains with English grammar skills. This one-year study expands on prior research by longitudinally examining the written language growth (i.e., writing length, sentence complexity, sentence awareness and function words) of 29 deaf middle school students. A repeated-measures ANOVA with a between-subjects variable for literacy achievement level was used to examine gains over time and the intervention’s efficacy when used with students of various literacy levels. Students, whether high- or lowachieving, demonstrated statistically significant gains with writing length, sentence complexity and sentence awareness. Subordinate clauses were found to be an area of difficulty, and follow up strategies are suggested. An analysis of function word data, specifically prepositions and articles, revealed different patterns of written language growth by language group (e.g., ASL users, oral students, users of English-based sign).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_theopubs/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1011&amp;amp;context=utk_theopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-05-30T05:15:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Theory and Practice in Teacher Education Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>8663231</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_theopubs/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Wolbers, K., Dostal, H. &amp; Bowers, L. (2012).  “I was born full deaf.” Written language outcomes after one year of Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI). Journal of Deaf Studies and Deaf Education, 17(1), 19-38. doi:10.1093/deafed/enr018.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1093/deafed/enr018</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>