<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Urban Schools: Creating Diverse Populations and Vibrant Cities</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jcastor@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Castor</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey Michael</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A lack of public education in downtown areas is causing a lack of diversity in urban populations. Because families with young children perceive that they must retreat to the suburbs for quality public schooling, downtown populations are largely limited to young professionals and empty nesters. Inviting families with children to the city through the provision of quality public education will improve cities economically and socially. The economic improvement comes simply through number of residents and increased tax revenues. The social benefits are increased safety, vibrancy, stability, and civic engagement. Safety comes through “eyes on the street,” an idea from Jane Jacobs in &lt;em&gt;The Life and Death of Great American Cities&lt;/em&gt;. Because there are people on the streets and people watching the streets there is less fear of crime and a feeling of greater safety. Vibrancy and stability are achieved through keeping residents for an entire life cycle who will be active in civic functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring the school into the urban condition, it must be re-imagined as a school/community center, a place that supports the children’s education, varied community members, and a program beyond the typical 8:00 a.m. – 3:00 p.m. school day. I propose four key ways this urban school will fulfill the needs of a diverse urban population. The first, BOND, focuses on education and advancement through interaction. The next, MOVE, addresses designing spaces in support of physical activity that adds to the program outside of the typical elementary school program. The third is CARE, promoting the education and development of the children. The last, GROW, entails protecting the future through a safe and sustainable design.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2399</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2729&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2399</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2729</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-09T19:03:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4016321</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2399</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Akerman</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas K. Davis, Marleen K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>