<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>WHITE PRIVILEGE AND SOCIAL STUDIES PRE-SERVICE TEACHERS</title>
<publication-date>2015-01-14T13:17:24-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>curry@coastal.edu</email>
<institution>Coastal Carolina University</institution>
<lname>Curry</lname>
<fname>Kristal</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>social studies education</keyword>
<keyword>social justice</keyword>
<keyword>white privilege</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article explores the dynamic of the Silenced Dialogue within a graduate-level, teacher preparation diversity course by analyzing student-created reflections about Peggy McIntosh’s article regarding White privilege. The paper compares themes that emerged in White vs. Black student reflections, male vs. female student reflections, and those of students preparing to teach social studies compared to those preparing to teach in other disciplines available in the program. Social studies candidates had complex responses to race. They seemed to feel comfortable with the topic, but were also world-weary and likely to dismiss current racism as being less than it used to be, and therefore, not much of a current issue. As compared to candidates in other disciplines who were surprised by the readings on White Privilege and felt challenged to act on their new understandings, social studies candidates were more likely to place current race relations in a historical context and emphasize the improvements made in recent decades, rather than changes that may still need to be made. This paper concludes with the problematic implications of social studies teachers who see racism as real, but largely a problem of the past.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol5/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1067&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1067</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-14T08:45:45-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/catalyst/article/1067/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>6526911</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol5/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-14T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xbe01038)</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>