<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development, Stability, and Molecular Mechanisms of Macrolide Resistance in &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter jejuni&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Caldwell</lname>
<fname>Dave</fname>
<mname>Bryson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Previous studies on macrolide resistance in &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt; were primarily focused on the isolates from various origins using &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; systems. In this study, both &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; experiments were conducted to examine the development, stability, and genetic basis of macrolide resistance in &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt;. All &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; selected Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants were derived from the same parent strain &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; NCTC 11168. To determine if long-term exposure of low-level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; to low-dose tylosin selects for high-level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants (MIC &gt; 512 μg/ml), two low-level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants (MIC = 32 or 64 μg/ml) were used to inoculate chickens at 15 days of age in two independent experiments. Total and Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; populations in swabs collected at different time points were determined by differential plating and MIC test. The &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; stability was tested by repeated subculturing of Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants in Ery-free broth medium. The &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; stability was tested by inoculating 3-day-old chickens (12-13 birds/group) receiving nonmedicated feed with Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants and collecting cloacal swabs from each chickens at 12, 22, 38, and 47 days of age. Total and Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; populations in culture (after 10, 20 and 33 passages) or swab were determined by differential plating and MIC test. Genomic DNA from each of 63 selected Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants was used for PCR amplification and sequence analysis of 23S rRNA gene and ribosomal proteins L4 and L22. Mutation in CmeABC multidrug efflux pump was transferred to Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; strains to determine the role of CmeABC efflux pump in Ery resistance. Chicken studies showed that the length of exposure time to subtherapeutic level of tylosin is not a sole factor contributing to the emergence of highly Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt;. Prolonged exposure of low-level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; (MIC = 32 or 64 μg/ml) to tylosin did not select for highly Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants. The low- level Ery resistance (MIC = 32μg/ml) was stable after 10 passages &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; but majority of &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; were sensitive to Ery after 20 passages. The instability of low-level Ery resistance was also observed in chickens as early as 9 days postinoculation and Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants were rarely isolated 35 days postinoculation. However, high-level Ery resistance (MIC &gt; 512μg/ml) displayed remarkably stability &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;. All high-level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants selected &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; displayed the A2074G mutation in 23S rRNA gene, distinct from the specific mutation (A2074C) observed in all highly Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants selected &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt;. No mutations were observed in ribosomal proteins L4 for all &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; selected Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants but specific mutations in L4 (G74D or G57D) were widely found in low level Ery&lt;sup&gt;R&lt;/sup&gt; mutants selected &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; (Ery MIC = 8-64 μg/ml). Insertion of three amino acids TSH at position 98 in L22 was only observed in mutants selected &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; with Ery MIC ranging from 32-512 μg/ml. The CmeABC efflux pump worked synergistically with other mechanisms to confer Ery resistance in &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt;. Together, these findings indicated that &lt;em&gt;C. jejuni&lt;/em&gt; utilize complex and different mechanisms to develop Ery resistance &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/266</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1299&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>266</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1299</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-10T12:18:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1139441</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/266</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jun Lin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kelly R. Robbins, Barton W. Rohrbach, Stephen P. Oliver</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/CaldwellDave.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>