<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Technology-Training for Preservice Teachers in Schools, Colleges, and Departments of Education Affiliated with Selected Teacher Education Professional Organizations: The State of Practice in 2008</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McCoy</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;By means of a researcher-created survey instrument, this study sought to determine: 1) whether teacher education programs differ in the ways in which they deliver technology training for preservice teachers; 2) to what degree technology training for preservice teachers is offered partially online or completely online and/or as distance learning; and, 3) whether schools, colleges, or departments of education (SCDEs) make provisions for preparing preservice teachers to be online teachers in a virtual classroom or school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings, based on the responses of 41 participants, showed that most schools, colleges, and departments of education in the study rely primarily on a stand-alone technology course and integrating technology into other education courses. Although schools, colleges, and departments of education in this study offer some education courses online, few (less than 12%) of them characterized their technology courses for preservice teachers as “online.” In addition, only 14% of those participating in this study indicated their programs directly address the competencies needed for teachers to be online instructors in virtual setting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/471</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1535&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>471</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1535</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-19T08:57:20-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1155668</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/471</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Waugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Schuyler Huck, Jay Pfaffman, Gary Skolits</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/McCoyShelleyAnn.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>