<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Diagnosis and Distribution of Florida Sand Darter, Ammocrypta bifascia (Teleostei; Percidae), in the Flint River, Georgia</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-16T13:32:34-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>camswift@pacbell.net</email>
<institution>Emeritus, Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County</institution>
<lname>Swift</lname>
<fname>Camm</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gmoyer@mansfield.edu</email>
<institution>Department of Biology, Mansfield University. Previous address: U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Conservation Genetics Laboratory</institution>
<lname>Moyer</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>cfallon18@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Georgia, Athens</institution>
<lname>Fallon</lname>
<fname>Christine</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>brett.albanese@dnr.ga.gov</email>
<institution>Georgia Dept. of Natural Resources</institution>
<lname>Albanese</lname>
<fname>Brett</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cryptic biodiversity</keyword>
<keyword>Apalachicola drainage</keyword>
<keyword>Ichawaynochaway Creek</keyword>
<keyword>seining</keyword>
<keyword>snorkeling</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biodiversity</discipline>
<discipline>Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Genetics</discipline>
<discipline>Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract: &lt;/em&gt;In 2013, we observed the presence of an undocumented &lt;em&gt;Ammocrypta&lt;/em&gt; species in the lower Flint River, Georgia. The occurrence represents the first record of the genus in Georgia. Subsequent surveys at 24 sites, using seining or snorkeling, documented additional specimens from mainstem sites (n = 3) between Albany and Bainbridge and from Ichawaynochaway Creek (n = 5 sites), a large tributary to the Flint River. We used morphological and genetic data to identify specimens to species. Morphological examination included 23 morphometric and 8 meristic characters from fifteen specimens that were compared to specimens from Williams (1975). For genetic analyses, we targeted the mtDNA cytochrome c oxidase and nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer 2 (ITS-2) genes and compared them to specimens from throughout the geographic range of &lt;em&gt;Ammocrypta&lt;/em&gt;. Morphological analyses showed broad overlap in measurements and counts with &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt; (Florida Sand Darter). The mtDNA data also grouped our specimens with &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt; from the Choctawhatchee River, which is the type locality of &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia. &lt;/em&gt; While nuclear data was monomorphic when compared to other &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt;, the mtDNA of Flint River &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt; shared a unique haplotype that was one or more substitutions apart from other &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia &lt;/em&gt;haplotypes. Georgia specimens appear to be native, having a haplotype that is different from other &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt; and a distribution pattern that corresponds closely to other fishes. We observed &lt;em&gt;A. bifascia&lt;/em&gt; from only a handful of scattered localities in the mainstem of the river and the lower portion of its largest tributary. Past surveys may have failed to detect the species due its limited distribution and the difficulty of collecting small benthic fishes in large river habitats.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss60/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1305&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1305</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-07-16T19:06:41-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1305/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>18550122</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss60/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Initial records of A. bifascia in the Flint River were made during Paddle Georgia (June 2013) and Fall Float on the Flint (October 2014), events of the Georgia River Network, then organized by April Ingle, Joe Cook, Dana Skelton, and Gwyneth Moody.  Field assistance was provided by Garrett Hopper, Nathan Herron, and the Aquatic Biology lab (The Jones Center at Ichauway), Deborah Weiler and Peter Dimmick (Georgia DNR), Kenneth Swift and Paddle Georgia participants. Matthew Rowe and Zachariah Abouhamdan (Georgia DNR) assisted with photo editing and map production, respectively.  Stephen Golladay, Krista Capps and Mary Freeman are thanked for their advisement and Mary and Bud Freeman for their wisdom regarding Ichawaynochaway Creek fishes.  We thank Sandra Bohn, Ashantye Williams, Shannon Julian and Meredith Bartron (USFWS) for sequencing and data curation along with the University Kansas Biodiversity Institute and the Florida Museum of Natural History for tissue samples, and the Georgia Museum of Natural History for specimen archival.  

Support for genetic analyses was provided by Mansfield University’s Faculty Professional Development Committee Grant (GRM) and by The Environmental Resource Network, Inc. (T.E.R.N.), the official “Friends Group” of the Wildlife Conservation Section of the Wildlife Resources Division of Georgia DNR.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xe5ee538)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Flint River Ammocrypta</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>CorrectedAcknowledgments.docx</archive-name>
<upload-name>CorrectedAcknowledgments.docx</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1305&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>