<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Economic Cost Models of Scientific Scholarly Journals</title>
<publication-date>1998-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>King</lname>
<fname>Donald</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electronic journals</keyword>
<keyword>scholarly reading</keyword>
<keyword>scientific journals</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper summarizes costs of publishing scientific scholarly journals. Activities are described for five publishing components: article processing (e.g., manuscript processing, editing , composition, etc.), non-article processing (i.e. similar activities related to covers, tables-of-content, letters, book reviews, etc.), reproduction (e.g., printing, collating, binding, etc.), distribution (e.g., wrapping, labeling, sorting, mailing, subscription maintenance, etc.), and support (e.g., marketing, administration, finance, etc.). A model is derived for each of these components consisting of cost parameters (e.g., number of issues, pages, subscriptions, etc.) and cost elements (e.g., cost per page of editing, set-up cost per issue, postage cost per issue copy mailed, etc.). Total costs of a &quot;typical&quot; journal are presented where cost parameters are estimated from a sample of scientific scholarly journals and cost elements derived from estimates reported in the literature. Costs of electronic publications are also derived.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/231</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1416&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>231</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1416</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-31T12:05:45-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16095447</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/231</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Donald W. King and Carol Tenopir. “Economic Cost Models of Scientific Scholarly Journals.” In Economic, Read Costs and Benefits of Electronic Publishing in Science--A Technical Study: Proceedings of the ICSU Press Workshop, Keble College, Oxford, UK, March 31 to April 2, 1998. URL: http://www.bodley.ox.ac.uk/icsu/kingppr.htm.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Economic, Read Costs and Benefits of Electronic Publishing in Science--A Technical Study: Proceedings of the ICSU Press Workshop</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>