<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Listeria monocytogenes by High-Intensity Ultrasound in the Presence of Salts</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stanley</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Inactivation of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 and &lt;em&gt;Listeria monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;suspended in salt solutions Na2PO4, NaCl, NaNO3, NH4Cl, CaCl2, AlCl3, and &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;in salt solutions NaCl, NaNO3, AlCl3 at concentrations ranging from 0 to 5% (wt/vol) by high-intensity ultrasound at two different temperature conditions (ice water bath, 40ºC water bath) and three ultrasonic intensity levels (9.49, 21.83, 49.22 W/cm2) was determined. Increases in sonication treatment time, intensity and temperature led to increased lethality of both pathogens. However, cell lethality, as a function of solute concentration, varied depending upon type of salt. CaCl2, NaCl, NaNO3, NaPO4, and NH4Cl had little or no effect on survival of &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 (&lt; 1 log reduction) regardless of other treatment conditions at 9.49 W/cm2. Concentrations &gt; 0.5% of CaCl2, NaNO3, NaPO4, and NH4Cl adversely affected survival (1.0 - 1.6 log reduction) with treatment of 21.83 W/cm2 in an ice bath, and showed greater inactivation (1.2 - 4.0 log reduction) at 40°C. Treatment of 49.22 W/cm2 showed the greatest impact regardless of other parameters. At 40°C, treatment for 10 minutes at 49.22 W/cm2 led to total inactivation for bacteria suspended in 0.5% NH4Cl, 1% CaCl3, 2% NaCl, 5% NaPO4, and all concentrations of AlCl3. Complete inactivation also occurred in an ice bath for 5% AlCl3, which was shown to be the most effective salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NaCl and NaNO3 had little or no effect on survival of &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;(&lt; 1 log reduction) regardless of other treatment conditions at 9.49 W/cm2. Concentrations &gt;0.5% of NaCl and AlCl&lt;sub&gt;3 &lt;/sub&gt; adversely affected survival (0.2 -1.6 log reduction) with treatment of 21.83 W/cm2 in an ice bath and showed greater inactivation (0.4 - 5.2 log reduction) at 40°C. Regardless of other treatment parameters, sonication at 49.22 W/cm2 showed the greatest lethal impact. Treatment for 10 minutes at 40°C at 49.22 W/cm2 led to a 4.8 - 5.7 log reduction for cells suspended in all concentrations of NaNO3. Typically, L. monocytogenes was more resistant to ultrasound treatment than &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7. Inactivation of pathogens is attributed to cavitation-induced shear forces, reaction of cavitation-generated hydrogen peroxide with microbial cell wall constituents and electrostatic interactions of dissociated salts with cell membranes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2227</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3628&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2227</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3628</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-11T08:26:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4697285</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2227</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jochen Weiss, F. Ann Draughon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>