<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Deeds of William of Villehardouin: An Annotated Translation of a Part of the Medieval Work, &lt;i&gt;La Chronique de Morée&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hmcclur2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McClure</lname>
<fname>Houston</fname>
<mname>Franklin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Morea</keyword>
<keyword>French</keyword>
<keyword>Greece</keyword>
<keyword>Villehardouin</keyword>
<keyword>Crusade</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>French and Francophone Literature</discipline>
<discipline>French Linguistics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, titled &lt;em&gt;The Deeds of William of Villehardouin: An Annotated Translation of a Part of the Old French La Chronique de Morée&lt;/em&gt;, I have translated a portion of one of the remaining French texts from a period just following the Fourth Crusade (1202-1204). The portion I used of the text is taken from Jean Longnon&#39;s critical edition in Middle French based on the sole 14&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century manuscript now at the Royal Library in Brussels 15702. However, the events related in the &lt;em&gt;Chronique&lt;/em&gt; span an earlier period of 1095-1304&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The stanzas that I will translate, 439 to 534, concern Prince William of Villehardouin, the last prince of Morea, which is the old name for the Peloponnesian peninsula in Greece. This passage explores William&#39;s life across his assistance of King Charles, his defense of Morea, and his court hearings concerning the ownership of the land of Madame Margaret. I have provided historical footnotes for prominent people and places. Through analysis of the lexicon used in the original text, I will also attempt to make inferences as to the author&#39;s provenance because he is currently unknown. Though written in Middle French, the text is heavy with Italianisms. Any discoveries relating to the author&#39;s homeland could help reference the growth and history of French as a language in this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; Longnon, Jean. &lt;em&gt;Livre De La Conqueste De La Princée De L&#39;Amorée: Chronique De Morée (1204-1305)&lt;/em&gt;. Paris: Librairie Renouard, H. Laurens, successeur, 1911.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3788</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5079&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3788</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5079</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-25T10:59:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8216191</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3788</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Anne-Hélène Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Romeiser, Sébastien Dubreil</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>French</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>