<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Possible Glial Role in the Mammalian Circadian Clock</title>
<publication-date>1994-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prosser</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Edgar</lname>
<fname>Dale</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Heller</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>Craig</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Miller</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Suprachiasmatic nucleus; Circadian rhythm; Glia; Octanol; Halothane; Fluorocitrate; Brain slice</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Cell Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary mammalian circadian clock is located within the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN), but the cellular organization of the clock is not yet known. We investigated the potential role of glial cells in the clock mechanism by determining whether disrupting glial activity affects the in vitro circadian rhythm of neuronal activity and the in vivo circadian activity rhythm in rats. We used two agents (octanol and halothane) that block gap junctions, and one (fluorocitrate) that inhibits glial metabolism. All three agents disrupted the circadian pattern of neuronal activity. Octanol flattened the rhythm at the highest concentration (200 μM) and induced a small phase delay at a lower concentration (66 μM). Halothane and fluorocitrate induced ultradian rhythmicity. Fluorocitrate injected into the SCN of an intact rat induced arrhythmicity for about 1 week, after which the rhythm reappeared with a 1.6 h delay. These results suggest that glia play an important role in the SCN circadian clock.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/14</coverpage-url>
<label>14</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1013</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-10T07:48:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1352747</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/14</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Rebecca A. Prosser, Dale M. Edgar, H. Craig Heller, Joseph D. Miller, A possible glial role in the mammalian circadian clock, Brain Research, Volume 643, Issues 1-2, 18 April 1994, Pages 296-301, ISSN 0006-8993, DOI: 10.1016/0006-8993(94)90036-1.
(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-4KTNC19-18/2/46a342cc6d8f2a786beeb3ab557efe3c)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-4KTNC19-18/2/46a342cc6d8f2a786beeb3ab557efe3c</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>