<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Some Aspects of Affect Measurement on Rorschach&#39;s Test and the Multidimensional Personality Questionnaire</title>
<publication-date>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hunter</lname>
<fname>Greta</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate some of the ways in which the relationship between two types of measures that assess positive and negative expectations about the world might be improved. The first measure, an index in the Burstein-Loucks comprehensive scoring system (1989) for Rorschach&#39;s test, was based on object relations theory. The second measure consisted of two higher-order factors of the Multidimensional Personality Questionnaire (Tellegen, 1982), an empirically-derived instrument. Revision of the Burstein-Loucks index did not further improve the magnitude of the relationship between the two measures, although it may have slightly changed the nature of that relationship. The significance of finding even a relatively small amount of shared variance between two such different types of instruments is discussed. The high levels of interrater reliability possible by using a clinical-intuitive approach to scoring data is also discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2788</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4310&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2788</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4310</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-08-22T09:44:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6020428</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2788</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alvin G. Burstein</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sandra Fowler, John W. Lounsbury, Mary Sue Younger</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>