<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>How They Flew: Modern Flight Test of Pioneering Wright Aircraft</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ohman</lname>
<fname>Klas</fname>
<mname>Walace</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The first controlled and sustained powered flight was arguably the single most important transformational world event of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century.  This accomplishment just over 100 years ago on the isolated, cold and windy Outer Banks of North Carolina was nothing short of miraculous.  What enabled two bicycle mechanics from Dayton, Ohio to succeed where many others had tried and failed is also most incredible.  However, unlike some other technical advancements, primarily either the Wrights or those interviewing them tell this story - with little independent verification.  It is precisely for this reason that re-tracing the steps of these pioneers with the benefit of modern flight test methodology and without the bias of history is such an interesting undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A controlled and sustained powered flight consists quite simply of two parts. First, it must be powered and sustained – not gliding, but taking off and landing at the same elevation.  Second, it must be controlled – the pilot must not just be along for the ride.  The Wrights early on realized that gliding flight was possible and practical by studying the results of the earlier aviation pioneer, Otto Lilienthal.  They further realized that his methods of control were sub-optimal.  Eventually, the Wrights reasoned, sustained powered flight would be achievable if the forces of drag and weight could be overcome on an aircraft that was capable of being controlled.  They knew so strongly that control was paramount to powered flight that it is this aspect of the problem which was the basis of their 1906 Patent # 821,393  [1].  Their advances were not without problems, however, only some of which were technical.  There was at the time a very high-pressure race to see who would be the first to achieve the feat of sustained, powered flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They produced an historic equivalent of a modern technology demonstrator aircraft and documented the event photographically.  Even with this evidence, it still took until 1944 for the United States to recognize their just place in aviation history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of first flight competition, the remote location of their test site, the size of their test team, and several other factors, it can be postulated that perhaps some details of their flight test program and the exact physical properties of their aircraft might be not recorded exactly as they existed.  These details could have been changed or omitted for proprietary reasons, or just not included because at the time it did not matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis will document the daily flight test activities of the author and a team of multi-service test pilots as they review the historical record and put replicas of three pioneering Wright aircraft through tests that mimic those we feel the Wrights must have performed themselves.  Through these tests several key issues will be brought to light as well as insight into the incredible skill, determination, scientific method and luck which ultimately allowed the brothers to achieve their goal one windy morning in December, 1903.  Additionally, many facets of testing historic aircraft in an age of concern for risk management and safety along with parallels to modern flight test will be presented.  Historical data will come from a number of sources, while actual flight test data will be from reports of trials conducted by the author (Navy test pilot), and both operational and test pilots from the United States Air Force and United States Army.  These trials were conducted between 4 to 8 October 2002 in Jockey’s Ridge State Park, North Carolina; 1 to 12 October 2003 in both Jockey’s Ridge and Currituck County Airport in North Carolina; 13 and 14 December 2003 in Dayton, Ohio; and finally January 10, 2004 in Dayton, Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2314</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3735&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2314</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3735</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-16T13:04:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4729369</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2314</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. D. Kimberlin, R. J. Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>