<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effect of religiosity and campus alcohol culture on collegiate alcohol consumption</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wells</lname>
<fname>Gayle</fname>
<mname>Maddox</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to assess the interactive relationship of college environment and religiosity on the college alcohol experience of students attending two institutions, one secular and one a religious college. Reference group theory was the theoretical foundation utilized in this study. The data for this research was gathered from two college samples, one a secular university and one a religious liberal arts college. Five hundred and twenty-nine students participated in the project. The data was based on student responses to two survey instruments. The Religiosity Measure is an eight-item survey that assesses religiosity, and the College Alcohol Survey is a twenty-page survey that investigates collegiate alcohol use. A pilot study was carried out using twenty-one college students to assess the survey instruments. A variety of statistical procedures were used, including Mann-Whitney U tests, Spearman Rho correlations, chi-square, and multinomial logistic regression.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6411</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8385&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6411</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8385</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:39:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24074691</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6411</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jack Ellison, Bill Wallace, George Harris</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>