<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Examination of Career Experiences of Black Senior Level Administrators in College Athletics</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rpointe2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Pointer</lname>
<fname>Russell</fname>
<mname>Andrew</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Black</keyword>
<keyword>Athletic Director</keyword>
<keyword>Sports</keyword>
<keyword>Barriers</keyword>
<keyword>Experience</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the career experiences of Black senior level administrators (SLAs) in college athletics using Critical Race Theory (CRT). Senior level administrators included the following: Athletic Directors (ADs), Deputy ADs, Executive ADs, and Senior-Associate ADs. Seven Black SLAs participated via phone interviews.Interviews were transcribed verbatim and three rounds of coding produced three primary themes and eight subthemes. The findings produced the following themes: having champions in one’s corner, navigating the system, and embracing individuality. The idea of having champions in one’s corner means creating and maintaining relationships that provide guidance, encouragement, and advocacy. Secondly, navigating the system means learning about and understanding barriers, timing, location, opportunities, and campus culture. Lastly, embracing individuality reveals unique paths and involves finding value in being an outlier.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5134</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6541&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5134</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6541</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415064</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5134</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven N. Waller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James H. Bemiller, Robin L. Hardin, Adam Love</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>