<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Experiences with the Office of Public Health Nutrition, Nassau County Department of Health, Nassau County, New York</title>
<publication-date>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Price</lname>
<fname>Bobbette</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this eight-week field experience was to provide the student with an opportunity to integrate course theory learned at the University of Tennessee with the actual practice of public health in Nassau County, New York. It also allowed the student to compare programs in health departments, specifically the functions of public health nutrition in such agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Varied experiences in the Nassau County Department of Health contributed to the student achieving this purpose. The characteristics of Nassau County, as well as its people, were studied. Findings revealed health problems and needs unique to the county. Orientation to units within the health agency allowed the student to understand its organization and to view the role the health department performed in solving the community&#39;s health problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conference periods and cooperative work with the Director of Nutrition and her staff made the student aware of the responsibilities of the nutrition unit within the health department and the relationship of nutrition services to various community agencies. Observation of and participation in a variety of activities typical of a public health nutritionist made the student realize the many different roles the nutritionist must assume in order to tailor nutrition services to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience emphasized for the student the idea that the nutritionist cannot function alone in solving the nutritional problems of the community she serves. She is only one among many in the public health field striving ultimately to reach a common goal. Therefore, the health department offers an ideal setting in which the interdisciplinary approach to solving health problems can be used effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3907</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5389&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3907</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5389</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-26T08:49:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9036948</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3907</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Rose Gram, Irshad Ahmad</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>