<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Paternal Involvement: Effects on Delinquency</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wynn</lname>
<fname>Porche&#39;</fname>
<mname>Teshia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Despite the numerous research studies published regarding the influence of parenting on delinquent behavior, there is yet a clear understanding of how fathers’ parenting practices specifically influence behaviors.  Because the majority of previous studies have solely focused on how mothers’ parenting practices affect adolescent behavioral outcomes, research has failed at specifically defining characteristics of fathers’ parenting practices and their influence on behaviors.  Because this has been a debatable topic of research for several years, the purpose of the present study is to determine if fathers’ involvement, in the adolescent years, contributes to more favorable behaviors than when fathers are not involved during this time.  It attempts to answer this question by examining the relationship between fathers’ involvement and violent delinquency across racial groups, using social control theory as a theoretical framework.  The National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health (ADD Health) In Home Wave I, Public Use Version data set was used to explore this relationship.  For the present study, data collected from a representative sample of 5,783 cases were analyzed.  Findings indicate overall higher levels of fathers’ involvement do not reduce violent delinquency but the effect of fathers’ involvement on delinquency varies across racial groups.  The findings showed that higher levels of fathers’ involvement do not reduce violent delinquency but the effect of fathers’ involvement on delinquency varies across racial groups.  The findings showed that higher levels of fathers’ involvement were associated with higher levels of delinquency for African American adolescents but had no effect on delinquency for White and Asian groups.  Results show other factors including gender and G.P.A had a significant effect on violent delinquency.  Policy implications suggest increase in the presence of the father or father figure especially in single parent homes that may in turn increase supervision and control of adolescents, which may lead to fewer opportunities to commit delinquent acts.  Policy implications for G.P.A suggest the improvement of educational standards and learning systems to help adolescents focus more on academic achievement than on unconventional activities or negative behavior.  Also implications for gender suggest educating male adolescents on ways in which to achieve goals within society without being aggressive and violent.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4822</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6333&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4822</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6333</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-28T13:21:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10670917</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4822</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hoan Bui</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry Cable, Lois Presser</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>