<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluating the Effects of Various Painting Techniques on Athletic Field Surface and Root Zone Characteristics</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bogle4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Ogle</lname>
<fname>Bryan</fname>
<mname>McKinley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Athletic</keyword>
<keyword>Field</keyword>
<keyword>Paint</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Every year, athletic field marking paint is applied by thousands of turfgrass managers for a range of sports on both natural and synthetic turf athletic fields. Research was conducted to compare different treatments consisting of various nozzle sizes and pressure settings for applying athletic turf paint.  Applications occurred eight times, simulating an NCAA football schedule. Treatments were applied in 2015 and 2016 to ‘Tifway 419’ (Cynodon dactylon L.) bermudagrass sod established in 2011 and maintained on a USGA sand-based root zone (United States Golf Association, 2018). Soil samples from each treatment area were subject to analysis consisting of bulk density, percent organic matter, and rate of water infiltration. Soil sample findings were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) using the statistical program SAS (version 9.3; SAS Institution Inc.) to determine treatment effects. Each treatment was measured to determine the quantity of paint sprayed from the different nozzles and pressure settings. Digital images of each treatment area were taken and uploaded into Turf Analyzer, a java-based computer software. The software was used to determine differences in color saturation, uniformity, and brightness of paint treatments applied to the turfgrass. Multiple images were taken over several days following the initial paint coat and were evaluated to determine which treatment had the least amount of fading over time.Results of this study will be used to produce a guide to provide to turfgrass managers responsible for painting athletic field surfaces throughout the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5607</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7141&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5607</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7141</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-11T12:42:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>20539107</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5607</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Sorochan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tom Samples, Brandon Horvath</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>