<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development and Validation of a Crisis Self-Efficacy Scale</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>spark37@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Park</lname>
<fname>Sejin</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Crisis communicaiton</keyword>
<keyword>Self-efficacy</keyword>
<keyword>Scale development</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study develops a valid and reliable self-efficacy scale specific to the crisis context. The rationale for developing the scale is first to provide a tool for crisis communication researchers to better understand behavioral aspects of crisis. Second, as people have different levels of crisis self-efficacy, it is difficult for crisis managers to develop audience-specific messages and create crisis preparedness programs. A crisis self-efficacy scale enables crisis managers to develop more effective message strategies to protect publics and minimize crisis damage. The scale also provides practitioners a useful longitudinal index of progress in crisis preparedness programs to track changes in public efficacy during the intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the scale development identify four constructs of crisis self-efficacy: action efficacy, preventive efficacy, achievement efficacy, and uncertainty management efficacy. Each construct measures a unique aspect of crisis self-efficacy. Specifically, the action efficacy reflects one’s beliefs about his/her ability to take protective actions in crisis, while preventive efficacy is defined as one’s beliefs about his/her level of preparedness for crisis. Next, achievement efficacy is defined as one’s beliefs about his/her goal accomplishment in crisis, and uncertainty management efficacy is one’s beliefs about his/her ability to deal with uncertainties in crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People’s demographic information is tested to examine indicators of crisis self-efficacy. Three predictors are identified: gender, household income, and state residency. First, the results reveal that there is a gender difference in crisis self-efficacy; males have higher crisis self-efficacy levels than females. Next, there is a trend in the relationship between household income and crisis self-efficacy; as income goes up, the level of crisis self-efficacy also rises. Finally, state residency predicts individual’s crisis self-efficacy when the number of disasters in participants’ states is considered. Theoretical and practical implications are discussed, and directions for future research are identified.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3661</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5124&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3661</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5124</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-17T10:55:40-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5124/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8164646</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3661</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Elizabeth A. Foster</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael J. Palenchar, Abbey B. Levenshus, Jennifer A. Morrow</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>