<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Myth y la magia: Magical Realism and the Modernism of Latin America</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hwiddifi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Widdifield</lname>
<fname>Hannah</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>magical realism</keyword>
<keyword>modernism</keyword>
<keyword>surrealism</keyword>
<keyword>latin america</keyword>
<keyword>miguel angel asturias</keyword>
<keyword>men of maize</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Latin American Languages and Societies</discipline>
<discipline>Literature in English, North America, Ethnic and Cultural Minority</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The similarities between Latin American magical realism and European surrealism have long been regarded as part of a shared, cohesive movement in literature and art. After all, they share certain nonsensical and fantastical traits that place both movements far away from the Realism that modernism, as a whole, refutes. But in light of postcolonial theory, it becomes more and more necessary to explore magical realism as a geographically and politically situated movement with its own unique value in discussions of Modernism; not an offshoot of surrealism, but a sister genre, born in the distinct atmosphere of a region trying to self-identify in the face of postcolonial modernization. By exploring the conventions of the genre through some of its foundational texts—&lt;em&gt;A Universal History of Infamy, The Kingdom of this World,&lt;/em&gt; and particularly, &lt;em&gt;Men of Maize&lt;/em&gt;—we can then reinsert magical realism into a larger discussion about modernism in order to enrich and complicate what its global iterations mean outside of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick historical background regarding the origins of magical realism, first as a regional genre and then as a field of academic study, the thesis will engage with a close reading of some of the mythological elements of Miguel Angel Asturias’ &lt;em&gt;Men of Maize&lt;/em&gt;. The novel will be read in light of mythmaking, postcolonial theory, and theory regarding both genre and novel conventions. The claim in the end is that &lt;em&gt;Men of Maize&lt;/em&gt; showcases a Latin American encounter with modernism and modernity that results in a fractured identity, which Asturias ultimately attempts to heal through myth and magical realism.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3421</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4661&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3421</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4661</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-27T14:01:34-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4661/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6745648</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3421</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisi M. Schoenbach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allen R. Dunn, Urmila S. Seshagiri</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>