<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Documentation of end-of-course test development for Keyboarding in Knox County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Rose</lname>
<fname>Kay</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study documents the development of a system-wide end-of-course test for Keyboarding in Knox County, Tennessee. In the 1999-2000 school year, the Knox County, Tennessee, school system implemented a time-line for end-of-course testing for vocational courses that would mirror the end-of-course tests in core subjects. In September, 1999, initiative objectives and a timeline were established for construction of end-of-course tests for 15 vocational courses in Knox County, Tennessee. Each vocational class teacher in the 12 Knox County, Tennessee, high schools was instructed to formulate an end-of-course test for their respective courses. Research gathered in this study pertained to demographic data analysis, response to five research questions, and end results. Research questions were: (1) why require system-wide end-of-course testing in Keyboarding, (2) what are the federal, state, and local guidelines, procedures, and timeline for developing end-of-course testing, (3) what Tennessee standards and competencies are addressed in the teaching of Keyboarding, (4) what generic procedures are followed for competency test development or construction, and (5) who are the local school system teacher practitioners responsible for serving as subject matter experts for competency test development for the Knox County Keyboarding course. Based on the findings of this study, conclusions reached were: (1) Keyboarding in Knox County, Tennessee, is an integral component of the Information Technology curriculum, (2) accountability serves to link state and federal standards at the local level, (3) federal, state, and local guidelines, procedures, and timeline serve as a three-fold catalyst for the development of end-of-course testing, (4) Tennessee standards and competencies serve as the basis for test development of the standards-based factual and conceptual questions, (5) the use of five process clusters in test construction demonstrates a systematic approach in test development, and (6) local school system practitioners with expertise in the teaching of Keyboarding and knowledge of Keyboarding standards and competencies are qualified to develop end-of-course tests. Fellow researchers, school administrators, and teachers can benefit from the results of this research in regard to development of a valid and reliable test.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5986</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7619&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5986</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7619</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467648</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5986</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vickie Johnson Stout</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>