<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Survey of Borreliae in ticks, canines, and white-tailed deer from Arkansas, U.S.A.</title>
<publication-date>2012-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>RFryxell@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fryxell</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Steelman</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Szalanski</lname>
<fname>Alan</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Kvamee</lname>
<fname>Ken</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of North Texas Health Science Center at Fort Worth</institution>
<lname>Billingsley</lname>
<fname>Peggy</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of North Texas Health Science Center at Fort Worth</institution>
<lname>Williamson</lname>
<fname>Philip</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Borrelia</keyword>
<keyword>Ticks</keyword>
<keyword>Vector borne</keyword>
<keyword>Surveillance</keyword>
<keyword>Deer</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Eastern and Upper Midwestern regions of North America, &lt;em&gt;Ixodes scapularis&lt;/em&gt; (L.) is the most abundant tick species encountered by humans and the primary vector of &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi,&lt;/em&gt; whereas in the southeastern region &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma americanum&lt;/em&gt; (Say) is the most abundant tick species encountered by humans but cannot transmit &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi.&lt;/em&gt; Surveys of Borreliae in ticks have been conducted in the southeastern United States and often these surveys identify &lt;em&gt;B. lonestari&lt;/em&gt; as the primary &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt; species, surveys have not included Arkansas ticks, canines, or white-tailed deer and &lt;em&gt;B. lonestari&lt;/em&gt; is not considered pathogenic. The objective of this study was to identify &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt; species within Arkansas by screening ticks (n = 2123), canines (n = 173), and white-tailed deer (n = 228) to determine the identity and locations of Borreliae endemic to Arkansas using PCR amplification of the flagellin (&lt;em&gt;flaB)&lt;/em&gt; gene.  &lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field collected ticks from canines and from hunter-killed white-tailed were identified to species and life stage. After which, ticks and their hosts were screened for the presence of &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt; using PCR to amplify the &lt;em&gt;flaB&lt;/em&gt; gene. A subset of the positive samples was confirmed with bidirectional sequencing.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total 53 (21.2%) white-tailed deer, ten (6%) canines, and 583 (27.5%) Ixodid ticks (252 &lt;em&gt;Ixodes scapularis&lt;/em&gt;, 161 &lt;em&gt;A. americanum&lt;/em&gt;, 88 &lt;em&gt;Rhipicephalus sanguineus&lt;/em&gt;, 50 &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma maculatum,&lt;/em&gt; 19 &lt;em&gt;Dermacentor variabilis,&lt;/em&gt; and 13 unidentified &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma&lt;/em&gt; species) produced a &lt;em&gt;Borrelia flaB&lt;/em&gt; amplicon. Of the positive ticks, 324 (22.7%) were collected from canines (151 &lt;em&gt;A. americanum,&lt;/em&gt; 78 &lt;em&gt;R. sanguineus&lt;/em&gt;, 43 &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis,&lt;/em&gt; 26 &lt;em&gt;A. maculatum,&lt;/em&gt; 18 &lt;em&gt;D. variabilis&lt;/em&gt;, and 8 &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma&lt;/em&gt; species) and 259 (37.2%) were collected from white-tailed deer (209 &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis,&lt;/em&gt; 24 &lt;em&gt;A. maculatum,&lt;/em&gt; 10 &lt;em&gt;A. americanum,&lt;/em&gt; 10 &lt;em&gt;R. sanguineus&lt;/em&gt;, 1 &lt;em&gt;D. variabilis&lt;/em&gt;, and 5 &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma&lt;/em&gt; species). None of the larvae were PCR positive. A majority of the &lt;em&gt;flaB&lt;/em&gt; amplicons were homologous with &lt;em&gt;B. lonestari&lt;/em&gt; sequences: 281 of the 296 sequenced ticks, 3 canines, and 27 deer. Only 22 deer, 7 canines, and 15 tick &lt;em&gt;flaB&lt;/em&gt; amplicons (12 &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis&lt;/em&gt;, 2 &lt;em&gt;A. maculatum&lt;/em&gt;, and 1 &lt;em&gt;Amblyomma&lt;/em&gt; species) were homologous with &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt; sequences.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data from this study identified multiple Borreliae genotypes in Arkansas ticks, canines and deer including &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. lonestari;&lt;/em&gt; however, &lt;em&gt;B. lonestari&lt;/em&gt; was significantly more prevalent in the tick population than &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt;. Results from this study suggest that the majority of tick-borne diseases in Arkansas are not &lt;em&gt;B. burgdorferi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/59</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1059&amp;amp;context=utk_planpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>59</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1059</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-15T09:39:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4312786</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/59</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Parasites &amp; Vectors 2012, 5:139 doi:10.1186/1756-3305-5-139</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>