<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of Root Stimulating Bacterium and its Root Stimulating Abilities</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sharma</lname>
<fname>Anjana</fname>
<mname>Rajen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, the characterization of a novel root stimulating bacterium (RSB) is reported and the root stimulating ability of RSB is compared to &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas &lt;/em&gt;and other related bacteria. A morphological examination of RSB was conducted. Nutritional and biochemical characterization was performed in order to obtain a profile of RSB. Pigment analysis indicated the presence of nostoxanthin, a pigment commonly found in &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas &lt;/em&gt;bacteria. Lipid analysis of RSB revealed the presence of sphingolipids in addition to other fatty acids suggesting similarity with other &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas&lt;/em&gt; bacteria. Pulse-field gel electrophoresis of RSB and &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas echinoides&lt;/em&gt; showed a high level of difference in the DNA of these two organisms suggesting difference at least at the strain level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The root stimulating ability of RSB, &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas &lt;/em&gt;and other related bacteria were evaluated using mung bean bioassays. Results of these bioassays suggest that the spent medium used for culturing RSB and &lt;em&gt;Sphingopyxis macrogoltabida &lt;/em&gt;contain acidic and neutral compounds that contribute to their promotion of adventitious root formation whereas the spent medium used to culture &lt;em&gt;Novosphingobium capsulata, Sphingomonas echinoides &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas paucimobilis &lt;/em&gt;contains root stimulating components of acidic nature. Thin layer chromatography of acidic fractions obtained from RSB, &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas echinoides, Sphingomonas paucimobilis, Sphingopyxis macrogoltabida&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Novosphingobium capsulata &lt;/em&gt;spent growth medium showed Rf values close to those for the standards indolelactic acid (ILA) and indoleacetic acid (IAA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on all these tests, RSB most closely resembles bacteria of the &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas &lt;/em&gt;group and the rooting ability observed for RSB is characteristic of some of the &lt;em&gt;Sphingomonas &lt;/em&gt;and related bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2373</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3732&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2373</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3732</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T12:23:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4693503</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2373</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Otto J. Schwarz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Beth C. Mullin, Leslie G. Hickok, Robert N. Trigiano</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>