<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>futurefictions</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:51:50-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mcaoile@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Caoile</lname>
<fname>Mara</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Historic Preservation and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;futurefictions &lt;/em&gt;is the title of my self-directed project which contemplates about the speed in which a city changes over time in order to compose new and dynamic architecture that encourage the preservation of history and cultural resilience through the lens of contemporary urban narratives. The subject of study is Manila, the capital city of the Philippines, and a city that is close to my existence. Manila as a post-colonial society embodies the impact of how the sense of time affects the sense of place: from the remnants of past foreign occupations, to the rapid influence of modern globalization. Manila poses critical dialogues that address contemporary topics related to the speed of growth and change in the developing world. This study explores how architecture can be used to engage the past existence and present realities of the city of Manila into a future that promotes the translation and adaptation of the Filipino identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project suggests a temporary structure that speaks to the dichotomy of permanence and impermanence that define the city of Manila. The architecture is influenced by the tradition of street festivals, and how their permanence in the identity of culture and impermanence in the passing of time speak to the urban resilience that is unique to this city. These festivals are also a reflection of how the network of roads, streets, and different transportation systems are constantly defined and redefined by the different yearly rituals of the city. These rituals are celebrated in the proposed architecture, but also ignite a conversation about how design can be used to reimagine the future narratives of a place.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/architecturedesign/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1172&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1172</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-16T18:01:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11972551</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/architecturedesign/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Akerman</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>