<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Field Experience with the Nutrition Section Dallas City Health Department, Dallas, Texas</title>
<publication-date>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mullis</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>McNeill</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis relates observations and experiences during an eight-week field experience while with the Nutrition Section of the Dallas City Health Department. The purpose of this field experience was to integrate academic theory and practical application in the field of public health nutrition. In addition, the field experience was to provide an opportunity to observe nutritional problems related to the various stages of the life cycle and to work with other ethnic groups, including blacks and Chicanos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience was designed to allow the author to familiarize herself with the philosophy and principles of public health. Through observation and participation in the nutrition program, the author was able to develop her professional skills in public health nutrition. In addition, observation in the various community agencies increased the author&#39;s awareness of the programs provided by these agencies. Planning and implementation of a project provided an opportunity for professional growth and self evaluation of performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience provided insight into the interdisciplinary approach to public health. Throughout the field experience the author was aware of the need for cooperation, coordination, good public relations, and flexibility when directing an effective nutrition program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3996</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5482&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3996</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5482</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-20T11:30:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9152196</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3996</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John T. Smith, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>