<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Age-at-death Estimation: Accuracy and Reliability of Age-Reporting Strategies</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>creilly1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Bailey</lname>
<fname>Christine</fname>
<mname>Ashley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Forensic Anthropology</keyword>
<keyword>Age-at-death Estimation</keyword>
<keyword>Biological Profile</keyword>
<keyword>Age-Reporting Strategies</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;One task of a forensic anthropologist is to assist law enforcement in the identification of unknown human skeletal remains by building a biological profile. Age-at-death estimations are an informative aspect of biological profiles as they help law enforcement narrow down potential victim identifications. However, age-at-death estimation continues to be a challenge within forensic anthropology due to the uncertainty regarding method selection and the production of a final estimate for law enforcement.The purpose of this research is to identify the age-reporting strategies that provide the most accurate and reliable (low inaccuracy and low bias) age-at-death estimations when evaluated by total sample, age-cohort (20-39; 40-59; 60-79), and sex. The age-reporting strategies in this study were derived from six age-at-death estimation methods and tested on 58 adult individuals (31 males and 27 females) from the William M. Bass Donated Skeletal Collection, at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. An experience-based approach where the observer produced a final estimation using the data collected and their expert judgment was included to assess the appropriateness of experience-based estimations in medico-legal contexts. Two-way repeated measures ANOVAs were conducted to determine if there were significant differences in reliability between the age-reporting strategies.The results show that the most accurate and reliable age-reporting strategy varied if the sample was evaluated as a whole, by age, or by sex. The most accurate and reliable strategy for the total sample was the experience-based approach. When the sample was divided by age Suchey-Brooks pubic symphysis performed the best for the 20-39 age-cohort, the experience-based approach for the 40-59 age-cohort, and Buckberry-Chamberlain auricular surface for the 60-79 age-cohort. Finally, when separated by sex, Hartnett pubic symphysis performed the best for males and the experienced-based approach performed the best for females.While none of the age-reporting strategies evaluated in this study were consistently the most accurate and reliable for all of the sample categories, the experience-based approach performed well in each category. This research helps shed light on the performance of different age-reporting strategies and provides further support to the reliance on multiple aging indicators and professional judgment in developing a final age-at-death estimation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5146</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6553&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5146</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6553</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415087</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5146</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dawnie W. Steadman, Giovanna M. Vidoli</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Amy Z. Mundorff</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>