<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ecology of Organohalide-Respiring &lt;i&gt;Dehalococcoides mccartyi&lt;/i&gt;: Corrinoid Cofactor-Related Community Interactions and Controls over Strain Selection</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bsimsir@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Şimşir</lname>
<fname>Burcu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Organohalide-respiration</keyword>
<keyword>corrinoid cofactor</keyword>
<keyword>Dehalococcoides</keyword>
<keyword>reductive dechlorination</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Environmental Microbiology and Microbial Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Organohalides such as tetrachloroethene (PCE) and trichloroethene (TCE) are among the most prevalent toxic groundwater contaminants. Remediation of organohalide-contaminated sites has high priority, and efficient and cost-effective remedies are needed to prevent environment and human exposure through contaminated water. Bacterial organohalide-respiration plays a major role in organohalide detoxification. &lt;em&gt;Dehalococcoides&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;mccartyi&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;are key mediators in bioremediation, since only &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; strains have been documented in complete detoxification of chlorinated ethenes to benign ethene. &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; depends on other microorganisms in the environment for essential growth requirements (e.g., hydrogen and vitamins). For successful implementation of the reductive dechlorination to remediate contaminated sites, microbial interactions controlling &lt;em&gt;Dhc &lt;/em&gt;reductive dechlorination must be elucidated. The overall objective of this research was to address the key gaps in the scientific understanding of the controls over &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; reductive dechlorination activity, including &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; corrinoid-related interactions with other microorganisms. Detailed hydrogeological and microbial characterization of mixed chlorinated solvent contaminated Third Creek site (Knoxville, TN) attributed an important role to the creek sediment, where organohalide-respiring bacteria (e.g., &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dehalobacter&lt;/em&gt;) co-exist, for detoxification of contaminants. Different chlorinated solvent-amendments affected &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; strain selection and non-dechlorinating microbial composition in enrichment cultures derived from Third Creek sediment. Corrinoid-auxotroph &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; require corrinoid cofactor for the reductive dehalogenase enzyme systems. Microorganisms including &lt;em&gt;Acetobacterium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Clostridium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Geobacter&lt;/em&gt;, and methanogens were identified as corrinoid-producers in the enrichment cultures. 5,6-dimethyl-benzimidazole cobamide (DMB-Cba) was the most abundant corrinoid in enrichment cultures to support &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; reductive dechlorination. Different lower base-amendments affected &lt;em&gt;Dhc &lt;/em&gt;reductive dechlorination rates and extents. Lower base-amendments to enrichment cultures caused a shift from production of DMB-Cba to production of corrinoids with the amended lower bases, some of which caused lower dechlorination rates. In addition, different &lt;em&gt;Dhc &lt;/em&gt;strains became abundant with different lower base-amendment in cultures, demonstrating the role of corrinoid in &lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt; strain selection. Lastly this research demonstrated that different geochemical conditions and corresponding microbial populations determined the composition and concentration of bioavailable corrinoid pools; thus directly controlling &lt;em&gt;Dhc &lt;/em&gt;reductive dechlorination activity. The findings of this research are relevant to environmental remediation practitioners and provide valuable information for improving bioremediation strategies to achieve successful contaminated-site cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4111</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5347&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4111</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5347</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-17T09:17:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8745186</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4111</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank E. Löffler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Terry Hazen, Qiang He, Gary Sayler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>