<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>System Fault Tolerancing and Self-Reported Usability of a Closed-Loop Robotic System for Reading Comprehension Skill Development in Children Who are Deaf or Hard of Hearing</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-15T18:26:15-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mmigovic@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Migovich</lname>
<fname>Miroslava</fname>
<mname>I</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biomedical Devices and Instrumentation</discipline>
<discipline>Biomedical Engineering and Bioengineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Children who are deaf or hard of hearing often suffer from low literacy and reading comprehension rates [1]. Over the past 50 years, research had concluded that literacy rates for these children rarely pass a fourth-grade level [2]. However, little research has been done regarding interventions for reading comprehension skill development [3]. Our long-term study seeks to incorporate social robotics and reading comprehension development to provide an option for in-home and in-school reading focused interventions. In the current study, we present an initial validation of a closed-loop social robotic system for reading comprehension testing. Results suggest our robot-based system is capable of recording and interpreting human responses and can provide contingent feedback to answers to evidence-derived reading comprehension questions. The system demonstrated few errors and was found to be acceptable, falling within the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; quartile range when compared to other studies, according to the System Usability Scale (SUS) [4]. These results demonstrate the potential utility of the system with the target population; additional testing with age-matched participants is needed to verify the relationship between errors and SUS scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords—Social Robotics, Reading Comprehension, System Usability, Deaf or Hard of Hearing&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/engineering/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1245&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1245</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-15T14:57:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14266911</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/engineering/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Tickle College of Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical, Aerospace, and Biomedical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>