<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of the Pet Loss Support Hotline: The Impact of Pet Loss on Pet Owners</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lremilla@uoguelph.ca</email>
<lname>Rémillard</lname>
<fname>Liam</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research has shown that human grief due to pet loss (i.e. sudden death or euthanasia of a pet) is similar to the grief symptoms of people who have experienced the death of a significant other. Telephone helplines and support groups for people who are experiencing grief are commonplace in society. However, only recently have hotlines emerged as a means of providing assistance for pet owners in dealing with the death of their pets. At present there is minimal research evaluating the value of these services and callers’ grief. The present study aims to evaluate the value of the Ontario Veterinary College Guelph Pet Loss Support Hotline (PLSH) and also to identify factors associated with grief among the callers. The first stage of research involved content analysis of written notes about calls to the hotline. General themes emerging from the content analysis include a lack of social support, strong human-animal bond, and symptoms of severe or complicated grief. In addition, callers noted behavioural, psychological and somatic challenges resulting from their loss. The&lt;a&gt;[MM1]&lt;/a&gt; results of this study informed the second stage of research involving developing a survey to be sent to hotline callers and pet owners who did not contact the hotline but have experienced pet loss. The survey includes items evaluating the role and value of the PLSH and validated measures of grief, pet attachment, pet and human attachment orientation, social support, and general health., Stage two findings will inform training of PLSH volunteers and improve our understanding of pet loss grief.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/26</coverpage-url>
<label>26</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1084</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-13T14:08:54-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3697197</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/26</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T18:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Poster: Scheduled poster session</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Grief and bereavement</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>