<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Reanalysis of the Osteological and Cultural Remains from Ausmus Burial Cave, Claiborne County, Tennessee (3CE20)</title>
<publication-date>1989-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tucker</lname>
<fname>Carole</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Few excavations or analyses of remains from burial caves have been published. Those that are reported are frequently cited without considering context of the original excavations and analyses. This consideration is important, because previously collected data would be interpreted differently using modern approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study is a reanalysis of Ausmus Burial Cave (3CE20), Claiborne County, Tennessee. The site was excavated in the 1930&#39;s, and the authors&#39; methodology, conclusion, and conjectures reflect this time. Their hypothesis was that the skeletons represented intruders in the area, they were killed in battle, and their bodies were dropped unceremoniously in the pit cave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reanalysis: (1) describes the data more completely and from current perspectives, (2) responds to questions concerning human interment in pit caves, and (3) includes additional skeletal material, discovered in 1975.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is concluded that at least 25 Late Woodland/Early Mississippian individuals were recovered from 3CE20. They represent both genders and all age groups, except fetal. There is no statistical difference in age distribution between 3CE20 and other Norris Basin sites of the same time period. The same results are found when 3CE20 individuals are compared to the Late Woodland Hamilton component individuals of Hiwassee Island (42MG31, 46MG31, 47MG31, 73MG31, 78MG31).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistically significant differences in gender exist between 3CE20 and a 50:50 ratio. However, this result may be spurious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paleopathological analysis reveals that several pathologies were undetected in the original report or were misdiagnosed. These findings are significant and place serious doubt upon the original interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4221</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5687&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4221</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5687</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-07T10:31:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9448776</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4221</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>P. S. Willey</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Maria O. Smith, Charles H. Faulkner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1989-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1989-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>