<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development and Validation of the Social Justice Behavior Scale</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lflood@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Flood</lname>
<fname>Lee</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Despite social justice leadership receiving an increasing amount of attention by researchers, a methodological imbalance with qualitative inquiries dominating the existing empirical literature base persists. Compounding this issue is the lack of a discipline-specific, quantitative instrument made for the exact purpose of exploring the nature of social justice leadership. This study aimed to answer the calls of a number of scholars (Jean-Marie, Normore, &amp; Brooks, 2009; Nilsson, Marszalek, Linnemeyer, Bahner, &amp; Misialek, 2011; Otunga, 2009) by developing and validating a scale. The Social Justice Behavior Scale (SJBS) was developed through the creation of items based on a literature review, informed directly by a meta-analysis, and refined through the Delphi Technique. Surveys were digitally distributed to principals in the United States. The final dataset consisted of 227 principals from 27 states. Following a principal components analysis with oblimin rotation, the SJBS was found to have three components made up of 23 items that accounted for 62.16% of the total variance. Cronbach’s alpha for the entire instrument was .933. The SJBS shows promise as a quantitative research instrument moving forward. Future recommendations include collecting additional data to run a confirmatory factor analysis, distributing the instrument in additional contexts, and bolstering future investigations into social justice leadership through the use of the SJBS as a research tool.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5367</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6903&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5367</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6903</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545375</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5367</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Pamela Angelle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Morrow, Gary Skolits, James McIntyre</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>