<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Black Flies (&lt;em&gt;Simuliidae:Diptera&lt;/em&gt;) of the Great Smoky Mountain National Park and Vicinity</title>
<publication-date>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Traore</lname>
<fname>Sitan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Larval black flies were collected monthly from four selected streams in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park between June 1991 and July 1992. One large size (13 m wide Little River), one small (1m wide Tipton Place) and two medium sized streams, one in the sun (6.45 m wide Mill Creek site #1) and one in the shade (6m wide Mill creek site #2) streams and additional creeks in Knox, Monroe, Morgan, Blount counties in eastern Tennessee and Haywood County in western North Carolina will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larvae of &lt;em&gt;Simulium tuberosum&lt;/em&gt; (Lundstrom) complex, &lt;em&gt;S. venustum/ verecundum&lt;/em&gt; Say, &lt;em&gt;S. quebecense&lt;/em&gt; Twinn, &lt;em&gt;S.pamassum&lt;/em&gt; Malloch, &lt;em&gt;S. impar&lt;/em&gt; Davies, Peterson, &amp; Wood, &lt;em&gt;Prosimulium mixtum&lt;/em&gt; Syme &amp; Davies, and &lt;em&gt;Stegoptema mutata&lt;/em&gt; Malloch were collected from leaves, sticks and rocks submerged in water from different collection sites. &lt;em&gt;S.tuberosum&lt;/em&gt; larvae or pupae were present almost year around, while &lt;em&gt;S. venustum/verecundum&lt;/em&gt; were present only in October, November, March, April and May in the four streams and rivers. &lt;em&gt;P. mixtum&lt;/em&gt; larvae were collected when the water temperature was lowest in December, January, February,March and a few in April. &lt;em&gt;S. quebecense&lt;/em&gt; larvae were rare and collected only in March, April,and May. &lt;em&gt;S. pamassum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;S. impar&lt;/em&gt; were collected from medium size and small size creeks. &lt;em&gt;Stegoptema mutata&lt;/em&gt; was found only from Tipton Place and from an unnamed creek in Morgan County. &lt;em&gt;P. magnum&lt;/em&gt; was collected mainly in Knox County. Some rare species such as &lt;em&gt;P. arvum, P. rhyzophorum&lt;/em&gt; were collected in Knox County and &lt;em&gt;S. loerchae&lt;/em&gt; in Sevier County from an unnamed small creek near Pigeon River.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chromosome identification was used to separate sibling species of black flies. Our study of chromosome identification indicated that &lt;em&gt;S. tuberosum&lt;/em&gt; species complex consisted of FG/CDE, FG, CKL and A, the &lt;em&gt;S. venustum&lt;/em&gt; cytospecies was CC, and &lt;em&gt;S. verecundum&lt;/em&gt; cytospecies was AA, &lt;em&gt;Stegopterna mutata&lt;/em&gt; would found to be diploid cytospecies. Future research will further address species differentiation with chromosome identification.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3294</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4731&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3294</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4731</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-01T12:49:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6932071</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3294</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Reid R. Gerhardt</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles D. Pless, Earnest Bernard</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>