<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Aqueous Micellar Gels of Multiresponsive Hydrophilic ABA Linear Triblock Copolymers</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jwoodcoc@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Woodcock</lname>
<fname>Jeremiah</fname>
<mname>Wallace</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Thermo Sensitive</keyword>
<keyword>random copolymer</keyword>
<keyword>Light responsive</keyword>
<keyword>enzyme triggered</keyword>
<keyword>monomer</keyword>
<keyword>NMR</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Laboratory and Basic Science Research</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation presents the synthesis of a series of well-defined multiresponsive hydrophilic ABA linear triblock copolymers and the study of their aqueous micellar gels. By incorporating a small amount of stimuli-responsive groups into thermosensitive outer blocks of ABA triblock copolymers, the lower critical solution temperatures (LCST) of thermosensitive blocks can be modified by external stimuli. Consequently, the sol-gel transition temperatures (&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt;) of their aqueous solutions can be altered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1 describes the synthesis and solution behavior of a series of thermo- and light-sensitive triblock copolymers, poly(ethoxytri(ethylene glycol) acrylate-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;-nitrobenzyl acrylate)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-poly(ethylene oxide)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-poly(ethoxytri(ethylene glycol) acrylate-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;-nitrobenzyl acrylate), with different contents of light-responsive &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;-nitrobenzyl groups. Aqueous solutions of these block copolymers with a 10.0 wt% concentration exhibited thermo-induced sol-gel transitions. Upon UV irradiation, the hydrophobic &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;-nitrobenzyl groups were cleaved, resulting in an increase in the LCST and consequently gel-to-sol transitions. The UV-irradiated solutions again underwent temperature-induced sol-gel transitions but at higher temperatures. The change of &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt; was, in general, larger for the copolymer with a higher&lt;em&gt; o&lt;/em&gt;-nitrobenzyl content after UV irradiation. Chapter 2 presents the synthesis of thermo- and enzyme-responsive ABA triblock copolymers, poly(ethoxydi(ethylene glycol) acrylate-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-4-((dihydroxyphosphoryl)oxy)butyl acrylate)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-poly(ethylene oxide)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-poly(ethoxydi(ethylene glycol) acrylate-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-4-((dihydroxyphosphoryl)oxy)butyl acrylate), and the enzyme-induced formation of thermoreversible micellar gels from their moderately concentrated aqueous solutions at 37 °C. The dephosphorylation by acid phosphatase decreased the LCST of thermosensitive outer blocks from above to below 37 °C. The enzyme-induced gelation of 7.9 wt % aqueous polymer solutions at pH 4.4 was monitored by rheological measurements. The &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt; decreased and the gel strength increased with the increase of reaction time. The gels formed were thermoreversible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3 presents the synthesis of two thermo- and pH-sensitive tertiary amine-containing ABA triblock copolymers and the sol-gel transitions of their aqueous solutions with a 10 wt% concentration at different pH values. Chapter 4 describes the use of reversible addition-fragmentation chain transfer (RAFT) polymerization for the synthesis of well-defined thermosensitive polymethacrylates and polyacrylates. Eight chain transfer agents were synthesized. The RAFT polymerizations of alkoxyoligo(ethylene glycol) (meth)acrylates using these chain transfer agents were well controlled, producing well-defined polymers. A summary of this dissertation research and future work are presented in Chapter 5.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1239</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2331&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1239</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2331</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-10-03T11:18:47-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2331/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2271548</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1239</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bin Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George kabalka, Wei He, Michael Kilbey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>