<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Critical Case Study of Program Fidelity in TennCare</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-08T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cmyers9@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Myers</lname>
<fname>Carole</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
<suffix>Dr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Purpose: The purpose of this study was to evaluate the fidelity of the design of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennessee’s Medicaid managed care program in comparison to the actual program&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operation. Program fidelity is a broad measurement of how true the implemented&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;program is to the intended program (Heflinger &amp; Northrup, 2000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: In the span of only 15 years, the introduction of managed care and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;other market-based strategies from the private sector precipitated a transformation of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;delivery of Medicaid services in the United States. These monumental changes remain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;poorly understood. The implementation of managed care in Tennessee’s Medicaid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;program is an excellent public policy exemplar because of the far-reaching scope of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;program and the ongoing development of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Method: A hallmark of case study research is that detailed information is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;collected from multiple sources (Creswell, 2003; Feagin, Orum and Sjoberg, 1991;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stake, 2000; Yin, 2003). Source data for this single case study design included&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;interview data from key stakeholders and a variety of documents. Documents analyzed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;included: newspaper and journal articles; correspondences; the original TennCare and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TennCare Partners waiver applications; judicial decrees; legislative documents; task&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;force reports; and other case studies. Interviews were conducted with 26 informants,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;including two former Governors of Tennessee; a former HCFA Administrator; a variety of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;state government and managed care executives and advocates; and a complement of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;provider representatives including administrators, managers and caregivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Themes were developed to organize the vast amount of interview data. The&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;salience of themes that emerged in early interviews were challenged, clarified and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;further distilled by an iterative process of content analysis and data triangulation that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;included multiple close readings of interview transcripts and documents, clarification and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;testing of ideas with selected stakeholders and confirmation of details with document&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sources. The triangulation of retrospective recollections of events and key impressions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;captured in recorded interviews with a wide variety of time-stable documents provided a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rich understanding of people and events that shaped the development and operation of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TennCare. Each theme was also organized and developed through the construction of a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;chronological history of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings: An intricate web of circumstances and people shaped the initial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;development and evolution of TennCare. Although TennCare has been successful in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;extending health care coverages, this success has been overshadowed by a myriad of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operational problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thematic analysis illuminated both the promises and failures of TennCare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three themes were prominent in the telling of the TennCare story: authority,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;management and fragmentation. Governor McWherter (1987-1995), the creator of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TennCare, established a strong executive authority to model and implement TennCare;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a void was created when he left office. Subsequent administrations have not adequately&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;transitioned to a more balanced and inclusive authoritative structure, nor have they&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;developed an adequate oversight model. Continued mismanagement of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;administration of benefits and failure to meet established care standards set the stage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for the imposition of federal judiciary authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;vi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management of the operational phase of TennCare has largely been reactionary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and politicized and, in many instances, inappropriately abdicated or conferred upon the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;wrong or unprepared people or entities. Turmoil and turnover in state government&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hindered stabilization of the program. The stability and evolution of the marketplace that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McWherter expected has not been broadly realized; the state has retreated from basic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;managed care principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state failed to integrate the management the health, behavioral health and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pharmacy carve-outs. This fragmentation resulted in diffuse accountability across&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;vendors and within state government, unnecessary duplication of services, gaps in the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;delivery and management of patient care and increased patient hassle and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More broadly, the state was found to have conflicting roles as both the manager of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;behavioral health vendors and a direct provider of behavioral health services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web of connectivity between themes changed over time, as themes presented&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as a cause, catalyst or consequence of the others at different times in TennCare&#39;s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;history. A poignant example of this connectivity is how the mismanagement of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TennCare program after the initial implementation led to the breakdown in key alliances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the eventual imposition of federal judicial authority in the form of the consent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;decrees. Consent decrees resulted in reactive and disjointed management which&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;significantly contributed to the gap between what was envisioned for TennCare and what&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;actually resulted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: The study illustrated that an intricate web of circumstances and people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;shaped the initial development and evolution of TennCare, a program designed to solve&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a state-level problem with national implications. Although TennCare has been&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;successful in increasing the number of Tennesseans with health care coverage, these&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;successes have been overshadowed by pervasive operational problems, a failure to fully&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;implement basic building blocks of managed care, such as risk-sharing and competition,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and effectively manage the vendors employed by the state. Conclusions related to the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;three themes show a pattern of missed opportunities and a troubling inability to transition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from the chaos of TennCare’s implementation to effective program operation. The&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;illuminated themes will be informative to planners of similar state initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/80</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1095&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>80</label>
<document-type>unpublished_paper</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1095</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-22T07:25:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1473174</context-key>
<withdrawn>2016-12-02</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/80</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-08T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Dissertation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>