<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Time Series Analysis of MODIS NDVI data with Cloudy Pixels: Frequency-domain and SiZer analyses of vegetation change in Western Rwanda</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>elove4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Love</lname>
<fname>Ephraim</fname>
<mname>Robert</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Spatial Statistics</keyword>
<keyword>GAM</keyword>
<keyword>Frequency Domain</keyword>
<keyword>Rwanda</keyword>
<keyword>NDVI</keyword>
<keyword>Remote Sensing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>African Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Environmental Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Geographic Information Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Nature and Society Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Peace and Conflict Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Physical and Environmental Geography</discipline>
<discipline>Policy Design, Analysis, and Evaluation</discipline>
<discipline>Remote Sensing</discipline>
<discipline>Social Policy</discipline>
<discipline>Spatial Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Remote sensing is a valuable source of data for the study of human ecology in rural areas. In this thesis, I attempt to analyze the presence of a long-term trend indicative of post-resettlement adaptation in the vegetation signals of Western Rwanda. There is a dearth of research utilizing medium resolution imagery to study difficult environments, such as tropical-montane regions, where complex topography and cloud cover diminish image accuracy. I attempt to add to the extant literature on frequency-domain smoothing methods as well as the literature on human-environment interaction in tropical-montane regions by applying a &lt;em&gt;harmonic filtering and smoothing algorithm&lt;/em&gt; to the ‘MOD13Q1’, 16-day composite, 250m, NDVI, MODIS imagery. To create a more robust time-series, I combine Gaussian generalized additive models and discrete Fourier analysis of the residuals to impute values to a filtered time series, based on MODIS’s own pixel reliability data. These methods significantly improve the quality of the time-series being analyzed, compared with the raw data, or imputation of the mean signal. To control for conflating variables, I take a &lt;em&gt;difference-in-differences&lt;/em&gt; (DD) approach (Abadie, 2005) comparing resettled regions to older regions, identified in Google Earth. Harmonic filtering and smoothing shows a definite long-term trend of post-resettlement changes in the vegetation signal, demonstrated by the DD approach, analyzed in SiZer maps (Chaudhuri &amp; Marron, 1999). Further research will be needed to determine whether this is indicative of cropping changes, or other impacts of post-resettlement adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3389</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4754&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3389</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4754</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-13T06:36:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6974753</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3389</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Nicholas N. Nagle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Liem Tran, Yingkui Li</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>