<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Detection of Biomarkers of Potential Pathogens in Varied Matrices</title>
<publication-date>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medical Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Methods that use signature biomarkers have become increasingly important in the field of environmental microbiology. Signature lipid biomarker (SLB) analysis is a method of analysis for the quantitative definition of viable biomass, community composition, and nutritional status of microbiota isolated from a wide variety of environmental matrices, including air, soil and water. Biomarkers examined in this thesis were glyco- and phospholipids, and dipicolinic acid. Organisms tested were &lt;em&gt;Cryptosporidium parvum, C. baileyi, C. muris, &lt;/em&gt;Eimeria tenella, E. acervulina, E. maxima, Escherichia coli, &lt;em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three species of &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cryptosporidium &lt;/em&gt;were examined using &lt;/em&gt;signature lipid biomarker analysis. This analysis was successfully applied to the species-specific identification of &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;C. parvum, C. baileyi &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;C. muris. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;The glycolipid fraction from the SLB analysis was also examined for &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;C. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;parvum &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;, as the possibility of a unique biomarker (10-hydroxy stearic acid) &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;was present in research done by others. This compound was shown to be an artifact of sample preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SLB analysis was also used to examine the phospholipids of &lt;em&gt;Eimeria &lt;/em&gt;tenella, E. acervulina, &lt;em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;E. maxima&lt;/em&gt;. This analysis clearly differentiated &lt;/em&gt;these three species from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SLB analysis was also used to examine chlorine-injured &lt;em&gt;Escherichia &lt;/em&gt;coli &lt;em&gt;. The experiments presented herein ensure the validity of oxirane fatty &lt;/em&gt;acids as indicators of sterilization efficiency. The detection of epoxidated fatty acids firmly establishes that the cells have been in contact with hypochlorite, thus providing a chemical marker for hypochlorite exposure and sterility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the examination of dipicolinic acid from endospores, a new extraction and methylation technique was devised and GC/MS analysis was employed for the detection of dimethyl dipicolinate. Preliminary studies also evaluated spectrofluorometric analysis using terbium chloride. &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis &lt;/em&gt;spores were detected using the new in situ SFE extraction and methylation technique and GC/MS with a lower limit of quantification of 3 x 104 spores in a sand mixture, and the lower limit of detection was observed to be 3 x 103 spores.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1990</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3349&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1990</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3349</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T10:10:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4639817</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1990</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. White</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gary Stacey, Thomas C. Montie, Robert N. Moore</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>