<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>From Management to Sustainability:  Strategies for Producers, Consumers, and Small Businesses; Journal:  Journal of Management and Sustainability</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Hunter</lname>
<fname>Maria</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>JC</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Hospitality Administration and Management</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The effects of climate change and other stressors on the agricultural sector provide proof that the need to achieve agricultural sustainability is a legitimate issue that should be addressed immediately. The ultimate financial benefits to achieving sustainability are immense. This study investigated the causes of climate change and reported how it directly and indirectly affects the agricultural sector of the Southeastern Region of the United States. We concluded that crops vary with the different adaptation strategies and with the predicted rise in temperature and fluctuation in precipitation. It is essential for producers to monitor closely their previous growing seasons. Long term investments include plant breeding, rotating crops, building infrastructure, and mitigation systems. Climate awareness and its impacts on agriculture by consumers, producers, and policymakers are essential to develop adaptation strategies to mitigate the effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_retapubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_retapubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-31T11:01:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Retail, Hospitality, and Tourism Management Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4948172</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_retapubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-31T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>