<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Architectural Microcosm: From City to Building</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jin</lname>
<fname>Qi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STATEMENT OF THESIS/HYPOTHESIS &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis explores the reciprocal relationship of the building and the city. I argue that the building can be a microcosm of the city, as Alberti has said: &quot; . . . for if a city, according to the opinion of philosophers be no more than a great house, and on the other hand the house be a little city . . .&quot;&lt;sup&gt;1 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In demonstrating the interrelationship of building and city as reciprocals, I have analyzed three precedents, which will inform my design approach. Based on Kevin Lynch&#39;s analysis&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, I have identified five fundamental elements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;District&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Path&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Node&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landmark&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these elements are common to most cities and buildings, I argue that specific design is developed based on transformative factors in two broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socio-cultural factors, arising from cultural tradition and social norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical factors, arising from physical settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I will demonstrate that a building with physical and spatial continuity to its city environment can be fully involved in the urban context. It connects the urban fabric physically and programmatically. In my design thesis, I will argue that the building can be interpreted as a microcosm of the city in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have selected Knoxville, Tennessee, because it is a typical example of 20&lt;sup&gt;th &lt;/sup&gt;century American urbanism: a grid with a central business district, pockets of urban decay, and ambiguous sprawl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have selected a specific vacant site in downtown area, which is the best representation of Knoxville&#39;s urban fabric. I have decided to provide a multi-use Institute of Culinary School, because the programmatic and structural diversity of such a building represents the diversity of a city, in both physical and programmatic aspects. Through my design, I will demonstrate that a building can be a microcosm of its city context in a reciprocal way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXPLANATION OF MY HYPOTHESIS &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A city is a network of spaces, in which Kevin Lynch identified the importance of paths, nodes, edges, districts, and landmarks. The city is defined by particular parts within it. A building, as one of the units of the city, has structural coherence with the city. The building is organized to some degree much like a city. In a building, &quot;paths&quot; are the circulation zones, &quot;nodes&#39; are more active areas within the building based on program or movement, &quot;edges&quot; define spaces, &quot;districts&quot; are differentiated areas in a building often for differentiated users, and &quot;landmarks&quot; are the critical focal points within a building. In this way, a building can be understood as a small city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A city and its parts exchange their analogies of structure between the spaces, e.g. corridor/street, courtyard/square, etc. We can suppose that these two systems, a city and a building, can have the same geometrical characteristics of spatial forms, but at different scales. &quot;They are differentiated only by the dimensions of the walls which bound them and by the patterns of function and circulation which characterize them.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;3 &lt;/sup&gt; We can picture this sort of unity by taking the logic of a public place into the interior of the building. Moreover, a building can also have the same diversity of functions. Both cities and buildings are platforms for events. Buildings are not isolated and self-contained sculptures. They play an explicit part in the continuity of the urban fabric and the urban social life. Thus a building can be a microcosm of a city by the similarity of physical structure and programmatic structure. I advocate that the city and its buildings form a reciprocal relationship. The more involved a building is with the form and content of its surroundings, the more those surroundings become appropriated by the building. And just as a building changes the image of its surroundings, so the surroundings will change the image of the building. This reciprocal relationship states that a city and its buildings reinforce each other and interact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will explore this hypothesis in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Through program (mixed use)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Through a design strategy which focuses on the utilization of path, node, edge,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;district and landmark&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Through a design in which the building and its context are inextricably linked&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4482</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6013&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4482</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6013</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-12T09:56:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10010202</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4482</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marleen K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Scott Wall, Barbara Klinkhammer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>