<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SP291-A-Growing Vegetable Transplants for Home Gardens</title>
<publication-date>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Gardening</keyword>
<keyword>Vegetable</keyword>
<keyword>Transplants</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Some of the most frequently grown and productive vegetables are commonly set into the garden as transplants. These include tomatoes, peppers, eggplant, headlettuce, cabbage, cauliflower, broccoli and brussels sprouts. Other vegetables that are some times set as trans plants include kohlrabi, can ta loupe, watermelon, summer squash, okra and cucumbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several advantages to using trans plants rather than direct seeding. Even more advantages can be realized from pro duc ing your own transplants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transplants allow you to replace early-harvested vegetables immediately and to produce an oth er crop quickly. Yield losses from poor ger mi na tion are eliminated. Pro duc ing your own trans plants allows control of factors such as cultivar, plant size and contain er material and size. The chanc es of introducing insects or diseases into the gar den are reduced. There is also assurance of trans plant availability if they are home grown.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexgard/37</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=utk_agexgard&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>37</label>
<document-type>vegselect</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1036</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-15T07:23:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Home Garden, Lawn, and Landscape</publication-title>
<context-key>1275917</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexgard/37</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>SP291A-10M-8/94(Rev) E12-2015-00-046-95</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>