<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pinpointing the Molecular Basis for Metal Ion Effects on Plasminogen Activator Inhibitor-1 (PAI-1)</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jbucci@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bucci</lname>
<fname>Joel</fname>
<mname>Cullen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Biophysics</discipline>
<discipline>Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Plasminogen activator inhibitor type-1 (PAI-1) specifically inhibits the proteases tissue type plasminogen activator and urokinase plasminogen activator to control the activation of fibrinolysis. Vitronectin interacts with PAI-1 primarily through the somatomedin B (SMB) domain to stabilize and localize PAI-1 to sites of injury. Our laboratory observed that transition metals such as copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; have VN dependent, reciprocal effects on how long PAI-1 remains active. We aim to determine the molecular basis for effects of copper&lt;sup&gt;2+ &lt;/sup&gt;on PAI-1 activity. We employed a computational algorithm (MUG) to predict metal binding clusters, and introduced mutations hypothesized to create metal binding deficiency. We compared mutants to wild-type by: measurement of stability kinetics, thermodynamic parameters using isothermal titration calorimetry, and protein dynamics using hydrogen deuterium exchange. Active PAI-1 binds copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; in the low nanomolar range, while latent binds an order of magnitude weaker. In a mutant lacking the N-terminal histidines of PAI-1, we observed reduced copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; binding, but this does not abolish accelerated transition to the latent form. PAI-1 mutants lacking the carboxylate containing resides in the gate region, as well as a histidine of s4B proximal to the flexible joint region require more copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; than wild-type to promote accelerated latency formation, making these residues candidates for further metal binding characterization. SMB-PAI-1 complex binds copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; with comparable affinity and stoichiometry as PAI-1 alone. Finally, the SMB domain stabilizes PAI-1 by localized effects on dynamics in the same regions that are affected by copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, binding of SMB does not sterically interfere with copper binding to PAI-1, but rather negates copper&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; effects directly through changes in dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3896</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5212&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3896</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5212</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-26T13:03:18-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5212/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8225969</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3896</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cynthia Peterson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Elizabeth Howell, Engin Serpersu, Rebecca Prosser, Michael Best</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>