<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hankel Operators on the Drury-Arveson Space</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jsunkes@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sunkes</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Complex Analysis</keyword>
<keyword>Operator Theory</keyword>
<keyword>Hankel Operators</keyword>
<keyword>Drury-Arveson Space</keyword>
<keyword>Function Theory</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Analysis</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Drury-Arveson space, initially introduced in the proof of a generalization of von Neumann&#39;s inequality, has seen a lot of research due to its intrigue as a Hilbert space of analytic functions. This space has been studied in the context of Besov-Sobolev spaces, Hilbert spaces with complete Nevanlinna Pick kernels, and Hilbert modules. More recently, McCarthy and Shalit have studied the connections between the Drury-Arveson space and Hilbert spaces of Dirichlet series, and Davidson and Cloutare have established analogues of classic results of the ball algebra to the multiplier algebra for the Drury-Arveson Space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this dissertation is to contribute to this growing body of research by studying the Hankel operators on the Drury-Arveson Space. We begin by establishing basic results regarding the function theoretic properties of the Drury-Arveson space and general properties of Hankel operators. It is then shown that every invariant subspace of the d-shift on the Drury-Arveson space is an at most countable intersection of kernels of Hankel operators. We then prove that if a function and its reciprocal lie in the Drury-Arveson space, then that function must be a cyclic vector. In addition, we prove that each multiplier invariant subspace on the vector-valued Drury-Arveson space is an intersection of kernels of vectorial Hankel operators, and we characterize a special class of symbols which induce a bounded Hankel operator in terms of a Carleson measure condition on the symbol.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3750</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5187&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3750</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5187</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-25T20:02:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8219609</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3750</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stefan Richter</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mike Frazier, Carl Sundberg, Michael Berry</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>