<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthetic Turf Surface Temperature Reduction and Performance Characteristics as Affected by Calcined Clay Modified Infill</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ereasor@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Reasor</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>Hall</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Synthetic Turf</keyword>
<keyword>Calcined Clay</keyword>
<keyword>Temperature</keyword>
<keyword>Irrigation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Other Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Other Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Synthetic turf research plots containing crumb rubber (CR) infill were established in Knoxville, TN in 2012 and 2013. Calcined clay (CC) was amended to CR in several ratios: a 50:50 (vol vol-1) blend; a 50:50 blend with a polymer coating on CC (50 CR:50 CCC); a 15 mm layer of CC under 15 mm of CR (CR over CC); and a 15 mm layer of CC over 15 mm of CR (CC over CR). A 100% CR and a 70:30 blend of CR to sand (70 CR:30 S) were included for comparison. Surface temperature was measured in the summer of 2012 and 2013 at -10, 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, and 150 minutes following 2.8 cm of irrigation. Irrigation reduced surface temperature 60 to 85% regardless of treatment. By 30 minutes after irrigation, surface temperature increased to 74 to 102% of the temperature recorded 10 minutes prior to irrigation. Temperature on the 50 CR:50 CC and CC over CR treatments 150 minutes after irrigation were 10 to 24% and 20 to 21% lower than the hottest surfaces, which ranged from 95 to 137% of the pre-irrigation temperature. Simulated traffic was applied using the Cady Traffic Simulator for a total of 180 traffic events each year. Trends in surface hardness among treatments were inconsistent over years with values ranging from 70 to 160. CC modified infill treatments resulted in a faster increase of surface hardness with traffic compared to 100% CR and 70:30 S. Traffic affected particle size diameter of infill materials. Infill particles ranging in size from 3.35 to 1.0 mm decreased in diameter an average of 1.0 to 12.0%. Particles ranging from 1.0 to &lt;0.002 mm increased in diameter an average of 0.3 to 3.8%. This increase in size was least pronounced for the 100% and 70 CR:30 S treatments and most pronounced for treatment CC over CR. Significant temperature differences were not consistent among treatments and surface hardness with CC tended to measure higher than 100% CR and 70 CR:30 S. The results of this experiment indicate the use of CC in synthetic turf may be limited.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2750</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3940&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2750</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3940</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-24T06:27:52-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3940/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5192802</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2750</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John C. Sorochan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James T. Brosnan, Thomas J. Samples</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>