<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>How To Put the Thanks Back In</title>
<publication-date>1970-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has been in municipal government for very long knows what a thankless job it can be. Public pats-on-the-back are few and far between. The Tennessee Municipal Guide Series is designed to help put the &quot;thanks&quot; back in. It&#39;s not a cure-all, but if used properly it can certainly lead to a more successful and appreciated operation. The specific purpose of the guides is to give you a general, over-all look at what is involved in, and what it takes to do each of the more common jobs a municipal government performs. Hopefully, this &quot;portrait of a city&quot; will inspire concrete efforts to enhance, or improve your services.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/65</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1064&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>65</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1064</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-08T07:00:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2646704</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/65</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Tennessee Municipal Guide Series. &lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1970-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>