<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Creating Culturally Relevant Instructional Materials: A Swaziland Case Study</title>
<publication-date>2013-07-23T12:05:50-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Villanova University</institution>
<lname>Titone</lname>
<fname>Connie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Villanova University</institution>
<lname>Plummer</lname>
<fname>Emily</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Villanova University</institution>
<lname>Kielar</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the field of English language learning, research proves that culturally relevant reading materials improve students’ language acquisition, learning motivation, self-esteem, and identity formation. Since English is the language of instruction in many distant countries, such as Swaziland, even when English is not the native language of those countries, how can native English speakers most easily produce and expand the reach of culturally relevant materials for foreign settings that require English materials? In a study involving undergraduate university students, the researchers investigate the extent to which individuals recognize and demonstrate the importance of cultural context and relevance when creating their own books for Swaziland students. From the study, it is clear that the focus must shift from simple book production and donation to first gaining a deeper understanding of the relationship between the learners’ lived realities and the cultural content depicted in the materials. The researchers conclude that five distinct characteristics should be present in instructional material in order to increase the engagement, language acquisition, and self-worth of the English Language Learner.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1215</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-23T11:23:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>4339027</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>A Swaziland Case Study</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>