<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sensitivity of a real-time PCR method for the detection of transgenes in a mixture of transgenic and non-transgenic seeds of papaya (&lt;em&gt;Carica papaya&lt;/em&gt; L.)</title>
<publication-date>2013-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mnrao@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nageswara-Rao</lname>
<fname>Madhugiri</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ckwit@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kwit</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>sagarwal@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Agarwa</lname>
<fname>Sujata</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mpatton6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Patton</lname>
<fname>Mariah</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jskeen5@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Skeen</lname>
<fname>Jordan</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University</institution>
<lname>Skeen</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Hawaii</institution>
<lname>Manshardt</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>nealstewart@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stewart</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
<mname>Neal</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Coat protein (CP)</keyword>
<keyword>Genetically-engineered</keyword>
<keyword>Papain</keyword>
<keyword>Quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR)</keyword>
<keyword>Seeds</keyword>
<keyword>Transgene</keyword>
<keyword>Virus resistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genetically engineered (GE) ringspot virus-resistant papaya cultivars ‘Rainbow’ and ‘SunUp’ have been grown in Hawai’i for over 10 years. In Hawai’i, the introduction of GE papayas into regions where non-GE cultivars are grown and where feral non-GE papayas exist have been accompanied with concerns associated with transgene flow. Of particular concern is the possibility of transgenic seeds being found in non-GE papaya fruits via cross-pollination. Development of high-throughput methods to reliably detect the adventitious presence of such transgenic material would benefit both the scientific and regulatory communities.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assessed the accuracy of using conventional qualitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) as well as real-time PCR-based assays to quantify the presence of transgenic DNA from bulk samples of non-GE papaya seeds. In this study, an optimized method of extracting high quality DNA from dry seeds of papaya was standardized. A reliable, sensitive real-time PCR method for detecting and quantifying viral coat protein (&lt;em&gt;cp&lt;/em&gt;) transgenes in bulk seed samples utilizing the endogenous &lt;em&gt;papain&lt;/em&gt; gene is presented. Quantification range was from 0.01 to 100 ng/μl of GE-papaya DNA template with a detection limit as low as 0.01% (10 pg). To test this system, we simulated transgene flow using known quantities of GE and non-GE DNA and determined that 0.038% (38 pg) GE papaya DNA could be detected using real-time PCR. We also validated this system by extracting DNA from known ratios of GE seeds to non-GE seeds of papaya followed by real-time PCR detection and observed a reliable detection limit of 0.4%.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method for the quick and sensitive detection of transgenes in bulked papaya seed lots using conventional as well as real-time PCR-based methods will benefit numerous stakeholders. In particular, this method could be utilized to screen selected fruits from maternal non-GE papaya trees in Hawai’i for the presence of transgenic seed at typical regulatory threshold levels. Incorporation of subtle differences in primers and probes for variations in &lt;em&gt;cp&lt;/em&gt; worldwide should allow this method to be utilized elsewhere when and if deregulation of transgenic papaya occurs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/65</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1065&amp;amp;context=utk_planpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>65</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1065</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-09T13:19:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4567481</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/65</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>&lt;em&gt;BMC Biotechnology&lt;/em&gt; 2013, 13:69 doi:10.1186/1472-6750-13-69</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-09-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>