<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Revitalization of urban waterfronts in port cities : the case of New York and Boston</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Ramalhosa</lname>
<fname>Francisca</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to study urban revitalization in old port areas in the United States, which for various reasons are no longer used for port activities, specifically the cases of New York and Boston.  In the 1960s, changes in port technology and transportation systems led to major transformations in port activities. Waterfronts that for years were used exclusively for port activities were now vacant. In this context, New York and Boston are two major port cities that succeeded when planning for their waterfronts.  This thesis studied the major technological changes that led to vacant harbor land and then the importance of that land for the city and, therefore, the importance for revitalization. The projects adopted by New York-Battery Park City-and Boston-Waterfront and Faneuill Hall area were analyzed in order to come to some conclusions about what is possible to do in waterfronts. These two cases are viewed as successful. This thesis explains why.  Although there is not an exact formula for redevelopment of waterfronts, it was possible to draw some guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5282</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6690&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5282</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6690</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847191</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5282</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James Spencer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Planning</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>