<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Environmental Impact Assessment in Post-Colonial Societies: Reflections on the Proposed Expansion of the Panama Canal</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-24T12:48:16-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>State University School of Law</institution>
<lname>Gonzalez</lname>
<fname>Carmen</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>panama canal</keyword>
<keyword>environment</keyword>
<keyword>post-colonial</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Panama&#39;s destiny has been shaped by its geographic location at the crossroads of international trade. Lacking mineral wealth or extensive arable lands, the country has prospered or declined based on the use made by others of the country&#39;s major resource-the Panama Canal. The Panama Canal is a potent symbol of Panamanian identity, a reminder of Panama&#39;s lengthy colonial history, and an important generator of income for the modem Panamanian nation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss2/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1067&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1067</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-20T08:22:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5362295</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss2/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Associate Professor, Seattle University School of Law. I would like to thank Daniel Suman, Frank Valdes and Colin Crawford for organizing an enlightening one week seminar in Panama during which the Canal expansion and many other topics were explored. I am especially grateful to the many Panamanian scholars, government officials and non-governmental organization representatives who took the time to meet with us and to share their thoughts and insights.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Proposed Expansion of the Panama Canal</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>