<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Socio-economic readjustment of farm families displaced by the TVA Land Purchase in the Norris Area</title>
<publication-date>1940-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Neilsen</lname>
<fname>Ralph</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;At various times in recent years it has been necessary that families or groups of families be removed from their established communities due to the creation of public parks, the formation of artificial lakes by governmental agencies, the retirement of submarginal artificial land, and other related projects. To a considerable extent in the past the land has been condemned and bought, the people forced to leave, and get reestablished as best they might. To some extent guidance and assistance in relocation has helped to reduce hardship. Nevertheless in many instances the social loss to these residents has been great. Relocation in a new area may be easy or difficult depending upon the type of people, how closely connected their lives are to activities peculiar to the area, the nature of their new environment, distance moved, and other factors. By an analysis of what has happened to families relocated from the Norris Dam Area it is hoped that relocation projects of a similar nature may be more intelligently considered. Only when the probably effect on various elements of the population is known and when the successes or failures in adjustment are studied may similar projects be conducted with the least distress to persons involved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5812</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7490&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5812</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7490</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359291</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5812</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>C. E. Allred</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1940-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>