<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Memory and meaning in architecture : Explain Explore Experience</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Hendricks</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>Bryon</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Buildings designed today should have memory and meaning latent in their form. The site should instruct and direct the architecture that will be placed on it. Architect Tadao Ando states: &quot;The purpose of architecture is basically the construction of place&quot; (Frampton, 133). This basic principle of architecture is lost if architects fail to consider the region, the culture of the building&#39;s users, the communities within which the building exists, the site on which it is built, or the expression the building creates. Architecture is not just the making of a building; it is the analysis of the site and the understanding of what is needed on the site. In order to make meaningful architecture we must address the site at three levels: the physical place, the cultural place, and the spiritual place. This thesis explains how architecture links memory and meaning through a reinterpretation of the regional climate, cultural heritage, and the multitude of physical and conceptual aspects that constitute site conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5235</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6643&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5235</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6643</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847087</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5235</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brian Ambroziak</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>