<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>REFOCUSING ROLES ...A LOOK AT REFOCUSING PROGRAMMATIC EMPHASIS FROM LIVING UNITS TO AMENITY SPACES IN APARTMENT LIVING</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lkneebon@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kneebone</lname>
<fname>Laura</fname>
<mname>Mae</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>micro-unit</keyword>
<keyword>micro-housing</keyword>
<keyword>apartment</keyword>
<keyword>urban housing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Interior Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As growth within cities increase, so does the demand for living options within the city context. A cultural shift is drawing more individuals and families back into the heart of cities instead of fleeing to the outskirts of surrounding highway towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This increase in desire for city living has raised issues surrounding the lack of living options within the city that may accommodate those needing and/or seeking affordable living options. Micro-unit apartment housing has become the trending answer to this need, providing compact affordable living spaces within the core of a city. Micro-unit apartments can be currently found in most major cities and are spreading to mid-size cities as their demand and popularity grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While compact living may meet demands for economically sustainable housing, it rises questions about the social stainability of living in such a small space. This thesis aims to introduce a re-defined, community focused, Micro-unit apartment building within a mid-sized city. Focus within the apartment complex will be shifted away from the units, to centrally focused amenity and public spaces. This shift intends to redirect social trends of housing from individuality focused design, to community focused design that encourages neighborly socially sustainable relief spaces within Micro-unit apartment living.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2827</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3965&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2827</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3965</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-26T18:07:43-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5225488</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2827</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert C. French, Lisa J. Mulliken</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>