<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Methodology for Evaluation of Audio-Tutorial Modules in the Development of Cognitive Knowledge and Intellectual Skills in the Sensory Evaluation of Foods</title>
<publication-date>1974-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>English</lname>
<fname>Cynthia</fname>
<mname>Sharaphane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Eighteen undergraduate students at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, were subjects in a research study to evaluate audio-tutorial modules in the development of cognitive knowledge and intellectual skills in sensory evaluation of foods. Student opinions toward testing and teaching methods and pertinent background information were obtained by a student information sheet. Practical examinations, written examinations, and the Kelley Audiovisual Scale were completed by each subject before presentation of an independent study module, immediately following the presentation, and four weeks following the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results indicated that the students had a positive attitude toward audiovisuals and preferred independent study and test methods with the presence of an instructor. The test scores indicated that intellectual skills increased more than cognitive knowledge and were retained longer. Therefore, audio-tutorial modules using audiovisuals may be an appropriate instructional strategy and learning experience for increasing intellectual skills.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4109</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5517&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4109</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5517</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-29T11:11:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9211465</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4109</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Betty L. Beach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dorothy Lyon, Al Grant</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1974-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1974-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>