<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Test of Feasibility and Acceptability of Online Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction for Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Women and Men at Risk for High Stress: Pilot Study</title>
<publication-date>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jabson Tree</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gayle Patterson</lname>
<fname>Joanne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background: In conservative and rural areas, where antidiscrimination laws do not exist, lesbian, gay, and bisexual (LGB) people are at risk for excess stress arising from discrimination. Stress-reducing interventions delivered via innovative channels to overcome access barriers are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective: This study aimed to investigate the feasibility and acceptability of online mindfulness-based stress reduction (OMBSR) with LGB people in Appalachian Tennessee at high risk for stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: In 2 pilot studies involving pre-post test designs, participants completed 8 weeks of OMBSR, weekly activity logs, semistructured interviews, and surveys of perceived and minority stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Overall, 24 LGB people enrolled in the study and 17 completed OMBSR. In addition, 94% completed some form of mindfulness activities daily, including meditation. Participants enjoyed the program and found it easy to use. Perceived stress (Cohen, perceived stress scale-10) decreased by 23% in women (mean 22.73 vs mean 17.45; &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;10=3.12; &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;=.01) and by 40% in men (mean 19.83 vs mean 12.00; &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;5=3.90; &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;=.01) between baseline and postprogram. Women demonstrated a 12% reduction in overall minority stress (Balsam, Daily Experiences with Heterosexism Questionnaire) from baseline to 12-week follow-up (mean 1.87 vs mean 1.57; &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;10=4.12; &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;=.002). Subscale analyses indicated that women’s stress due to vigilance and vicarious trauma decreased by 21% and 20%, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: OMBSR may be a useful tool to help LGB people reduce general and minority-specific stress in socially conservative regions lacking antidiscrimination policies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_publichealth/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;amp;context=utk_publichealth&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-08-29T09:15:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Public Health Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15230155</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_publichealth/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>JMIR Ment Health</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>