<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Placental Transfer and Maternal-Fetal Utilization of Manganese by Third Trimester Pregnant Heifers</title>
<publication-date>1971-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wanamaker</lname>
<fname>Boyce</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although manganese has been demonstrated to be required for normal life processes, little information is available on the placental transfer and maternal-fetal utilization of this mineral in the bovine. Nine pregnant and three non-pregnant heifers were used in this study. They were dosed with a tracer level of radio-manganese for blood balance and subsequent placental transfer and maternal-fetal manganese utilization studies. Results of this study suggested total blood radio-manganese levels to drop from 14% of the administered dose at 3 hours to 1.8% after 144 hours. Blood clearance studies indicated that equilibrium between red cells and plasma was reached 38 hours post-dosing, and further data suggested that approximately 50% of the plasma manganese was protein bound. Eighteen percent of an intravenous &lt;sup&gt;54&lt;/sup&gt;Mn dose was excreted by pregnant heifers 144 hours after dosing. Bile appeared to be a major excretory pathway for manganese, and urine a minor excretory pathway. Liver served as the main metabolic pool for manganese in both the dam and fetus. Data suggested that heifers retained a calculated 1.16 mg manganese per day and deposited 82 ug (7.0% of that retained) in the total products of conception. Third-trimester bovine fetuses (272 days) contained 19.1 mg stable manganese; placenta, 2.10 mg and placental fluids 1.20 mg, for a total of 22.4 mg manganese in the total products of conception. Pregnant heifers deposited in the total products of conception a calculated 82 ug manganese per day, suggesting that 82 ug manganese per day was needed to support the products of conception in the pregnant heifer.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3209</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4535&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3209</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4535</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-09T11:36:55-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6627973</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3209</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sam L. Hansard</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Karl M. Barth, C.C. Chamberlain, M.C. Bell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1971-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1971-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>