<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>University of Tennessee Library Lectures, 1955-1957 (no. 7-9)</title>
<publication-date>1957-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>AR.0281</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Lecture No.7 was presented on May 13, 1955, by Mr. Jack Dalton, at that time Librarian of The Alderman Library, University of Virginia, and now Director of ALA&#39;s International Relations Office. An outstanding exponent of the value of a liberal education and one of the foremost philosophers in the field of librarianship, Mr. Dalton was the logical choice to speak on &quot;Liberal Education, Specialization, and Librarianship.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;The Research Library in Transition,&quot; Lecture No.8, was a particularly apt title, descriptive as it was of The University of Tennessee Library at the time. Dr. Herman H. FussIer, Director of Libraries and Professor in the Graduate Library School of the University of Chicago, delivered the lecture on April 17, 1956. With his background as scholar, administrator, and author, Dr. FussIer was well equipped to investigate the subject under scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Robert Vosper, Director of Libraries of the University of Kansas, completed the trio with Lecture No.9, &quot;A Rare Book Is a Rare Book,&quot; on March 7, 1957. The acquisitions program of the University of Kansas Library bespeaks Mr. Vosper&#39;s harmony with his subject, which is one of growing interest to the library staff and the faculty of this University.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libarcutlect/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1002&amp;amp;context=utk_libarcutlect&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-25T07:55:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>University of Tennessee Library Lecture Series</publication-title>
<context-key>1171017</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libarcutlect/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1957-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>