<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Comparison of Salmonella enterica Serovars: Are Prevalence, Virulence and Responses to Environmental Conditions Serovar or Strain Dependent?</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nzhang1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Zhang</lname>
<fname>Nan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>gene regulation</keyword>
<keyword>poultry</keyword>
<keyword>Salmonella</keyword>
<keyword>stress</keyword>
<keyword>virulence</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; are considered the leading cause of foodborne illnesses with frequent outbreaks in United States. While more than 2500 serovars have been identified, &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Typhimurium and &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Enteritidis are primarily responsible for most human infections while &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Kentucky and &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Heidelburg are currently the most prevalent serovars associated with poultry contamination. The relationship between virulence and prevalence is not fully understood, but may be a result of environmental stress exposure such as acid stress. In this research, organic acid (acetate) and inorganic acid (hydrogen chloride) were applied to 15 different serovars isolated from human infections or poultry. The growth curves and pH changes were graphed over time. In addition, the virulence gene &lt;em&gt;hilA&lt;/em&gt; which regulates the pathogenesis of &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; were evaluated using real-time PCR at four different time points, 0, 2, 4, and 24 hours after &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; was exposed to two different acids individually. We found: 1) growth of &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; and the changes of pH were inversely related; 2) the greatest changes of &lt;em&gt;hilA &lt;/em&gt;gene expression occurred between 0 and 2 hours; 3) the expression of &lt;em&gt;hilA&lt;/em&gt; was serovar and strain dependent; and 4) hydrogen chloride had a greater impact on &lt;em&gt;hilA &lt;/em&gt;gene expression than acetate did. Our study gives a better understanding of the &lt;em&gt;hilA&lt;/em&gt; pathway used by &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt;. At the same time, the effect of environmental stimuli on each serovar was revealed. Differences between serovars were unveiled by comparing the responses to acids as well.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2484</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2907&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2484</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2907</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-23T19:40:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4252771</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2484</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Irene Hanning</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael Davidson, Faith Critzer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>