<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Use of differential framing to measure implicit social cognitions associated with aggression</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lebreton</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this dissertation was to respond to the call offered by James (1998; James &amp; Mazerolle, 2002; James et al., 2001) for the development and validation of new indirect measurement systems applicable to implicit social cognitions. Such a measurement system is described herein. This measurement system is based on the notion of differential framing—that is, the idea that individuals with different personalities tend to frame the same situations and stimuli in qualitatively different manners. A test based on differential framing was developed to assess framing proclivities associated with dispositional aggression. This test is called the Differential Framing Test or DFT. Data were collected and analyzed from four different samples. The DFT demonstrated strong predictive validity yielding cross-validities in the .305 and .403. Furthermore, and in direct contrast to many indirect measurement systems (e. g., Thematic Apperception Test), the current measurement system demonstrated appropriate levels of internal consistency and test-retest reliability, given its early stage of development. Overall, it appears that differential framing represents a viable approach to measuring personality-related implicit cognitions. Furthermore, this approach yields results that are not redundant with other measures of implicit social cognitions (e. g., Conditional Reasoning Tests). Results are discussed in light of directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6349</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8301&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6349</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8301</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:36:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450598</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6349</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence R. James</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Joan R. Rentsch, Michael D. McIntyre, Michael Nash, Esteban Walker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial and Organizational Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>