<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Design and Analysis of a Vacuum Tube D. C. Voltage Regulator Having Specified Characteristics</title>
<publication-date>1958-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Brantley</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>Lamar</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Advancing technology in the fields of Radar and Computers has placed increased emphasis on the performance of d. c. voltage regulators in the past few years, and there certainly is no reason to believe that this trend will subside in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vacuum tubes have been used for many years as a means of regulating output voltages of d. c. power supplies. The consequent development of a &quot;cookbook&quot; technique of design for such circuitry has led to many misconceptions and misunderstandings as to the characteristics available from the vacuum tube regulator and the methods of obtaining these characteristics. In many cases the design engineer, having a muddled concept of voltage regulators, specifies a regulated voltage having characteristics far exceeding his particular need. This overdesign and subsequent cost spiral is exceedingly wasteful. On the other hand, inadequate design least to degredation of system performance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1721</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3070&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1721</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3070</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-19T13:43:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4464552</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1721</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>J. F. Pierce</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edgar D. Ecawls, C. H. Weaver, James D. Tillman, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1958-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1958-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>