<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>University of Tennessee Library Lectures, 1967-1969 (no. 19-21)</title>
<publication-date>1969-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>AR.0281</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jerrold Orne, Librarian, The University of North Carolina, delivered the nineteenth lecture, &quot;Librarianship TodayCrisis or Change,&quot; on April 4, 1967. In a sense, Dr. Orne provided the theme for this collection; that is, change should be considered the natural result of growth and ought not be feared as a critical disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The twentieth lecture, &quot;Twentieth Century Scholarship and the Research Library: A Marriage of Convenience,&quot; was given by John H. Berthel, Librarian, The Johns Hopkins University, on May 7, 1968. Mr. Berthel reminded us of the necessity for intensive dialogue between scholarship and the research library in the face of continually expanding knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In concluding this volume, it seems appropriate that the twenty-first lecture, presented by W. Carl Jackson, Director of Libraries, The Pennsylvania State University, treated the challenge of the machine. On April 22, 1969, Mr. Jackson&#39;s contribution, &quot;Automation and the Academic Library,&quot; provided a sensible outline for implementing these changes which are destined to affect all libraries.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libarcutlect/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1006&amp;amp;context=utk_libarcutlect&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1006</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-25T08:04:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>University of Tennessee Library Lecture Series</publication-title>
<context-key>1171086</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libarcutlect/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1969-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>