<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Most Important Aviation System: The Human Team and Decision Making in the Modern Cockpit</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Allee</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Cody</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The most critical aviation system is the human operator in the cockpit of modern aircraft.  Regardless of the advancements in microelectronics and automated decision-making apparatus, the human will still remain ultimately responsible for the safety of those in the air and on the ground.  Humans, however, are not entirely predictable or consistent when functioning in this capacity.  The relationship between crewmembers becomes a critical aspect of this system, and this paper focuses on methods to improve both individual and especially crew decision-making in aviation.  Concepts and structure from the Navy’s Crew Resource Management program are used as the background for discussion.  Initially, the individual is examined, followed by an assessment of the physical systems in the cockpit, and finally methods for improving human interaction are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand how decisions (whether good or bad) are made, an examination of the inputs to the human decision maker is required.  The methods people use to evaluate their environment and choose a course of action will be discussed, as well as the effects of culture and experience on this process.  The physical information and control systems of an aircraft will be briefly reviewed, and suggestions for improving the efficacy of the information provided and aircrew employment will be offered.  Finally, the interrelationship between humans involved in the system will be studied, including suggested means to facilitate and improve these interactions.  The intent is to provide insight to the human team and methods to improve decision making in the modern cockpit.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1820</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3175&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1820</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3175</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-11T10:50:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4574977</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1820</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph D. Kimberlin, George W. Garrison</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>