<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Regional Anesthesiology Ultrasound-Guided Nerve Block Simulator</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-13T09:11:31-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>apurkaya@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Purkayastha</lname>
<fname>Avik</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dcall@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Call</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mzare@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Zare</lname>
<fname>Mehdi</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mfister1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Fister</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biomedical Devices and Instrumentation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the model is to allow residents in anesthesiology to practice the ultrasound guided supraclavicular nerve block procedure without having to practice on an actual patient so that they can hone their skills before performing the actual procedure. Our goals when creating the device were having a life-like feel, having the model be anatomically correct, and having the model provide an accurate ultrasound. After 3 iterations we were able to satisfy all 3 requirements but the most accurate ultrasound was provided by the second model, which did we believed did not satisfy the other requirements well enough. For future iterations we will mix the necessary materials in different proportions until we determine which exact proportion of starting materials is necessary to make the most accurate ultrasound.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/101</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1101&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>101</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1101</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-05-12T17:22:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>7096543</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/101</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This is an assignment performed under Dr. Reinbolt for BME 469 and under Dr. Langdon, an anesthesiologist at UT Medical Center.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>