<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Expression of the Transcription Factor STAT-1α in Insulinoma Cells Protects against Cytotoxic Effects of Multiple Cytokines</title>
<publication-date>2001-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Hohmeier</lname>
<fname>Hans</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas</institution>
<lname>Newgard</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Destruction of pancreatic islet β-cells in type 1 diabetes appears to result from direct contact with infiltrating T-cells and macrophages and exposure to inflammatory cytokines such as interferon (IFN)-γ, interleukin (IL)-1β, and tumor necrosis factor TNF-α that such cells produce. We recently reported on a method for selection of insulinoma cells that are resistant to the cytotoxic effects of inflammatory cytokines (INS-1res), involving their growth in progressively increasing concentrations of IL-1β plus IFN-γ, and selection of surviving cells. In the current study, we have investigated the molecular mechanism of cytokine resistance in INS-1rescells. By focusing on the known components of the IFN-γ receptor signaling pathway, we have discovered that expression levels of signal transducer and activator of transcription (STAT)-1α are closely correlated with the cytokine-resistant and -sensitive phenotypes. That STAT-1α is directly involved in development of cytokine resistance is demonstrated by an increase of viability from 10 ± 2% in control cells to 50 ± 6% in cells with adenovirus-mediated overexpression of STAT-1α (p &lt; 0.001) after culture of both cell groups in the presence of 100 units/ml IFN-γ plus 10 ng/ml IL-1β for 48 h. The resistance to IL-1β plus IFN-γ in STAT-1α-expressing cells is due in part to interference with IL-1β-mediated stimulation of inducible nitric-oxide synthase expression and nitric oxide production. Furthermore, overexpression of STAT-1α does not impair robust glucose-stimulated insulin secretion in the INS-1-derived cell line 832/13. We conclude that expression of STAT-1α may be a means of protecting insulin-producing cell lines from cytokine damage, which, in conjunction with appropriate cell-impermeant macroencapsulation devices, may allow such cells to be used for insulin replacement in type 1 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/12</coverpage-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-08T07:34:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1386269</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>MECHANISMS OF SIGNAL TRANSDUCTION: 


    *                      Guoxun Chen, 

    *                      Hans E. Hohmeier, 

    *                      and Christopher B. Newgard

 Expression of the Transcription Factor STAT-1α in Insulinoma Cells Protects against Cytotoxic Effects of Multiple Cytokines
                      J. Biol. Chem. 2001 276: 766-772. First Published on October 6, 2000,  doi:10.1074/jbc.M008330200</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-07-08T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.jbc.org/content/276/1/766.abstract</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>