<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Statistical Information in Pharmaceutical Product Advertising</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T12:01:35-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>iju@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ju</lname>
<fname>Ilwoo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Advertising and Promotion Management</discipline>
<discipline>Health Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the contexts of prescription drug (DTC) advertising, statistical information has been frequently used. However, little is known about how the statistical information affects consumer attitude toward the advertisement and perceived importance of an advertised illness. Based on an experiment, the present study explored the mechanism of consumers&#39; DTC advertising information processing using structural equation modeling (SEM) approach. The findings revealed that: (a) the use of statistical information in DTC advertising positively related to perceived message effectiveness; (b) perceived message effectiveness positively related to attitude toward the advertisement and perceived importance of an advertised illness; and (c) message framing (gain versus loss) moderated the statistical information effects on consumers&#39; perceptions. Theoretical and practical implications of DTC advertising were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/session1/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1050&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1050</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-14T02:48:25-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1050/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2402789</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/session1/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>