<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Racism and Mental Health: When it Hurts to be Black</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-22T12:11:26-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>datallent@crimson.ua.edu</email>
<institution>Desiree Tallent</institution>
<lname>Tallent</lname>
<fname>Desiree</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Mental Health</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Counseling Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Race and Ethnicity</discipline>
<discipline>Social Justice</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This presentation provides information on types of racism, including personal, institutional and cultural aspects.  The prevalence of racism among Black people is also highlighted.  Additional attention is given to the negative emotional outcomes of experiencing racism as well as the resulting behavioral impact of experiences with racism among Black individuals.  Special attention is given to how these issues may manifest in one’s personal life and student life.  In addition to understanding how racism impacts mental and behavioral health, information is provided on positive coping methods which can lessen the dire effect of racism.  These positive coping methods include the role of racial identity as a healing process.  More so, specific examples of how to seek help from others and how to be a self-advocate for racial healing through personal empowerment are provided.  Virtual handouts will be made accessible which will include links and other resources that provide information on key points, including positive coping strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2021/session4/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1261&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1261</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-21T21:01:38-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1261/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>21218447</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2021/session4/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Desiree Tallent graduated from the University of Alabama in 2017 with a Ph.D. in School Psychology.  Her research interests include exploring the presence of racism in public schools and how it contributes to the School-to-Prison Pipeline.  Dr. Tallent also takes much pride in her role as an advocate for students and families who often do not have a voice our outlet to speak up for themselves. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Participants will practice specific skills of racial identity including expanding their knowledge of racism, how racism impacts our daily lives, and how to positively cope with racism’s negative effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will leave with tangible resources for future reference, including information on racial identity and suggestions for positive coping strategies including references for reading materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will gain knowledge on the types, prevalence, and impact of racism as well as positive strategies to cope with the negative effects of racism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will evaluate the strengths and challenges of increasing their awareness of racism and learning positive ways to negate the negative impact of racism.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Understanding how racism impacts emotional and behavioral health is a beginning step in personal awareness, empowerment and healing  By increasing awareness of racism and how it impacts daily life, individuals are more likely to better cope with the negative effects of racism.  With knowledge and understanding of the impacts of racism, individuals are empowered and instilled with a sense of hope.  Furthermore, learning positive ways to cope with the negative impact of racism promotes positive mental and physical health as well as personal healing. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>