<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The value of scholarly reading in the life sciences</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Volentine</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>user studies</keyword>
<keyword>scientists</keyword>
<keyword>outcomes measurement</keyword>
<keyword>libraries</keyword>
<keyword>reading qualitative techniques</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Surveys of academic staff in six universities in the U.K. provide insights for publishers and universities into scholarly article, book, and other publication reading patterns of academics and differences based on academic discipline of readers. These surveys were part of the 2011 &lt;em&gt;UK Scholarly Reading and the Value of the Library Study &lt;/em&gt;funded by JISC Collections and based on Tenopir and King Studies conducted since 1977. Reading patterns of life and environmental scientists differ from other disciplines, in particular social sciences. Scholarly articles, especially those obtained from the library’s e-journal collections, are vital to the work of all academic disciplines. Life and environmental scient-ists come into contact with multiple sources of information every day, including social media, and the biggest limitation scientists describe when it comes to finding and obtaining articles is cost and time. Knowing more about academic reading patterns help publishers and librarians design more effective journal systems and services now and into the future.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_commstudpubs/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_commstudpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-01-06T17:24:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Communication Studies Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4956810</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_commstudpubs/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-01-06T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>