<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Integration of land use and transportation : selection of an appropriate model with Nashville MPO case study</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lambert</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Stuart</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study analyzes the information concerning the process of a selection technique for integrated land use/transportation models. The research presents a general history of the integration of the modeling process. It also includes an inventory that describes land use, transportation, and other integrated models. The main focus of this analysis deals with the process of the selection of an appropriate model applied to a specific region or agency. The selection process includes an investigation of what constitutes a good integrated model and the actual selection process itself. This selection process is conceptualized as a matrix table illustrating the method, which allows models to be weighed according to appropriate criteria. The thesis begins with a brief history of the land use/ transportation modeling techniques. Following the history is an overview of some of the current and operational models for the integration process. The main focus of the research follows which entails the selection process of an appropriate model for a specific region. The study answers the question as to what is the best method for selecting a model. The research concludes with an analysis of the selection process for the Nashville Metropolitan Organization case study and their applications. The study reveals that each agency has to select the appropriate model to best fit their needs. To achieve this, an understanding must first set out to determine what the agency is trying to achieve. This study provides a planning agency or firm with the necessary information to achieve the right selection for their specific requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5249</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6657&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5249</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6657</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847112</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5249</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bruce E. Tonn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Planning</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>