<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1731 Identifying Oak Trees Native to Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Native Tennessee Trees</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;From the bottomland swamps in the west to the mountain peaks in the east, Tennessee is enriched with a medley of forest trees like few other states. Diversity in soil types, climate and elevation give Tennessee an environmental gradient that provides habitats for approximately 190 native forest trees and large shrubs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oak trees are an important component of many Tennessee forests and are of particular interest to landowners, homeowners, the forest industry, students and outdoor enthusiasts alike. Oaks are deserving of special recognition, due to their important role in Tennessee’s history, both ancient and modern. Unmatched in economic and biological value, oaks provide not only fi ne lumber for wood products, but also acorns and foliage that feed an array of wildlife. Due to their handsome and sturdy appearance, oaks are also a welcome addition to the landscaping of yards and homesteads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty distinct species of oak are native to Tennessee. Correctly identifying oaks can sometimes be challenging, even for well-trained foresters and botanists. Close observation of several physical traits and clues is often required in addition to looking at the leaves. Introduced species (those not native to Tennessee), such as sawtooth oak, are not addressed in this publication.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfores/11</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1010&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfores&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>forestry</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1010</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-30T13:52:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Forestry, Trees, and Timber</publication-title>
<context-key>1254382</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfores/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1731-1M-8/06(Rep.) E12-4915-00-003-07 07-0037</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>