<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Agents watching agents?: evidence from pension fund ownership and firm value</title>
<publication-date>2002-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Woidtke</lname>
<fname>Tracie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Agency theory; Institutional investors; Corporate governance; Ownership structure</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Corporate Finance</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper examines the valuation effects associated with the incentive structures of different types of institutional investors using the ownership levels of public and private pension funds in a firm. The results suggest that institutional monitoring is associated with valuation effects when both observable and unobservable aspects of the relationship between institutions and firms are taken into account. Moreover, the valuation effects vary according to the objective functions of institutions’ administrators. Thus, other shareholders do not necessarily benefit from relationships between institutions and managers, and they could be hurt when the institutional agents watching firm agents have conflicts of interest with other shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_finapubs/5</coverpage-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-04T06:19:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Finance Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1423717</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_finapubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Tracie Woidtke, Agents watching agents?: evidence from pension fund ownership and firm value, Journal of Financial Economics, Volume 63, Issue 1, January 2002, Pages 99-131, ISSN 0304-405X, DOI: 10.1016/S0304-405X(01)00091-5.
(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6VBX-44CNPM0-1/2/c51ec6446a27850eaae79a8b73eafee0)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-04T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6VBX-44CNPM0-1/2/c51ec6446a27850eaae79a8b73eafee0</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>