<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Evolution of Early Franciscan Thought and Practice as Evidenced by the Rules and Testament of Francis of Assisi</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pardue</lname>
<fname>Bradley</fname>
<mname>Cameron</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History of Religion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thesis is an examination of the early thoughts and practices of the Order of Friars Minor (O.F.M.) and of its founder, Francis of Assisi, in light of the rules that he produced for his followers. Building on the work of David Flood, careful textual analysis of the earliest extant rule, the &lt;em&gt;regula non bullata&lt;/em&gt; (1221), is directed at reconstructing the stages of that text’s development. The &lt;em&gt;regula non bullata &lt;/em&gt;is then compared with the official rule of the Order, the &lt;em&gt;regula bullata&lt;/em&gt; (1223). Continuities and alterations between these two texts are considered and the sources of change are explored. This comparison will focus on five major themes: admission to the Order, discipline of the brothers, the prohibition of money, care for the sick, and missions among the Saracens. Much of the existing Franciscan historiography has characterized developments in the decades following 1220 as structural rather than substantive, insisting that the ideals of Francis were maintained. The analysis presented here calls into question this conclusion and argues that the historiography has incorrectly represented the changes that Francis’ Order underwent through the process of institutionalization.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4681</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6296&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4681</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6296</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-16T07:03:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10608053</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4681</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Bast</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas Heffernan, Thomas Burman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>