<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Value of a Videotaped Storyboard in a Non-Broadcast, Client Oriented Video Production:  A Case Study</title>
<publication-date>1986-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Willard</lname>
<fname>Clifton</fname>
<mname>Duane</mname>
<suffix>II</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to demonstrate the value of using the videotaped storyboard in the pre-planning and pre-production approval of a client oriented, corporate videotaped training program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology in this study is as follows: (1) to undertake the production of a corporate videotape training program; (2) to gather the necessary pre-production information about the topic, the audience, the manner in which the videotape program will be used; (3) to develop a storyboard based on the information obtained; (4) to present this storyboard for production approval; (5) to videotape the storyboard; (6) to present this videotaped version of the storyboard prior to production; (7) to compare and evaluate the responses to the different storyboard formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Library research on the use of the storyboard for pre-production planning and client approval revealed some information about the printed format of the storyboard but nothing about use of a videotaped storyboard. The articles that mentioned storyboards referred to the printed format with pictures or picture descriptions on one side of the page and the audio script on the other. There were different variations of the same theme but no mention of the videotaped storyboard as a technique in pre-production planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer applied the use of both the videotaped storyboard and a standard storyboard to gain approval for final production of a video training program for the Greater Knoxville Chamber of Commerce. It was clear that the videotaped form of the storyboard clarified the conceptualization of the program and prevented the production of a program based on the approval of a standard storyboard that would be rejected when viewed on videotape. The use of the videotaped storyboard format was the key factor in clarifying the producers visualization of the finished program and the expectations of the client of the finished program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4337</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5755&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4337</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5755</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-15T06:39:33-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9690655</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4337</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Norman R. Swan, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barbara A. Moore, George C. Johnson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>