<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Proposed Course of Study in Safety for Industrial Education Students</title>
<publication-date>1953-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gannaway</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>Edgar</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Statement of the Problem&lt;/em&gt;) The purpose of this study is an attempt to set up a course of study in safety for students of industrial education. It should be understood that industrial education students include potential teachers of industrial arts and vocational trade and industrial subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer feels that safety education in most school shops in not emphasized as much as it should be and that more should be done to encourage safety education to those students who are planning to teach in the industrial education field. It is hoped that this study will be of help to present as well as future teachers of industrial education in discharging their responsibilities of explaining, organizing, and operating a safety program in the school shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since one of the generally accepted objectives of both industrial arts and vocational industrial education is to encourage students to have basic facts about industry, the writer feels that the students should be taught safety standards that are commonly accepted by the industry. It is realized that some differences will exist between the school shop safety program and an industrial safety program in large industries where full time specialist are employed to operate the safety program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the first objective that all teachers should have in safety is the protection of the student, but the teachers should also be familiar with his own liability in case of injury to a student. This phase of the study will also be included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the presentation of this study, major consideration will be given to the following questions: (1) who is liable in case of an accident in the school shop,  (2) how can a safety program be set up and operated in a school shop, (3) why should records be kept on accidents and what information should be obtained when an accident is caused, (4) what safety precautions should be taken with the usual types of woodworking machines, (5) what safety precautions should be taken with the usual types of metalworking machines, and (6) what material and medicine should be kept in the first aid cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4388</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5890&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4388</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5890</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-07T12:33:09-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9803621</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4388</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Clyde H. Wilson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>F. A. Van Eynde, James N. Luton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1953-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1953-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>