<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Quantization of maximally charged slowly moving black holes</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gsiopsis@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Siopsis</lname>
<fname>George</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We discuss the quantization of a system of slowly moving extreme Reissner-Nordström black holes. In the near-horizon limit, this system has been shown to possess an &lt;em&gt;SL&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;,R) conformal symmetry. However, the Hamiltonian appears to have no well-defined ground state. This problem can be circumvented by a redefinition of the Hamiltonian due to de Alfaro, Fubini, and Furlan (DFF). We apply the Faddeev-Popov quantization procedure to show that the Hamiltonian with no ground state corresponds to a gauge in which there is an obstruction at the singularities of moduli space requiring a modification of the quantization rules. The redefinition of the Hamiltonian in the manner of DFF corresponds to a different choice of gauge. The latter is a good gauge leading to standard quantization rules. Thus the DFF trick is a consequence of a standard gauge-fixing procedure in the case of black hole scattering.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOI:10.1103/PhysRevD.63.104018&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_physastrpubs/16</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1016&amp;amp;context=utk_physastrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>16</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1016</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-10-03T09:08:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Physics and Astronomy Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3764169</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_physastrpubs/16</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://prd.aps.org/abstract/PRD/v63/i10/e104018</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Physical Review D</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>