<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Embedded Repository: Introducing an Institutional Repository to a New Audience Via Location-Aware Social Networking</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rbedenbaugh@tamu.edu</email>
<institution>Texas A &amp; M University - College Station</institution>
<lname>Bedenbaugh</lname>
<fname>Robin</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>hollymercer@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mercer</lname>
<fname>Holly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Institutional repositories</keyword>
<keyword>Social networking</keyword>
<keyword>Marketing</keyword>
<keyword>Location-based services</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The authors report the outcome of a partnership between a university marketing and communications department and a university library. The research aimed to determine whether providing links to institutional digital repository content on location-based social media is a viable marketing approach. Foursquare tips were added to locations on the Texas A&amp;M University campus with links to repository content. The authors subsequently monitored repository traffic using Google Analytics to determine how many users were being referred by the Foursquare service. Research indicates that users will click through links on Foursquare to visit the institutional repository, and that they will explore further once they are there. This was an initial exploration. More data will be needed to determine precisely the best way to market services through location-based or location-aware services.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/91</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1091&amp;amp;context=utk_libfpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>91</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1091</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-01-21T06:38:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Other Library Publications and Works</publication-title>
<context-key>5001981</context-key>
<withdrawn>2016-12-12</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_libfpubs/91</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Bedenbaugh, R., Mercer, H. &quot;The Embedded Repository: Introducing an Institutional Repository to a New Audience Via Location-Aware Social Networking.&quot; Practical Academic Librarianship: The International Journal of the SLA Academic Division, North America, 2.1, Aug. 2012. Available at: http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/91/.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-01-21T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>