<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Histologic assessment and grading of the exocrine pancreas in the dog</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Steiner</lname>
<fname>J</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Woosley</lname>
<fname>K</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>D</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>canine</keyword>
<keyword>hyperplasia</keyword>
<keyword>inflammation</keyword>
<keyword>pancreas</keyword>
<keyword>pancreatitis</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Histologic grading schemes for canine inflammatory conditions are sparse, and in the case of the canine pancreas, have not been previously described. In a previous study, we determined that histologic lesions of the exocrine pancreas occurred much more frequently than gross lesions. The intention of the current study was to develop a histologic grading scheme for nonneoplastic lesions following extensive assessment of the exocrine pancreas from dogs presented for necropsy examination. The parameters of the proposed scheme include neutrophilic inflammation, lymphocytic inflammation, pancreatic necrosis, pancreatic fat necrosis, edema, fibrosis, atrophy, and hyperplastic nodules. In this case series, the most common lesion was pancreatic hyperplastic nodules (80.2%), followed by lymphocytic inflammation (52.5%), fibrosis (49.5%), atrophy (46.5%), neutrophilic inflammation (31.7%), pancreatic fat necrosis (25.7%), pancreatic necrosis (16.8%), and edema (9.9%). Only 8 of the 101 animals had no evidence of any of the lesions in any of the sections examined. Fibrosis, atrophy, and/or lymphocytic infiltration most commonly accompanied nodules. Neutrophilic inflammation, when present, was often associated with necrosis (pancreatic necrosis, pancreatic fat necrosis, or both) and occasionally with hyperplastic nodules. The utilization of a grading scheme for exocrine pancreatic lesions will be useful in advancing the classification of exocrine pancreatic disease in the dog, which may lead to multicenter studies of exocrine pancreatic disorders in the dog and in other species.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/77</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1076&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>77</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1076</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T10:48:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2324206</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/77</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Shelley Newman, J M. Steiner, K Woosley, D A. Williams, and L Barton. &quot;Histologic assessment and grading of the exocrine pancreas in the dog&quot; Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation 18 (2006): 115-118.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>