<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Pattern Scale in the Near Environment on Preschool Play Behavior</title>
<publication-date>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Brickey</lname>
<fname>Janis</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Interior Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research investigated if scaled pattern designs affect children&#39;s play behavior, specifically play segment length. The sample included three and four year old children at a child development laboratory. The behavioral setting analyzed was located in an existing quiet area during free play. Under control conditions, the spatial area, 42&quot; x 42&quot; x 36&quot;, was regulated  to validate the experimental conditions. Subjects acted as their own controls while playing under three conditions, control and two experimental (large and small pattern applied to vertical surfaces). Data were collected by observation and video taped for reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felt board and Fisher Price used as table toys, were rotated throughout the study. The arrival and departure of each subject who played with the toys in the area were recorded. Analysis of variance tests were conducted across conditions. Results confirmed that the small pattern scale conditions augmented play segment length while subjects play with the felt board. Play with the Fisher Price toys was statistically insignificant. These results are applicable to design of environments where attention span increases are desired.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2522</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3887&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2522</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3887</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-11T13:16:34-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4915251</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2522</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alton J. DeLong</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Millend Gupta, Deborah Tegano, Carl Dyer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>