<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effect of Specific Versus Generalized Supervisory Feedback on Counseling Self-Efficacy of Counselors-In-Training</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Clark</lname>
<fname>Sheri</fname>
<mname>Lyn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study assessed the effects of general and specific supervisory feedback on counselors’-in-training ratings of counseling self-efficacy (CSE). Fifty-four students in counseling-related graduate programs from two universities in the southeast and one in the mid-west volunteered as participants. Thirty-seven participants were female (68.5%), 14 were male (25.9%), and three did not indicate their sex (5.6%). Forty out of 54 participants (74.1%) indicated they were Caucasian-American, five were African-American (9.3%), one was Hispanic-American (1.9%), one was Asian-American (1.9%), and three indicated that they were best described as “other” (5.6%). The median number of months of previous clinical supervision for the participants was one month. This study made use of a two-group pretest-posttest design. The independent variable was performance feedback, with two levels (specific and general). The dependent variables included post-test scores on the Counselor Activity Self-Efficacy Scales (CASES; Lent, Hill, &amp; Hoffman, 2003). State anxiety was also assessed with the state scale of the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-S; Spielberger, 1982). After completing pretest measures, participants performed a ten-minute mock counseling session with a confederate. After the mock counseling session, the confederate provided either specific feedback or general feedback statements to the participants. Participants then filled out post-test measures. After the measures were collected, participants received an extensive debriefing. The three hypotheses for counseling self efficacy were: (a) there would be a significant difference between the two groups’ counseling self-efficacy scores with participants receiving specific feedback obtaining higher counseling self-efficacy scores; (b) there would be a significant difference between pre- and post-test scores of counseling self-efficacy with the post-test scores being significantly higher than pre-test scores; and (c) while both groups were expected to score similarly in the pre-test measure of counseling self-efficacy, it is predicted that the participants receiving specific feedback reporting higher counseling self-efficacy scores in the post-test measures. There was no difference between counseling self-efficacy scores of participants who received general or specific supervisory feedback. Post-measure counseling self-efficacy scores were significantly higher than the pre-measure scores. There was no group x time interaction. The three hypotheses for anxiety were: (a) there will be a significant difference between the two groups’ anxiety scores with the participants receiving specific supervisory feedback will report significantly less anxiety than those receiving global supervisory feedback; (b) there will be a significant difference between pre- and post-test scores of state anxiety with the post-test scores being significantly lower than pre-test scores; and (c) while both groups are expected to score similarly in the pre-test measure of state anxiety, it is predicted that the participants receiving specific feedback reporting lower state anxiety scores in the post-test measures. There was no difference between anxiety scores of participants who received general or specific supervisory feedback. Post-measure anxiety scores were significantly higher than the pre-measure scores. There was no group x time interaction. Implications and issues to be considered in future research were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1900</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3328&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1900</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3328</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-12T11:53:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4580102</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1900</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jacob Levy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark Hector, Suzanne Molnar, John Lounsbury, Victor Barr</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>