<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of Large-Scale Models and HVDC Control Strategies to Improve Resiliency of North American Power System</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lsundare@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Sundaresh</lname>
<fname>Lakshmi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;With drastic transformation of the electrical power system, the challenges related to planning, operation, and maintenance of power systems are increasing. The controls and operating procedure of the power systems till now have designed assuming certain inherent characteristics of the power system like inertia, response time and control behavior. However, these assumptions are not accurate and a need to reevaluate the system has become a priority. With improved wide area measurements and analysis techniques detecting wide area phenomena, analyzing them and eventually developing mitigation procedure that not only ensure resiliency but in some cases even improve have become the standard. Resiliency of a power system is an amalgamation of broad concepts like robustness, resourcefulness, rapid recovery, adaptability. The exact implication of these concepts on power system planning and operation is subject to the characteristics of the system and also the phenomena under study. Therefore, based on these distinctive characteristics, it is important to identify the appropriate tools and techniques to assess them. In this thesis, new algorithms to analyze the wide area measurements, new models are developed to analyze future scenarios and new control techniques to ensure the resiliency of the system is discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5866</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7632&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5866</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7632</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-10T23:12:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20527776</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5866</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Yilu Liu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jiuping Pan, Hector Pulgar, Fangxing Li</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2023-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>