<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Qualitative Analysis of &lt;em&gt;Grutter v. Bollinger&lt;/em&gt;: Implications for Use in Professional Programs Conducted Under &lt;em&gt;Geier v. Bredesen&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rudolph</lname>
<fname>Marva</fname>
<mname>Lane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Political Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study represents an analysis of the public policy mandated in &lt;em&gt;Grutter v. Bollinger&lt;/em&gt; and the public policies and procedures administered through &lt;em&gt;Geier v. Bredesen&lt;/em&gt; at professional schools in the State of Tennessee. To gather information and ensure objectivity, a multiple information-gathering approach was used, which included administering a written questionnaire, reviewing court documents, conducting elite interviews, and participating in various University of Tennessee-based committees. Both &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; used affirmative action policies to help achieve student body diversity in public higher education institutions. &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; used affirmative action as a voluntary means to support the argument that diversity is a compelling governmental interest. Diversity included, but was not limited to, racial diversity. In &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt;, Tennessee professional higher educational institutions were court-ordered to use affirmative action policies to remove the legacy of de jure segregation. In &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt;, diversity was the desired goal but was limited primarily to racial diversity of two racial groups, Blacks and Whites. Through the admissions processes they examined, &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; dealt with both applications of affirmative action policies—non-remedial (diversity) and remedial (correcting past discrimination). In 2003, the &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; case became the national standard for all colleges and universities, public and private, in the use of race-conscious admissions policies in undergraduate, graduate, and professional programs. In 2006, a Final Order of Dismissal was issued on the &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; lawsuit. As a result, public higher education institutions in the State of Tennessee must now abide by the standard laid out in &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central question posed in this study was whether &lt;em&gt;Geier’s&lt;/em&gt; admissions policies comply with the current &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; standard. The findings indicate that, as originally written and applied, &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; admissions policies do not meet the current &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; standard. Under &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt;, race was the only type of diversity sought, and race was limited only to Blacks and Whites. Therefore, &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt;, as originally written, is not narrowly tailored and does not pass the strict scrutiny test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt;, much progress was made to increase student body diversity, particularly of historically underrepresented groups. As Tennessee moves into the post- &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; era, administrators of the state public colleges and universities continue to assert that diversity is a compelling governmental interest. Future efforts must demonstrate the ability to maintain the progress made under &lt;em&gt;Geier&lt;/em&gt; while complying with the &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt; standards. This must be done while recognizing that &lt;em&gt;Grutter&lt;/em&gt;, the current law of the land, is still being scrutinized and challenged.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/281</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1334&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>281</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1334</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-05T09:28:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1133500</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/281</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Otis H. Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John M. Scheb, Patricia K. Freeland, Joy T. DeSensi</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Political Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/RudolphMarva.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>