<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Durability and Fatigue Behavior of CIP Concrete Connections for Accelerated Bridge Construction</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pzhu@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Department of Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering</institution>
<lname>Zhu</lname>
<fname>Peng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Closure pour materials</keyword>
<keyword>Durability</keyword>
<keyword>Performance criteria</keyword>
<keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
<keyword>Longitudinal joint</keyword>
<keyword>Transverse joint</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Structural Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Continuous longitudinal and transverse U-bar joint connections between flanges of the decked bulb-Ts (DBTs) or between precast panels for accelerated bridge construction are investigated.  The procedure for selecting durable closure pour (CP) materials for the connections is discussed firstly. The accelerated construction is quantified as two categories: overnight cure and 7-day cure of CP materials. Candidate materials are selected first based on literature review as well as tests of compressive strength and flow and workability. Then, performance criteria for selecting durable CP materials for both categories are developed based on durability tests of selected candidate materials. These durability tests include freezing-and-thawing durability, shrinkage, bond, and permeability tests. To investigate the longitudinal U-bar joint details, four pairs of full-scale slabs connected by a U-bar detail with one of the selected CP materials, overnight cure and 7-day cure, were tested.  The loading demand necessary in the slab testing is determined based on the maximum forces in the longitudinal joint from an analytical parametric study. Static and fatigue tests under four-point flexural loading and three-point flexural-shear loading were conducted. Test results were evaluated based on flexural capacity, curvature behavior, cracking, deflection and steel strain. The transverse U-bar joint details are investigated to provide negative moment continuity in the multi-span bridges. Four full-scale specimens connected by a U-bar detail with one of the selected CP materials, overnight cure and 7-day cure, were tested.  Static and fatigue tests under tension loading were conducted. The loading demand necessary in the beam testing is determined based on the maximum forces in the transverse joint from an analytical study. Test results were evaluated based on tension capacity, cracking, displacement and steel strain. Based on the test results, the developed longitudinal and transverse U-bar joint details are viable connection systems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/932</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1996&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>932</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1996</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-10-28T08:37:41-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1996/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1621908</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/932</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Zhongguo John Ma</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edwin G. Burdette, Baoshan Huang, John Stanley Rabun</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>