<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Angiotensinogen Gene Silencing Reduces Lipid Accumulation and Inflammation in Cultured 3T3-L1 Adipocytes</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>wxin@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carroll</lname>
<fname>Wenting</fname>
<mname>Xin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>obesity</keyword>
<keyword>metabolic disorders</keyword>
<keyword>renin-angiotension system</keyword>
<keyword>inflammation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular, Genetic, and Biochemical Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Obesity is characterized by metabolic complications which are related to several life-threatening diseases. Dysregulated inflammatory adipokines secretion from adipose tissue is believed as the major contributor to obesity-associated local and systemic inflammation, insulin resistance, and other metabolic dysfunctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies in our lab and others pointed to the role of local adipose tissue renin-angiotensin system (RAS) in the pathogenesis of obesity, inflammation and insulin resistance. We hypothesized that adipocytes-derived angiotensinogen (Agt) played a critical role in adipogenesis and/or lipogenesis as well as adipose inflammation. To test, we established 3T3-L1 preadipocytes stably transfected with Agt-shRNA or scrambled sequence (Sc-shRNA). Transfected preadipocytes were differentiated and used to investigate the role of adipocytes-derived Agt using microarray and PCR analyses, as well as cytokine/adipokine profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, results confirmed that Agt gene silencing significantly reduced the expression of Agt and its hormone product angiotensin II (Ang II), as well as lipid accumulation in 3T3-L1 adipocytes compared to cells transfected with Sc-shRNA. Silencing of Agt gene also suppressed the production of pro-inflammatory adipokines, including interleukin-6 (IL-6), tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α [alpha]), and monocyte chemotactic protein-1 (MCP-1), in 3T3-L1 adipocytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microarray studies identified several genes involved in lipid metabolism and inflammatory pathways which were down-regulated by Agt gene inactivation, such as glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase 1 (Gpd1), carboxylesterase 3 (Ces3), retinol saturase (Retsat), serum amyloid A 3 (Saa3), nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain containing 1 (Nod1), signal transducer and activator of transcription 1 (Stat1) and chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 12 (Cxcl12). Additional analysis using mouse adipogenesis PCR arrays detected lower expression levels of adipogenic/lipogenic genes, such as peroxisome proliferator activated receptor gamma (Pparg), sterol regulatory element binding transcription factor 1 (Srebf1), adipogenin (Adig), and fatty acid binding protein 4 (Fabp4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, this study directly demonstrates the critical effects of Agt in preadipocytes differentiation, adipocytes lipid metabolism and inflammation. These results further support a potential role for adipose tissue-derived Agt in the pathogenesis of adiposity and obesity-associated metabolic complications.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1312</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2483&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1312</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2483</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-08-02T11:48:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3172301</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1312</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Naima Moustaid-Moussa</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Arnold M. Saxton, Dr. Brynn H. Voy, Dr. Guoxun Chen, Dr. Cheryl J. Kojima, Dr. Gina M. Pighetti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>