<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Job Satisfaction and Work Ethic among Workers in a Japanese Manufacturing Company Located in the United States</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Elkins</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavior and Ethology</discipline>
<discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This correlational and descriptive study synthesizes previous research regarding the impact of work ethic on job satisfaction when moderated by demographics, work dynamics, and occupational choice. Data from a sample of both exempt and non-exempt workers working at a Japanese-owned manufacturing plant was used to explore the relationship between the levels of job-satisfaction and work ethic reported by workers in various job categories and working environments. The sample consisted of 462 individuals who were identified using a stratified sampling of equal size. The study obtained responses from 328 workers through a respondent and non-respondent survey, representing 70% response rate. The researcher concluded that the 66 non-respondents could be included in the statistical analysis without prejudice toward the OWEI instrument; however, special attention should be given to any findings involving the JSS subscale Fringe Benefits due to differences between respondents and non-respondents. Specials examination was also given to the demographic variables of age and country. The researcher employed two robust tests, Wilks’s Lambda and Pillai’s Trace, to mitigate differences between respondents and non-respondents. Exempt workers made up 46.6% of the sample, and non-exempt workers represented 53.4%. The researcher used the Pearson r and the Multiple Analysis of Variance (MANOVA) in analyzing data. The OWEI and JSS instruments showed an overall positive, by low though significant correlation. Differences were identified between exempt and non-exempt workers in various job categories. This study should be of value to human resource practitioners interested in improving the level of job satisfaction among varied work groups.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/159</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1206&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>159</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1206</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-29T08:29:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1125247</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/159</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Ralph G. Brockett, Doo Lim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/ElkinsSam.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>