<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spatial Geographic Mosaic in an Aquatic Predator-Prey Network</title>
<publication-date>2011-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Chaves-Campos</lname>
<fname>Johel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hulsey</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>Darrin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The geographic mosaic theory of coevolution predicts 1) spatial variation in predatory structures as well as prey defensive traits, and 2) trait matching in some areas and trait mismatching in others mediated by gene flow. We examined gene flow and documented spatial variation in crushing resistance in the freshwater snails &lt;em&gt;Mexipyrgus churinceanus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mexithauma quadripaludium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nymphophilus minckleyi&lt;/em&gt;, and its relationship to the relative frequency of the crushing morphotype in the trophically polymorphic fish &lt;em&gt;Herichthys minckleyi&lt;/em&gt;. Crushing resistance and the frequency of the crushing morphotype did show spatial variation among 11 naturally replicated communities in the Cuatro Ciénegas valley in Mexico where these species are all endemic. The variation in crushing resistance among populations was not explained by geographic proximity or by genetic similarity in any species. We detected clear phylogeographic patterns and limited gene flow for the snails but not for the fish. Gene flow among snail populations in Cuatro Ciénegas could explain the mosaic of local divergence in shell strength and be preventing the fixation of the crushing morphotype in &lt;em&gt;Herichthys minckleyi&lt;/em&gt;. Finally, consistent with trait matching across the mosaic, the frequency of the fish morphotype was negatively correlated with shell crushing resistance likely reflecting the relative disadvantage of the crushing morphotype in communities where the snails exhibit relatively high crushing resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0022472&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/38</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1037&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>38</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1037</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-31T11:22:01-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4948201</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/38</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-31T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>