<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thriving During Multiple Pandemics: Movement, Mindfulness, Meaningful Engagement, and Mastery as Strategies for Resilience</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-25T14:31:20-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jsamuel@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Samuel</lname>
<fname>Javiette Vashann</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Who could have known that 2020 would wreak so much havoc on America? From COVID to the deaths of Ahmaud Arbery, Breonna Taylor, George Floyd, and countless others, black communities are plagued with health disparities; systemic racism; discrimination; violence and death by law enforcement as they go about their day-to-day lives. This workshop will focus on ways to support, encourage, and empower black students, faculty, staff, and community members to excel personally and professionally. As we continue to experience a myriad of issues related to COVID and social injustice, including but not limited to the loss of loved ones, loss of monumental milestones such as graduations and weddings, the loss of income and other resources, while at the same time dealing with social justice issues and political unrest it is imperative that we focus on our physical, mental health, and overall well-being. Practical tips, tools, and strategies will be provided as Dr. Samuel encourages participants to be their best self by maintaining an active lifestyle, engaging in important relationship while being socially distanced and isolated; staying in a positive headspace; and mastering things that are important to you.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2021/session5/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1263&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1263</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-22T12:33:56-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>21228573</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2021/session5/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Javiette Samuel serves as Assistant Vice Chancellor for Diversity and Engagement. She has over 20 years of professional experience at land-grant universities including PWIs and HBCUs. She provides leadership for UT’s engagement and outreach efforts. Samuel seeks to develop and strengthen university-community partnerships while cultivating relationships with key partners to advance the diversity, equity, and inclusion agenda. Dr. Samuel works with a variety of units across campus on collaborative initiatives that increase recruitment and retention of underrepresented students, faculty, and staff. Samuel has served as an administrator at the University of Kentucky and Kentucky State University. Dr. Samuel also spent nearly nine years at Tennessee State University as an Extension Specialist/Associate Professor/Program Leader focusing on research-based outreach and evidence-based programs. In all of her work she has built and sustained meaningful networks, partnerships, equity-minded practices, and culturally-grounded pedagogies that can be enacted to foster the success of all stakeholders. Dr. Samuel has spent her entire career motivating faculty, staff, and students to excel both personally and professionally while mentoring and engaging individuals, especially women in ways that encourage them to become active leaders on campus and in the community as they pursue educational, professional, and personal aspirations. Samuel earned her bachelors, masters and doctorate from the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. She is an active member of Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority, Incorporated.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Monitor</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will examine positive life strategies as we continue to experience unprecedented times due to COVID, racial, and social inequities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will explore characteristics such as physical activity, mindfulness, meaningful engagement, and mastery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will identify opportunities for utilizing the information learned as they seek to maintain a healthy lifestyle during quarantine/isolation and social unrest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This workshop relates to the conference theme because it addresses some of the issues that are disproportionately affecting the health and well-being of black and brown communities. It will offer some tips and solutions for addressing the aforementioned.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>