<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Titling and Untitled Housing in Panama City</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-24T12:48:15-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Florida International University</institution>
<lname>Esquirol</lname>
<fname>Jorge</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Panama</keyword>
<keyword>United Housing</keyword>
<keyword>Titling</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Panama City is experiencing a luxury condominium building explosion. A wall of high-rises now dominates the city&#39;s coastal skyline, and more are underway despite mounting supplies of unsold units. This type of development seriously impacts its surroundings. Public utilities struggle to meet the demand for new installation and high load services. Single family neighborhoods are choked by towers rising all around them. And, an already deteriorating environment and creaky infra-structure strain against the competing goals of increased development, quality of life, urban transportation, and environmental protection.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss2/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1066&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1066</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-20T08:06:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5362233</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss2/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Professor of Law and Director of International and Comparative Law Programs, Florida International University. I would like to thank Aya Gruber, Daniel Suman, and Catalina Villegas for their helpful comments on this paper and Marisol Floren-Romero for her expert research assistance. I would also like to thank Colin Crawford and Daniel Suman for coordinating our research trip to Panama in December 2007. My gratitude to the Georgia State University Center for the Comparative Study of Metropolitan Growth for its financial support and to the Watson Institute for International Studies at Brown University for an enriching research stay.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>United Housing in Panama</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>