<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thermal Stability of Binary Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si and Ternary NiAl-Mo Eutectic Alloys</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gali</lname>
<fname>Aravind</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thermal stability of multiphase intermetallics at temperatures to 1400°C was investigated by studying two model eutectic systems: Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si having a lamellar microstructure and NiAl-Mo having a fibrous microstructure. In drop cast Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si, coarsening was found to be interface controlled. The coarsening rate could be significantly reduced by microalloying with Ce and Re, two elements which were chosen because they were expected to segregate to the Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si interfaces and decrease their energies. Similarly, directional solidification, which is also expected to lower the Cr- Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si interfacial energy, was found to dramatically decrease the coarsening rate. In the case of NiAl-Mo, coarsening was found to occur by fault migration and annihilation. Microalloying with B was found to significantly decrease the coarsening rate. The fiber density in the B-doped alloy was smaller than in the undoped alloy, suggesting that B affects the coarsening rate by lowering the fault density. X-ray energy dispersive spectroscopy (XEDS) analysis of Ce doped drop cast Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si showed that Ce is present at the Cr/Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si interface. XEDS analysis of Re doped Cr-Cr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Si and EELS analysis of B doped NiAl-Mo were inconclusive.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1963</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3394&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1963</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3394</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-20T08:50:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4608226</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1963</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Easo P. George</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George M. Pharr, Claudia J. Rawn, Madhu S. Madhukar</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>