<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The CMS experiment at the CERN LHC</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sspanier@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Spanier</lname>
<fname>Stefan M</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>several institutes</institution>
<lname>et. al</lname>
<fname>S. Chatrchyan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Particle Detector</keyword>
<keyword>LHC</keyword>
<keyword>CMS Hadron Collider</keyword>
<keyword>Higgs</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Elementary Particles and Fields and String Theory</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) detector is described. The detector operates at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN. It was conceived to study proton-proton (and leadlead) collisions at a centre-of-mass energy of 14 TeV (5.5 TeV nucleon-nucleon) and at luminosities up to 1034 cm^2s^-1 (1027 cm^2s^-1). At the core of the CMS detector sits a high-magneticfield and large-bore superconducting solenoid surrounding an all-silicon pixel and strip tracker, a lead-tungstate scintillating-crystals electromagnetic calorimeter, and a brass-scintillator sampling hadron calorimeter. The iron yoke of the flux-return is instrumented with four stations of muon detectors covering most of the 4p solid angle. Forward sampling calorimeters extend the pseudorapidity coverage to high values (jhj _ 5) assuring very good hermeticity. The overall dimensions of the CMS detector are a length of 21.6 m, a diameter of 14.6 m and a total weight of 12500 t.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_physastrpubs/5</coverpage-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1005</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-12T08:29:44-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Physics and Astronomy Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1640534</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_physastrpubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-11-12T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://iopscience.iop.org/1748-0221/3/08/S08004</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>