<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extemporizing Pippi, Experimenting SPUNK: Community, Temporality, and The Politics of Free Improvisation</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>boyler@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Oyler</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Alan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>free improvisation</keyword>
<keyword>experimentalism</keyword>
<keyword>music</keyword>
<keyword>Norway</keyword>
<keyword>SPUNK</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Musicology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis examines the music of the Oslo-based experimental ensemble SPUNK. Maja S.K. Ratkje, Kristin Andersen, Lene Grenager, and Hild Sofie Tafjord have operated at the juncture of site-specific conceptual art and experimentalism since the early 1990s, recording and releasing much of their work for Norway’s Rune Grammofon label. Employing voice, electronics, and acoustic instrumentation in a free improvisational style, the group’s music demonstrates a robust and varied engagement with a range of experimental and avant-garde traditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing from ethnographic, theoretical, and historical methodologies, as well as my own experiences as a free improvisor and listener, I situate SPUNK’s work within the contested rubrics and fluctuating discourses underlying Euro-American experimental musical practice. I interrogate free improvisation’s political and aesthetic valences, tempering my analysis through interviews with the group and close “readings” of their recorded work. I focus particularly on their twelve-year long opus, &lt;em&gt;Das Wohltemperierte SPUNK&lt;/em&gt;, a massive project unfolding in discrete acoustic environments throughout Oslo. With respect to this expansive work, I argue that free improvisation enacts a critical ontology that I call &lt;em&gt;processual community&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4920</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5931&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4920</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5931</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-24T09:53:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9918715</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4920</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rachel M. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gerard Cohen-Vrignaud, Leslie Gay</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Music</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Music</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>