<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Grade A milk producers in Rutherford County, Tennessee : problem A: Characteristics of Rutherford County Grade A milk producers and their farms : problem B: Management practices of Rutherford County Grade A milk producers : problem C: Factors influencing dairy management practice adoption by Rutherford County Grade A milk producers : three related special problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1966-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Ross</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Martin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Dairying is the fourth most important source of agricultural income in Tennessee (5:26). Annual farm receipts from the sale of milk have averaged approximately 85 million dollars during the period 1960-1964. The number of dairy cows reported on Tennessee farms in 1964 was approximately 453, 000. Average milk production per cow was only 4, 800 pounds, while the national average was approximately 7, 545 pounds. Research indicates that average production of less than 6, 000 pounds per cow is unprofitable, and that cows producing below this level should be culled and replaced. Rutherford County is located in the central basin in Middle Tennessee. The agriculture of the county is rather diversified. The total agricultural income for the county is approximately seven and one-half million dollars (14:7) . Livestock and livestock products rank first as a source of income and usually return over three million dollars annually. Dairying ranks second with an annual gross incane of over two and one-half million dollars.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6056</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7695&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6056</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7695</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074435</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6056</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lewis H. Dickson, Don O. Richardson, William M. Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1966-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>