<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Analyzing relationships between student mobility and value-added gain-scores in East Tennessee elementary schools</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Duran</fname>
<mname>O&#39;Brian</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship between student mobility and Value-Added gain-scores in East Tennessee elementary schools. One large school district was selected as the population; forty-seven elementary schools were included in the analysis. Tennesse·e Value-Added Assessment System (TV AAS) gain-scores in Language Arts, Math, and Reading for grades three, four, and five were analyzed.  While it cannot be stated that mobility is a causal factor in poor student achievement, this study supported previous research that found that mobility was a contributing factor associated with poor student achievement. A Pearson&#39;s Correlation Coefficient Test revealed that composite Federal Free/Reduced Lunch percentages displayed a stronger relationship with lower value-added gain-scores than student mobility rate percentages. However, the two variables closely overlap in the analysis.  Findings also revealed that when mobile students were removed from the Pearson&#39;s Correlation Coefficient analysis, value-added gain-scores in Language Arts and Math increased at thirty-four schools. Nineteen school value-added gain-scores increased in Reading. The system-wide average score increase for each school represented in the study was .50. Only Math value-added gain-scores were statistically significant (R = .43) when mobile student scores were removed from the Pearson&#39;s analysis; Alpha was set at the .05 level of significance.  Recommendations for classroom, school, district, and state level strategies to counteract the negative impact of student mobility are provided as well as recommendations for further study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5206</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6750&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5206</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6750</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-11T12:24:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13799982</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5206</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gerald C. Ubben</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>