<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cerulean Warbler (&lt;em&gt; Dendroica cerulea &lt;/em&gt; Breeding Ecology and Habitat Selection, Initial Response to Forest Management, and Association with Anthropogenic Disturbances in the Cumberland Mountains of Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Beachy</lname>
<fname>Tiffany</fname>
<mname>Ahren</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objectives of this research were to (1) assess the pre-treatment conditions on Royal Blue and Sundquist Wildlife Management Areas (WMA) in terms of Cerulean Warbler (&lt;em&gt;Dendroica cerulea&lt;/em&gt;) habitat selection, territory density, and nest survival, (2) summarize the initial response of cerulean nest-site habitat selection, territory density, and nest survival to silvicultural treatments, and (3) to examine the relationship between anthropogenic disturbances and cerulean abundance and occurrence in the Cumberland Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cerulean Warblers consistently selected territories and nest sites that differed from the available habitat in 2005 and 2006. Specifically, ceruleans on Royal Blue tended to choose areas with larger trees that provided more overstory cover with more vines whereas ceruleans on Sundquist selected for more open conditions. This variation may be driven by the current habitat conditions on Royal Blue and Sundquist WMA. There were consistently more cerulean territories on Royal Blue than Sundquist. Cerulean Warbler nest survival during 2005 and 2006 was affected by temporal (year and nest stage) and habitat-related factors. Cerulean micro-site selection within the nest tree appeared to be linked to nest survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study plots on Royal Blue and Sundquist WMAs were subjected to either a modified-shelterwood, shelterwood, or single-tree selection treatment; one plot per site was a control. Each treated plot on Sundquist gained at least one territory after the harvest; the treated plots on Royal Blue maintained the same number of territories. Nest success was lower in 2007 than in 2005; nest site selection did not differ between years. Continued study is needed to examine the effect of the silvicultural treatments on cerulean habitat selection, territory density and nest survival over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cerulean Warbler abundance and occurrence did not change with distance from the edge of clearcuts, mines, and older successional disturbances. These findings suggest that the current configuration of forest and edge habitat in the Cumberland Mountains may not have a significant effect on cerulean distribution. We do not know whether habitat quality in terms of fecundity differs between edge and interior forests. This is an important research need as the Cumberland Mountains become more fragmented by human development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3628</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4981&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3628</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4981</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-09T13:07:23-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8119559</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3628</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Buehler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kathleen E. Franzreb, Patrick D. Keyser, Charles P. Nicholson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>