<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Generation of Architectural Form: Standardization and Adaptation</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Park</lname>
<fname>Sungmo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The form of an object is a diagram of forces; in this sense, at least, that from it we can judge or deduce the forces that are acting or have acted upon it; in this strict and particular sense, it is a diagram.”&lt;/em&gt; –D’Arcy Wentworth Thompson, &lt;em&gt;On Growth and Form&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout architectural history, architects have made efforts to develop a diversity and efficiency of form to adapt to the natural environment. A prominent issue that has developed from this is what are the factors that have influenced and become form generators?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D’Arcy Wentworth Thompson, in &lt;em&gt;On Growth and Form&lt;/em&gt;, describes how nature creates a great diversity of forms from an inventory of basic elements. According to Thompson, every creature is formed in accordance with a response to the actions that of natural force. “In short, the form of an object is a diagram of force.”&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, the formative processes in natural structures are normally governed by ‘least-energy’ responses such as honeycomb structure and poppy seed surface. The premise that form is a diagram of force can also be applied to architectural form and structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In architectural terms, a force may be considered as any factor which may affect any given form. Peter Pearce, in &lt;em&gt;Structure in Nature is a Strategy for Design&lt;/em&gt;, points out that there are two forces, intrinsic forces and extrinsic forces which act on the making of the form. He claims that intrinsic forces are those governing factors which are inherent in any particular system. Conversely, extrinsic forces are those governing influences which are external to any particular architectural system. He further maintains that “All forms in nature are determined by the interaction of intrinsic with extrinsic forces.”&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, architectural form also should be expressed to the reciprocal action of intrinsic force and extrinsic force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis raises issues regarding standardization and adaption in the making of architectural form. In the context, standardization is mainly related to intrinsic forces in that standardization makes systems which are efficient in their use of natural materials and energy resources. Adaptation is mainly connected with extrinsic forces to allow the diversity of form to develop in accordance with the built environment. Therefore, through the standardization and adaptation, architectural form should be accomplished the state of the equilibrium. In this thesis, I am exploring a new methodology of the generation of architectural form based on the process of standardization and adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Thompson, D’Arcy Wentworth, &lt;em&gt;On growth and form.&lt;/em&gt; Cambridge, Eng.: University Press, 1961. P.16&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;Pearce, Peter. &lt;em&gt;Structure in nature is a strategy for design&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge: MIT Press, 1978. p.xv&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4808</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6298&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4808</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6298</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-18T12:17:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10625558</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4808</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Scott Wall</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jon Coddington, Edgar Stach</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>