<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Genetic Analysis of Feline Calicivirus (FCV) Isolates Associated with a Hemorrhagic-like Disease</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Abd-Eldaim</lname>
<fname>Mohamed</fname>
<mname>Mostafa</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Stephen Kania</keyword>
<keyword>Melissa Kennedy</keyword>
<keyword>Michael Karlstad</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Feline Calicivirus (FCV) is one of the most common causes of upper&lt;br /&gt;respiratory tract disease in cats. Other disease syndromes associated with&lt;br /&gt;FCV infection have been reported. Recently, calicivirus infections&lt;br /&gt;associated with a hemorrhagic-like disease leading to significant mortality in&lt;br /&gt;cats has been reported. The clinical signs are similar to those observed with&lt;br /&gt;the Calicivirus of Rabbit Hemorrhagic Disease. This investigation&lt;br /&gt;characterized two FCV isolates associated with hemorrhagic-like disease.&lt;br /&gt;Nucleotide sequencing of the complete genome was done on these two&lt;br /&gt;isolates and four isolates representing other disease syndromes. Previously&lt;br /&gt;reported sequence data for the entire genome of classical FCV (six isolates)&lt;br /&gt;and a portion of the capsid gene for hemorrhagic-like FCV (three isolates)&lt;br /&gt;were used in the genetic analysis. Sequence data were used to determine&lt;br /&gt;relationships among the isolates and any correlates with phenotype.&lt;br /&gt;Nucleotide sequence comparisons of the entire genome and individual&lt;br /&gt;ORF’s revealed high homology among all isolates. However, data from this&lt;br /&gt;study suggest that the virulence may have genetic determinants as revealed&lt;br /&gt;by phylogenetic clustering based on a specific 75 nucleotides stretch from&lt;br /&gt; the capsid protein gene of the isolates associated with hemorrhagic-like&lt;br /&gt;disease.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1677</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3203&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1677</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3203</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-08T12:23:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4407940</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1677</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>L.N.D. Potgieter</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>