<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterizing Local Order and Physical Properties of Rare Earth Complex Oxides</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tshambli@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Shamblin</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Jacob</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>pyrochlore</keyword>
<keyword>radiation tolerance</keyword>
<keyword>neutron scattering</keyword>
<keyword>magnetism</keyword>
<keyword>ionic conductivity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Ceramic Materials</discipline>
<discipline>Condensed Matter Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Other Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With more than 500 compositions, materials possessing the pyrochlore structure have a myriad of technological applications and physical phenomena. Three of the most noteworthy properties are the structure’s ability to resist amorphization making it a possible host matrix for spent nuclear fuel, its exotic magnetic properties arising from geometric frustration, and fast ionic conductivity for solid-oxide fuel cell applications. This work focuses on these three aspects of the pyrochlore’s many potential uses. Structural characterization revealed that pyrochlore-type oxides have a tendency to disorder from a high symmetry cubic structure to a lower symmetry orthorhombic arrangement in response to a variety of experimental conditions (i.e. changing composition, altering stoichiometry, and high-energy ion irradiation). The magnetic properties and structure of orthorhombic Dy&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiO&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; [dysprosium titanate] have been successfully determined using neutron diffraction. Most notably, Dy&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiO&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; displays a transition from two-dimensional to three-dimensional magnetic order at temperatures less than 2K and has magnetic moments that can order/disorder independently for each Dy site in response to an applied magnetic field. Broadband dielectric spectroscopy measurements also revealed that ionic conductivity in radiation-induced amorphous Gd&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; [gadolinium titanate] is more than 250 times larger compared with the crystalline phase. This dramatic increase is caused by a higher concentration of charge carriers coupled with enhanced mobility.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3875</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5308&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3875</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5308</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-11T14:07:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8718711</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3875</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Maik K. Lang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Haidong Zhou, Joshua R. Sangoro, Brian D. Wirth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>