<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Volunteer Management Needs Assessment of the Tennessee 4-H Program</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rcasteel1@k12tn.net</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Casteel</lname>
<fname>Robbie</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>4-H</keyword>
<keyword>Volunteer Management</keyword>
<keyword>Needs Assessment</keyword>
<keyword>Tennessee</keyword>
<keyword>Volunteers</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this descriptive study was to conduct a state-wide needs assessment of Tennessee 4-H Youth Development Extension Agents to determine the perception in working with 4-H Volunteer Leaders and the knowledge level of volunteer management.  This study also determined the need for a formalized 4-H Volunteer Leader management system.  Targeted participants were University of Tennessee (UT) Extension Agents and Tennessee State University (TSU) Extension Agents with 4-H job responsibility.  Participants were asked to complete a four part questionnaire instrument.  Components one through three of the instrument were used to determine the need for a formalized 4-H Volunteer Leader management system, the knowledge level in managing and the perception of working with 4-H Volunteer Leaders.  The final component was used to collect demographic information. 	After completion of a pilot study, 161 Extension Agents were targeted to participate in the study.  The questionnaire was administered on web-based data collection system known as Survey Monkey.  Results indicated 90% of Extension Agents agreed there is a need for readily available, web-based materials.  Results also indicated a need (66% agreeing) for a comprehensive 4-H Volunteer Leader management system.  Also, results found high proficiencies, up to 97%, in both knowledge levels of managing 4-H Volunteer Leaders and perceptions of working with 4-H Volunteer Leaders.  Demographic information was correlated among measures of knowledge, perception and the need for a formalized 4-H Volunteer Leader management system.  Significant correlations were found between risk management of 4-H Volunteer Leaders and Extension tenure, also between Extension tenure and the perception of 4-H Volunteer Leaders being welcome within the school system.  Significant correlations were also between recruiting volunteers and outside of Extension volunteer/employee management; between outside of Extension volunteer/employee management and removing 4-H Volunteer Leaders.  Implications indicate a need for additional resources to provide training and information for both agents and 4-H Volunteer Leaders.  Findings also indicate materials should be web-based for easy access for both agent and 4-H Volunteer Leader use.  Data responses show there is a need for a formalized 4-H Volunteer Leader management system that would encompass all aspects from recruitment to retention of 4-H Volunteer Leaders.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/611</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1035&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>611</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1035</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-06T06:50:36-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1035/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1104029</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/611</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bryan Q. Patterson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carrie Ann Stephens, H. Dwight Loveday</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>