<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Therapist actions and corresponding narrative change during therapy : a case study</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Champion</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Clare</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate narrative change over the course of therapy, particularly the relationship between therapist behaviors and narrative change. To explore this relationship, one family&#39;s journey through therapy was recorded. Therapist statements were coded for the presence of the therapist being responsive to the clients, asking for elaboration from the clients, and challenging what the clients said in therapy. Client narratives were coded and given scores on coherence, the extent to which the narratives made sense to the reader and were free from distracting remarks, and richness, the extent of detail in the narrative. Findings reveal that coherence appeared to be a stable trait which did not change during therapy, but richness appeared to develop and grow in this case. Among therapist behaviors, asking for elaboration when needed appears to be the most important factor in leading to the corresponding growth in richness. While these findings are an interesting first step in understanding narrative change in the therapeutic context, it is important to note that this was a case study. Limitations to this study are discussed and directions for further research are suggested.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5899</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7532&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5899</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7532</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467555</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5899</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert G. Wahler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>