<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cryogenic Line Quench Experiment In Microgravity</title>
<publication-date>1991-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sathasivam</lname>
<fname>Kanishkan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This experiment was designed to provide a visual understanding of the nature of saturated liquid nitrogen flow boiling in a microgravity environment. This was undertaken by obtaining visual records of the flow patterns on film, and qualitatively analyzing them to form a definitive picture of the flow. An experimental apparatus was designed and built to obtain these visual records in microgravity. Liquid nitrogen was supplied from a dewar to an accumulator, from which it was then delivered to a test section. The accumulator was home-built and made of stainless steel. It contained a metal bellows vessel within it. Gaseous helium was supplied to the accumulator to provide the driving pressure. The test section was a 36 inch long, 1/2 inch O.D. quartz tube. Film recordings of the flow patterns were made with a movie camera at various film speeds, with the camera being positioned at different axial locations along the quartz test section. This experiment provided a flow pattern description of the transfer line chilldown and quench process for saturated liquid nitrogen in microgravity, and generated a visual data-base that will support other similar experiments in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3282</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4712&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3282</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4712</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-03-26T08:44:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6904368</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3282</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Basil N. Antar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank Collins, Michael Chaney</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aerospace Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1991-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1991-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>