<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Environmental Analysis and White Cell applications FTIR Spectroscopy</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Oliveros</lname>
<fname>Maria</fname>
<mname>Gabriela</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biological and Chemical Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The research is concerned with atmospheric chemistry &amp; physics, and analyzing the environment with respect to the quantity of molecules is in the air we breathe. Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy is used to identify the IR active molecules in our atmosphere. FTIR Spectrometer determines the intensity loss for molecules that have absorbed IR light. The FTIR spectroscopy is performed using the light from the sun or a carbon rod light source in the lab. A Sun-tracking device was employed to direct the sunlight into the spectrometer. Open-path measurements were made using multiple mirror reflections of the carbon rod light source over the top of the SERF (Science and Engineering Research Facility) building. From the Open-path measurements it was determined that the CO and N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O change concentrations during the day and night. Two different open path setups were employed with good success. Time-dependence of the IR spectra for many of the greenhouse gases are presented. In addition, we have performed Gaussian 03 calculations of the IR spectra for many of the greenhouse gases as well as for the nitroethane molecule.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/423</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1456&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>423</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1456</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T13:52:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1148703</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/423</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert N. Compton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert J. Harrison, Marianne Breinig, John Stewart Hager</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/OliverosMariaGabriela.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>