<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pharmacokinetics of intravenous and oral tramadol in the bald eagle (Haliaeetus leucocephalus)</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Souza</lname>
<fname>Marcy</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Martinez-Jimenez</lname>
<fname>Tomas</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>Sherry</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Analgesia is becoming increasingly important in veterinary medicine, and little research has been performed that examined pain control in avian species. Tramadol is a relatively new drug that provides analgesia by opioid (mu), serotonin, and norepinephrine pathways, with minimal adverse effects. To determine the pharmacokinetics of tramadol and its major metabolite O-desmethyltramadol (M1) in eagles, 6 bald eagles (Haliaeetus leucocephalus) were each dosed with tramadol administered intravenously (4 mg/kg) and orally (11 mg/kg) in a crossover study. Blood was collected at various time points between 0 and 600 minutes and then analyzed with high-performance liquid chromatography to determine levels of tramadol and M1, the predominate active metabolite. The terminal half-life of tramadol after intravenous dosing was 2.46 hours. The maximum plasma concentration, time of maximum plasma concentration, and terminal half life for tramadol after oral dosing were 2156.7 ng/ml, 3.75 hours, and 3.14 hours, respec vely. In addition, the oral bioavailability was 97.9%. Although plasma concentrations of ramadol and M1 associated with analgesia in any avian species is unknown, based on the obtained data and known therapeutic levels in humans, a dosage of 5 mg/kg PO q12h is recommended for bald eagles. Pharmacodynamic studies are needed to better determine plasma levels of tramadol and M1 associated with analgesia in birds.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/6</coverpage-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1005</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-27T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1288698</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Marcy J. Souza, Tomas Martin-Jimenez, Michael P. Jones, and Sherry K. Cox. &quot;Pharmacokinetics of intravenous and oral tramadol in the bald eagle (Haliaeetus leucocephalus)&quot; Journal of Avian Medicine and Surgery 23.4 (2009): 247-252.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.bioone.org/action/showMultipleAbstracts</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Avian Medicine and Surgery</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>