<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Analysis of Certain Relationships Between Intelligence Quotients, English Placement Test Scores, and Scholastic Averages of Students Enrolled in Modern Foreign Languages, 1930-1936, University of Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1937-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ensor Tallent</lname>
<fname>Emma</fname>
<mname>Ruth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>French Linguistics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From the Definition and Scope of the Study)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At the outset of the project, originally undertaken in the fall of 1936, it was hoped to discover certain definite facts regarding the status of foreign languages at the University (the trend of enrollment toward each of the various languages or away from them, and from what other subjects of the curriculum students came to foreign languages or to what subjects they went from them; the total enrollment in the various languages over the years studied, etc., etc.). It was not at that time fully appreciated how much effort and time would be needed for a broad investigation which would involve a considerable number or factors. But it soon became evident that the study must be narrowed to a more modest scope, one which would reasonably be contained within the limits of a Master&#39;s thesis. It was decided, therefore, as the title of the thesis indicates, to restrict the investigation to a study and an analysis of the relationships between Intelligence Quotients, English Placement Test Scores, and Scholastic Averages of students enrolled in modern foreign languages during 1930-1936.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis consists of eight correlations, their evaluation and interpretation. The correlations are for the following: (1) intelligence quotients and scholastic averages, (2) intelligence quotients and averages of modern foreign language grades, (3) intelligence quotients and averages of English grades, (4) English placement test grades and scholastic averages, (5) English placement test grades and averages of modern foreign language grades, (6) English placement test grades and averages of English grades, (7) averages of modern foreign language grades and scholastic averages, and (8) averages of modern foreign language grades and averages of English grades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preceding the correlations are descriptions of the collection, selection and analysis of the data. Following the correlations come conclusions which were drawn from the relationships discovered. It is felt that the conclusions may have some validity, since they are based on a fairly large number of figures, and cover a total of six academic years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign languages taken into consideration are French, Spanish, and German. Italian, having been taught only in the year 1931-1932, failed to offer sufficient data for consideration.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4373</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5879&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4373</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5879</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-03T10:42:51-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9785851</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4373</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Walter E. Stiefel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>F. F. Frantz, Gerald E. Wade</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>French</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1937-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1937-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>