<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Measuring the Livability of Shakespeare&#39;s London</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:54:17-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ryessler@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yessler</lname>
<fname>Reagan A</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Using a modified version of the currently used Economist Intelligence Unit Global Livability Report, I will measure the livability of London during the lifetime of William Shakespeare (1564-1616), using both qualitative and quantitative historical data, and reaching a final quantitative measure of livability. I will measure five broad criteria categories: stability, healthcare, culture/environment, education, and infrastructure. I will eliminate criteria based on their anachronisms with the period; thus, criteria such as public healthcare, level of corruption, public education indicators, telecommunications, international links, and energy provisions must be eliminated or reconfigured, as they did not exist in early modern London as they do now. In keeping with the view that this report should be measured by the standards of the time, not by modern ones, views on the value of child labor and other such contemporarily illegal acts will be judged based on the historical context. Reflecting the number of sub-criteria, stability will constitute 25% of London’s livability, healthcare 15%, culture/environment 35%, education 10%, and infrastructure 15% of the overall livability score. Scores will be broken down into 20 point increments, with scores of 80-100 points reflecting ideal livability, and scores of 50 or less will reflect severely restricted living.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/18</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1171&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1171</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-16T12:09:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11969827</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ron Foresta</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>