<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Statistical Analysis and Forecast of the University of Tennessee Enrollment</title>
<publication-date>1950-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Boling</lname>
<fname>Edward</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Statistics and Probability</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statement of the Problem: It is the problem of this investigation to analyze by use of statistical methods the number of students enrolled at The University of Tennessee from 1899 to 1950, and with the aid of such analysis to forecast possible future enrollments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data used in this investigation will be limited in that only the resident students of that portion of The University of Tennessee which is located at Knoxville, Tennessee, will be used. Thus, the Colleges, Schools and Experiment Stations located in Memphis, Martin, Jackson, Columbia, Greeneville, Nashville, Crossville and Springfield, and the University extension work carried on throughout the counties of the state are not to furnish data for this study. The analysis of the enrollment data will cover the period beginning 1899 and ending 1950 with particular emphasis being given to the data in the past two decades. With the aid of the results of the analysis, the possible future enrollment will be forecast through 1970. It is essential that, continuously, recognition be given to the vast number of unknown variables entering into a forecast of future college enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2994</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4368&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2994</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4368</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-08T09:12:15-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6432889</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2994</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. M. Deepree</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David B. Chambers, O. M. Suskind</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Statistics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1950-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1950-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>