<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Numerical study of the electron-phonon interaction in multiorbital materials</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sli43@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Shaozhi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electron-phonon coupling</keyword>
<keyword>electron-electron correlation</keyword>
<keyword>phase diagram</keyword>
<keyword>charge-density-wave</keyword>
<keyword>orbital-selective</keyword>
<keyword>breathing phonon</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis examines the electron-phonon (&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph) interaction in multiorbital correlated systems using various numerical techniques, including determinant quantum Monte Carlo and dynamical mean field theory. First, I studied the non-linear &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph coupling in a one band model and found that even a weak non-linear &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph couplings can significantly shape both electronic and phononic properties. Second, I study the interplay between the &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph and electron-electron (&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;) interactions in a multiorbital Hubbard-Holstein model in both one- and infinite-dimension. In both cases, I found that a weak &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph interaction is enough to induce a phase transition from the Mott phase to the charge-density-wave phase. Moreover, I find that not only the &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-&lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt; correlation but also the &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph interaction can induce an orbital-selective phase. Our results imply that the &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph interaction is significant in the multiorbital correlated materials, such as the iron-based superconductors. Last, I studied the offdiagonal &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph interaction in a two-dimensional three-orbital model defined on a Lieb lattice. I consider an sp-type model, which is like a 2D analog of the barium bismuthate high temperature superconductors. I found a metal-to-insulator (MI) transition as decreasing temperature at half filling and identified a dimerized structure in the insulating phase. With hole doping, the ordered polarons and bipolarons correlations disappear but the short-range correlations are present, implying that polarons and bipolarons preform in the matellic phase and freeze into a periodic array in the insulating state. In sum, this thesis reveals the importance of the &lt;i&gt;e&lt;/i&gt;-ph interaction in the multiorbital materials and gives an alarm to people when study these multiorbital materials.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4998</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6539&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4998</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6539</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T14:08:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13415367</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4998</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven S. Johnston</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Elbio R. Dagotto, Takeshi Egami, Thomas A. Maier, Hanno Weitering</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5432-6802</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Portions of this document were previously published in the following journal
Europhysics Letters 109, 27002 (2015)
Phys. Rev. B 92, 064301 (2015)
Phys. Rev. E 93, 063313 (2016)
Phys. Rev, B 94, 235126 (2016)
Phys. Rev. B 95, 121112(R) (2017)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>