<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tuning Sol-Gel Phase Diagrams of Doubly Thermosensitive Hydrophilic Diblock Copolymers in Water</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>njin@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jin</lname>
<fname>Naixiong</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Water-soluble</keyword>
<keyword>pH-responsive</keyword>
<keyword>thermosensitive</keyword>
<keyword>diblock copolymer</keyword>
<keyword>phase diagram</keyword>
<keyword>lower critical solution temperature</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation presents the synthesis of stimuli-responsive hydrophilic diblock copolymers and the study of their behavior in water under various conditions. The polymers were made by “living”/controlled radical polymerization. Chapter 1 presents a background of this dissertation. Chapters 2-4 describe a family of doubly thermosensitive diblock copolymers with a small amount of carboxylic acid groups incorporated into either one or both blocks. The lower critical solution temperature (LCST) of the weak acid-containing block increases with increasing pH due to the ionization of carboxylic acid. Chapter 5 presents the preparation of pH-sensitive diblock copolymer micelle-embedded agarose hydrogels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2 describes the synthesis and solution behavior of poly(methoxytri(ethylene glycol) acrylate-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-acrylic acid)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-poly(ethoxydi(ethylene glycol) acrylate) (P(TEGMA-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-AA)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-PDEGEA)). PTEGMA and PDEGEA are thermosensitive polymers with LCSTs of 58 and 9 °C [degree Celsius], respectively, in water. A 20 wt% aqueous solution of P(TEGMA-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-AA)-&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-PDEGEA with pH of 3.11 underwent transitions from a free-flowing liquid, to a free-standing gel, to a hot liquid, and to a cloudy mixture upon heating. The &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt; [sol-to-gel transition temperature] and &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;gel-sol&lt;/sub&gt; [gel-to-sol transition temperature] are closely related to the LCSTs of the two blocks. Upon raising pH, the &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;gel-sol&lt;/sub&gt; increased, while the &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt; remained the same. Accordingly, only the upper boundary of the sol-gel phase diagram shifted upward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3 presents the tuning of &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt; of moderately concentrated aqueous solutions of doubly thermosensitive diblock copolymers by incorporating a small amount of AA groups into the lower LCST block and changing the solution pH. The AA content had a significant effect on the pH dependence of &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;sol-gel&lt;/sub&gt;. Chapter 4 shows that by incorporating a small amount of carboxylic acid groups into both blocks of a doubly thermosensitive diblock copolymer, the C-shaped sol-gel phase diagram can be readily and reversibly shifted by changing the solution pH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5 presents the fabrication of pH-sensitive diblock copolymer micelle-embedded agarose hydrogels. The gel properties were not significantly affected by the incorporation of the micelles even when the polymer concentration reached 5 mg/g. The pH-induced release of the payload from the core of micelles in a hybrid gel was studied. Chapter 6 presents conclusions and future work.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1743</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2845&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1743</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2845</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-18T21:20:06-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3732427</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1743</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bin Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark D. Dadmun, Charles S. Feigerle, Wei He</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>