<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>JAEPL, Vol. 1, Winter 1995-1996</title>
<publication-date>1995-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>State University of New York (SUNY) at Brockport</institution>
<lname>Brand</lname>
<fname>Alice</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
<suffix>(Editor)</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Creative Writing</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>Liberal Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Essays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary C. Doane. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Reality: Constructivism, Metaphor, and Cosmology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Two philosophies of metaphor are contrasted in constructing discourse and reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek Owens. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earthworm Hermeneutics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; As an alternative to recent misreadings of boundary politics, a more responsible, outsider pedagogy needs to be cultivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Doherty. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strictly Ballroom? Dancing Along the Borders of Movement and Writing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Multiple intelligences are exercised when movement and writing intersect in the composition curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellen W. Kaplan. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Subversive Play: Using Play, Dream, and the Body in the Classroom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The as-if world of play brings body-centered knowledge into the expressive writing class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Randi Patterson and Kim Jernigan . &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Found Play: Learning and Teaching the Value of Reading and Writing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The &quot;found&quot; play is designed to make explicit the interpretive strategies that students use in everyday life, in a literary work, and in critical reading and writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Jo Grossman. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apples, Cupcakes, and Beige: Subjectivity and Academic Discourse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; The relationship between intentional autobiographical reference and academic research yields a discourse called the writer-scholar&#39;s story of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anne Mullin. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Plea for Re-Form Aesthetics in the Writing Classroom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The emphasis on meaning and ideas should be refocused on form as an important aesthetic element in writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cramer Cauthen. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing Ritual and the Cultural Unconscious: The Great Mother Archetype in the Composition Class&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Jungian theory and feminist epistemology can be synthesized through their mythopoetic ways of making knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristie S. Fleckenstein. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotional Implication: Performing Within Emotional Gaps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The role of emotional implication is a process by which writers leave and fill emotional gaps within a text, thus creating their readers, text worlds, and themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linda T. Calendrillo. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Imagery, Psychology, and Rhetoric: An Examination of Recurring Problems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The parallel debates on mental imagery in contemporary psychology and classical rhetoric have led to its marginal status in composition studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hildy Miller. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Images at the Heart of Things: The Writer&#39;s Unconscious Speaking&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Two case studies depict ways in which mental imagery from a Jungian perspective influences writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martha Goff Stoner.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mastery: Or, Where Does True Wisdom Lie?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Zen philosophy and contemporary physics heighten awareness of wisdom as a process not a product.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jaepl/vol1/iss1/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1025&amp;amp;context=jaepl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>fullissue</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-03T10:33:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>The Journal of the Assembly for Expanded Perspectives on Learning</publication-title>
<context-key>4286638</context-key>
<submission-path>jaepl/vol1/iss1/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>JAEPL, Vol. 1, Winter 1995-1996</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>