<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cruelty Intervention Advocacy, a new approach to animal hoarding interventions</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>allison.cardona@aspca.org</email>
<lname>Cardona</lname>
<fname>Allison</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Animal hoarding affects thousands of animals and people across the United States. Conservative estimates place the number of new cases at two to three thousand per year, though no centralized database exists, so the full scope of the problem is unknown. Unlike intentional, single acts of cruelty, animal hoarding impacts a large number of animals over a prolonged period of time. Any type of animal can be hoarded, though the majority of hoarding situations involve cats and dogs, with numbers ranging from a few dozen to several hundred and even thousands of animals living in a single location. Accumulation of urine, feces and clutter in sometimes quite cramped and poorly ventilated living quarters are common place hazards to both humans and animals in hoarding homes. It is not just the hoarded animals who suffer, though they are the frequent victims of contagious illness, lack of veterinary care and generalized chronic ill health; the people who hoard animals live daily with them and are exposed to the same dangerous environmental conditions. They are often in a state of self-neglect and in need of vital social services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complexity of animal hoarding cases makes resolution a distinct challenge for animal and human service professionals. Because so little is known about the mental health components and the animal aspect is so visible, responses vary widely, depending on the agency and perception of the individual. Agencies unfamiliar with animal hoarding may seek immediate removal of the animals and criminal prosecution, which does not typically address the underlying mental health and environmental concerns. Removal of the animals addresses the most apparent symptom and not the root of the problem. Without mandated counseling and monitoring, animal hoarders will inevitably recollect, putting more animals at risk of long-term neglect and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ASPCA recognizes that collaboration across animal welfare, law enforcement and social services is crucial to a holistic resolution of cases. Through its New York City-based Cruelty Intervention Advocacy program, the ASPCA is creating a progressive approach to managing this public health issue by developing an in-house team of animal welfare professionals, social workers and humane law enforcement agents. Cases are handled on an individual basis through a variety of internal and external services: spay/neuter, veterinary care, surrender of animals, connection to social services and long-term monitoring. Participation in the program is voluntary, though the humane law enforcement department is engaged throughout the process in the event that animal cruelty or other charges need to be considered. Team members conduct an overall assessment and connect the individual to services, advocating for the recognition of animal hoarding as a serious mental health issue. Since its inception in 2010, the program has handled 80 cases, involving 118 individuals and assisted over 2,500 animals. Intervention strategies and ongoing case management of five hoarding cases are highlighted in this presentation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1067&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1067</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-20T08:05:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3552350</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Allison Cardona, Director of Cruelty Intervention Advocacy Program. In her almost ten years at the ASPCA, Allison has worked in a variety of departments and disciplines, including disaster response, community outreach, cruelty investigations, volunteer management, program development and grants administration. Allison received her Bachelor of Science in Public Affairs from Empire State College and is fluent in Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleen Doherty, Program Manager, Cruelty Intervention Advocacy Program. Colleen joined the ASPCA&#39;s Cruelty Intervention Advocacy Program in 2011 and has excelled in her position as the primary case worker and intervention coordinator. She has skillfully managed a significant caseload in addition to overseeing a grant program for financially disadvantaged pet owners, collaborating with a network of partner veterinary clinics and social service agencies. Currently a student at St. Joseph&#39;s College in Brooklyn, NY, Colleen has an anticipated graduation date of 2015, with a major in Community Health.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Allison Cardona, 347-346-3712, 520 8th Avenue, NY, NY 10018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleen Doherty, 646-455-9668, 520 8th Avenue, NY, NY 10018&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>MEDALLION ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>The link between human and animal violence</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>