<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Classification of subwatershed slopes and geotechnical characterization of steep slopes on reclaimed mine lands in East Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>White</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
<mname>Hamilton</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Civil engineering</keyword>
<keyword>Strip mining</keyword>
<keyword>Slopes (Soil mechanics)</keyword>
<keyword>Reclamation of land</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Mining and logging activity in the Appalachian region create both excessive runoff and sedimentation in local streams and rivers. Also, the Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977 led to over compaction of mine spoil which has led to reclaimed mine lands which will not grow economically viable native hardwood forests. In recent years a construction technique known as low compaction grading has allowed for suitable tree growth but stability and sedimentation have not yet been explored. The purpose of this paper is to create a rapid assessment method to classify the characteristics of watersheds based upon their geomorphology, and then to match this process to the established Rapid Geomorphic Assessment (RGA) method; these methods are intended to correspond to the tendency for a given slope to produce sediment. Also, this research attempts to match upland disturbance areas common in East Tennessee to sediment production characteristics.Lastly, mine spoil physical characteristics were determined and used to determine slope stability on steep reclaimed mine slopes using the low compaction grading technique, and to determine the medium&#39;s suitability for tree growth. No correlations were found between the developed Rapid Slope Assessment and the established RGA method. Sediment production characteristics were measured and compared for several land use disturbance areas common to East Tennessee and it was determined that logging roads were the most prone to high sediment production and then mining roads, logged areas, and mined areas followed in that order. Lastly, dry and wet unit weights, moisture contents, and grain size distributions were measured for reclaimed mine slopes using the low compaction grading method, and slope stability was assessed using an infinite slope analysis. It was determined that the nuclear density gauge was the most reliable and convenient way to measure unit weight.Furthermore the factor of safety against slope failure ranged from 1.9 to 1.4. These relatively low factors of safety are acceptable due to the low cost and consequence of slope failure on surface mine sites.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5693</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7315&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5693</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7315</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467441</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5693</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eric Drumm</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>