<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>In Service Performance Evaluation of Erosion Prevention Sediment Control Devices</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ahangul@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hangul</lname>
<fname>Ali</fname>
<mname>Riza</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Erosion Prevention</keyword>
<keyword>Sediment Control</keyword>
<keyword>Soil Disturbance</keyword>
<keyword>Highway Construction</keyword>
<keyword>Erosion Plans</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Erosion Prevention and Sediment Control (EPSC) market continuously expands with the addition of new products based on research and development. While some products may require special equipment for installation, others are installation ready. There have not been any investigations conducted on installation complications and cost to gain feedback from construction field personnel with regard to which practices are performing better and/or are preferred. The objective of this thesis is to further evaluate the current practices from performance and cost perspectives, in order to improve the plans development efficiency for the Tennessee Department of Transportation’ Roadway Design, Environmental, and Operations Divisions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4878</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6068&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4878</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6068</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-24T05:09:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10064812</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4878</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John S. Schwartz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jon Hathaway, Thanos Papanicolaou</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The performance, both in terms of reduction of sediment erosion and off-site transport and product durability, has only been studied during the active roadway construction sites for a limited degree. A few examples include, T. Diehl, Suspended Sediment Concentrations at Six Highway Construction Outfalls, USGS 2014, Statewide Construction Storm Water Turbidity Monitoring Study for the Tennessee Department of Transportation (TDOT) 2010-2012. TDOT Materials and Test Division, National Wattle (Sediment Tube) Survey Report, April 2006, and Summary report, Detailed Analysis related to the Functionality of TDOT Standard Erosion and Sediment-Control Structures under Conditions Presented by the 2-year/24-Hour Storm Event in Tennessee, July 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to implement the results of the subject studies in to a practice as well as assessing the current practices, the objective of this research defined as to investigate in service performance of the effectiveness of the current EPSC device installation practices in field. In addition, this research further to evaluates the application guidance and quantity calculation methods currently provided for each EPSC device, also total cost of installed devices based on initial installation, maintenance and field performance. Outcome of this research will result in improved quality of standard drawings, accuracy of contract plans as well as construction cost estimate which should reduce the number of change orders, and construction cost overruns. The practices included in the construction plans and SWPPP will need to control runoff, stabilize slopes and exposed soils and limit the movement of soils into drainage systems and natural areas. A key element to ensure effectiveness of the erosion and sediment control plan is the implementation of an inspection and maintenance program. Frequent inspection and maintenance activities ensure that the installed temporary sediment control practices are operating effectively throughout the course of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EPSC market continuously expands with the addition of new products based on research and development. While some products may require special equipment for installation, others are installation ready. There have not been any investigations conducted on installation complications and cost to gain feedback from construction field personnel with regards to which practices are performing better and/or are preferred.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>