<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Technology-Based Self-Service: From Customer Productivity Toward Customer Value</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Anıtsal</lname>
<fname>İsmet</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this dissertation is to investigate the&lt;br /&gt;concept of customer productivity in a technology-based&lt;br /&gt;self-service context (e.g., self-checkouts in grocery&lt;br /&gt;stores) to understand how customer productivity and&lt;br /&gt;customer value are related to each other. A preliminary&lt;br /&gt;qualitative study initially explored the meaning of&lt;br /&gt;customer productivity and the labor provided by customers&lt;br /&gt;in self-service shopping and TBSS environments. Based on&lt;br /&gt;these exploratory insights and the extant literature, a&lt;br /&gt;conceptual framework was developed to identify the&lt;br /&gt;relationships between customer inputs into a TBSS option&lt;br /&gt;and customer outputs from that option influenced by&lt;br /&gt;customer perceptions of self-service technology (SST) and&lt;br /&gt;contact employee performance. Two adopter categories were&lt;br /&gt;employed for comparison purposes: enthusiastic adopters and&lt;br /&gt;reluctant adopters.&lt;br /&gt;The quantitative study utilized a survey research&lt;br /&gt;design. After pre-testing the scale items with a large&lt;br /&gt;student sample, the latent variable structural equation&lt;br /&gt;model was tested by data collected from both enthusiastic &lt;br /&gt;and reluctant adopters who were customers of a large&lt;br /&gt;national grocery chain.&lt;br /&gt;There were 27 hypotheses in total. Besides testing the&lt;br /&gt;proposed hypotheses, the dissertation also investigated a&lt;br /&gt;total of seven potential relationships between the&lt;br /&gt;exploratory construct of emotional effort and the SST&lt;br /&gt;performance, contact employee performance, effort saving,&lt;br /&gt;time saving, quality of customer labor, quality of service&lt;br /&gt;and customer productivity.&lt;br /&gt;This research regarding the customer productivity and&lt;br /&gt;its relationship to customer value has made important&lt;br /&gt;contributions to managers and researchers by filling gaps&lt;br /&gt;in the productivity, retailing and services marketing&lt;br /&gt;literatures.&lt;br /&gt;It fills certain gaps in the literature by:&lt;br /&gt;• introducing the new concept of customer productivity&lt;br /&gt;in services marketing area,&lt;br /&gt;• providing an understanding the concept of customer&lt;br /&gt;productivity in a technology-based self-service&lt;br /&gt;environment,&lt;br /&gt;• incorporating both quantity and quality dimensions&lt;br /&gt;into inputs by customer and outputs for customer in&lt;br /&gt;testing multiple links toward customer productivity,• empirically testing a conceptual framework on customer&lt;br /&gt;productivity,&lt;br /&gt;• predicting links based on the antecedents of customer&lt;br /&gt;productivity, retailer support (SST and contact&lt;br /&gt;employee) and the overall outcome,&lt;br /&gt;• establishing the link between customer productivity&lt;br /&gt;and customer value,&lt;br /&gt;• exploring the concept of emotional effort and&lt;br /&gt;introducing it as a viable construct in customer&lt;br /&gt;productivity,&lt;br /&gt;• differentiating between enthusiastic and reluctant&lt;br /&gt;adopters of TBSS options in general and self-checkouts&lt;br /&gt;in particular.&lt;br /&gt;This dissertation research also provides important&lt;br /&gt;implications for managers. It contributes to the existing&lt;br /&gt;practical business applications in terms of retail&lt;br /&gt;strategies and tactics as concerns customers usage of&lt;br /&gt;technology-based self-service by:&lt;br /&gt;• presenting the emerging concept of customer&lt;br /&gt;productivity as a new source of competitive advantage,&lt;br /&gt;• providing a unique way to create and deliver customer&lt;br /&gt;value based on the concept of customer productivity –&lt;br /&gt;the self-productivity as perceived by customer,&lt;br /&gt;• differentiating between the input and output sides of&lt;br /&gt;the system for customer productivity to provide&lt;br /&gt;further tactical details that can be used in&lt;br /&gt;implementation phase of the crafted strategy,&lt;br /&gt;• differentiating between quality of customer labor and&lt;br /&gt;quality of service, and suggesting that the&lt;br /&gt;significant link between them can potentially be used&lt;br /&gt;to develop a customer training program to accelerate&lt;br /&gt;the adoption of self-checkouts by reluctant adopters,&lt;br /&gt;• underlining the importance of emotional effort as a&lt;br /&gt;viable concept that can be used as a competitive tool&lt;br /&gt;to increase perceived quality levels for both customer&lt;br /&gt;labor and service,&lt;br /&gt;• providing ideas on how new generation SSTs can&lt;br /&gt;successfully be developed based on a number of&lt;br /&gt;consequences such as contact employee performance,&lt;br /&gt;quality of customer labor and emotional effort,&lt;br /&gt;• differentiating between enthusiastic and reluctant&lt;br /&gt;adopters to understand what can potentially be done at&lt;br /&gt;strategic and tactical levels with regard to&lt;br /&gt;introducing, targeting and positioning self-checkout&lt;br /&gt;systems, other TBSS options and even technology-based&lt;br /&gt;business-to-business self-services.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1680</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3206&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1680</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3206</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-08T13:56:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4409536</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1680</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David W. Schumann</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ann E. Fairhurst, Pratibha A. Dabholkar, Daniel J. Flint</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>