<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Selection and Assessment of Potential Therapy Animal Candidates: Animal Welfare and Ethical Considerations in AAI</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>klwycoff@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Wycoff</lname>
<fname>Kirby</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As the field of Human-Animal Interactions continues to evolve, there is an increasing demand for carefully selected and highly trained animals to serve humans in multiple and varied capacities. Regardless of the species, or the particular role (AAT, Psychiatric Support Dog, Equine Assisted Learning), animals are increasingly being “drafted” for roles in human health services. As the field continues to expand, we have a critical obligation to humanely utilize animals to serve our needs, without ignoring their own. Central to this issue is the question of how human service professionals make decisions about the suitability of potential therapy animal candidates for specific service roles. Only with the use of appropriate assessment instruments, that have the sensitivity to assess the traits that are relevant to the demands of a particular job, are we able to provide high quality clinical services to human clients, while respecting our animal partners in the process. This presentation will highlight one tool that may aid in an ethical decision-making process when considering potential therapy animal candidates. The Clothier Animal Response Assessment Tool (C.A.R.A.T™) is a multi-dimensional assessment tool developed by Suzanne Clothier, which is being used broadly in the field of Human-Animal Interactions in the selection and assessment of potential therapy animal candidates. With this tool, professionals involved in AAT are better equipped to answer the following questions: What are the unique demands of this job? What are the unique characteristics of this animal? Can we reasonably (fairly and humanely) expect that this particular animal can do this particular job? This poster presentation will highlight the ethical questions that practitioners may want to consider, as well as possible tools that they can use to address those ethical concerns when considering the potential suitability of therapy animal candidates. Current applications and future directions related to the selection of therapy animal candidates in the field of Human-Animal Interactions will also be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1087&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1087</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-26T07:52:55-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3787304</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Biography of Principal Investigator: Dr. Kirby L. Wycoff is a Nationally Certified School Psychologist well as a license eligible psychologist in the state of Pennsylvania. Dr. Wycoff graduated from the Graduate School of Applied and Professional Psychology at Rutgers University with a Doctor of Psychology degree. She completed her APA approved pre-doctoral internship at a residential school in Hershey PA in 2011. She remained on staff as the postdoctoral resident where she is currently providing clinical care, crisis response, assessment and program development and consultation services across grades K-12. Dr. Wycoff spearheaded a new initiative in the Student Health Services where she developed programming and curriculum for an Animal Assisted Therapy Program intended to increase social and emotional competence in Elementary, Middle and High School students. Dr. Wycoff was nominated for the 2012 “Pennsylvania Psychological Association’s Early Career Psychologist of the Year Award” for her innovative work using Animal Assisted Therapy in clinical settings.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Kirby L. Wycoff, Psy.D., NCSP Post-Doctoral Psychology Resident/Fellow The Milton Hershey School&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T18:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Poster: Scheduled poster session</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>4.6.13.final.handout.uTENN.The_Selection_and_Assessment_of_Potential_Therapy_Animal_Candidates.Ethical_Considerations.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>4.6.13.final.handout.uTENN.The_Selection_and_Assessment_of_Potential_Therapy_Animal_Candidates.Ethical_Considerations.pdf</upload-name>
<url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1087&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>