<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relative Invertebrate Abundance and Biomass in Conservation Reserve Program Plantings in Northern Missouri</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-24T14:16:45-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Missouri</institution>
<lname>Burger</lname>
<fname>Loren</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Missouri Department of Conservation</institution>
<lname>Kurzejeski</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Missouri Department of Conservation</institution>
<lname>Dailey</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>V.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Missouri</institution>
<lname>Ryan</lname>
<fname>Mark</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>brood ecology</keyword>
<keyword>brood habitat</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>Conservation Reserve Program</keyword>
<keyword>insect</keyword>
<keyword>invertebrate</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We measured relative invertebrate abundance, biomass, and diversity in Conservation Reserve Program (CRP) fields planted to red clover (Trifolium pratense)/timothy (Phleum pratense), timothy, orchard-grass (Dactylis glomerata), tall fescue (Festuca pratensis), warm-season grasses (big bluestem [Andropogon gerardi]/switch grass [Panicum virgatum]), orchard-grass/Korean lespedeza (Kummerowia stipu/,acea), and conventionally-tilled soybeans, to assess brood habitat quality for northern bobwhite (Colinus virginkinus). We sampled invertebrate populations by vacuuming along 3 15-m transects (4.56 m2/sample) within 4 fields of each planting type, at 2-week intervals from 1 July to 15 August 1990 and 1991. Invertebrate abundance and biomass were lowest in early August (P &lt; 0.05). The CRP fields planted to a red clover/timothy mixture, and dominated by red clover, had the highest levels of invertebrate abundance and biomass (P &lt; 0.05). Conventionally-tilled soybeans had lower invertebrate abundance and biomass than all CRP covertypes (P&lt; 0.05). Mean invertebrate abundance and biomass in CRP fields were 4 times that of soybean fields. In northern Missouri, CRP fields could provide quality brood habitat if structural characteristics are also consistent with brood foraging needs. Incorporation of a legume in CRP plantings may produce higher invertebrate densities and improve the value of these fields as brood habitat.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol3/iss1/14</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1087&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>14</label>
<document-type>habitat_ecology</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1087</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-24T12:54:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10469364</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol3/iss1/14</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>