<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fine-scale habitat use related to crop depredation by female white-tailed deer in an agricultural landscape</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Adams</lname>
<fname>Kent</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The white-tailed deer (&lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) is the most popular game animal in the United States but is also responsible for a large amount of damage to agricultural crops.  Understanding how deer use agricultural landscapes on a small scale will facilitate management.  Global Positioning System (GPS) telemetry collars were attached to 16 female white-tailed deer at Chesapeake Farms, Kent County, Maryland, during 2 summer growing seasons (10 in 2001 and 6 in 2002).  Twelve collars collected usable data and collar success averaged 90 and 86 percent in 2001 and 2002, respectively.  Mean adaptive kernel home-range sizes (25.22 ha in 2001 and 39.36 ha in 2002) did not differ between years (p = 0.14).  Mean core areas (3.12 ha in 2001 and 6.28 ha in 2002) were larger in 2002 (p = 0.04).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A habitat selection analysis was performed to determine which habitats were selected more or less than others during the soybean growing season.  Habitat use pooled across all deer was different from random in both years (p &lt; 0.0001).  Habitat use differed among individual deer (p &lt; 0.0001).  Agricultural crops were among the most selected habitats in both years.  In 2001, corn ranked first and soybeans ranked fourth.  In 2002, corn and soybeans were selected equally and ranked third.  Other important habitats included wooded and early successional areas.  Selection of clover ranked comparatively low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assess temporal use of selected habitats throughout the growing season, I calculated percentage of daily deer locations occurring in corn fields, soybean fields, clover plots, early successional areas, and wooded areas.  Deer use of natural cover and food sources declined as use of crops increased.  Temporal use patterns of some habitats changed between 2001 and 2002, which was likely related to a drought the second year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducing deer damage to agricultural crops while maintaining a healthy deer population requires an integrated strategy that incorporates both deer harvest and habitat management.  Considering deer use of an agricultural landscape on a small scale will assist managers in abating damage and providing quality deer hunting opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1885</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3241&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1885</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3241</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-19T12:49:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4602377</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1885</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisa I. Muller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank van Manen, John B. Wilkerson, Craig A. Harper</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>