<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Dental Analysis of the South Dakota Arikara Including a Comparative Analysis of C. G. Turner&#39;s 1967 &lt;em&gt;The Dentition of Arctic Peoples&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grant</lname>
<fname>Michele</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A metric and non-metric dental trait analysis was performed on the South Dakota Arikara population housed at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Fifty-one male, female, and sex indeterminable individual skeletons from the Larson, Leavenworth, Mobridge, and Sully excavations were examined for standard metric and non-metric dental traits. These data were subjected to standard chi-square analyses in order to test for statistically significant sexual dimorphism. Significant sexual dimorphism was found on the basis of many of the metric dental traits. Several non-metric dental traits also exhibited significant sexual dimorphism. This analysis was then compared to C.G. Turner&#39;s Arctic populations data and other analyses based on standard dental traits. The South Dakota Arikara data were similar to data obtained from other Asian-derived populations, but differed significantly from data obtained from African-derived and European-derived populations. Instances of non-metric dental trait sexual dimorphism may be traced to studies linking metric and non-metric dental trait sexual dimorphism to developmental dental genetics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4199</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5652&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4199</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5652</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-11-02T10:49:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9336118</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4199</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Jantz, Andrew Kramer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>