<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Latitudinal Gradient in the Body Mass Index (BMI), and the BMI&#39;s Geometric and Statistical Relationships to the Surface Area: Volume Ratio and Body Shape</title>
<publication-date>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>O&#39;Neil</lname>
<fname>Brandy</fname>
<mname>Lea</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The body mass index (BMI), weight/height&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (W/H&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;), is currently the index of choice for assessment of nutritional status. Statements in the literature about the BMI as a potential expression of “cold adaptation” or “Bergmann’s Rule” beg the question: What does that BMI measure in terms of size, shape, and the surface area:volume (SA:V) ratio? Geometric modeling shows that the BMI captures both size and shape and is inversely related to the SA:V ratio. This admixture of size/shape information, combined with the unmeaningful absolute value of the BMI, preclude precise understanding of what it measures. A new weight-height-based variable was derived –the mean effective breadth (MEB)- which more clearly relates to the SA:V ratio and heuristically represents what weight-for-height does: it alters body breadth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous findings of a geographical cline in the BMI in Native Americans were expanded to a worldwide sample of 328 adult populations. The BMI and MEB increased with increasing latitude, while the SA:V ratio decreased. All three ratios were also correlated with variables that alter the biological SA:V ratio: sitting height, relative sitting height, and bi-acromial and bi-iliac breadths. The MEB showed higher correlations with latitude, weight, height, sitting height, relative sitting height, and bi-acromial breadth than did the BMI, though coefficients were similar to those of the SA:V ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BMI’s geometric and statistical associations with the SA:V ratio and measures of proportion or shape corroborate and amplify others’ findings that the BMI is not a shape-independent index of body size or nutritional status. The W/H&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ratio was originally conceived by Quetelet as a “proof” of body proportionality. Nutritional epidemiologists should beware these associations when using BMI cutoff categories to diagnose chronic energy deficiency or obesity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4230</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5695&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4230</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5695</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-16T12:55:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9483892</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4230</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Andrew Kramer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lyle W. Konigsberg, Richard L. Jantz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>