<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Wastewater Treatment Improvements for Rush Strong School</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T08:50:44-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kgrisso2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Grissom</lname>
<fname>Kelli Michelle</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>CSANFOR2@VOLS.UTK.EDU</email>
<lname>Sanford</lname>
<fname>Christina</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>agipson5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Gipson</lname>
<fname>Katie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>scounts1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Counts</lname>
<fname>Sharon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In 2000, Rush Strong Elementary School implemented a recirculating sand filter to treat their low-flow wastewater effluent. The existing wastewater treatment system was producing effluent that did not meet the regulations of Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation (TDEC). Jefferson County School System requested that Rocky Top Water Solutions create a design that would bring the school into compliance with TDEC regulations in a cost-effective manner. In order to satisfy this request, the team developed multiple alternative designs. These designs consider the client’s preferences and employ a multi-criteria decision matrix that was used to evaluate the alternatives based on four criteria categories derived from a triple bottom line sustainability analysis: cost, operation and maintenance, efficient technologies, and feasibility. This analysis yielded a recommendation of a 100% recirculation rate during low flows to account for summer breaks, where there is no influent flowing into the system. It was also recommended to add a modification filter layout so that the laterals can be continuously cleaned, as these systems are prone to such complications as clogging. With the proposed system improvements, it is believed that the school’s effluent will comply with state regulations and the system will work in an efficient manner.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/engineering/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1149&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1149</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-19T06:01:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10039533</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/engineering/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Jenny Retherford</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>