<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Resiliency and Leadership of Burley Tobacco Producers in Greene County, Tennessee: A Qualitative Study</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mtrose@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rose</lname>
<fname>Melody</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>adaptive</keyword>
<keyword>leadership</keyword>
<keyword>community</keyword>
<keyword>resilience</keyword>
<keyword>tobacco</keyword>
<keyword>greene</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to identify the perceptions of current Greene County burley tobacco producers regarding the resiliency in a declining global tobacco industry and how the producers perceive their leadership in burley tobacco production will be impacted in Greene County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten Greene County producers participated in this study through an interview conducted utilizing a series of 33 questions aimed at determining specific themes in regards to resiliency in their communities, as well as the individual producers adaptive leadership styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tobacco remains a viable and economic contributor to the Greene County economy. This study focused on current and past Greene County burley tobacco producers and/or industry representatives who have significant impacts on Greene County. This study first provided an in-depth review on the significant history of the tobacco industry and illustrated the importance of the crop to burley tobacco farmers, to the communities within Greene County, and to the economic vitality of Greene County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data collected from interviews were synthesized to correlate perceptions of current tobacco production in Greene County from the inception of the tobacco program to present-day in regards to cultural norms and economic impact, while simultaneously providing a portrayal of tobacco as a viable cash crop and its significance to present-day global production with the direct correlation of a community&#39;s response to overcoming significant change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was discovered burley tobacco has historical ties to the producers in Greene County, but with the significant changes that have occurred within the industry in the last 20 years, it has become almost impossible to remain profitable. As a result, Greene County producers have utilized an adaptive leadership approach to forge new paths in agriculture enterprises, as well as becoming leaders on the forefront of a dwindling industry in Greene County, contributing to resiliency in a changing market environment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3806</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5066&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3806</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5066</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-24T07:55:53-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/5066/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8206299</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3806</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carrie Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph Brockett, Christopher Stripling</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communications</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>