<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Quantitative Analysis of Influenza Virus-Specific B Cell Responses Generated by Infection and Vaccination</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Chattanooga</institution>
<lname>Joo</lname>
<fname>Hye</fname>
<mname>Mee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The two cellular components of B cell memory are antibody (Ab)-secreting cells (ASCs) and memory B cells (B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt;). B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; are quiescent cells that respond to “recall” antigen and contribute substantially to vaccine effectiveness. The rational evaluation of vaccination strategies is dependent on quantitative information on the state of B cell memory. Despite the importance of B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; in resistance to infection, there is little information on the nature of B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; populations generated by influenza infection or vaccination. The major goal of this dissertation was a comprehensive quantitative analysis of the frequency and distribution of influenza-specific B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; generated by influenza infection of the respiratory tract, or by vaccination with inactivated virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve this, a prerequisite was the development of a sensitive and reproducible limiting dilution assay (LDA) for determining influenza-specific B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; frequencies. The results in Chapter 2 demonstrated that a strategy utilizing BPL-inactivated virus particles was effective for the in vitro activation of virus-specific B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt;. This strategy selectively activates virus-specific B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; and, importantly, achieves this without a requirement for CD4+ T cell associated factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this strategy, the frequency of Influenza specific B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; in different anatomical sites was measured and we also tested three different forms of influenza virus immunization strategy; (i) intranasal (i.n.) infection, (ii) i.n. vaccination, (iii) intramuscular (i.m.) vaccination. The results in Chapter III, IV showed that following different forms of immunization, B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; dispersed broadly to organized lymphoid tissues throughout the body, and a population of ASCs was established in the bone marrow. ASC and B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; frequencies in these locations reflected the magnitude of the primary B cell response to the form of immunization. Thus, the frequencies were higher following i.n. infection. Interestingly, the state of B cell memory in the lung was profoundly influenced by the form of immunization. The lung was a preferential site of B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; localization after i.n. infection. However, this was not the case after i.m. immunization when B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; frequencies in the lung were considerably lower than in other sites. Our findings point to an effect of influenza infection on the lung environment that profoundly influences ASC and B&lt;sub&gt;Mem&lt;/sub&gt; trafficking to this site.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/52</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1080&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>52</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1080</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-12-22T10:45:23-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1096597</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/52</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Y. Sangster</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barry T. Rouse, Tim Sparer, Stephen J. Kennel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>