<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Preparation and characterization of organofunctional sol-gel materials and their application in toxic metal separation</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Im</lname>
<fname>Hee-Jung</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Inorganic-organic hybrid SiOz sol-gels anchored with amino (NHz-CHzCHz-NH-, TMSen, and -NH-CH2CH2-NH-, Bis-TMSen) and mercapto (HS-) ligands have been studied as new sorbents for heavy metal (e. g., Cu2+, Hg”, Cd2+, Zn2+, and Ni2+) separation. The TMSen—anchored gels were found to be selective for Cu” removal in the presence of Cd2+ and Zn”. In comparison, mercapto-anchored gels remove both Cu2+ and Cd2+ from a mixture of Cu”, Cd2+ and Zn”. These ligand-anchored materials, which were easily prepared fi&#39;om off-the-shelf chemicals in ca. 1 hr, were hydrophilic and thus showed fast kinetics of metal uptake and removal (from the gels) in aqueous solutions. The ligand-anchored sol gels loaded with metal ions were regenerated with acid, and the materials could then be used in subsequent metal removal cycles. The effect of the reaction conditions [catalysts, ligand/Si(OMe)4 ratios, curing temperatures, and surfactant existence] on sol-gel properties and performance were investigated. In addition, the kinetics of Cu2+ uptake and removal by these ligand-anchored sol-gel materials were studied.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6248</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8200&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6248</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8200</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450343</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6248</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ziling (Ben) Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jamie L. Adcock, Lee Magrid, David Joy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>