<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>BG-4, a novel anticancer peptide from bitter gourd (Momordica charantia), promotes apoptosis in human colon cancer cells</title>
<publication-date>2016-09-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>vdia@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Vermont</lname>
<fname>Dia</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Missouri, Columbia</institution>
<lname>Krihnan</lname>
<fname>Hari</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Momordica charantia is a perennial plant with reported health benefits. BG-4, a novel peptide from &lt;em&gt;Momordica charantia,&lt;/em&gt; was isolated, purified and characterized. The trypsin inhibitory activity of BG-4 is 8.6 times higher than purified soybean trypsin inhibitor. The high trypsin inhibitory activity of BG-4 may be responsible for its capability to cause cytotoxicity to HCT-116 and HT-29 human colon cancer cells with ED50values of 134.4 and 217.0 μg/mL after 48 h of treatment, respectively. The mechanism involved in the cytotoxic effect may be associated with induction of apoptosis as evidenced by increased percentage of HCT-116 and HT-29 colon cancer cells undergoing apoptosis from 5.4% (untreated) to 24.8% (BG-4 treated, 125 μg/mL for 16 h) and 8.5% (untreated) to 31.9% (BG-4 treated, 125 μg/mL for 16 h), respectively. The molecular mechanistic explanation in the apoptosis inducing property of BG-4 is due to reduced expression of Bcl-2 and increased expression of Bax leading to increased expression of caspase-3 and affecting the expression of cell cycle proteins p21 and CDK2. This is the first report on the anti-cancer potential of a novel bioactive peptide isolated from &lt;em&gt;Momordica charantia in vitro&lt;/em&gt; supporting the potential therapeutic property of BG-4 against colon cancer that must be addressed using &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; models of colon carcinogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_foodpubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1006&amp;amp;context=utk_foodpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1006</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-08T12:18:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Food Science and Technology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>10728087</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_foodpubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Dia, Vermont P. and Hari B. Krishnan. “BG-4, a Novel Anticancer Peptide from Bitter Gourd (Momordica charantia), Promotes Apoptosis in Human Colon Cancer Cells.” Scientific		 Reports 6 (2016).  http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep33532</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1038/srep33532</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-09-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Scientific Reports</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>