<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Infrared Spectrum of Formyl Fluoride</title>
<publication-date>1957-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stratton</lname>
<fname>Roy</fname>
<mname>Franklin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nine bands were observed in HOOF and thirteen DCOF. A rotational analysis was completed on five of the fundamental bands in each molecule. The ground state moments of inertia are internally consistent. The value of B which is quoted is actually B̅ = 1/2 (B+C). As the symmetric top approximation is used throughout, no information was obtained about the actual values of B and C themselves. We know, however, that they cannot differ by very much because symmetric top approximation gives consistent results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment of inertia were used to determine the approximate position of the hydrogen atom. The moments of inertia, however, are relatively insensitive to the position of the hydrogen atom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band centers were used to determine some of the vibrational constants. Several ω&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;°&#39;s were calculated, but none of the ω&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&#39;s could be determined. If the combination band ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;+ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; could be observed, it would then be possible to find ω&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rotational analysis could probably be completed on several of the combination bands. It seems likely that some of these, notably 2ν&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, in both molecules, might require that the symmetric top approximation be abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results quoted here might be improved considerably if some of the bands could be examined under higher resolution. It seemed that the parallel component of ν&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; (in both molecules) could be resolved with only a slight improvement in resolution. The unresolved regions in ν&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, apparently caused by interference between the lines, might also be cleared up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems likely that higher resolution would force one to give up the symmetric top approximation entirely. In any case, in a complete analysis of these molecules, it would be desirable to consider their asymmetry. Tables&lt;sup&gt;1,2&lt;/sup&gt; have been made by machine calculation which may be used to calculate the rotational energy levels of the asymmetric top for J up to 40. These tables would allow the asymmetry to be considered with a minimum of labor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2963</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4454&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2963</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4454</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-22T13:41:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6268879</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2963</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alvin H. Nielsen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William H. Fletcher, Dewy W. Morgan, W. E. Deeds, Isabel H. Tipton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1957-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1957-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>