<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Efficacy of Endo-Fighter® for Cattle Grazing Endophyte-Infected Tall Fescue Pastures During Summer and Early Fall</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Norman</lname>
<fname>Rebekah</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Two 84-day grazing trials were conducted (Aug 24 – Nov 17, 2006; Jun 14 - Sept 7, 2007) near Spring Hill, TN to determine the efficacy of Endo-Fighter (R), an ADM Alliance Nutrition, Inc. product designed to be fed to cattle grazing or fed endophyte-infected fescue or hay and Prototype, an improved version of Endo-Fighter (R). Tall fescue pastures with &gt;90% of pasture exhibiting infestation (E+), thus producing high concentration of ergot alkaloids in the grass, were grazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006 sixty weaned crossbred heifers (325 ± 17 kg) (2007, steers, 267 ± 18 kg) were used in a randomized block design (2007, CRD), blocked by previous treatment and randomly allotted to pastures with four animals per 1.2-ha paddocks and five replications per treatment. Treatments were ADM Alliance Nutrition, Inc. mineral products: 1) Mastergain (R) mineral = Control; 2) Endo-Fighter (R) mineral; 3) Prototype mineral. Animals had free choice access to E+ grass, water and shade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heifers were weighed on d 0, 1, 28, 56, 83, and 84 (2006) and on d 0, 1, 22, 43, 64, and 85 (2007). In 2006 data collected were initial, d 28, d 56, and final weights, and ADG. In 2007 data collected were initial, d 22, d 43, d 64, and final weights, and ADG for each period. Blood serum was collected at each weigh date for prolactin analysis. Mineral consumption and animal grazing behavior were determined at 14-d intervals. Data were analyzed using the MIXED procedure of SAS. For all variables, contrasts were performed to compare Control to mineral supplements containing Endo-Fighter (R) or Prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006 total ADG (kg) and average daily mineral consumption (g) were: 0.61, 170*; 0.56, 122*; 0.50, 146; for Control, Endo-Fighter (R) and Prototype, respectively (*P &lt; .09). In 2007 data were 0.61, 134; 0.57, 147; 0.56, 116; for Control, Endo-Fighter (R), and Prototype, respectively. For both years, serum prolactin was not different (P &gt; 0.05) among treatments. Animal performance and prolactin levels were not significantly affected by the feeding of Endo-Fighter (R) or Prototype in these trials. However, lack of response to Endo-Fighter (R) and Prototype in 2006 may have been attributed to mild weather conditions. In 2007 lack of response may have been a result of extreme heat and drought conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/418</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1451&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>418</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1451</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T12:08:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1148290</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/418</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John C. Waller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Clyde D. Lane, Kelly R. Robbins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/NormanRebekah.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>