<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nitrogen and Sulfur Influence Nutrient Usage and Accumulation in Onion</title>
<publication-date>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>Dean</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Georgia</institution>
<lname>Coolong</lname>
<fname>Timothy</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of New Hampshire - Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Georgia</institution>
<lname>Randle</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Anion analysis; Cation analysis; HPLC; ICP-AES; Macronutrient; Micronutrient; Pungency; Pyruvic acid; Soluble solids</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Horticulture</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Breeding and Genetics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;To study the effects of nitrogen (N) and sulfur (S) fertility on onion (&lt;em&gt;Allium cepa&lt;/em&gt; L.) bulb pungency, bulb fresh and dry weight, nutrient uptake and accumulation in the bulb, “Granex 33” onions were greenhouse grown using nutrient solution culture. A factorial arrangement of solutions containing 1.7, 15.0, and 41.7 mg L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; S and 10, 50, 90, and 130 mg L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; N were used. Bulb pungency and bulb fresh and dry weight were affected by both S and N treatments. Depletion patterns for most of the macronutrients from the nutrient solutions during plant growth were affected by N and S levels, and differed depending on the N and S combination. In certain N and S combinations, magnesium (Mg) and calcium (Ca) usage were unaffected over time. Bulb N levels increased with N fertility and decreased slightly with S availability, while bulb phosphorous levels responded linearly to N fertility. Overall changes in bulb Ca and Mg levels were minor, but were influenced by N and S fertility. Bulb S content was affected by low S and N fertility, decreasing with each. Boron levels in onion bulbs decreased with increasing N and S fertility, while bulb manganese, iron, and zinc concentrations tended to increase with increasing N availability and decrease with increasing S. Potassium, copper, and molybdenum bulb concentrations were unaffected by N or S fertility. These results have the potential of being used as a reference in developing nutritional programs designed for optimal onion performance having specific flavor intensities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/25</coverpage-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-30T08:23:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1587292</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/25</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Coolong, T. W., Kopsell, D. A., Kopsell, D. E. &amp; Randle, W. M. (2005). Nitrogen and Sulfur Influence Nutrient Usage and Accumulation in Onion. Journal of Plant Nutrition, 27(9), 1667-1686.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~db=all~content=a713648648~frm=titlelink</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>