<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Characterization of Pulsatile Flow by Positron Emission Particle Tracking</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>npatel39@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Patel</lname>
<fname>Nitant</fname>
<mname>Piyushbhai</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Positron Emission Particle Tracking (PEPT)</keyword>
<keyword>Multi-PEPT</keyword>
<keyword>Pulsatile Flow</keyword>
<keyword>Turbulent Flow</keyword>
<keyword>Lagrangian Flow Measurement</keyword>
<keyword>Hemodynamics</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Multi-positron emission particle tracking (M-PEPT) is a Lagrangian measurement technique that can be used to evaluate flow attributes. This study seeks to characterize steady flow in a tube, pulsatile flow in a circular and pinched cross section tube and explore particle detection uncertainties of our M-PEPT measurement. A pump driven flow loop and motorized ball valve are designed to create the pulsatile flow of frequency 2.1 Hz in a 19 mm diameter and 3.2 mm thick Masterkleer PVC tube. Anion exchange resins of 600-800 microns are labeled with fluorine-18 (half-life: 109.8 minutes) and pumped through the flow loop at flow velocity near 1 m/s, Womersley number near 70 and approximate Reynolds number of 20,000. Bulk flow velocity and pressure are measured to define the pulsatile flow features. In addition, particle trajectories are collected using M-PEPT and synchronized to a trigger signal produced by laser-photodiode mounted on the motorized ball valve. Trajectories are divided into 20 equally spaced time gated frames in each pulse cycle. A three-dimensional velocity field is generated at each phase of the pulse cycle by integrating time gated data from several hundred pulse cycles. The average location uncertainty in the M-PEPT measurement is calculated to be near 0.31 mm in the x and y-direction and 0.2 mm in z. The turbulent kinetic energy and diffusion characteristics of a steady flow is also presented.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5011</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6418&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5011</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6418</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-08T14:23:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13276667</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5011</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Arthur E. Riggles</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John D. Auxier II, Lawrence H. Heilbronn</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2372-1658</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Portions of this document were previously published in Experiments in Fluids Journal.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>