<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Roles of Stress Appraisal and Self-Efficacy in Fostering Resilience to Improve Psychosocial Outcomes Following Negative Life Events Among College Students:  A Multiple Mediation Analysis</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jbecker4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cody</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>stress appraisal</keyword>
<keyword>self-efficacy</keyword>
<keyword>resilience</keyword>
<keyword>self-concept</keyword>
<keyword>life events</keyword>
<keyword>coping</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>School Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this dissertation study was to explore the interrelationships between stress appraisal, self-efficacy, and psychosocial outcomes (i.e., resilience and self-concept) within the context of negative life events among college students. Participants (n = 220) were undergraduate students enrolled at a large southeastern university. Study participants completed the &lt;em&gt;Life Experiences Survey&lt;/em&gt; (Sarason et al., 1978), the &lt;em&gt;General Self-Efficacy Scale&lt;/em&gt; (Sherer et al., 1982), the &lt;em&gt;Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale&lt;/em&gt; (Connor &amp; Davidson, 2003), the &lt;em&gt;Multidimensional Self-Concept Scale&lt;/em&gt; (Fleming &amp; Courtney, 1984), and the &lt;em&gt;Perceived Stress Scale&lt;/em&gt; (Cohen et al., 1983). Two hypothesized models of multiple mediation were proposed to explain the relationships between these variables. Model 1 examined the relationship between negative life change and resilience as mediated by stress appraisal and self-efficacy. Model 2 examined the mediating relationship between negative life change and self-concept through stress appraisal and self-efficacy. The path coefficients for the models were estimated through Ordinary Least Squares regression using the INDIRECT SPSS macro with bootstrapping procedures (Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008). Significant indirect effects were found for stress appraisal and self-efficacy in both models. Results support a mediating relationship between negative life change and psychosocial outcomes through stress appraisal and self-efficacy. Future research recommendations and implications including potential interventions are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2409</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3127&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2409</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3127</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-08T18:24:33-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/3127/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4295822</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2409</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sherry K. Bain</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Christopher H. Skinner, Jeannine R. Studer, John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>School Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>