<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Regulation of B cell response to respiratory viruses</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asundar2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Sundararajan</lname>
<fname>Aarthi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>B cell</keyword>
<keyword>Respiratory tract</keyword>
<keyword>MHV-68</keyword>
<keyword>Influenza</keyword>
<keyword>IgA</keyword>
<keyword>Immunology</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Immunology of Infectious Disease</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Viruses replicating in the respiratory tract (RT) triggers a wide- range of cytokines and chemokines that have antiviral and pro-inflammatory features, instigating an efficient virus- specific B and T cell response that aids in virus- clearance. The majority of antibody secreting cells (ASCs) localizing in the upper RT secrete IgA that can effectively neutralize viruses. In addition, elements of B cell memory are generated that can provide protection from re-infection. Studies examining these aspects, following murine gammaherpesvirus 68 (MHV-68) infection comprise chapter 2 of the dissertation work. Our studies demonstrate that following MHV-68 infection, unlike influenza infection, resulted in a generalized deficiency of virus-specific IgA induction and deficient B cell memory establishment in the respiratory tract. The studies indicate that these aspects of B cell response are regulated by features of virus- replication in the RT. These studies lead to the speculation that these features of B cell response may represent an evolutionary adaptation of viruses that establish long-term latency and are transmitted periodically after reactivation and shedding in secretions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following cognate interactions with CD4+ T cells, the B cells undergo proliferation, isotype-switching and differentiate towards extrafollicular (low affinity, rapid) or germinal center pathway (high affinity). It is not clear what factors regulate these pathways of B cell differentiation, especially in the context of virus infection in the RT. Studies examining these aspects following influenza infection comprise chapter 3 of the dissertation work. Our studies establish a model for the investigation of host and viral factors that modulate the quality and effectiveness of the B cell response to influenza infection. The findings indicate that the strength of the extrafollicular B cell response depends on the nature of the infecting virus. We present evidence that this pathway of rapid antiviral antibody production relates to the production of non-specifically acting factors in the lung and also dependent of the cytokine profile of virus-specific CD4+T cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the current dissertation findings point out to an influence of virus and host associated factors in regulating features of B cell response in the RT.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1131</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2144&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1131</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2144</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-17T11:53:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1944181</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1131</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thandi M. Onami</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark Y.Sangster, Barry T.Rouse, Tim E. Sparer, Chunlei Su</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>