<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Out with the Old in with the New: Housing Issues for the Middle-Class in Panama City, Panama</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-24T12:48:21-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Rogers</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>J.D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Panama City</keyword>
<keyword>Panama</keyword>
<keyword>Housing</keyword>
<keyword>Middle-class</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Panama City is currently experiencing unprecedented growth in all sectors of its economy.&#39; An abundance of foreign investment, coupled with a stable socio-political environment, and several large infrastructure investments by the Panamanian government, created a boom of economic expansion in Panama&#39;s capital city.2 This recent surge in enterprise has led to several societal benefits, including growth in the middle-class and an influx in employment. 3 However, as with most economic upheavals, this recent surge is not without negative repercussions. In the twentieth century, housing shortages plagued Panama. Exacerbated by the current economic trend, these housing shortages are likely to continue into the twenty-first century.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss2/11</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1073&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>policynotes</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1073</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-24T12:29:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5377470</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss2/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Eric J.D. Rogers. Study Space Fellow, Center for the Comparative Study of Metropolitan Growth at Georgia State University College of Law. I would like to thank the Center for its fellowship, which enabled me to attend the Panama Study Space.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Housing Issues in Panama City</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>