<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tuning Cell Fate on Self-assembled Structures</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>xwu9@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wu</lname>
<fname>Xiaohui</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Self-assembled</keyword>
<keyword>Cell</keyword>
<keyword>Polymer</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer and Organic Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation presents novel biodegradable copolymers with dendritic architecture, classic polymers, and inorganic materials with controlled surface topography, stiffness, and surface energy for investigating cell-material interactions and targeting tissue engineering applications. Chapter I reviews the recent progress in bone and nerve regeneration, the key factors of materials influencing cell-material interaction, and self-assembled polymer structures. Chapter II presents a divergent method to synthesize biodegrable com-dendritic tri-block copolymers consisting of poly(ethylene glycol) and poly(L-lactide) or poly(e[epsilon]-caprolactone) and the MC3T3-E1 cell response to their spherulites. Chapter III presents the fabrication of deformable poly(e-caprolactone) honeycomb films prepared via a surfactant-free breath figure method in a water-miscible solvent and how the tunable topography regulates MC3T3-E1 cell functions. Chapter IV investigates the fabrication of photo-cured poly(e-caprolactone) triacrylate films with tunable pore size via breath figure method and how the pore size regulates MC3T3-E1 cell behavior. Chapter V invented a facile method to fabricate honeycomb films with submicron pores using monodisperse silica nanoparticle as template and studied the MC3T3-E1 cell functions on those honeycomb films. Chapter VI described a novel method to fabricate microgrooves with honeycomb patterns and investigated the MC3T3-E1 cell functions on this special topography. Chapter VII introduces a facile method to obtain controllable surface energy on poly(e-caprolactone) substrates via controlling the composition of edge-on and flat-on lamellae and how MC3T3-E1 cells behave on those substrates with different surface energy. Chapter VIII synthesizes biomimetic calcium carbonate concentric microgrooves with tunable width via self-assembly and studies the MC3T3-E1 cell response to those microgrooves. Chapter IX describes one method to fabricate controllable topographical features and mechanical properties on poly(e-caprolactone) substrates using uniaxial and biaxial stretching and how those substrates regulate MC3T3-E1 cell functions. Chapter X studies rat pheochromocytoma (PC12) response to the banded spherulites of poly(e-caprolactone) and polyhydroxybutyrate. Chapter XI presents the preparation of honeycomb-patterned copolymer films with tunable pore size and how the pore size regulates NPC cell attachment, proliferation, and differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2498</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3177&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2498</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3177</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-02T09:20:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4381530</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2498</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Shanfeng Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roberto S. Benson, Andy Sarles, Peter K. Liaw, Shanfeng Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>