<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modulation of HSV-induced angiogenesis in HSK pathogenesis</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Sujin</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The formation of a functional, integral vascular network is a fundamental process in the growth and maintenance of tissues. Vascularization occurs by three distinct processes: vasculogenesis, angiogenesis, and arteriogenesis (1). Cell function and survival is dependent on oxygen and nutrient supply from blood vessels. During embryogenesis and organogenesis, the coordinated growth of endothelial cell ensures adequate vessel generation. This process called vasculogenesis, involves the de novo differentiation of endothelial cells (EC) from mesodermal precursors. The distinct process of blood vessels generation from pre-existing vessels, calledangiogenesis, is required in adult life during the female reproductive cycle, tissue repair and wound healing (2). Angiogenesis is the mechanism of blood vessel formation afterthe first few days of embryogenesis, and is essential for all tissue growth (3). In adults, angiogenesis occurs during inflammatory reactions and cancer. The molecular mechanisms controlling angiogenesis are becoming clearer, and therapy targeting these processes is becoming closer to clinical trials. The understanding that the formation of blood vessels depends on the acquisition of a blood supply has led to the development of new therapies for cancer and other angiogenic diseases based on inhibition of neovascularization.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6260</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8212&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6260</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8212</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450356</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6260</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Barry T. Rouse</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert N. Moore, Leon N. D. Potgieter, Albert T. Ichiki</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>