<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fire regimes of kipuka forests in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lewis</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Currently, ecosystem processes that maintain the forests of the American Southwest are operating outside the historical range of variation that existed prior to Euro-American settlement. Areas that have been minimally disturbed by humans should be targeted for research because they contain valuable information about past ecological processes. In El Malpais National Monument, islands of older substrate material are surrounded by younger lava flows. These areas, known as kipukas, likely preserve presettlement forest structure and contain trees old enough to provide information on past ecological processes. The purpose of this study is to reconstruct fire history on minimally disturbed kipukas in El Malpais National Monument, New Mexico. Eight sites were sampled and I 05 fire-scarred samples were collected. Increment cores were taken from living ponderosa pine (Pinus ponderosa Dougl. ex. Laws) trees on two kipukas to examine the age structure of the kipuka forests and to determine whether fire suppression away from the kipukas may be allowing ponderosa pines to encroach onto areas not in their local distribution in the monument. Weibull Modal Fire Intervals ranged from 2.8 years to 42.8 years. The MOI was used because it has been shown to be a superior measure of central tendency, and more effective at identifying Southwestern fire structure independent of variables such as environmental gradient and habitat type. The age structure analyses indicated large numbers of ponderosa pine seedlings as well as a large age cohort &lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5255</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6663&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5255</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6663</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847120</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5255</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Henri Grissino-Mayer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>