<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>I Never Learned About That in Library School: Curriculum Changes in LIS.</title>
<publication-date>2000-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>LIS</keyword>
<keyword>Library and Information Science</keyword>
<keyword>curriculum</keyword>
<keyword>education</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Professional organizations are concerned that programs in Library and Information Science (LIS) may not be teaching up-to-date skills to prepare new information professionals for their first jobs. But good schools also need to provide the broader knowledge that will allow graduates to adapt and continue to function in a constantly changing information world. Due to these concerns, the Special Libraries Association, Association for Library and Information Science Education, Medical Library Association, American Library Association, and others are all looking into what LIS curricula includes now and ought to include in the future, to ensure that the educational programs are keeping up with the knowledge needs of the field. Some of the findings in recent reports from these organizations are discussed. A look is taken from the LIS school perspective at the kind of changes that are being made.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/87</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1128&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>87</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1128</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-11-09T17:23:19-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15741160</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/87</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Online Vol. 24</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>