<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Expression of luxI in Bacillus Thuringiensis for the Development of a Bacteriophage-based Bioreporter System for the Detection of Anthrax</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tomaszewski</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In light of the recent anthrax attacks of 2001in the United States, the need for a rapid, sensitive, and real-time surveillance system for detecting pathogenic bacteria has become readily apparent. A proof-of-principle study involving development of a bacteriophage-based bioreporter system for the detection of &lt;em&gt;Bacillus anthracis&lt;/em&gt; spores has been initiated in the surrogate strain &lt;em&gt;Bacillus thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; 4Q7. The final goal of the project is to develop an engineered bacteriophage with the &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; gene from &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fischeri&lt;/em&gt;, which upon infection of the target organism, would produce the signal molecule, &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-(3-oxohexanoyl)-L-homoserine lactone (OHHL), capable of inducing bioluminescence in a neighboring OHHL bioluminescent bioreporter cell. Studies done in this project involve expression of a plasmid borne &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; gene in &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt;, quantification of OHHL produced, and examination of the effect of the OHHL degrading enzyme lactonase found in &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; gene was expressed under a xylose-inducible promoter in &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; 4Q7. This strain was capable of producing a detectable amount of OHHL within 3 hours post-induction as determined by bioluminescent assays with the OHHL bioreporter, RoLux. In addition, OHHL concentrations of approximately 500 nM were reached during late-log phase growth of the &lt;em&gt;luxI &lt;/em&gt;engineered &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; strain. Other aspects of the study included optimization of the detection of OHHL with the RoLux bioreporter. Finally, the &lt;em&gt;aiiA&lt;/em&gt; gene, or lactonase, from &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; 4Q7 was detected, cloned, and sequenced, and determined to be functional. Assays involving incubation of OHHL with growing cultures of &lt;em&gt;B. thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; provided evidence that the degradation of OHHL by lactonase would not have an effect on detecting the molecule from the engineered strain at early log-phase of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for advancement of this project are made, along with future work in this area is provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2342</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3691&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2342</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3691</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-15T10:38:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4714375</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2342</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gary Sayler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Sanseverino, Pamela Small, Stephen Oliver</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>