<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a valid parent potentiation instrument for prospective parents</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Kris</fname>
<mname>Wilks</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined necessary components for positive parenting in order to develop and validate a Parent Potentiation Instrument (PPI) for prospective parents that would assist them in becoming aware of particular dimensions for growth opportunities regarding positive parenting. In addition, this study addressed constructs that could be included in a PPI as well as determining instrument validity and internal reliability. The scale techniques incorporated in the development of this instrument were Likert ( 1967), Thurstone (1929), and Factor Scaling (Neutens, 1975). A panel of seven expert jurors were asked to rate and weight six domains as to their significance regarding healthy parenting. These domains were; Emotional Health, Physical Health, Spiritual Health, Intellectual Health, Social/Interpersonal Health, and Environmental Health (both personin- situation and planetary). They were asked to validate 289 items, compiled from an extensive review of the literature. As a result, there were 116 items included in the initial instrument along with a demographic section. Three hundred eleven volunteers participated in a pilot study and the data generated were analyzed through factor analysis and Cronbach&#39; s coefficient alpha. The results of the analysis revealed that the PPI contained one of the original domains, Environmental Health. Factor analysis revealed three constructs that best represented the PPI; Current Health Status, Childhood Experiences, and Environmental Health During Childhood.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6340</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8292&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6340</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8292</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450455</context-key>
<withdrawn>2021-06-21</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6340</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jack Ellison, David Patterson, Robert J Pursley, Bill Wallace</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>