<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Architecture of Amelioration</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>plagie@yahoo.com</email>
<lname>Plagemann</lname>
<fname>Geoffrey</fname>
<mname>Russell</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>architecture</keyword>
<keyword>amelioration</keyword>
<keyword>Wolf Creek Dam</keyword>
<keyword>fish hatchery</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Scar:  A lingering sign of damage or injury, either mental or physical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technological advancement scars the landscape.  It has been our practice to ignore, or worse, hide these marks that have been made as society continues to advance.  Industries past left us relics and ruins of bygone eras of promise and production.  The time we live in has recognized the untenable failures of past generations, however there are methods of industry that continue to injure the landscape.  We will leave our scars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this time we must rethink the scar, define it, and recognize its beauty.  The first step of reclamation is acquiring awareness of where the scar came from.  Whether it is an injury, an accident, or a natural disaster, some traumatic event caused lasting damage.  Traumatic events whether natural - hurricanes, floods and earthquakes - or manmade - wars, genocide and assaults - can cause both physical and emotional scars.  Human tissues can repair themselves leaving scars, but there are also the scars of repair.  Even technological advancements in medicine cannot eliminate the scar.  Scarring is the natural healing process, yet we view them as unnatural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once recognized, we must accept the scar so that we do not destroy it.  We must accept the traumatic cause/effect relationships, and be conscious of the healing process.  The scar must be appreciated:  the time that it takes to make it, the time that it takes to heal, the history it can teach, and the story that it can tell.  To hide it would only be an injustice to those who came before us and to those yet to come.  With acceptance a scar’s beauty can be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every new era of technology, every successive generation, leaves a scar.  The opportunity to aid the greatest healer – time – is now.  Every scar tells a story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reclamation:  A restoration, as to productivity, usefulness, or morality.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/827</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1830&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>827</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1830</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-06T13:27:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1429800</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/827</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Scott W. Wall</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brian M. Ambroziak, Mark M. Schimmenti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>