<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Destined for Dissonance: Unpacking the Duality of Being Black and Christian</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:36:49-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cbanks6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Undergraduate Admission</institution>
<lname>Banks</lname>
<fname>Christie</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mbestiv@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Best</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>marc@marcforshort.com</email>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Marcus</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Abstract: We know that the Trans- Atlantic Slave Trade is how our African ancestors became involved with Christianity, and for many this involvement was a forced tactic of bondage. Does the disconnectedness from the horrors and hypocrisy of the slave trade make you question your faith? Or has the Black Church and its role in your community been a pillar in walking out your faith? Is the injustice that brought our people to America a part of our complex Christian history? Or is being Black and Christian an oxymoron? Du Bois’ &lt;em&gt;The Souls of Black Folk&lt;/em&gt; is as relevant a conversation today as it was in 1903. Join us in a dialogue where a preacher, a thinker, and a writer discuss the significance of trusting Christ with your life, but not white-washing that life away. We will provide historical and anecdotal data to showcase how your identity can be in Christ alone and the intersectionality in which our society operates doesn’t have to oppress your religious views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary: Conference themes that will be covered in this session are &quot;illuminating our power, unveiling our truth&quot; and &quot;Double Consciousness&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation will be broken into three parts- &lt;em&gt;Marcus will highlight Background on Du Bois Explain What Dual or Double Consciousness and how this thinking can be problematic. We will utilize flip charts to have in put from the audience with their stance on issues facing Black Christians in today&#39;s society.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew will then connect what it means in modern society. How things have changed since 1903, what remains, and how an &quot;everyday&quot; Christian can combat some the perceived and realized complexities in being a Black, American Christian. He will hone in on identity, code switching, intersectionality, and biblical history of African people and their christian faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christie will close by reiterating how to apply these themes to thrive in today&#39;s society and standing firm in one&#39;s Christian faith through theological and biblical references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also utilize videos, books, journal articles, and anecdotes to continue the conversation with the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1218&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1218</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-11T11:34:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13609181</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The presentation attached is a rough draft.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>