<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extensions of Commutative Rings With Linearly Ordered Intermediate Rings</title>
<publication-date>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gilbert</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Scott</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mathematics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This work concerns λ-extensions of (commutative) rings, which are defined as ring extensions &lt;em&gt;R &lt;/em&gt;⊆ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;  whose set of intermediate rings is linearly ordered by inclusion. λ-extensions from a subclass of the ∆-extensions of Gilmer-Huckaba and generalize the adjacent extensions of Ferrand-Oliver, Modica, and Dechene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter I, we characterize λ-domains (i.e., integral domains &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; with quotient field &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; such that &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; ⊆ &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; is a λ-extension), showing that they form a subclass of quasilocal i-domains. These results parallel results of Gilmer-Huckaba for ∆-domains. We relate λ-domains to divided domains and pseudovaluation domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter II concerns λ-extensions &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; ⊆ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; such that &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is decomposable as a ring direct product. We show that a nontrivial direct product of decomposition of such a &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; has only two factors and characterize λ-extensions of this form, extending the corresponding result of Ferrand-Oliver for adjacent extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter III treats λ-extensions &lt;em&gt;K &lt;/em&gt;⊆ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;  a field. The case where &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; has a nontrivial direct product decomposition is covered using a result from Chapter II. Substantial results are obtained if &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is indecomposable but not a field, generalizing results of Ferrand-Oliver and Modica for an adjacent extension &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; of a field &lt;em&gt;K. &lt;/em&gt;If &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is a field, we obtain good characterizations for &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; either purely inseparable or Galois over &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;. To facilitate proofs, the notion of a μ-extension of fields in introduced and related to λ-extensions of fields. We also relate infinite-dimensional λ-extensions of fields and the J-extensions of fields studied by Gilmer-Heinzer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter IV begins by studying the conductor of a λ-extension, obtaining analogues of the results of Ferrand-Oliver and Modica for adjacent extensions. We then consider λ-extensions &lt;em&gt;R &lt;/em&gt;⊆ &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt;  of integral domains and show that, under certain conditions (but not in generalA), the ring &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; is necessarily on overring of &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;. We classify the λ-extension overrings for two classes of integral domains and end with a useful class of examples of λ-extensions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3383</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4961&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3383</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4961</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-08-05T14:12:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7418561</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3383</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David E. Dobbs</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert McConnel, David Anderson, George Condo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>