<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Proposing an Information Value Chain to  Improve Information Services to Disabled Library Patrons  Using Assistive Technologies</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dpotnis@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Potnis</lname>
<fname>Devendra</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kjmallary@wcu.edu</email>
<institution>Western Carolina University</institution>
<lname>Mallary</lname>
<fname>Kevin</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Disabled patrons</keyword>
<keyword>information services</keyword>
<keyword>service innovation</keyword>
<keyword>assistive technologies</keyword>
<keyword>academic libraries</keyword>
<keyword>information value chain</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Information services offered by academic libraries increasingly rely on assistive technologies (AT) to facilitate disabled patrons’ retrieval and use of information for learning and teaching. However, disabled patrons’ access to AT might not always lead to their use, resulting in the underutilization of information services offered by academic libraries. We adopt an inward-looking, service innovation perspective to improve information services for disabled patrons using AT. The open coding of qualitative responses collected from administrators and librarians in 186 academic libraries in public universities in the United States, reveals 10 mechanisms (i.e., modified work practices), which involve searching, compiling, mixing, framing, sharing, or reusing information, and learning from it. Based on this information-centric reorganization of work practices, we propose an “information value chain,” like Porter’s value chain, for improving information services to disabled patrons using AT in academic libraries, which is the major theoretical contribution of our study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/451</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1452&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>451</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1452</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-07T03:39:58-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_infosciepubs/article/1452/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>22379410</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/451</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This paper is accepted for publication in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Information Science&lt;/em&gt;.   Reuse is restricted to non-commercial and no derivative uses.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Potnis, D. &amp; Mallary, K. (2021). Proposing an information value chain to improve information services to disabled library patrons using assistive technologies. Journal of Information Science. https://doi.org/10.1177/0165551520984719.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.1177/0165551520984719</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Information Science</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Post-print</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>