<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Theory becomes practice : combining reader-response theory and the new rhetoric in describing the meaning-making processes of college freshmen as they respond to poetry</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Tompkins</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;For my study, I investigated the meaning-making processes of college freshmen as they interpreted and discussed poetry. Operating from a theory base involving Reader-Response Theory and the New Rhetoric, I studied the students&#39; individual construction of meaning and their social construction and negotiation of meaning, respectively, as they interpreted poems. I used the methods of qualitative researchers in gathering the data: participant observation; a collection of artifacts that included student compositions, written notes, and audiotaped discussions from small-group work; purposive sampling of these artifacts; questionnaires; and field notes. I placed myself as a full participant observer, since I served as both professor and researcher in my own classroom. For each theory, I identified and described categories of the meaning-making processes derived from the artifacts, and I used the constant comparative method for refining them. For the purposive sampling procedure, I used maximum variation sampling of the student compositions and the audiotaped discussions in selecting salient examples to demonstrate these meaning-making processes for both theories.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6399</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8373&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6399</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8373</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:39:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24074675</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6399</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>C. Glennon Rowell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Linda Bensel-Meyers, Theodore W. Hipple, Thomas N. Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>