<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Stormwater Management in Tennessee: Guidelines to Preventative Maintenance Practices and Improvements</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chandler</lname>
<fname>Jacob</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The management of urban stormwater runoff is an important issue throughout Tennessee as urban development keeps expanding. With the rise of urban development, there is an ever-growing need for urban stormwater management systems and facilities which are built to protect downstream property owners from potential flood damage as well as to manage and control the increased stormwater runoff. However well-designed a drainage system or facility might be, adequate maintenance is vital for it to function as intended by the design engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis was written to serve as a document that provides information needed to support an effective maintenance program for urban stormwater management systems and facilities and includes information that can help educate both public and private owners of these systems and facilities about the importance, benefits and methods of maintaining their stormwater management systems and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information used to prepare this thesis was derived from a comprehensive literature search, a review of traditional reference sources and internet web sites to help determine what successful methods and programs are being used to ensure and improve maintenance of urban stormwater management systems and facilities. A survey questionnaire was also sent to all 95 counties in Tennessee and Tennessee municipalities with a 1990 census population of 2500 or greater to characterize the existing stormwater maintenance programs throughout the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings from the survey questionnaire include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;· As can be expected, as the population within a community’s jurisdictional boundary increases, the allocated budget for stormwater and street maintenance increases as well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;· The results of the survey questionnaire appear to suggest that a preventative maintenance program does not seem to significantly reduce the perceived number of stormwater problems that are attributed to needed maintenance within a community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;· Either communities do not have sufficient manpower to provide needed inspections for private stormwater handling facilities or the communities require the owner of the stormwater handling facility to perform the needed inspections and maintenance of the private stormwater handling facilities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;· Either respondents do not perceive any serious stormwater-related maintenance problems within their community and that they feel the current funding is adequate to handle these problems or some of the respondents may have anticipated the percentage increase that has been allocated for the next year’s budget&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of this report, the findings include stormwater maintenance protocols that were established based on the information provided by the various survey questionnaire respondents.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1962</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3320&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1962</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3320</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-25T12:33:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4629483</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1962</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Bruce A. Tschantz, P.E.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. James L. Smoot, P.E., Dr. William A. Miller Jr., P.E.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>