<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Plasticity of total and intracellular phosphorus quotas in Microcystis aeruginosa cultures and Lake Erie algal assemblages</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Saxton</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Arnold</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Bourbonniere</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>McKay</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Michael L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilhelm</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Blooms of the potentially toxic cyanobacterium &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; are common events globally, and as a result significant resources continue to be dedicated to monitoring and controlling these events. Recent studies have shown that a significant proportion of total cell-associated phosphorus (P) in marine phytoplankton can be surface adsorbed; as a result studies completed to date do not accurately report the P demands of these organisms. In this study we measure the total cell-associated and intracellular P as well as growth rates of two toxic strains of &lt;em&gt;Microcystis aeruginosa&lt;/em&gt; Kütz grown under a range of P concentrations. The results show that the intracellular P pool in &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; represents a percentage of total cell-associated P (50–90%) similar to what has been reported for actively growing algae in marine systems. Intracellular P concentrations (39–147 fg cell&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;) generally increased with increasing P concentrations in the growth medium, but growth rate and the ratio of total cell-associated to intracellular P remained generally stable. Intracellular P quotas and growth rates in cells grown under the different P treatments illustrate the ability of this organism to successfully respond to changes in ambient P loads, and thus have implications for ecosystem scale productivity models employing P concentrations to predict algal bloom events.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/65</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1065&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>65</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1065</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-01-03T07:46:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4951601</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/65</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Front. Microbiol., 18 January 2012 | doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2012.00003</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-01-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>