<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Grade A milk producers in Sullivan County, Tennessee : problem A: Characteristics of Sullivan County Grade A milk producers and their farms : problem B: Management practices of Sullivan County Grade A milk producers : problem C: Factors influencing dairy management practice adoption by Sullivan County Grade A milk producers : three related special problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Holland</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Sullivan County was one of several Tennessee counties participating in a statewide dairy study under the guidance of the Agricultural Extension Training and Studies Department and the Dairy Department of the University of Tennessee. Dairying is the largest source of agricultural income in Sullivan County. The dairy enterprise is made up of both Grade A and manufacturing milk producers (19: 7). The average size of farms for the county in 1959 was 57 acres. The United States Census of Agriculture f or 1959 listed 2,575 farms as comapred to 3, 499 farms in 1954 (19). The number of Grade A milk producers in the county has continued to decline. In March of 1963, the Federal Milk Market Administrator listed 74 Grade A milk producers as compared to only 64 as of December, 1964 (3). Many of the small dairymen were selling their farms for housing development projects.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6047</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7686&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6047</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7686</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074422</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6047</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lewis Dickson, Don O. Richardson, William W. Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>