<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Distribution, Status, and Life History Aspects of Two Rare Logperches, Percina burtoni and Percina apina</title>
<publication-date>2021-02-08T13:19:16-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jwsimmons0@tva.gov</email>
<institution>Tennessee Valley Authority</institution>
<lname>Simmons</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>W</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Tennessee-Cumberland Rivers</keyword>
<keyword>Percidae</keyword>
<keyword>natural history records</keyword>
<keyword>habitat use</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Blotchside Logperch, &lt;em&gt;Percina burtoni&lt;/em&gt;, and Tennessee Logperch, &lt;em&gt;Percina apina&lt;/em&gt;, are Tennessee-Cumberland River drainage endemics that have experienced range reductions due to anthropogenic influences. All known collection records were gathered to fully describe the historical distribution of these species for comparison to their currently inhabited range. Discussion of major impacts to rivers that contain or contained these species is included for an understanding of factors that may have influenced contemporary distributions. Extensive field surveys were conducted during 2014 to 2017 to aid in determination of the current status and distribution of populations. New information of previously unreported or undetected populations, population status, life history observations, and longevity estimates are presented.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss61/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1304&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1304</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-05-18T20:47:42-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1304/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>17792650</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss61/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS- Thank you to: J.M. Mollish who greatly assisted in field collections; J. Ellis and J. Saylor for additional field collection assistance; T. Near for his collaboration with specimen data; T.R. Russ and L. Etchison for North Carolina Wildlife Resources Commission occurrence records; M. Pinder for Virginia Division of Game and Inland Fisheries occurrence records; J. Ray, University of North Alabama, Florence, for additional records from Factory and Chisolm Creeks; and J. Davis for help with R code and graphs for longevity estimates.  S. Powers, J. Davis, and three anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments that greatly improved this manuscript.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-18T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xdd443e8)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Distribution, status, life history aspects-P. burtoni and P. apina</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>