<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessment of Professional Development Needs and Satisfaction of Technical College Instructors at Tennessee College of Applied Technology: 
A Descriptive Research Study</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>snadel@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Nadel</lname>
<fname>Sarah</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation project sought to identify the level of satisfaction with instructor training and development, instructor training strengths and weaknesses, and instructors’ suggestions for improvement at each Tennessee College of Applied Technology (TCAT). The preliminary study (exploratory case study) consisted of one-on-one interviews and classroom observations with TCAT instructors at one specific TCAT location. The main dissertation study collected data using an online survey, consisting of both qualitative and quantitative statements/questions based off of responses during the preliminary study. The survey utilized a 6-point Likert scale with rating from Strongly Disagree to Strongly Agree. Lastly, participant demographics were collected within the online survey. Participants were current TCAT instructors who taught at different locations within Tennessee. Participants were both male and female and were between 18-65+ years of age. Each participant spent time working in industry prior to teaching at TCAT. Participants were asked to participate in the current study through email recruitment sent by the Tennessee Board of Regents (TBR). The email included the purpose of the study, benefits to TCAT faculty, time frame of the survey, confidentiality and anonymity information regarding participation, and a link to the survey (see Recruitment Email document). Participants were asked to complete the online survey, and three recruitment emails were sent over the time frame of a month and a half to increase levels of participation. Additionally, each TCAT location president received flyers to post on campus with information regarding the study, a survey link, and a QR code for any possible participant to follow to participate in the study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5790</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7556&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5790</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7556</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419697</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5790</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jennifer A. Morrow</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gary Skolits, Louis Rocconi, Patrick Biddix</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>