<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Reframing and Reforming the Securities and Exchange Commission: Lessons from Literature on Change Leadership</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Securities and Exchange Commission</keyword>
<keyword>SEC</keyword>
<keyword>change leadership</keyword>
<keyword>change management</keyword>
<keyword>leadership</keyword>
<keyword>agency</keyword>
<keyword>institution</keyword>
<keyword>reform</keyword>
<keyword>Kotter</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Organizational Behavior and Theory</discipline>
<discipline>Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
<discipline>Strategic Management Policy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As a  reaction to perceived and actual regulatory failures at the Securities  and Exchange Commission (the SEC), from mistakes that contributed to the  financial crisis to the Bernard Madoff affair, the SEC has been engaged  in an operational transformation process. The growing literature on  management and leadership in times of change -- change leadership  literature -- offers a number of potentially valuable lenses through  which we may assess reform at the SEC.   &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;With the thought that  securities regulators and others may learn valuable lessons about the  SEC’s restructuring and reorganization from experts in change  leadership, this Article explores a selected group of principles from  change leadership literature. These principles are then mapped to recent  and current changes at the SEC. The resulting analysis offers certain  positive observations but also allows for certain critiques of,  questions about, and advice concerning the processes by which change  leaders are selected and institutional reform is undertaken at a federal  agency. As a result, the Article highlights certain strengths of and  exposes possible weaknesses in SEC reform efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/21</coverpage-url>
<label>21</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1017</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T07:17:21-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035029</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/21</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Reframing and Reforming the Securities and Exchange Commission: Lessons from Literature on Change Leadership (May 31, 2010). Villanova Law Review, Vol. 55, 2010; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 125. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1688147</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1688147</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>