<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nitrogen Levels Influence Biomass, Elemental Accumulations, and Pigment Concentrations in Spinach</title>
<publication-date>2007-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>Dean</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lefsrud</lname>
<fname>Mark</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Onion Lab</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>β-carotene; carotenoids; chlorophyll a and b; HPLC; lutein; macronutrient; micronutrient; Spinacia oleracea L</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Horticulture</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Breeding and Genetics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Spinach (&lt;em&gt;Spinacia oleracea&lt;/em&gt; L.) has one of the highest United States per capita consumption rates among leafy vegetable crops, and also ranks second for lutein and β-carotene carotenoid concentration. The objectives of this study were to determine the effects of nitrogen (N) concentration on elemental and pigment accumulation in spinach. Two spinach cultivars (&#39;Melody&#39; and &#39;Springer F1&#39;) were greenhouse grown in nutrient solution culture under N treatments of 13, 26, 52, and 105 mg L&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt;. Leaf tissue biomass increased from 45.6 to 273.2 g plant&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; and from 127.0 to 438.6 g plant&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; as N increased from 13 to 105 mg L- 1 for &#39;Springer F1&#39; and &#39;Melody&#39;, respectively. Leaf tissue N, phosphorus (P), calcium (Ca), magnesium (Mg), copper (Cu), and zinc (Zn) responded to N treatments. Lutein accumulations, expressed on a fresh weight basis, responded quadratically to increasing N treatments for &#39;Springer F1&#39;. Maximum lutein values were 110 and 76 μ g g&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; on a fresh weight basis, and maximum β-carotene values were 85 and 57 μ g g&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; on a fresh weight basis for &#39;Springer F1&#39; and &#39;Melody&#39;, respectively. Interestingly, N levels had a significant effect on carotenoid accumulation in both &#39;Springer F1&#39; and &#39;Melody&#39; when the pigments were expressed on a dry weight basis. Leaf tissue lutein increased from 0.59 to 1.06 mg g&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; and from 0.59 to 0.90 mg g&lt;sup&gt;- 1&lt;/sup&gt; on a dry weight basis with increasing N treatments for &#39;Springer F1&#39; and &#39;Melody&#39;, respectively. Reporting lutein and β-carotene on both a fresh and dry weight basis may be the most accurate way to express the carotenoid values of spinach.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/23</coverpage-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-30T07:58:00-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1587205</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Lefsrud, M. G., Kopsell, D. A. &amp; Kopsell, D. E. (2007). Nitrogen Levels Influence Biomass, Elemental Accumulations, and Pigment Concentrations in Spinach. Journal of Plant Nutrition, 30(2), 171-185.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~db=all~content=a773214262~frm=titlelink</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>