<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Initial Effects of Silvicultural Treatments on Food Availability and Vegetation Structure for Wild Turkeys</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Basinger</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The eastern wild turkey (Meleagris gallopavo silvestris) is an important game species in the mid-South region. Many non-industrial private landowners along with state and federal agencies actively manage property to enhance habitat for wild turkeys. In the past, diameter-limit cutting has been commonly used to harvest hardwood timber on public and private land in this region. Unfortunately, diameter-limit harvests typically “high-grade” stands, leaving low quality stems and altering forest composition in favor of less desirable species, such as red maple (Acer rubrum), sweetgum (Liquidambar styraciflua), winged elm (Ulmus alata), and yellow poplar (Liriodendron tulipifera). While the most biologically sound method to improve these stands may be clearcutting, it is not an attractive option for many managers who wish to improve forested habitat for wild turkeys and other wildlife species. Five silvicultural treatments were implemented within the Ridge and Valley physiographic province of east Tennessee in spring 2001 to compare effects of alternative forest management practices on annual food availability and vegetative structure for nesting and brood-rearing wild turkeys. Treatments included shelterwood harvest, wildlife thinning, wildlife thinning with prescribed burn, and prescribed burn only, along with control. Hard and soft mast production was measured and the structure and composition of the responding vegetation was recorded. In addition, macroinvertebrate populations were sampled to estimate food availability for wild turkey poults. Acorn production across stands at Chuck Swan was variable among treatments and years and showed no distinct pattern. Hard mast collected represents baseline data, as effects of treatments will not be apparent for a few years. Nonetheless, among individual vi white oaks, 30 percent of the trees produced 85 percent of the acorns in 2001 and 70 percent of the acorns in 2002. In addition, acorn production varied among individual white oaks as some produced acorns both years, some produced 1 year, and others did not produce acorns either year. Initial soft mast production was low the first growing season after treatments, but increased sharply the second year. However, variation resulting from the patchy spatial distribution of the responding understory vegetation prevented statistical differences among treatments. Herbaceous coverage remained unchanged within all treatments from 2000 (pre-treatment) to 2002. Although woody understory vegetation predominantly responded within all treatments, suitable nesting and brooding cover was established. Overall invertebrate density and biomass was similar within all treatments and did not change throughout the brood-rearing period in 2002. Density and biomass of invertebrate classes and orders varied among treatments. Wildlife thinnings and shelterwood harvests can be used to improve nesting and brood-rearing habitat and increase soft mast production. However, managers should give more consideration to identifying inherently good acorn producers within a stand before thinning or harvesting when increased acorn production is desired. After thinning, prescribed fire should be used to facilitate seed bank germination. Managers should be aware that an increase in soft mast production might not be evident until at least 2 years post treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1891</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3247&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1891</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3247</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-19T13:51:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4602703</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1891</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Craig H. Harper</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David S. Buckley, David A. Buehler, Cathryn H. Greenberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>