<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>FoodScape Knox</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:55:33-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cconle12@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Conley</lname>
<fname>Caroline Beth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;My capstone project is a completed business plan for a LLC company named FoodScape Knox. FoodScape Knox is a social enterprise whose aim is to build the local food economy and fresh food access within Knoxville. Foodscape Knox offers edible landscape design and installment to private landowners. For every landscape installment completed, another edible landscape is installed for free in a low-income neighborhood. The uniqueness of our service offered as well as the effort towards community development will act as the primary competitive advantage. In the long run, Foodscape Knox will start offering edible landscaping services to businesses and schools. We dream of a world that is sustainable and healthy, a world where there is collaboration and unity between neighborhoods, where nutritious food is accessible for everyone. Convinced that the changes needed on a global scale must be initiated at the local level, we are working to develop an ecological and accessible agriculture, adapted to the urban context. One garden at a time, we change our living environment, promote biodiversity and produce fresh, healthy and ultra-local food.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/business/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1207&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1207</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-05-02T15:06:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>12062688</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/business/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Tom Graves</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>