<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>“THE LAST ACCEPTABLE PREJUDICE”: STUDENT HARASSMENT OF GAY PUBLIC SCHOOL TEACHERS</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-14T13:10:38-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mbernstein@pegasuslaw.org</email>
<lname>Bernstein</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>gay rights</keyword>
<keyword>public school</keyword>
<keyword>harassment</keyword>
<keyword>Title VII</keyword>
<keyword>discrimination</keyword>
<keyword>teachers&#39; rights</keyword>
<keyword>bullying</keyword>
<keyword>homophobia</keyword>
<keyword>prejudice</keyword>
<keyword>gay</keyword>
<keyword>lesbian</keyword>
<keyword>equal protection</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the United States, where the “marketplace of ideas” is a key social philosophy, few Americans receive the benefits of attending public schools with “out” gay and lesbian teachers. Even in an era where civil rights for homosexual public employees are increasing, more than one quarter of adults in the United States continue to believe that school boards should be permitted to fire teachers known to be homosexual. Amid a permissive legal climate that too easily puts aside the rights of teachers in a myopic focus on students, incidents where students harass teachers based on the teachers’ sexual orientation go virtually unpunished. Although these cases are seldom litigated, they promote a closeted culture of silence in a profession that employs more than one million Americans, and they represent a significant fissure in the civil rights landscape. The anti-gay movement, drawing on a long legacy of discrimination, perversely employs notions of morality and role modeling to enforce a culture of heteronormativity and bigotry in schools. Without adequate gay and lesbian role models, students cannot be active participants in the multiple social locations and spheres that form the lived experience of citizenship. While states are increasingly protecting homosexual public employees through non-discrimination statutes, only federal guidance in the form of Title VII protection or a national non-discrimination statute are sufficient to properly shield teachers and institute a truly democratic American classroom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/rgsj/vol3/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1051&amp;amp;context=rgsj&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1051</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-14T12:37:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Race, Gender, &amp; Social Justice</publication-title>
<context-key>6461044</context-key>
<submission-path>rgsj/vol3/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Matthew Bernstein is a Staff Attorney at Pegasus Legal Services for Children in Albuquerque, New Mexico, where he represents children in child welfare and special education cases. Prior to law school, he taught history, English, and economics at Amy Biehl Charter High School in Albuquerque. He sends deep gratitude to Steven K. Homer, Susan Bernstein, Jerome Bernstein, and Hannah Bloom.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>“THE LAST ACCEPTABLE PREJUDICE”: STUDENT HARASSMENT OF GAY PUBLIC SCHOOL TEACHERS</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>