<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Elaidinized Lipid in Relation to its Effect on Batter Structure</title>
<publication-date>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Snodgrass</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>Jane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Batter aeration as affected by substitution of elaidinized lipid and related to other properties was investigated. Elaidinized lipid was substituted for hydrogenated safflower oil shortening at four levels, 0, 40, 60, and 80 percent, in the preparation of lipid samples. Lipid samples were characterized by gas-liquid and thin-layer chromatography and by melting point determination. Specific gravity and viscosity of the batters, volume index of the cakes, and lightness index of the crumb were determined. Batter structure was studied microscopically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An increase in trans isomer concentration from 8.8 percent to 40.6 percent was accompanied by an increase in melting point from 41.0 to 47.1°C with increasing level of substitution. Batters from the unsubstituted shortening were most highly aerated, as indicated by specific gravity, and had the greatest dispersity of air and lipid, as indicated by microscopic sections. The decreased extent of emulsification was associated with decreased batter viscosity, as well as the decreased aeration. Volume index of cakes in part reflected differences in aeration. Decreased lightness index of cake crumb with increasing level of substitution resulted from the decreased light-reflecting surface and relatively poor aeration. Batter structure was not affected beneficially by substitution of elaidinized lipid for hydrogenated shortening under the conditions of this study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3967</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5453&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3967</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5453</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T08:18:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9124008</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3967</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ada Marie Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gracyce E. Goertz, Mary Jo Hitchcock</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>