<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mowing and Light-weight Rolling of Creeping Bentgrass (&lt;em&gt;Agrostis stolonifera&lt;/em&gt; L.) Putting Greens during summer heat stress periods in the Transition Zone</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Strunk</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Daniel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A major challenge for golf course superintendents in the transition zone is to manage&lt;em&gt; Agrostis&lt;/em&gt; stolonifera L. (creeping bentgrass) putting greens during heat stress periods of June, July, and August. In 2004 and 2005, a study was conducted to compare the effects of alternating rolling and mowing with traditional methods of everyday mowing on the green speed, turf quality, and disease occurrence creeping bentgrass putting greens in the transition zone. Treatments consisted of mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; without rolling, mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, and mowing three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; alternating with rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Visual quality ratings for treatment effects determined a treatment and time interaction, which showed that alternating mowing with rolling had no significant change in turf quality throughout the study. In addition, mowing everyday maintained as high of quality through two months, but not at three months; while, mowing with rolling had significant decreases in quality by two months. There was no significance noted for disease incidence or root length among treatments or locations. Green speeds were statistically different for many of the collection dates for all locations. However, these speeds were only realistically different for 4 of 37 collection dates. Green speeds must exceed 15.2 centimeters of difference before the average golfer can distinguish a difference. A partial budgeting analysis was implemented to understand the economic effects as well. A mail survey was conducted in January 2006 to determine the standard mowing and rolling practices for golf courses in Tennessee, and it had a 37.5 percent response rate. A partial budgeting analysis was performed to determine the additional costs or savings generated by comparing mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, and alternating mowing with rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Adding rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; to a program of mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; increased overall total cost as expected for both triplex and walk behind mowers over all golf course types. However, alternating mowing with rolling three days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; has the potential to reduce total cost, particularly for courses using walk behind mowers, compared to only mowing six days week&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1809</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3162&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1809</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3162</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-09T13:52:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4567550</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1809</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John C. Sorochan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. Scott McElroy, Thomas J. Samples, Charles Hall, Thomas Nikolai</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>