<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Is Changing Your Layout Worth The Payout?: The Impact of Office Layout on Employee Wellness and Reactions</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:53:33-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ssteiche@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Steichen</lname>
<fname>Samantha Nicole</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;With an increase in focus on company culture over the past few years, thousands of companies are spending millions of dollars to renovate their office buildings. These investments are occurring with no research that proves that certain office layouts benefit employees more than others. Research in this area could not only save companies millions of dollars, but it could lead to an overall increase in employee wellness and reactions. The objective of this study is to find a correlation between the physical layout of work and employee wellness and reactions. This study is broken down into 5 separate parts: Office Privacy, Workspace Collaboration, Workspace Stress, Creativity, and Work Tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this study comes from a mixed method survey that’s purpose is to find if there are differences in employee attitudes and perceptions of jobs based on office layout. The target group for this survey is adults above 18 who have full time jobs. The survey over-collects data by not only asking participants about their workspace, but also by asking them questions about their industry, commute, relationship with supervisor, and the amount that work affects their health.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/business/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1129&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1129</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T18:21:10-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1129/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10008785</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/business/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Management</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Tim Munyon</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>