<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Longitudinal Investigation of the Bidirectional Relations Between Parental Sources of Knowledge and Child Disruptive Behavior</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>awimsatt@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wimsatt</lname>
<fname>Amber</fname>
<mname>Rochelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Disruptive Behavior Disorders</keyword>
<keyword>child behavior</keyword>
<keyword>parent-child relations</keyword>
<keyword>monitoring</keyword>
<keyword>sources of knowledge</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research indicates that parental sources of knowledge (i.e., child disclosure, parental solicitation, and parental control) play a role in the occurrence of antisocial and other problem behaviors in childhood and adolescence. Because sources of knowledge have not been examined regarding the extent to which they are specifically related to change in disruptive behavior disorder (DBD) symptoms and no research has examined the influence of child symptom clusters of DBD on parental sources of knowledge, the current study longitudinally examined reciprocal relations between child disclosure, parental solicitation, and the DBD symptom clusters of Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), Conduct Disorder (CD), and Oppositional Defiant Disorder (ODD). Participants were 89 children (56% males) recruited from a mid-sized southeastern community with ages ranging from 9-12 years (M = 10.4 years, SD = 1.1 years) at baseline. Results indicated that disclosure was negatively associated with both ODD and CD symptoms and solicitation was positively predictive of CD symptoms within time.  However, associations were not maintained across time. Furthermore, disclosure and solicitation were unrelated to ADHD symptoms at baseline and across time. In turn, ODD symptoms were negatively related to child disclosure within as well as across time; however this association was only marginally statistically significant within time. ADHD and CD symptoms were unrelated to disclosure at both time points. Finally, only ODD symptoms were marginally statistically negatively related to parental solicitation within time, but no symptom clusters were associated with solicitation across time. Implications and future directions are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/844</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1881&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>844</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1881</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-10-26T14:22:39-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1881/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1619474</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/844</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paula J. FIte</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Deborah Welsh, Jenny Macfie</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>