<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Social support and job satisfaction among student support services personnel</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Wilkerson</lname>
<fname>Lori</fname>
<mname>Simpson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Current research has investigated the potential relationship between social support and job satisfaction. Researchers have found that social support can contribute to job satisfaction by buffering the effects of job stress. Using Cobb&#39;s ( 197 6) buffering hypothesis, the purpose of this study was ( a) to determine how satisfied student support services personnel were with their jobs and their social relationships, (b) to discover whether or not there were any differences in age, ethnicity, gender, and length of employment with respect to job satisfaction and social support, and ( c) to discover whether or not job satisfaction and social support were significantly correlated. ·The researcher mailed questionnaire packets to a random sample of300 student support services personnel who were members of the Southeastern Association of Educational Opportunity Program Personnel (SAEOPP) association. The surveys for this study included (a) a demographic questionnaire, (b) the Job Satisfaction Survey, and (c) the Social Provisions Scale. After a subsequent follow-up, 150 usable surveys had been returned, yielding a response rate of 50.3 %.  Statistical tests utilized to analyze data included multivariate analysis of variance, analysis of variance, and coefficient correlation. Frequencies, means, and standard deviations were used to describe the demographics of the participants. Participants were predominately female, either African American or White, and have worked 10 years or less. The results of the multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) showed no significant differences between job satisfaction and (a) age, (b) ethnicity, (c) gender, or (d) length of employment. In addition, no significant relationships existed between social support and (a) age, (b) gender, or (c) length of employment. However, social support significantly correlated with ethnicity. African Americans experienced higher rates of reassurance of worth than did Whites. Also, job satisfaction significantly correlated with social support. Overall, the participants reported high social support and moderate satisfaction with their jobs. Participants reported high satisfaction with the nature of the work and the least satisfied with promotion. In addition, the social support variables of reassurance of worth, social integration, attachment, and reliable alliance strongly correlated with job satisfaction variables (supervision, nature of work, communication) at the p = .05 confidence level. In addition, social support variables of guidance, reassurance of worth, social integration, and attachment correlated with the job satisfaction variables of contingent rewards and coworkers at p = .05. Future research should explore the use of longitudinal or qualitative research methodologies to study job satisfaction and social support. One limitation of this research was the use of self-report measures. A different research method might reveal stronger relationships between social support and job satisfaction than this present study did. A different research method might find significant differences in social support and job satisfaction for age, ethnicity, gender, and length of employment. However, based on this study, student support services personnel should implement the use of activities and processes that develop strong relationships among employees.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5316</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6724&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5316</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6724</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847269</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5316</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>