<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fatigue in diabetes mellitus : testing a middle range theory of well-being derived from Neuman&#39;s theory of optimal client system stability and the Neuman&#39;s systems model</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Casalenuovo</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to test a middle range theory of well-being in adults with diabetes mellitus derived from Neuman’s Theory of Optimal Client System Stability and the Neuman Systems Model. The relationships among stress, well-being, and fatigue in adults living with diabetes mellitus were examined to test the theory that disruption in well-being in adults living with the stress of diabetes mellitus leads to greater fatigue. Data were collected from a convenience sample of 87 adults with Type 1 and Type 2 diabetes mellitus. Subjects completed a questionnaire packet that was designed to elicit demographic information, a measure of their stress related to living with diabetes mellitus, a measure of the physiological, psychological, sociocultural, developmental, and spiritual well-being, and a measure of their level of fatigue. Data were analyzed using bivariate correlation and hierarchical multiple regression.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6214</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8166&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6214</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8166</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450305</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6214</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Martha R. Alligood</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Debra C. Wallace, Kathy J. Ekkison, Robert H. Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nursing</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>