<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Smoking: The Whole Truth</title>
<publication-date>2013-06-03T05:46:24-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>azieb.kidanu@knoxcounty.org</email>
<institution>Knox County</institution>
<lname>Kidanu</lname>
<fname>Azieb</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>rthomas1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Rosa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although tobacco use is the most preventable risk factor for disease and premature death, it is the number one cause of death in the African American community, surpassing AIDS, homicide, diabetes, and accidents. Each year, approximately 45,000 African Americans die from smoking-related disease. As smoking rates decline among the white population, tobacco companies have increased advertising to target African Americans through magazines, commercials and sponsorship of entertainment events. So, it is imperative that we stand together in this issue and not allow anymore of our community members fall to tobacco. In this session conference attendees will participate in an interactive trivia competition to test their knowledge about cigarettes, cigars, hookahs and other tobacco products. Learn about the services available for tobacco cessation in the local community, how to help a friend or family member quit and ways to develop a healthy habit. Prizes will be awarded to the wining team, and attendees will have the opportunity to share personal messages or stories on the Tobacco Graffiti Wall.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2013/Session2/1</coverpage-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1080</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-27T05:52:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3556671</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2013/Session2/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>