<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Training performance transfer between CD-ROM-based instruction and traditional classroom instruction</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Zulauf</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to compare Kimberly-Clark employees&#39; perceptions of transfer of related training between CD-ROM-based learners and traditional classroom learners based on five descriptive factors (supervisor support, organizational support, peer support, self-efficacy, and motivation). Secondly, the study investigated differences between CD-ROM-based learners and traditional classroom learners based on eight demographic factors ( age, gender, years of full-time work experience, job title, years of experience as a supervisor, CD-ROM course experience, online course experience, and level of education). The Training Performance Transfer (TPT) (Petty &amp;Farris 2001) was the sole instrument used for the study. The entire workforce of the Kimberly-Clark, Loudon Mill was used as participants in the study. The respondents consisted of Machine Operators, Maintenance personnel, and Resources at the paper manufacturing facility. A total number of 370 surveys were distributed to the employees both in person and to their personal mail folders. There were 278 surveys completed, which accounted for a 75% response rate. Descriptive statistics including the mean, standard deviation, and frequencies were gathered for the demographic data to help interpret employees&#39; perceptions of the transfer of training process. A uni-variate analysis of variance (UNIANOVA) and the Tukey post hoc tests were used to analyze the perceptual data from the TPT. The UNIANOVA test divided the survey into five descriptors in order to measure the employees&#39; perceptions of the transfer of training process. Finally, descriptive statistics and the Tukey Honestly Significant Difference (HSD) post hoc test were used to analyze any differences that existed between the eight demographic variables.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6029</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7662&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6029</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7662</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467691</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6029</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Debbie L. Mackey, Randal H. Pierce</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>