<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Instrument Performance Enhancement and Modification through an Extended Instrument Paradigm</title>
<publication-date>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mahan</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;An extended instrument paradigm is proposed, developed and shown in various applications. The CBM (Chin, Blass, Mahan) method is an extension to the linear systems model of observing systems. In the most obvious and practical application of image enhancement of an instrument characterized by a time-invariant instrumental response function, CBM can be used to enhance images or spectra through a simple convolution application of the CBM filter for a resolution improvement of as much as a factor of two. The CBM method can be used in many applications. We discuss several within this work including imaging through turbulent atmospheres, or what we&#39;ve called Adaptive Imaging. Adaptive Imaging provides an alternative approach for the investigator desiring results similar to those obtainable with adaptive optics, however on a minimal budget. The CBM method is also used in a backprojected filtered image reconstruction method for Positron Emission Tomography. In addition, we can use information theoretic methods to aid in the determination of model instrumental response function parameters for images having an unknown origin. Another application presented herein involves the use of the CBM method for the determination of the continuum level of a Fourier transform spectrometer observation of ethylene, which provides a means for obtaining reliable intensity measurements in an automated manner. We also present the application of CBM to hyperspectral image data of the comet Shoemaker-Levy 9 impact with Jupiter taken with an acousto-optical tunable filter equipped CCD camera to an adaptive optics telescope.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2005</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3436&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2005</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3436</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-23T13:44:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4615475</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2005</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William E. Blass</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Chia C. Shih, Thomas Handler, Hamparsum Bozdogan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>