<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A County Wide Study of Pupil Transportation in McMinn County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1950-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Godsey</lname>
<fname>Reuben</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND FOR THE STUDY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for a study of school bus transportation in McMinn County, Tennessee, was first called to the attention of the writer in 1948. This was further accented by attendance at a number of school board meetings, and by hearing discussions of the routes that buses were traveling at that time. It was believed that some improvement of the routes could be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer discussed the transportation problem with the county superintendent of McMinn County. He urged the writer to give some thought to the problem as a thesis. The problem was later discussed with some of the officials of the College of Education at the University of Tennessee. Encouragement to study the problem was also given by these men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A McMinn County Survey Group was organized in September of 1949 under the guidance of some of the professors of the College of Education. This survey group set up the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Survey of the present physical conditions of buildings and grounds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Survey of the school plant utilization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Survey of population status and trends&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Survey of transportation system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5. Statement of education objectives and needs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. Survey of financial status of the county&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7. Recommendations concerning the present school program and building needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer selected the transportation problem as part of his contribution to the survey group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey group held a number of meetings during the past school year and it plans to continue these meetings through the summer. Weekly meeting approximately five hours in length were the pattern for the school year. Some leaders in the College of Education as well as a large number of educators and laymen participated in these meetings.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/854</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2082&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>854</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2082</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-15T13:53:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2062734</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/854</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bascom H. Story</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John W. Gilliland, Earl M. Ramer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1950-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>