<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization and Management of PPO and Glyphosate Resistant Palmer amaranth</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>josdcope@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Copeland</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Drake</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Palmer amaranth</keyword>
<keyword>protoporphyrinogen oxidase inhibitor</keyword>
<keyword>cover crop</keyword>
<keyword>PPO resistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research was conducted from the fall of 2016 to the fall of 2018 to characterize and manage PPO- and glyphosate-resistant Palmer amaranth (&lt;i&gt;Amaranthus palmeri&lt;/i&gt; S. Wats). Studies included a multi-county survey to determine the prevalence of PPO-resistant Palmer amaranth biotypes and the PPX2 mutations that confer PPO resistance, an in-field evaluation of control of PPO-resistant and PPO-susceptible Palmer amaranth populations with herbicide treatments applied at either sunrise or midday, and field studies that evaluated cover crop termination for control of Palmer amaranth in Roundup Ready Xtend速 and Liberty Link速 soybean systems [(&lt;i&gt;Glycine max&lt;/i&gt; (L.) Merr.].Results from this research indicate that PPO-resistant Palmer amaranth infests roughly 80% of west Tennessee fields, at least two herbicides with different, effective sites of action should be applied timely for POST herbicidal control of PPO-resistant Palmer amaranth, and that delaying cover crop termination in both Roundup Ready Xtend速 and Liberty Link速 soybeans can effectively reduce in-season POST applications and maximize Palmer amaranth control if the correct residual herbicide is included at planting timing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5238</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6782&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5238</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6782</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T08:36:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>14342643</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5238</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Larry Steckel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bobby Haygood, Angela McClure, Thomas Mueller, Scott Senseman, Scott Stewart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant, Soil and Environmental Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>