<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Small Mammal Activity Alters Plant Community Composition and Microbial Activity in an Old-Field Ecosystem</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, University of Copenhagen</institution>
<lname>Moorhead</lname>
<fname>Leigh</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Souza</lname>
<fname>Lara</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Wisconsin-Madison</institution>
<lname>Habeck</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Wisconsin-Madison</institution>
<lname>Lindroth</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, University of Copenhagen</institution>
<lname>Classen</lname>
<fname>Aimée</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>aboveground; belowground; communities; ecosystem function; foliar chemistry; nitrogen mineralization; plant chemistry; plant–animal interactions; rodent herbivory; soil microbes; species composition.</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Herbivores modify their environment by consuming plant biomass and redistributing materials across the landscape. While small mammalian herbivores, such as rodents, are typically inconspicuous, their impacts on plant community structure and chemistry can be large. We used a small mammal exclosure experiment to explore whether rodents in a southeastern old field directly altered the above ground plant species composition and chemistry, and indirectly altered the below ground soil community composition and activity. In general, when rodents were excluded, C3 graminoids increased in cover and biomass, contributing toward a shift in plant species composition relative to plots where rodents were present. The plant community chemistry also shifted; plant fiber concentration and carbon : nitrogen were higher, whereas plant nitrogen concentration was lower in exclosure plots relative to access plots. While microbial community enzyme activity increased when rodents were excluded, no significant changes in the fungal : bacterial or potential nitrogen mineralization occurred between treatments. Our results show that rodents can rapidly influence aboveground plant community composition and chemistry, but their influence on below ground processes may require plant inputs to the soil to accumulate over longer periods of time.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/72</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1073&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>72</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1073</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-20T09:01:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>10456129</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/72</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Moorhead, Leigh C., Lara Souza, Christipher W. Habeck, Richard L. Lindroth, Aimée T. Classen, “Small Mammal Activity Alters Plant Community Composition and Microbial Activity in an Old-Field,” Ecosphere 8, 5 (2017).
doi: 10.1002/ecs2.1777</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1002/ecs2.1777</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Ecosphere</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>