<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Scale-dependent heterogeneity in fracture data sets and grayscale images</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>aroy1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Roy</lname>
<fname>Ankur</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>fractures</keyword>
<keyword>scanline</keyword>
<keyword>lacunarity</keyword>
<keyword>fractal</keyword>
<keyword>multifractal</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lacunarity&lt;/em&gt; is a technique developed for multiscale analysis of spatial data and can quantify scale-dependent heterogeneity in a dataset. The present research is based on characterizing fracture data of various types by invoking lacunarity as a concept that can not only be applied to both fractal and non-fractal binary data but can also be extended to analyzing non-binary data sets comprising a spectrum of values between 0 and 1. Lacunarity has been variously modified in characterizing fracture data from &lt;em&gt;maps&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;scanlines&lt;/em&gt; in tackling five different problems. In Chapter 2, it is shown that normalized lacunarity curves can differentiate between maps (2-dimensional binary data) belonging to the same fractal-fracture system and that clustering increases with decreasing spatial scale. Chapter 4 analyzes spacing data from scanlines (1-dimensional binary data) and employs log-transformed lacunarity curves along with their 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; derivatives in identifying the presence of fracture clusters and their spatial organization. This technique is extended to 1-dimensional non-binary data in chapter 5 where spacing is integrated with aperture values and a lacunarity ratio is invoked in addressing the question of whether large fractures occur within clusters. Finally, it is investigated in chapter 6 if lacunarity can find differences in clustering along various directions of a fracture netowork thus identifying differentially-clustered fracture sets. In addition to fracture data, chapter 3 employs lacunarity in identifying clustering and multifractal behavior in synthetic and natural 2-dimensional non-binary patterns in the form of soil thin sections. Future avenues for research include estimation of 2-dimensional clustering from 1-dimensional samples (e.g., scanlines and well-data), forward modeling of fracture networks using lacunarity, and the possible application of lacunarity in delineating shapes of other geologic patterns such as channel beds.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2476</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2983&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2476</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2983</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-07T18:19:56-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2983/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4115912</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2476</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edmund Perfect</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William M. Dunne; Larry D. McKay; John S. Tyner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>