<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using Phenomenological Methods to Describe Maternal Perceptions of Positive Worksite Breastfeeding Support Experiences Across Various Industries</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Courtney</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>breastfeeding</keyword>
<keyword>worksite</keyword>
<keyword>support</keyword>
<keyword>breastmilk</keyword>
<keyword>phenemenology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background: Since paid maternity leave is uncommon in the United States, mothers who choose to breastfeed often return to work while breastfeeding. Adequate worksite support has been associated with longer duration of breastfeeding and greater job satisfaction; however, many mothers must navigate challenges upon returning to work. Despite recent worksite breastfeeding support improvements such as federal protections and the availability of model worksite breastfeeding support programs, it appears those employed in industry sectors that are traditionally more challenged to support pumping mothers, such as food service and retail establishments, education, and healthcare may continue to experience inadequate workplace support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: The purpose was to better understand mothers’ positive worksite breastfeeding support experiences in these historically challenging work sectors. Common factors associated with mothers’ positive experiences may subsequently be used to develop worksite breastfeeding support materials and help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Recruitment occurred via social media and snowball sampling. Participants (n=20) completed open-ended, semi-structured phone interviews. Audio-recorded interviews were transcribed. Significant statements were extracted from transcripts, formulated meanings were developed, and statements were organized into themes. Data collection, analysis, and determination of saturation were guided by phenomenological methodology. Member checking was performed with 10 participants toward the end of the study period by assessing participant agreement with emergent themes and drafted materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: Common themes that emerged from interview content included: maternal and managerial flexibility in working with suboptimal pumping spaces, ability to negotiate schedule flexibility, formal and informal managerial support, supportive coworkers, and maternal determination to continue breastfeeding. Most (90%) participants “strongly agreed” the themes were consistent with their experiences and 100% “strongly agreed” the drafted materials would help improve worksite breastfeeding support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: Elements of worksite support associated with successful experiences in these sectors may be used to develop a worksite breastfeeding support intervention to better support mothers to continue to breastfeed upon their return to the workforce.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5672</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7208&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5672</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7208</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-24T14:00:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>21246553</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5672</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Katherine Kavanagh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Marsha Spence, Sarah Colby, Samantha Ehrlich</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Background: Since paid maternity leave is uncommon in the United States, mothers who choose to breastfeed often return to work while breastfeeding. Adequate worksite support has been associated with longer duration of breastfeeding and greater job satisfaction, however, many mothers must navigate challenges upon returning to work. Despite recent worksite breastfeeding support improvements such as federal protections and the availability of model worksite breastfeeding support programs, it appears those employed in industry sectors that are traditionally more challenged to support pumping mothers, such as food service and retail establishments, education, and healthcare may continue to experience inadequate workplace support. Purpose: The purpose was to better understand mothers’ positive worksite breastfeeding support experiences in these historically challenging sectors. Common factors associated with mothers’ positive experiences can subsequently be used to develop worksite breastfeeding support materials and help. Methods: Recruitment occurred via social media and snowball sampling. Participants completed semi-structured, open-ended phone interviews. Audio-recorded interviews were transcribed. Significant statements were extracted from transcripts, formulated meanings were developed, and statements were organized into themes. Data collection, analysis, and determination of saturation were guided by phenomenological methodology. Member checking was performed toward the end of the study period by assessing participant agreement with emergent themes and drafted materials. Results: A total of twenty mothers completed phone interviews. Common themes that emerged from interview content included: maternal and managerial flexibility in working with suboptimal pumping spaces, ability to negotiate schedule flexibility, formal and informal managerial support, supportive coworkers, and maternal determination to continue breastfeeding. A total of ten participants completed follow-up surveys, of which 90% “strongly agreed” the themes were consistent with their experiences and 100% “strongly agreed” the drafted materials would help improve worksite breastfeeding support. Conclusion: Elements of worksite support associated with successful experiences in these sectors will be used to develop a worksite breastfeeding support intervention to better support mothers to continue to breastfeed upon their return to the workforce.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>