<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Photometric Analysis of Weapon Separation Characteristics</title>
<publication-date>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yurovich</lname>
<fname>Douglas</fname>
<mname>Paul</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aviation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This project attempted to implement a unique multi-camera photometric technology into the discipline of weapons separation testing from tactical jet aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was a U.S. Governmental, Department of Defense tasked affair, that utilized assets of the Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Naval Air Station, Patuxent River, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology employed consisted of a standard lens calibration procedure; an airspace calibration procedure, that defined the zone for the activity of motion, and targeting of the aircraft and specific store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With filmed flight test data in hand, the data was digitized through a motion sensor and stored as computer files. It was then transferred to 4D Video, an ImageBased Motion Measurement Company, Sebastopol, Ca., the Contractor, whose analysis quantified the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process as seen here has limited potential for future use, but with the augmentation of recent technological advancements, this process will become more efficient with manpower, assets and monies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is with continual evaluation and improvement that a Flight Test and Engineering organization can make this process the nucleus of a multi-camera photometric capability, giving the organization added accuracies in their ability to quantify weapon separation characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4930</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6375&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4930</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6375</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-01-17T08:51:56-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>11375971</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4930</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph D. Kimberlin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert Richards, Ted Paludan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>