<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A New Approach to the &lt;em&gt;Devīmāhātmya&lt;/em&gt;: The Greatness of the Goddess in its Purāṇic Context</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cecil</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although the text of the &lt;em&gt;Devīmāhātmya&lt;/em&gt; is itself a section of the &lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;, recent scholarship has taken a primarily extrinsic approach to the text and its use by emphasizing the life of the &lt;em&gt;Devīmāhātmya&lt;/em&gt; (henceforth &lt;em&gt;DM&lt;/em&gt;) well apart from the textual tradition of the purāṇas. A reading of the &lt;em&gt;DM&lt;/em&gt; in the context of the &lt;em&gt;MārkP&lt;/em&gt; is instructive, because it reveals some interesting thematic connections that are indicative of larger thematic trends within the purāṇa, which prior extrinsic studies have not explored. Broadly speaking, these themes glorify women and Goddesses as positive manifestations of some fundamental female energy and efficacy. These themes occur in the &lt;em&gt;DM&lt;/em&gt; and also occur in other narratives within the &lt;em&gt;MārkP&lt;/em&gt; that praise female actors who restore order in times of crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An evaluation of these thematic connections will show that the &lt;em&gt;DM&lt;/em&gt; is best understood not only as an important text in its own right, but as an important piece of the &lt;em&gt;MārkP&lt;/em&gt; as a whole. Conversely, the subject matter of the &lt;em&gt;MārkP&lt;/em&gt; should not be viewed as unrelated to that of the &lt;em&gt;DM&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, my thesis is a preliminary effort to situate a text glorifying the Goddess in its purāṇic context through an analysis of narrative and thematic content.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/346</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1380&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>346</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1380</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-15T09:54:19-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1145635</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/346</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rachelle Scott</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Johanna Stiebert, Miriam Levering</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/CecilElizabeth.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>