<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>WHAT DOES IT TAKE THEM JUST TO GET THE JOB? AN ANALYSIS OF EMPLOYABILITY SKILLS OF TODAY’S LIS GRADUATES: IMPLICATIONS FOR LIS CURRICULA</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T19:16:24-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>trembach@email.sc.edu</email>
<institution>University of South Carolina - Columbia</institution>
<lname>Trembach</lname>
<fname>Stan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dengl@email.sc.edu</email>
<institution>University of South Carolina - Columbia</institution>
<lname>Deng</lname>
<fname>Liya</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>athomas@sc.edu</email>
<institution>University of South Carolina - Columbia</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Andy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The information world is changing every day and so are the skills and competencies that an information professional needs. The school curricula, however, cannot be changed so fast. Therefore, a good curriculum has not only to be able to cover today’s needs but also to be adaptive enough to accommodate tomorrow’s needs. In order to have a better understanding of the information skills and competencies, the School of Library and Information Science at the University of South Carolina conducted a survey in 2010. Although there was limited response to the survey (17 in total), the results revealed that knowledge of SQL, telecommunications and networking, and network security are the most important areas of expertise. However, soft skills (such as teamwork, time management, and project management) are as important as the knowledge on technical issues. This qualitative study is built upon the previous survey and aims to understand which skills are more important and why from the information professionals’ perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study provides a strong impetus to assess current IS curricula from the standpoint of better preparing students for the rigors of the volatile job market so that they become fully equipped to meet the dynamic needs of a wide range of employers. A model IS curriculum, the study indicates, should be built around the principles of lifelong learning and open communication, supplying the students with a solid theoretical framework, conceptual foundations, and practical expertise with which they can realize their full potential and efficiently secure gainful employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords: LIS graduates, skills, employment, job market, LIS curricula&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/poster/13</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1053&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>13</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1053</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-14T08:12:40-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1053/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2403148</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/poster/13</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>