<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Deronda and the Tigress:  Judaism, Buddhism, and Universal Compassion In George Eliot’s Daniel Deronda</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmoats@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Moats</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>Frank</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>compassion</keyword>
<keyword>Buddha</keyword>
<keyword>Buddhism</keyword>
<keyword>Kabbalah</keyword>
<keyword>Mordecai</keyword>
<keyword>Israel</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Comparative Methodologies and Theories</discipline>
<discipline>Ethics and Political Philosophy</discipline>
<discipline>History of Religions of Eastern Origins</discipline>
<discipline>Jewish Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Literature in English, British Isles</discipline>
<discipline>Religious Thought, Theology and Philosophy of Religion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Many scholars have discussed Judaism and the ethics of George Eliot in &lt;em&gt;Daniel Deronda&lt;/em&gt;, but few have explored the impact of Buddhism upon the novel. This thesis is the first study to demonstrate the influence of Buddhism upon George Eliot&#39;s fiction. By tracing Eliot&#39;s interest in the emerging field of comparative religion, I argue that Buddhism offered Eliot a unique religion that was compatible with her secular humanism. Although Buddhism appears explicitly in &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; in only a few instances, I contend that Eliot uses the tradition of Jewish mysticism known as Kabbalism as the predominant theology in &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; because it contains many affinities with Buddhism, most notably the doctrine of the transmigration of souls. Mordecai interprets the transmigration of souls as a teleological justification for Jewish nationalism, but I assert that for Eliot, the transmigration of souls challenges national boundaries and instead promotes a universal compassion that extends to all cultures. I argue that Eliot employs many voices of Jewish dissent in &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; to illustrate the difficulty of reconciling cultural heritage with universal compassion strictly in terms of Judaism, and then I draw upon a metaphor in which Eliot compares Deronda to the Buddha to suggest that Deronda and his mission to re-establish Israel are antithetical to Eliot&#39;s vision of universal compassion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter one reviews &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; scholarship about Judaism, including work by Edward Said, Amanda Anderson, and Nancy Henry. This chapter reads these scholars in terms of particular Eliot letters, notes, and moments in &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Impressions of Theophrastus Such &lt;/em&gt;and asserts that Jewish nationalism in &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; precludes universal compassion. Chapter two chronicles Eliot&#39;s adoption of secular humanism and then argues that Buddhism offers both the cultural solidarity that Eliot prizes in Judaism as well as the universal compassion inherent in Eliot&#39;s secular humanism. The conclusion of this thesis asserts that the renunciation of the ego in Buddhism attracts Eliot, and it proposes that contextualizing &lt;em&gt;Deronda&lt;/em&gt; in terms of Eliot&#39;s conceptions of Buddhism helps resolve some of the tension between Judaism and compassion in the novel.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1270</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2400&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1270</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2400</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-05-23T13:12:59-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2400/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2910279</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1270</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Nancy Henry</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allen Dunn, Dawn Coleman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>