<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of Ultrasensitive Analytical Techniques to Detect Trace Elements</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>eromeror@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Romero Romero</lname>
<fname>Elisa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Resonant Ionization Mass Spectrometry</keyword>
<keyword>Accelerator Mass Spectrometry</keyword>
<keyword>Actinides</keyword>
<keyword>Ultra-sensitive techniques</keyword>
<keyword>Neutrino experiments</keyword>
<keyword>Ion source</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, two methods for ultra-trace analysis were investigated: the negative-ion based Accelerator Mass Spectrometry (AMS) and positive-ion based Resonant Ionization Mass Spectrometry (RIMS). The detection, monitoring and quantification of ultra-low levels of actinides is of considerable importance and represents a challenge in many fields of modern science: neutrino physics, dark matter searches, nuclear astrophysics, environmental science, etc. These fields demand more sensitive and more efficient techniques and are pushing the limits of conventional techniques for ultra-trace analysis. Employing the 14 MV tandem accelerator of the Australian National University, we demonstrated an AMS method capable of detecting ultra-low traces of Th and U from ultrapure Cu made underground for the Majorana Demonstrator. We made significant advancements on the actinide detection efficiency and sensitivity with the laser-based technique RIMS. We demonstrated that RIMS is a powerful analytical technique for actinides since it does not require large amount of material, has high selectivity, high efficiency and high sensitivity. Several three-step ionization schemes were studied and numerous high-lying and autoionizing levels were observed for Pu, Th, and U. We obtained efficiencies up to 51% for Pu, 32% for Th and 9% for U. These efficiencies represent the largest efficiencies reported for actinides and surpass significantly the efficiencies obtained in AMS for actinides which are between 0.1% to 1%. We performed sensitivity studies with a setup consisting of a Resonant Ionization Laser Ion Source (RILIS), a mass spectrometer based on the Holifield Radioactive Ion Beam Facility radioactive injector IRIS2 and a single ion counter. We obtained a detection limit of 103 atoms for 240Pu which is 1-2 orders of magnitude below previously reported. Atomic spectroscopic studies for Pu were done revealing four Rydberg series in the energetically high-lying region in the atomic spectrum. The first ionization potential (IP) of Pu was precisely determined as 48605.748 (95)stat(49)sys cm−1 using two methods. This value is a factor of three more precise than the one reported in the NIST database and constitutes a benchmark for modern relativistic atomic theories.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5729</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7495&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5729</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7495</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419595</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5729</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alfredo Galindo-Uribarri Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Adriana Moreo Dr., Kenneth F. Read Jr Dr., Lawrence W. Townsend Dr., Soren P. Sorensen Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>