<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The relationship between candidate self-monitoring, verbal impression management, and interviewers&#39; ratings in the employment interview</title>
<publication-date>1992-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Long</lname>
<fname>Esther</fname>
<mname>Joy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Past research has found that verbal and nonverbal communication are both powerful vehicles for impression management in the employment interview. Research on the socialpsychological trait of self-monitoring suggests that people differ in terms of their skill at impression management The primary purpose of the present research was to detennine if candidates&#39; self-monitoring orientations are related to interviewers&#39; ratings and hiring recommendations in actual employment interviews (Study 1) and to candidate impression management behavior in mock interviews (Study 2). Two hundred and thirty-three job candidates (college students) and 30 campus recruiters participated in the first study. Three hypotheses were tested in this study. The first hypothesis predicted that high self-monitoring candidates would be evaluated more favorably than low selfmonitoring candidates. The second hypothesis predicted that self-monitoring would be more strongly related to interviewers&#39; ratings and hiring recommendations for people-oriented jobs than it would for technically-oriented jobs. The third hypothesis predicted that self-monitoring would be more strongly related to ratings of fit than to ratings of general employability. Only the second hypothesis was supported in Study 1. Specifically, candidate self-monitoring was more strongly related to interviewers&#39; ratings and hiring recommendations for people-oriented jobs than it was for technically-oriented jobs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6132</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8120&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6132</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8120</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23359355</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6132</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory H. Dobbins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial and Organizational Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>