<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Identification, Functional Characterization and Phylogeny of the Nodulin-Like Anion Transporter (NLAT) Family in Plants</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Vincill</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>Daniel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A cDNA was isolated from soybean (&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt;) nodules that encodes a putative transporter (&lt;em&gt;GmN70&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;GmN70&lt;/em&gt; is expressed predominantly in mature nitrogenfixing root nodules. By western-blot and immunocytochemical analyses, GmN70 was localized to the symbiosome membrane of infected root nodule cells, suggesting a transport role in symbiosis. To investigate its transport function, cRNA encoding GmN70 was expressed in &lt;em&gt;Xenopus laevis&lt;/em&gt; oocytes, and two-electrode voltage clamp analysis was performed. Ooctyes expressing GmN70 showed outward currents that are carried by anions with a selectivity of nitrate &gt; nitrite &gt;&gt; chloride. These currents showed little sensitivity to pH or the nature of the counter cation in the oocyte bath solution. One-half maximal currents were induced by nitrate concentrations between 1 to 3 mM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A global protein BLAST search for NLAT-related proteins revealed the presence of multiple homologs in all plant genomes sequenced with members segregating into 6 distinct monophyletic clades. Two genes from Arabidopsis clustering within the same clade 1 (chromosome nomenclature:At2g39210 and At2g28120) and shared a high amino acid sequence identity with GmN70 (respective 63.7% and 56.3%) and cluster in the same clade (Clade 1) as GmN70 and LjN70. Investigation of the transport properties of these two &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; NLAT-like genes (renamed &lt;em&gt;AtNLAT1;1&lt;/em&gt; [At2g39210] and &lt;em&gt;AtNLAT1;2&lt;/em&gt; [At2g28120] showed similar transport properties as GmN70 and LjN70 and transported the inorganic anions, nitrate, nitrite, and chloride. Expression analysis and sub-cellular localization of &lt;em&gt;AtNLAT1;1&lt;/em&gt; show it to be expressed predominately in the leaf on the plasma membrane. Its expression is regulated by a diverse set of biotic and abiotic stress signals including &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas syringae&lt;/em&gt; pv. &lt;em&gt;tomato&lt;/em&gt;, salicylic acid, salinity, touch, and wounding suggesting a role in stress adaptation in plants. Consistent with these findings, transgenic &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; lines in which &lt;em&gt;AtNLAT1;1&lt;/em&gt; expression is knocked-down show an enhanced sensitivity to NaCl as well as a perturbed ionomic profile as revealed by inductively coupled plasma-mass spectroscopy (ICP-MS). Overall, the data presented in this body of work have provided insight into the biochemical and biophysical function and expression profiles of two members of the NLAT family, &lt;em&gt;GmN70&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AtNLAT1;1&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/453</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1514&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>453</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1514</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T12:03:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1151289</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/453</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel M. Roberts</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Beth Mullin, Rebecca Prosser, Jeffrey Becker, Cynthia Peterson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/VincillEricDaniel.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>