<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Behavioral Activation of Religious Behaviors:  Treating Depressed College Students with a Randomized Controlled Trial</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mea@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Armento</lname>
<fname>Maria Elizabeth Anne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>behavioral activation</keyword>
<keyword>treatment</keyword>
<keyword>religion</keyword>
<keyword>spirituality</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although spiritual or religious behaviors are sometimes targeted within behavioral activation protocols (Hopko &amp; Lejuez, 2007; Hopko, Lejuez, Ruggiero, &amp; Eifert, 2003), the efficacy of a protocol that exclusively develops a religiously-based behavioral repertoire has not been investigated. This randomized controlled study investigated the efficacy of a brief protocol for religious action in behavioral activation (PRA-BA) relative to a no-treatment “support” condition among mild to moderately depressed undergraduate students (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 50). PRA-BA consisted of an individualized one-session intervention and 2-week activation interval. Clinical outcomes assessed depression, environmental reward, anxiety, and quality of life. Repeated measures ANOVAs indicated that the PRA-BA group had significantly greater decreases in depression and anxiety and increases in environmental reward at post-treatment. There was also a statistical trend indicating that PRA-BA may improve quality of life. At one-month follow-up, treatment gains were maintained for the PRA-BA participants. This study provides encouraging support for the efficacy of a strictly religiously-based behavioral intervention toward attenuating symptoms of depression in college students.&lt;strong&gt;  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1052</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2209&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1052</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2209</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-12T15:55:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2056201</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1052</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Derek R. Hopko</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Todd M. Moore, Michael R. Nash, Barbara A. Murphy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>