<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mating System Biology of the Florida Native Plant: Illicium parviflorum</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nbuckley@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Buckley</lname>
<fname>Nicholas</fname>
<mname>Earl</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Illicium parviflorum</keyword>
<keyword>Self-incompatibility</keyword>
<keyword>Breeding system</keyword>
<keyword>Austrobaileyaceae</keyword>
<keyword>Pollination biology</keyword>
<keyword>Inbreeding Depression</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Developmental Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Evolution</discipline>
<discipline>Other Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Self-incompatibility is thought to have played a profound role in the evolution of the angiosperms. However, there is little evidence of self-incompatibility systems in early diverging lineages of flowering plants. &lt;em&gt;Illicium parviflorum&lt;/em&gt;, one such early-divergent angiosperm, is an evergreen perennial species endemic to central Florida, particularly within the Ocala National Forest. Although locally abundant, &lt;em&gt;I. parviflorum&lt;/em&gt; is currently listed as endangered at the state level due to being under constant threat of habitat disturbance and over-harvesting. Notably, this species had been described as self-incompatible due to its low seed-set. However, low seed set may also be a result of strong, early inbreeding depression. Using cross-pollinations, histology, and molecular analysis, I provide conclusive evidence that &lt;em&gt;I. parviflorum &lt;/em&gt;possesses the ability to self-fertilize, while finding no evidence of a self-incompatibility system. Furthermore, cross-pollinations of individuals within and between populations revealed heterosis, while seeds collected from self-pollinations were smaller than those collected from out-crosses, suggesting that inbreeding may be reducing fitness within populations. An analysis used to estimate parental genotypes of individuals in a population using AFLP markers identified two out of 23 plants to be the result of natural self-pollination, while the mean (+ s.e.) pollen: ovule ratio of &lt;em&gt;I. parviflorum &lt;/em&gt;was found to be 511 + 86, a ratio consistent with a species that relies primarily, but not exclusively, on outcrossing. Pollen/ovule ratios of &lt;em&gt;I. parviflorum &lt;/em&gt;and other small flowered &lt;em&gt;Illicium &lt;/em&gt;are&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;lower than their larger flowered, derived relatives, suggesting that the ancestral floral type to the &lt;em&gt;Illicium &lt;/em&gt;lineage was self-compatible. These results support the hypothesis that early angiosperm species had the ability to self-fertilize and that self-incompatibility systems did not arise until after the origin of the bisexual flower.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1310</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2429&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1310</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2429</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-06-21T14:36:24-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2429/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3008337</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1310</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph H. Williams</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Randall L. Small, Ben M. Fitzpatrick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>