<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>THE STEEL TOWER: A 21st CENTURY TALL BUILDING</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pduke1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Duke</lname>
<fname>Peter Guldenshuh</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Pittsburgh</keyword>
<keyword>Steel</keyword>
<keyword>Tower</keyword>
<keyword>Tall</keyword>
<keyword>Building</keyword>
<keyword>Architecture</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper outlines the need for a new mixed use high-rise project for the commercial business district of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. The proposed tower combines commercial, laboratory, residential, and tourist program into one tower of roughly 1.5 million square feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the new world headquarters for US Steel, the facility is sited and developed strategically in Pittsburgh&#39;s Golden Triangle. Its prominent location in the heart of downtown seeks to take advantage of the public transit in an effort to curb extraneous individual travel while further enriching the downtown experience. The building&#39;s height, orientation, and grounding are developed to relate to external environmental factors. As a site specific high-rise, emphasis is placed on view corridor and skyline composition. Furthermore, its dominant vertical orientation creates an urban landmark and a viewing platform available for public use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steel mega-structure uses a highly articulated diagrid in an effort to minimize material while emphasizing an organized loading strategy. The innovative structuring concept works as a dialogue for steel&#39;s future involvement in 21st century high rise building construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By combining sheer height and size with an innovative structural system, the Steel Tower seeks to become &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; tall building among many in Pittsburgh, PA.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1609</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2743&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1609</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2743</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-17T07:58:49-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2743/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4037911</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1609</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marleen Kay Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James Rose, Ryann Aoukarr</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>