<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Patterns and predictors of antimicrobial resistance among Staphylococcus spp. from canine clinical cases presented at a veterinary academic hospital in South Africa</title>
<publication-date>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa</institution>
<lname>Qekwana</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
<mname>N.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of South Africa, Johannesburg, South Africa</institution>
<lname>Oguttu</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Ross University School of Veterinary Medicine, Basseterre, Saint Kitts and Nevis</institution>
<lname>Sithole</lname>
<fname>Fortune</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, USA</institution>
<lname>Odoi</lname>
<fname>Agricola</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial resistance in staphylococci, often associated with treatment failure, is increasingly reported in veterinary medicine. The aim of this study was to investigate patterns and predictors of antimicrobial resistance among &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt; spp. isolates from canine samples submitted to the bacteriology laboratory at the University of Pretoria academic veterinary hospital between 2007 and 2012. Retrospective data of 334 &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt; isolates were used to calculate the proportion of samples resistant to 15 antimicrobial agents. The Cochran-Armitage trend test was used to investigate temporal trends and logistic regression models were used to investigate predictors of antimicrobial resistance in &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results show that 98.2% (55/56) of the &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; isolates were resistant to at least one drug while 42.9% were multidrug resistant. Seventy-seven percent (214/278) of the &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; isolates were resistant to at least one drug and 25.9% (72/278) were multidrug resistant. Resistance to lincospectin was more common among &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt;(64.3%) than &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; (38.9%). Similarly, resistance to clindamycin was higher in &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; (51.8%) than &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; (31.7%) isolates. There was a significant (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.005) increase in &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; resistance to enrofloxacin over the study period. Similarly, &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; exhibited significant increasing temporal trend in resistance to trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.004), clindamycin (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.022) and orbifloxacin (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.042). However, there was a significant decreasing temporal trend in the proportion of isolates resistant to doxycycline (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.041), tylosin (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.008), kanamycin (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.017) and amoxicillin/clavulanic acid (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.032).  &lt;h3&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High levels of multidrug resistance and the increasing levels of resistance to sulphonamides, lincosamides and fluoroquinolones among &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt; spp. isolates in this study are concerning. Future studies will need to investigate local drivers of antimicrobial resistance to better guide control efforts to address the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/138</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1136&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>138</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1136</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-11-04T09:36:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>15693206</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/138</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12917-017-1034-3</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>BMC Veterinary Research</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>