<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Say hello to hybrid: Investigating student and instructor perceptions of the first hybrid language courses at UT</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rlamance@utk.edu</email>
<lname>LaMance</lname>
<fname>Rachel Amanda</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>University of Tennessee</keyword>
<keyword>French</keyword>
<keyword>hybrid language courses</keyword>
<keyword>student perceptions</keyword>
<keyword>instructor perceptions</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Modern Languages</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The University of Tennessee began implementing 100-level hybrid French language courses in fall 2011, and this research investigates students’ and instructors’ attitudes toward the hybrid courses. Online surveys were used to assess the perceptions of 210 students and four instructors on five specific aspects of the hybrid courses: technology use and competence, time management, (language) learning, anxiety, and overall satisfaction. Approximately half of students enjoyed their hybrid course, and the data showed trends when factoring variables such as reported grade and comfort with the two components of the courses. Students expecting to receive As were more satisfied with their course than students expecting to receive lower grades. Also, students who were equally comfortable in classroom and online settings were more likely to appreciate the hybrid format than students who were more comfortable in the classroom setting. In addition, results showed increases in students’ and instructors’ comfort levels with technologies associated with the hybrid courses. Overall, results showed that hybrid courses were moderately successful, but recurring problems were a lack of student autonomy and a lack of proper training for both students and instructors. Improvements for future hybrid programs are outlined as well as suggestions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1177</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2353&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1177</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2353</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-30T13:37:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2714569</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1177</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sébastien Dubreil</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sébastien Dubreil, John B. Romeiser, Dolly J. Young</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>French</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>