<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Elastic properties of complex transition metal oxides studied by Resonant Ultrasound Spectroscopy</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>yluan@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Luan</lname>
<fname>Yanbing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Elastic Properties</keyword>
<keyword>Resonant Ultrasound Spectroscopy (RUS)</keyword>
<keyword>Transition Metal Oxides (TMO)</keyword>
<keyword>Geometrically Frustrated Materials</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The elastic properties of novel transition metal oxides have been investigated, using a powerful technique known as Resonant Ultrasound Spectroscopy (RUS). Two sets of transition metal oxides have been studied. One is the ruthenate Ca&lt;sub&gt;2-x&lt;/sub&gt;Sr&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;RuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; series with a layered perovskite structure, a Mott transition system that connects the Mott insulator Ca&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;RuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; with the unconventional superconductor Sr&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;RuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. The other set contains geometrically frustrated materials, including vanadium spinels AV&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; (A = Zn, Mn and Fe) and titanate pyrochlores A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; (A= Y, Tb, Yb, Ho and Dy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elastic response of five Ca&lt;sub&gt;2-x&lt;/sub&gt;Sr&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;RuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; single crystals (x = 2.0, 1.9, 0.5, 0.3 and 0.2) has been measured.  For 2.0 ≥ x ≥ 0.5, a dramatic softening over a wide temperature range is observed upon cooling, caused by the rotational instability of RuO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; octahedra (for x = 2.0 and 1.9) or the static rotation of the octahedra (for x = 0.5). For the Ca-rich samples (x = 0.3 and 0.2), the softening occurs in a very narrow temperature range, corresponding to the structural phase transition from high-temperature-tetragonal to low-temperature-orthorhombic symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elastic softening in ZnV&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; is observed near the cubic-to-tetragonal structural phase transition at 50 K. The elastic response of MnV&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; is quite unusual, displaying a softening over a wide temperature range with decreasing temperature. Upon cooling, C’ of FeV&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; becomes so soft that it drops to almost zero around 140 K, where the cubic-to-tetragonal structural transition occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;, all three elastic constants show normal “Varshni” behavior. For spin liquid Tb&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;, all three elastic constants show a pronounced softening below 50 K, indicative of a possible Jahn-Teller, cubic-to-tetragonal transition at very low temperatures. It is also found that the application of a magnetic field suppresses the elastic softening in this compound. Another spin liquid Yb&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; shows no elastic softening. The elastic moduli of the spin-ice compounds, Ho&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; and Dy&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;, show a broad “dip” around 100 K, which is believed to be caused by the strong crystal field effect in those two compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/993</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2118&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>993</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2118</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-05T06:20:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1919449</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/993</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Veerle M. Keppens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George M. Pharr, Chuck L. Melcher, Adriana Moreo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>