<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Betwixt and Between:  Qualitative Examinations of Leaders’ Internal Processes of Transition</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mritchi3@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Ritchie</lname>
<fname>Margaret</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Transition</keyword>
<keyword>Educational Leaders</keyword>
<keyword>Principals</keyword>
<keyword>Liminality</keyword>
<keyword>Leadership Transition</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examines alternative forms of school governance from the personal perspectives of leaders, reflecting upon their transition through the organizational governance change. The effects of moving from a local governance authority to a five school multi-academy trust was both thrust upon the leaders who participated in this study as they, in turn, thrust the change upon others. This new vision of schooling rippled throughout the schools involved, the community in which the schools are located, and the greater local authority that did not embrace this change. The purpose of this qualitative study was to examine alternative forms of school governance from the personal perspectives of leaders, reflecting upon their transition through the organizational governance change. Based on Van Gennep’s concept of liminality, Turner applied liminality as a theoretical framework to the middle stages of the rites of passage or what he called the transitional stage. Transition comes at a personal cost and leader perspectives are essential considerations in successful change. Findings centered on personal transition of the leadership and revealed that these transitions may have had a substantial impact in the ability of the leadership to navigate through the change process and lead more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6087</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7368&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6087</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7368</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-09-24T05:48:55-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/7368/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>19527259</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6087</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Pamela S. Angelle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patrick Biddix, Jimmy G. Cheek, Michael R. Fitzgerald</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>