<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>How to Stay Afloat When the Boat isn&#39;t &quot;Woke&quot;</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-12T15:06:43-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ccunni28@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>CUNNINGHAM</lname>
<fname>COURTNEY</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>wmarti27@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>MARTINEZ</lname>
<fname>WILLIAM</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Other</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Program Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to stay afloat when the boat isn&#39;t woke will explore the harsh realities of being a person a color (African American, Latin-x, Asian American, etc.) on a predominantly white campus. By discussing and defining both salient and non-salient identities that we all hold alongside giving real-world examples and anecdotes of each, we hope to inform session participants how they can best support themselves as well as the marginalized students around them. Using real-life examples and tangible tools we hope to add to their personally tool kit to create both an interactive and reflective session. The session will end with a group discussion and workshop on how students with marginalized identities can best care for and advocate for themselves to stay afloat when the boat isn’t “woke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significance to the Conference Participants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attendees will begin self-analysis of their own identities as well as the perceived identities of those in the room. Attendees will continue by engaging in a short lecture defining the listed terms from above. Attendees will also reflect about the every-day challenges of a student with marginalized identities and best practices on how to support them. Ending with the impacts of invisible labor and those who are tired while also engaging in a discussion on how to support self care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ntroduction of both presenters + Fields of Study  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ground Rules: Safe vs. Brace Space  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Addressing Model + Room Analysis  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflective Exercise ***Both Will and I will share our life experiences and in hopes that by challenge by choice the participants will share there&#39;s.  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who am I?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I show up?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have I been stereotyped?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection from the group  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impacts of those who are tired  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what does self-care look like?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can I support those people, if I can not relate?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/5</coverpage-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1246</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-27T16:59:59-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16085056</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Courtney Cunningham&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courtney Cunningham is the Assistant Hall Director in Reese Hall at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville (Go Vols) in Knoxville, Tennessee. Courtney did her undergraduate at Old Dominion University (Go Monarchs!) in Norfolk, Virginia holding a Bachelors of Science in Sociology. While at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Courtney is completing a capstone entitled, “Blacks Minds Matter”: the causes, effects and implications of Mental Health for African American college students. In her spare time, Courtney enjoys traveling, Mexican food, and shopping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Martinez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Martinez is a Graduate Teaching Assistant for the Center for Health Education and Wellness at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville (Go Vols) in Knoxville, Tennessee. William did his undergraduate work at Emory University holding a Bachelors in Anthropology and Sociology (Go Swoop and Dooley) in Atlanta, Georgia. William focuses his research on critical race theory and ethnic studies. In his spare time, he loves to read and play with his kittens Chowder and Pablo.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;N/A&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Monitor</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will be able to define and recognize examples the following terms: salient and non-salient identities, marginalize, privilege, invisible labor, and taxation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will listen to real-life experiences from the presenters as well as reflect and acknowledge experiences that have impacted their life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will be given skills and practices to best support those with marginalized identities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will be given skills and practices to best support and advocate for themselves when it comes to self-care&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The presenters will utilize their own identities while creating a safe and brave space to allow for those with differing identities to feel comfortable to challenge themselves by choice. While the conversation deals with serious topics, both presenters will keep it real and keep it light-hearted to make sure everyone feels included, welcomed, and respected. Real-world anecdotes that are applicable to students of color will also ensure the topic is relevant to all involved. Both presenters will also utilize a self-care and self-love model to ensure that participants grasp how important this topic is in diversity and inclusion work.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>