<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The accumulation of new carbon input and microbial residues in soil under long-term conservation agricultural management practices</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lli59@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Lidong</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>soil carbon</keyword>
<keyword>soil nitrogen</keyword>
<keyword>drying-rewetting cycles</keyword>
<keyword>isotope labeling</keyword>
<keyword>cover crops</keyword>
<keyword>reduced tillage</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A better understanding of the mechanisms of soil organic matter (SOM) stabilization is necessary for improving soil quality, especially in agroecosystems. This doctoral dissertation research studied the effects of long-term conservation agricultural management practices on the accumulation of newly added labile carbon (C) and microbially derived SOM. To study their accumulation in soil, newly added labile C was represented by carbon-13 (&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C) labelled glucose and the microbially derived SOM was represented by amino sugars.Short-term drying-rewetting cycles are common in surface soils, especially in agroecosystems, which may have different effects on different C pool. Understanding the accumulation and mineralization of newly added labile C in soil during drying-rewetting cycles is important for predicting soil organic C (SOC) storage in long-term. A 24-day incubation in microcosms was conducted with an agricultural soil under 36 years of conservation management. I added 13C-labelled glucose and applied different frequencies of drying-rewetting cycles to the microcosms. At the end of the 24-day incubation, 0.08%-1% of the added glucose C was incorporated into the extractable organic C (EOC) pool, 4%-27% of the added glucose C was incorporated into the microbial biomass C (MBC) pool, and 0.7%-5% of the added glucose C was incorporated into the hydrogen peroxide (H2O2)-resistant C pool. The drying treatment induced higher recovery of the added glucose C in each C pool. The vetch cover crops are more favorable for the stabilization of newly added labile C under repeated drying-rewetting cycles. Structural equation model shows that chemical association and biochemical recalcitrance rather than physical protection are major controls of labile C sequestration in soil under drying-rewetting cycles.Understanding the physical, chemical, and microbial processes controlling the retention of microbial residues in soil is essential for predicting the accumulation of microbially derived SOM. I measured amino sugar concentration, C and nitrogen (N) concentrations microbial respiration rate, extracellular enzyme activity, and soil aggregate composition in an agricultural soil under 31-years of conservation management. Structural equation models show that physical protection plays a critical role in muramic acid stabilization, while microbial activity and substrate availability are more critical for glucosamine.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5064</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6605&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5064</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6605</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T14:08:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13415489</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5064</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sean M. Schaeffer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer M. DeBruyn, Sindhu Jagadamma, Robert T. Ladd, Jie Zhuang</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5420-260X</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant, Soil and Environmental Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>