<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Next Generation: Looking at UTK Students’ Potential Future Engagement with GSMNP</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-23T18:59:21-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lmosadeg@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Mosadegh</lname>
<fname>Layla Marie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Marketing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research was to understand the next generation’s, aka Gen Z’s, engagement with Great Smoky Mountains National Park (GSMNP) by studying the motivations and perceptions surrounding engagement with GSMNP amongst undergraduate students enrolled for the 2018-2019 school year at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville (UTK). This research was conducted in the format of a hybrid case study with a combined marketing strategy plan that aims to answer the following questions:  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the motivations and perceptions surrounding engagement with Great Smoky Mountains National Park amongst undergraduate students enrolled for the 2018-2019 school year at the at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can Great Smoky Mountains National Park do to engage the next generation of visitors, volunteers, donors, fundraisers, and activists?  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quantitative portion of the research was conducted in the form of an anonymous online survey distributed to a convenience sample of undergraduate students enrolled at UTK. Findings from the survey guided talking points for the qualitative portion, focus groups, which were used to triangulate the survey data. These research findings informed the basis for sample marketing strategy applications targeted towards “The Next Generation.” The overall goal for this project was that the research findings and marketing strategy be presented to GSMNP for potential use.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/business/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1270&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1270</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-22T13:14:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14322494</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/business/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Marketing</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Melinda Micheletto</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>