<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sidestick Controllers During High Gain Tasks</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Goszkowicz</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Systems Engineering and Multidisciplinary Design Optimization</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research attempts to demonstrate the feasibility of a sidestick controller in a high gain environment. The research is assembled from several historical precedents and various projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New technologies have re-ignited interest in the use of sidestick controllers for commercial and military aircraft. There are many advantages and disadvantages utilizing a sidestick in fighter aircraft. Many pilots prefer the feel of a centerstick controller and the designer only needs to develop a few sets of command gradients or gearings to produce adequate handling qualities. However, centersticks require more cockpit room due to their larger size and range of motion. Consequently, designers would have a difficult time fitting a centerstick in small cockpits such as the F-16. The presence of a centerstick could obstruct the view of a center panel Multi-Function Display, preventing the pilot from quickly assimilating valuable information. Sidestick controllers are lightweight, ncan fit in small cockpits, and are better suited for aircraft capable of sustained high normal load factors. From a pilot-vehicle interface standpoint, sidesticks offer an unobstructed view of displays, a clear pathway during an emergency cockpit egress, and allows access to full command inputs for the diverse statures of today’s pilots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sidestick controller is not without its deficiencies. A sidestick controller prevents easy access to the console under the armrest forcing the designers to use that space for controls that may be set prior to flight. A sidestick also prevents the pilot from using the non-sidestick hand to control the aircraft while trying to do other tasks, such as writing on a kneeboard or using the console under the armrest. Additionally, the tendency toward PIO is more prevalent in air craft equipped with a sidestick than a centerstick. Flight test and simulation has shown that different Command Gradients and Gearings optimize performance for different tasks. However, it is not feasible to collapse the control laws into one usable set for all tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2060</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3424&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2060</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3424</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-02T08:19:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4657413</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2060</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. R. Kimberlin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. U. P. Solies, Dr. Fred Stellar</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>