<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hot Topic: Animal Control Law Revised by Legislature</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</institution>
<lname>Darden</lname>
<fname>Don</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>animal control</keyword>
<keyword>pets</keyword>
<keyword>euthanasia</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As of August 15, 2001: The Tennessee General Assembly recently enacted a new law that repeals the Dog and Cat Humane Death Act [Part 3] in its entirety. It was replaced with Chapter 70, referred to as the Non-livestock Animal Humane Death Act. According to Tennessee Code Annotated§ 39-14- 201, &quot;non-livestock animals&quot; refers to common household pets - dogs, cats, rabbits, chicks, ducks, and even potbellied pigs. The new law applies to public and private agencies, animal shelters, and other facilities operated for the collection, care, and/or euthanasia of stray, neglected, abandoned, or unwanted non-livestock animals. It does not apply to exotic animals. Generally, the new Jaw prescribes methods and procedures for euthanizing pets and prescribes penalties for violations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtastop/238</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1238&amp;amp;context=utk_mtastop&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>238</label>
<document-type>bulletin</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1238</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-28T06:45:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Hot Topics</publication-title>
<context-key>3967722</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtastop/238</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;#70&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-03-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>