<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Analysis of Cantilever Plates with Concentrated Loads</title>
<publication-date>1941-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Marks</lname>
<fname>Constant</fname>
<mname>Roberts</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Applied Mechanics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From the Introduction&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of a cantilever plate or slab with variable, discontinuous, concentrated, or eccentric loading occurs frequently in engineering design. Examples are substructure walls, piers, projecting floor slabs, and gear teeth. The solution of most of these problems can be made to depend on the analysis of the plate in question loaded with one or more concentrated loads. Such analyses are available for only a few cases of loading, and no practical method is available to the designer for making any kind of a reasonably accurate stress analysis for many cases he may encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper is developed an original analysis for an important limiting case (Case III). In addition, the cases that have been studied are collected and amplified and an approximate method developed of solving similar cases for which no analysis is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Appendix B is given a detailed description of the difference equation method used not only in the analysis developed in this paper, but also in one of the studies quoted. This description is essential to the understanding of the paper and also may prove of use in the solution of certain problems occurring in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bibliography includes, in addition to the writings referred to in this paper, several pertinent references on the subject of plate analysis in general.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4830</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6336&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4830</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6336</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-15T13:12:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10753541</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4830</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>E. S. Fabian</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Armour T. Granger, Edgar D. Eaves</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Major is listed as Applied Mechanics in original copy&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1941-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1941-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>