<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Professional Training and Responsibilities of Supervisors of Academic Teacher of the Deaf as Perceived by Selected Administrators, Principals, Supervisors, and Teachers of the Deaf</title>
<publication-date>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mba</lname>
<fname>Peter</fname>
<mname>O.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statement of the Problem: Schmitt, Quigley, and Quadagno (1968, pp. 3, 27) pointed out that little attention had been given to the qualification and responsibilities of supervisors of academic teachers of the deaf as regards &quot;evaluative studies.&quot; They stressed the need for some uniformity of practice in connection with the kind and degree of academic training and &quot;professional experience&quot; required of supervisors. Brill (1971, p. 138) supporting Schmitt and his partners, called attention to the relatively &quot;little objective research&quot; in regard to role definition for supervisors and necessary academic preparation for their position. Griffing (1968, p. 678) emphasized that definition of supervisory role is a major requirement and suggested that the practical approach to the &quot;dilemma&quot; lies &quot;in the analysis of tasks for supervisors&quot; (p. 682).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study, therefore, was to examine the difference in viewpoints of the writers by reviewing available literature on supervision in programs for the hearing-impaired, and relating these viewpoints to an analysis of the perceptions of administrators, principals, supervisors, and teachers of the deaf, as regards: (1) the professional training, qualifications, and experience, and (b) the responsibilities and duties of supervisors of academic teachers of the deaf.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3537</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5069&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3537</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5069</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-11-13T12:16:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7842138</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3537</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>A. Paul Wishart</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles L. Thompson, Glenn T. Lloyd, Earl M. Ramer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>