<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Tennessee Beef Performance Testing Program in Robertson County</title>
<publication-date>1962-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Watson</lname>
<fname>Craig</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A program for the performance testing of beef cattle in Tennessee was instigated in 1956 by the Extension Animal Husbandry Department and the Animal Husbandry-Veterinary Science Department of The University of Tennessee. In various meetings over the state with the extension personnel, the members of the Robertson County Livestock Association and the Agriculture Extension Agent in Robertson County became interested in this production testing program. Since Robertson County is a growing beef cattle county, performance testing beef herds in the county to determine the rate of gain and the quality of calves that were produced seemed advisable. In 1958 the Assistant County Agent set up four demonstration herds in the county and started the production testing program. These herds were Hereford, Shorthorn Hereford crosses, and Angus and were both registered and commercial herds. This study is a summary of the results of performance testing procedure for three years in these four herds.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4345</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5775&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4345</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5775</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-23T06:22:44-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9735729</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4345</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles S. Hobbs</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. J. Cooper, H. J. Smith, Lewis Dickerson, Robert Coates</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Problem in Lieu of Thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1962-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1962-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>