<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Microstructure and Creep Deformation Behavior of a Hierarchical-Precipitate-Strengthened Ferritic Alloy with Extreme Creep Resistance</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gsong1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennesse - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Song</lname>
<fname>Gian</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Ferritic steels</keyword>
<keyword>Hierarchical alloys</keyword>
<keyword>Heusler phase</keyword>
<keyword>Precipitation hardening</keyword>
<keyword>Creep properties</keyword>
<keyword>Neutron diffraction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Metallurgy</discipline>
<discipline>Structural Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Hierarchical NiAl [nickel-aluminium compound]/Ni&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiAl [nickel-titanium-aluminum compound] or single Ni&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiAl-precipitate-strengthened ferritic alloys have been developed by adding 2 or 4 weight percent [wt. %] of Ti [titanium] into a previously-studied NiAl-precipitate-strengthened ferritic alloy. A systematic investigation has been conducted to study the interrelationships among the composition, microstructure, and mechanical behavior, and provide insight into deformation micro-mechanisms at elevated temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The microstructural attributes of hierarchical or single precipitates are investigated in the Ti-containing ferritic alloys. Transmission-electron microscopy in conjunction with the atom-probe tomography is employed to characterize the detailed precipitate structure. It is observed that the 2-wt.-%-Ti alloy is reinforced by a two-phase NiAl/Ni&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiAl precipitate, which is coherently distributed in the Fe [iron] matrix, whereas the 4-wt.-%-Ti alloy consists of a semi-coherent single Ni&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;TiAl precipitate. The creep resistance of the 2-wt.-%-Ti alloy is significantly improved than the NiAl-strengthened ferritic alloy without the Ti addition and greater than the 4-wt.-%-Ti alloy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The microstructural evolution of precipitates during heat treatment at 973 K is investigated in the 2-and 4-wt.-%-Ti alloys. Transmission-electron microscopy and atom-probe tomography are used to study the precipitate evolution, such as the size, morphology, composition of the precipitates. It reveals that the hierarchical structure within the precipitate of the 2-wt.-%-Ti alloy evolves from the fine two-phase-coupled to agglomerated coarse structures, as the aging time increases. Moreover, the transition from the coherency to semi-coherency is concomitant with that of hierarchical structure within the precipitate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-situ neutron-diffraction experiments during tensile and creep deformations reveal the interphase load-sharing mechanisms during plastic deformation at 973 K. The evolution of lattice strains during high-temperature deformation is further verified by crystal-plasticity finite-element simulations. In-situ neutron-diffraction experiments during stress relaxation at 973 K exhibits the load, which is transferred from the matrix to precipitate is relaxed, which indicate the occurrence of the diffusional flow along the matrix/precipitate interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results could provide a new alloy-design strategy, accelerate the advance in the development of creep-resistant alloys, and broaden the applications of ferritic alloys to higher temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3666</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5081&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3666</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5081</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-12-15T06:56:48-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7946916</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3666</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Yanfei Gao, Hahn Choo, Hairong Qi</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>