<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Avian Ecology During Oak Savanna and Woodland Restoration in the Mid-South</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>chende25@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Henderson</lname>
<fname>Christine</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>avian</keyword>
<keyword>savanna</keyword>
<keyword>fire</keyword>
<keyword>nest</keyword>
<keyword>abundance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Natural Resources and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Natural Resources Management and Policy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Disturbance-dependent ecosystems in the eastern United States have been declining since European settlement, and, in recent years, early-successional species have followed. My objective for this research was to determine if oak savanna and woodland restoration (i.e., overstory thinning and prescribed fire) was a viable method of recovering declining earlysuccessional species to the landscape of the Mid-South. At 3 sites, Catoosa Wildlife Management Area (CWMA; Tennessee), Green River Game Lands (GRGL; North Carolina), and Land Between the Lakes National Recreation Area (LBL; Tennessee), oak savanna and woodland restoration projects were established and maintained. Closed-canopy stands were thinned and a 2-year burn schedule was implemented. In Chapter One, I present on nest- and stand-level vegetation metrics associated with Prairie Warbler (&lt;em&gt;Setophaga discolor&lt;/em&gt;) nest survival and nest-site selection at CWMA 7 years after canopy disturbance and consistent burning. In 2015 and 2016, Prairie Warblers had average nest success (0.937 ± 0.007) compared with other studies and selected for increased herbaceous groundcover around the nest compared with available habitat. Nest survival in 2015 was lower than in 2016. A positive trend between groundcover and nest survival was found. In Chapter Two, I describe nest- and stand-level vegetation metrics associated with Red-headed Woodpecker (&lt;em&gt;Melanerpes erythrocephalus&lt;/em&gt;) nest survival and nest-site selection at CWMA 7 years after canopy disturbance and consistent burning. Red-headed Woodpeckers had very high nest success (84.1%) compared with other studies and selected nest sites with greater herbaceous groundcover, dead basal area, and midstory density (in 2016) compared with available habitat. A negative trend was found between nest survival and live basal area. In Chapter Three, I describe vegetation metrics (herbaceous groundcover, live and dead basal area, and midstory density) influencing 28 bird species’ abundances at CWMA, GRGL, and LBL 2010–2012 and 2014–2016. Moderate to high amounts of disturbance were associated with increased populations of early-successional species while low to moderate amounts of disturbance either did not affect or were positively associated with populations of most mature forest species. Oak savanna and woodland restoration is a viable method to increase populations of early-successional bird species while retaining most mature forest species.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4948</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6179&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4948</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6179</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-08T10:51:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10269275</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4948</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Patrick Keyser</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Buehler, Joseph Clark, Emma Willcox</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>