<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Structure function studies of Sml1, an inhibitor of DNA : synthesis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Dice</lname>
<fname>Lezlee</fname>
<mname>Turner</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Smll is a protein found in yeast that is implicated in regulating ribonucleotide reductase (RNR) and is a member of the Rad53/Mecl cell cycle checkpoint pathway. RNR catalyzes the reduction of ribonucleotides to deoxyribonucleotides. This action is the ratelimiting step of DNA precursor synthesis. 5ml 1 has been shown in other studies to bind to Rnrl, of yeast, thereby inhibiting the reduction activity when DNA synthesis is not required (Zhao, X., Mueller, EGO., and Rothstein, R. ( 1998)). The project presented here utilizes recombinant, truncated mutant forms of Smll and site-directed mutants to investigate the oligomerization and phosphorylation of Smll. Wild type Smll has been truncated by 8, 20, and 38 amino acids, omitting the N-terminal region, which is not thought to interact with Rnrl. These mutants have been used to investigate the oligomeric state of Smll by size-exclusion chromatography and sedimentation equilibrium analytical ultracentrifugation. To characterize phosphorylation of 5ml 1 several serines have been mutated to alanines and a glutamic acid was mutated to a glutamine. The results from these studies have led to the identification of the phosphorylation sites and the key recognition residues of Smll necessary for Dunl kinase activity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5214</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6622&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5214</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6622</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847055</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5214</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Chris Dealwis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>