<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Flexible work arrangements in the United States : a historical analysis applying a systems model</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Brickey</lname>
<fname>Janis</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of flexible work arrangements, flextime, was investigated applying historical research methods. A systems approach integrated elements of Schuler and Jackson’s (1996) Human Resource Management (HRM) model and Bronfenbrenner’s (1979) human development model. The literature on the models provided guidance to the development of the research variables: national systems, work systems, family systems, and individual systems. The time frame, between 1970 and 1999, was determined by the initial review as to the start of flextime in the United States. Literature analysis focused on HRM journals and Monthly Labor Review published during the time frame. Flextime title counts (frequency counts) were conducted for each of the decades from the literature reviews. Other secondary data included Consumer Price Index, Current Population Survey data and Census Bureau data on population age distribution, employment data, household composition and income, educational levels, and life expectancy. Primary data were collected from individuals who were the median age of working Americans in 1975, 1985, and 1995. Each decade, 19705, 19805, and 19905, was analyzed through the primary and secondary data and the information was collapsed into a final model. Findings indicated that the use of flextime may not be as prevalent as the literature suggested. Many of the reports were by human resources and managers on the availability of flextime with other options. The role of management or supervisors in the discretion was discussed throughout the literature.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6205</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8157&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6205</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8157</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450293</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6205</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Randal Pierce, James D. Moran III</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>