<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Epidemiology of select species of filarial nematodes in free-ranging moose (&lt;i&gt;Alces alces&lt;/i&gt;) of North America</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cgrunenw@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grunenwald</lname>
<fname>Caroline</fname>
<mname>Mae</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>parasitic nematodes</keyword>
<keyword>Alces alces</keyword>
<keyword>parasitic diseases of wild mammals</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Other Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;North American moose (&lt;em&gt;Alces alces&lt;/em&gt;) are a culturally and economically valued species. Recent population declines raise concern for the survivability of this natural resource. The Minnesota population has experienced the most dramatic decline, with a 60% loss in total numbers since 2006. Nematode parasites, particularly some species of filarids, are important pathogens of moose and could be contributing to morbidity and mortality. This study investigates the eco-epidemiology of two filarial parasites of moose: &lt;em&gt;Rumenfilaria andersoni&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Elaeophora schneideri. &lt;/em&gt;By surveying cervid species from six U.S. states, we discovered &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni &lt;/em&gt;was present in moose from all sample locations with prevalence varying between 20-40%. This suggests &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni &lt;/em&gt;is distributed throughout North America. We also observed &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni &lt;/em&gt;in white-tailed deer (&lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) but not elk (&lt;em&gt;Cervus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;) or caribou (&lt;em&gt;Rangifer tardanus&lt;/em&gt;). Sequence analysis of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; suggested the existence of two distinct clades. Molecular screening of Minnesota tabanid flies discovered 1.5% harbored &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt;, with only &lt;em&gt;Chrysops&lt;/em&gt; spp. deerflies containing &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni &lt;/em&gt;DNA. This is the first report of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni &lt;/em&gt;in moose and white-tailed deer herds within the contiguous U.S. and the first time horseflies have been implicated as the vector. Molecular surveys for parasitic nematodes in brain tissues from Minnesota moose that died from unknown causes revealed 63% produced 18S sequences closely aligning with &lt;em&gt;E. schneideri&lt;/em&gt;, a neurological pathogen of moose previously unreported in Minnesota. Molecular screening of Minnesota tabanid flies revealed &lt;em&gt;E. schneideri &lt;/em&gt;was present in the environment and transmission could occur locally. Prevalence ranged between 0-100% per trapping site, with &lt;em&gt;Chrysops&lt;/em&gt; spp. and &lt;em&gt;Hybomitra&lt;/em&gt; spp. horseflies implicated as vectors. This is the first report of &lt;em&gt;Chrysops &lt;/em&gt;spp. serving as a carrier of &lt;em&gt;E. schneideri &lt;/em&gt;and the first report of &lt;em&gt;E. schneideri &lt;/em&gt;in Minnesota, suggesting &lt;em&gt;E. schneideri &lt;/em&gt;is an emerging pathogen in the Minnesota herd&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Together these data demonstrate the presence of multiple parasitic nematode species in vulnerable moose populations, yet it is still unclear what the implications are for herd health. Further research is warranted to determine if a link between nematode infections and declining moose populations exists.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3582</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5035&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3582</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5035</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-09T13:56:59-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7702163</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3582</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Chunlei Su</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Gerhold, Lisa Muller, Elizabeth Fozo, Todd Reynolds</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>