<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Information-seeking Behavior of Social Sciences and Humanities Researchers in the Internet Age</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ge</lname>
<fname>Xuemei</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study focuses on how Internet technology influences and contributes to the information-seeking process in the social sciences and humanities. The study examines the information-seeking behavior of faculty and doctoral students in these fields and observes and extends Ellis’s model of information-seeking behavior for social scientists, which includes six characteristics: &lt;em&gt;starting, chaining, browsing, differentiating, monitoring, and extracting. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted at Tennessee State University. Thirty active social sciences and humanities faculty and doctoral students were interviewed about their use of Internet resources, their perception of electronic and print materials, and their opinions concerning the Ellis model and how it might be applicable to them. The research confirmed all&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;the continuing relevance of all characteristics of the Ellis model, and theorized that an extended model could potentially include two additional characteristics: &lt;em&gt;preparation and planning&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;information management&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the interview results, the researcher provides suggestions on how current information services and products can be improved to better serve social sciences and humanities researchers, discusses the implications of these new characteristics for information-searching needs, and makes recommendations for improving library services and technologies that will meet the needs of future social sciences and humanities scholars.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1899</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3256&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1899</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3256</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-20T11:26:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4609222</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1899</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peiling Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carol Tenopir, Kendra Albright</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Information Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>