<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>“Why are College Foreign Language Students’ Self-efficacy, Attitude, and Motivation so Different?”</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>utktrace@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Texas at San Antonio</institution>
<lname>Hsieh</lname>
<fname>Pei-Hsuan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>International Education</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Self-efficacy</keyword>
<keyword>Modern language students</keyword>
<keyword>Achievement motivation</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Simply taking foreign language courses and being exposed to the language does not guarantee successful and positive learning experiences. When examining factors that influence foreign language learning, motivation should be considered. To extend current foreign language literature, this study integrated self-efficacy and Gardners&#39; AMTB variables to the understanding of learner motivation and achievement. Participants were 249 undergraduate students learning Spanish, German, and French. Regression results suggested that self-efficacy, positive attitude, and anxiety were good predictors of language achievement. MANOVA results revealed that students&#39; motivation levels differed significantly based on the following student differences: 1) group status (successful or unsuccessful test results), 2) self-efficacy, and 3) heritage connection to the language they were taking. The study provides interpretations and implications of the findings. The magazine publisher is the copyright holder of this article and it is reproduced with permission. Further reproduction of this article in violation of the copyright is prohibited.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol38/iss1/11</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1155&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1155</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-12T14:14:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>1391366</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol38/iss1/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>College Foreign Students</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>