<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Use of Sugar Substitutes and Dietary Habits of Pregnant Adolescents in East Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Valdrighi</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Information was collected from 34 pregnant adolescents between the ages of 13 and 18 to determine whether consumption of sugar substituted products is a component of their food practices. The concern has been raised that use of sugar-substituted products by pregnant women may lower kilocaloric intake below recommended energy levels resulting in low weight gains. Low maternal weight gain in has been correlated to poor pregnancy outcome. Establishing current usage rates and evaluating the relationship between use of sugar substituted products and overall dietary adequacy was a secondary purpose of this study. Both quality of diet and quantity of nutrients may be negatively influenced by the use of sugar substitutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants were interviewed by the primary investigator about demographic and socioeconomic information, nutrition and health practices, and nutrition attitudes, particularly towards their use of sugar-substituted products. Self-reported dietary records and one 24-hour food recall were completed also by&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-third of the participants indicated they used sugar substituted foods in their last month of pregnancy. However, reported frequency of use was less than once a week. Therefore, no current usage rates or correlations between use of sugar-substituted products and dietary adequacy could be established. Although 37% of the mothers younger than 18 were classified as underweight at conception, sugar-substituted products were not used as a means to limit energy Intake. Peer influence did not seem to play a role in a participant&#39;s use of sugar-substituted products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An examination of participants&#39; obstetrical data revealed that mean maternal weight gain averaged 39. 2 pounds with a range of 1.25 to 65.25 pounds. Although the mean amount is higher than the acceptable weight gain range for all pregnant women (25-30 pounds), it may have been beneficial as only one infant weighed less than 5.5 pounds. The mean dietary intakes of this group were adequate except for calcium and iron. The mean intakes were &gt; 100% of the Recommended Dietary Allowances (RDA) for protein, vitamin A, thiamin, niacin, riboflavin, ascorbic acid, and phosphorus, 94% of the RDA for energy, and &lt; 80% of the RDA for calcium and iron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, results indicate that use of sugar-substituted products was not a component of pregnant adolescents&#39; food practices in this study. Therefore, the assumption that pregnant teens may use a significant amount of sugar substitutes as a means to limit their energy intake was not supported. In addition, the mean energy intake for the group was 94% of the RDA. In regard to weight gain, 51.5% of the teens gained more than 40 pounds compared to 12.1 % who gained less than 25 pounds. These findings could be interpreted that pregnant teenagers may not be as concerned with maintaining &quot;ideal&quot; body images or hiding their pregnant state as was suggested in the literature. Therefore, sugar-substituted products would not play a major role in the diets of pregnant adolescents.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4096</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5495&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4096</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5495</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-27T12:13:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9202995</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4096</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Betty Ruth Carruth</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jean D. Skinner, Edward T. Howley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>