<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Les auteures surréalistes : French and Francophone Women Surrealist Writers -- Joyce Mansour, Valentine Penrose and Gisèle Prassinos</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mdunwood@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dunwoody</lname>
<fname>Maitland</fname>
<mname>Sierra</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>surrealism</keyword>
<keyword>authorship</keyword>
<keyword>women</keyword>
<keyword>writers</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>French and Francophone Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Other Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The notion of the “author” and the purpose of its existence have been the subject of many contemporary debates, with Roland Barthes and Michel Foucault as key. For Barthes, language defines a literary work and the author is relegated to a minor place. And he believes that certain movements, surrealism as an example, effectively aided in the “death” of the author. Though that may sometimes be the case, within the movement of surrealism the author and their language are of almost equal importance – which differs entirely from Barthes’ view considering his notions on the surrealist movement and authorship. In addressing the validity of Barthes’ and Foucault’s views regarding the author, this work reveals the importance of the author for marginalized groups, specifically women surrealists. In looking at how researchers and critics regarded the works of Joyce Mansour, Valentine Penrose and Gisèle Prassinos, this work shows the importance of authorship for surrealist women. Additionally, their relationships with their male counterparts and each other are explored. Together, they show how the knowledge of their authorial presence furthers the understanding of their work and how the very nature of the surrealist movement hindered their recognition. Authorship creates a space for these women’s voices to be heard. This work posits that the author cannot be dead, as it enables women surrealists to assert their agency over their works – separate from their male counterparts who dominated the surrealist movement.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4734</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5760&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4734</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5760</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-21T05:44:15-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9721462</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4734</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Romeiser</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Benjamin Lee, Chris Holmlund</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>French</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>