<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius: Population Genetics and Antimicrobial Resistance</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rvidela@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Videla</lname>
<fname>Ricardo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</keyword>
<keyword>Staphylococcus population genetics</keyword>
<keyword>Staphylococcus antimicrobial resistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Microbiology and Immunobiology</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; is a Gram-positive coagulase-negative coccus. It is a normal inhabitant of the skin of dogs. However, clinical disease can be observed in animals that are immunossuppressed or if the skin barrier is altered. This bacterium is recognized as the main cause of canine pyoderma and has also been associated with other conditions such as infection of the urinary tract, the ears, and surgical wounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methicillin resistance and resistance to other antimicrobials regularly used by veterinarians is common among &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; which can complicate treatment. The first report of &lt;em&gt;mecA&lt;/em&gt;, gene responsible for methicillin resistance, in &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; is from 1999. Since then, resistance to methicillin and to other antimicrobials has become increasingly more common, making this bacterium a possible reservoir for antimicrobial resistance genes. The reason for the increase in the presence of antimicrobial resistance among &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; is still not well understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research focuses on characterization of &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; isolates from the United States in order to determine their genetic diversity, antimicrobial susceptibility profiles, and possible relationships among the two. A description of the genetically related populations that are present in the country may help in the understanding of the mechanisms of expansion of this microorganism. Also, the availability of more current information on the susceptibility to antimicrobials should help in the reestablishment of the consequences of misusage of antimicrobials and highlights the need for the development of novel treatment alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1694</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2573&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1694</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2573</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-02T06:47:32-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2573/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3559574</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1694</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stephen, A. Kania</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David A. Bemis, Cristina Lanzas, Karla J. Matteson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>