<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Robust-Adaptive Magnetic Bearing Control of Flexible Matrix Composite Rotorcraft Driveline</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hdesmidt@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>DeSmidt</lname>
<fname>Hans</fname>
<mname>August</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kwwang@umich.edu</email>
<institution>University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Kon-Well</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ecs5@engr.psu.edu</email>
<institution>The Pennsylvania State University</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Edward</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Magnetic Bearings</keyword>
<keyword>Composite Shafts</keyword>
<keyword>Adaptive Vibration Control</keyword>
<keyword>Whirl Instability</keyword>
<keyword>Supercritical Driveline</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Acoustics, Dynamics, and Controls</discipline>
<discipline>Propulsion and Power</discipline>
<discipline>Structures and Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Recent studies demonstrate that a key advantage of Flexible Matrix Composite (FMC) shaft technology is the ability to accommodate misalignments without need for segmenting or flexible couplings as required by conventional alloy and graphite/epoxy composite shafts. While this is indeed a very promising technology for rotorcraft driveshafts, the high damping loss-factor and thermal stiffness and damping sensitivities of the urethane matrix, makes FMC shafting more prone to self-heating and whirl instabilities. Furthermore, the relatively low bending stiffness and critical speeds of FMC shafts makes imbalance vibration a significant challenge to supercritical operation. To address these issues and advance the state-of-the-art, this research explores Active Magnetic Bearing (AMB) technology together with a robust-adaptive hybrid H&amp;#; feedback/Synchronous Adaptive Vibration Control law designed to ensure stable supercritical operation of a prototype FMC rotorcraft driveline. The effectiveness of the proposed new approach is demonstrated through analysis of a helicopter driveline testbed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mechpubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1002&amp;amp;context=utk_mechpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-22T13:43:21-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Mechanical, Aerospace and Biomedical Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>1119691</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mechpubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>DeSmidt, H.A., Wang K.W. and Smith, E.C., ”Robust-Adaptive Magnetic Bearing Control of Flexible Matrix Composite Rotorcraft Driveline,” Journal of the American Helicopter Society,  Vol. 53, No. 2, pp. 115-124., 2008.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-22T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>