<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extended Warranties, The Great Lie: Why The King Has No Clothes</title>
<publication-date>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Bentley University</institution>
<lname>Missirian</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper examines how states have effectively eviscerated consumer protections in consumer product purchases all while under the guise of allegedly adding more consumer protection. The state and federal governments have sacrificed the consumer in the name of economic profit and economic revival by selling the consumer into economic slavery. Businesses are allowed to prod and encourage the consumer to purchase a diverse range of products through a barrage of advertising. Consumers are told that they can gain an added peace of mind, comfort, and security in the use of these products by purchasing extended warranties and service plans. What they are not told is that the legislature has allowed and encouraged many businesses to sell this added protection without providing the consumer anything of substance. Apparently, it is now legally and commercially acceptable to stand behind your product just as long as that does not mean expending any money. &lt;em&gt;Caveat emptor&lt;/em&gt; is not dead but alive in a different suit.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/transactions/vol17/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1355&amp;amp;context=transactions&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1355</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-12-17T11:35:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Transactions:  The Tennessee Journal of Business Law</publication-title>
<context-key>7957450</context-key>
<submission-path>transactions/vol17/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-17T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>