<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Young Adult Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender and Questioning Non-Fiction Collections (LGBTQ) and Countywide Anti-Discrimination Policies.</title>
<publication-date>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>atinyk@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>stringer-stanback</lname>
<fname>kynita</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Public Libraries, Collection Development, Evaluation, Young Adults’ Literature, Gay Literature</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Public Libraries</keyword>
<keyword>Collection Development</keyword>
<keyword>Evaluation</keyword>
<keyword>Young Adults’ Literature</keyword>
<keyword>Gay Literature</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examines news articles and anti-discrimination ordinances that affect Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Trans, &amp; Questioning (LGBTQ) communities in the four largest counties from five Southeastern States: Florida, Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina and Virginia. The possible impact of such policies on the collection of non-fiction young adult materials in the public libraries in those counties is explored.  The holdings of each county are compared to a list of 23 titles compiled from literary award winners selected from the time period 1996-2003 using the Lambda Literary Foundation Awards, the American Library Association Stonewall Awards, and an American Library Association GLBT Roundtable Bibliography. Findings suggest that there is no relationship between anti-discrimination ordinances and the level of collecting LGBTQ material.  Collections in the largest cities were apt to follow American Library Association guidelines for non-discriminatory collection development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/30</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1029&amp;amp;context=utk_libfpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>30</label>
<document-type>unpublished_paper</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1029</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-03T06:51:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Other Library Publications and Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1216852</context-key>
<withdrawn>2011-08-12</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_libfpubs/30</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://ils.unc.edu/MSpapers/3528.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>