<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sexual Dimorphism in Modern Black and White Cranial Vault Thickness: A Forensic Application for Sexual Discrimination</title>
<publication-date>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fuller</lname>
<fname>Butler</fname>
<suffix>IV</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In forensic anthropology, the emphasis in research lies within the continual pursuit of the best methods for human identification through analysis of the skeletal remains available. Most of the methods developed by researchers both past and present have utilized the various skeletal collections curated at museums and universities throughout the country in order to try and deduce patterns and trends visible in the osseus record of human existence. Here, 126 specimens from the University of Tennessee (U.T.) William M. Bass Collection (n=31) and Terry Collections (n=95) are analyzed, to determine the level of sexual dimorphism present in the thickness of the cranial vault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurement of the specimens was carried out using instruments developed by both the researcher and the University of Tennessee College of Engineering. The findings from these measurements have yielded information which may be useful in human identification, specifically sex assignment of unknown individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings indicate a significant difference between males and females at many of the fifteen points measured on the skulls with females predominating in thickness in the more anterior portions of the skull (frontal and parietal bones) and males dominating in thickness in the more posterior portions of the skull (occipital and cranial base). The effects of race and age, on cranial thickness, are not significant in this sample as shown through statistical analysis. Membership in collection was also analyzed and the results showed that Terry members had thicker cranial vaults than the more modern U.T. specimens, with the exception of the posterior measurements on the occipital. Finally, methods of reduction of the number of points needed to discriminate between the sexes are also pursued and the points of the frontal and parietal bones found to be the most informative in deducing sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is shown that this method correctly discriminated nearly 70% of the material in the sample, yet the applications of this particular method of discrimination may be limited in that autopsied skulls, allowing for full access to the fifteen points measured, are essential. To recalibrate the method to fit fewer points, the original data set would be required and a new discrimination model would need to be constructed based upon the new parameters. Given this limitation, this method may prove more useful in sexing museum specimens or individuals in a curated study collection as opposed to specimens from the field. Further research into a more field-based method of cortical thickness discrimination is suggested and may be pursued further.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4127</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5578&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4127</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5578</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-18T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9281372</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4127</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Jantz, Lyle Konigsberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>