<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Martha’s (and Steve’s) Good Faith: An Officer’s Duty of Loyalty at the Intersection of Good Faith and Candor</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>officer</keyword>
<keyword>executive</keyword>
<keyword>good faith</keyword>
<keyword>candor</keyword>
<keyword>disclosure</keyword>
<keyword>loyalty</keyword>
<keyword>fiduciary duty</keyword>
<keyword>personal facts</keyword>
<keyword>privacy</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agency</discipline>
<discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Ethics and Professional Responsibility</discipline>
<discipline>Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  short paper begins to explore whether a corporate officer’s duty of good  faith extends to public disclosures of personal facts. Specifically,  the paper preliminarily attacks the following question: in the post  Stone v. Ritter, post-Gantler v. Stephens era in which we now live, is  the absence or inadequacy of an executive officer’s disclosure of  personal facts a breach of the duty of good faith and, as a result, the  fiduciary duty of loyalty under Delaware law?  The answer to this  question is tied up in recent jurisprudence of the Delaware Supreme  Court at the intersection of the duty of good faith, the duty of  disclosure (or candor), and the applicability of fiduciary duties to  corporate officers.  Accordingly, in a preliminary analysis, this paper  first describes that jurisprudence and then applies it to executive  disclosures of personal facts.  The paper closes with a brief conclusion  that includes a cautionary note about the use of its findings in a  litigation setting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/19</coverpage-url>
<label>19</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1019</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T07:40:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035053</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/19</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Martha’s (and Steve’s) Good Faith: An Officer’s Duty of Loyalty at the Intersection of Good Faith and Candor (July 29, 2009). University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 71. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1440919</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1440919</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>