<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>HPV Vaccination Receptivity</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:53:42-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>katdscot@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>Katie</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The human papillomavirus (HPV) infection is a prevalent health concern for college students. The HPV vaccine has the power to significantly impact rates of infection. This study sought to understand how the strength of a provider’s recommendation for the HPV vaccine impacted perceived quality of medical care, as well as how PQMC impacted willingness to pursue vaccination. In a quantitative survey with a sample of 126 participants ages 18 to 26, a positive correlation was found between strength of recommendation and PQMC. A positive correlation was also found between PQMC and willingness to pursue vaccination. No difference was found between male and female participants in how they assessed strength of recommendation. The implications of this study suggest that providers who are more conscientious of the strength of their recommendation and invested in the way patients perceive the quality of their medical care might be more successful in getting patients to pursue vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/communicationinformation/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1139&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1139</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-17T09:13:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10027938</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/communicationinformation/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Michelle Violanti</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>