<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fail to prepare, prepare to fail boxers&#39; experiences of training for competition</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Simpson</lname>
<fname>Duncan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Education</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;One-on-one physical and mental competition involving the possibility of injury or even death makes combat sports good candidates for applied sport psychology interventions (Lane, 2008; Schinke, 2007). To date limited research has been conducted on the psychological demands of combat sports, particularly boxing. A few studies (Lane 2006; 2008; in press; Schinke, 2004, 2007) have focused on the researchers&#39;/practitioners&#39; perspective on the world of boxing, but they have failed to discuss the experiences of the participants&#39; themselves. Some scholars in sport psychology have called for studies that &#39;give a voice&#39; to marginalized or neglected groups (Fisher, Butryn, &amp; Roper, 2003; Ryba, 2005; Ryba &amp; Kashope-Wright, 2005; Schinke et al. 2006). As a group, boxers are among the least researched athletes within the sport psychology literature. Therefore, the primary purpose of this study was to explore boxer&#39;s experiences of training for competition.To accomplish this purpose phenomenological interviews were conducted with nine professional boxers ranging in age from 22 to 42 years. Each participant was asked to respond to the following open-ended question: &quot;When you think of your experience of training for competition, what stands out for you?&quot; All interviews were audio-recorded and transcribed verbatim. Qualitative analysis of the transcripts revealed a total of 341 meaning units, which were further grouped into sub-themes and general themes. A final thematic structure revealed six major dimensions that characterized these boxers&#39; experiences of training for competition: Achieving Potential, Preparing, Sacrificing, Finding Support, Fearing and Loving/Hating. The current study found a substantial amount of new findings not previously discussed in research. For example, Achieving Potential was central to their experiences. They feared of losing and letting themselves and others down.Boxers had both strong positive and negative feelings towards their sport. Gym partners provided advice, bonded and provided fun and humor and yet, were needed for rivalry and competition. Lastly, the boxers wanted to know that their trainers ultimately cared about their health above all else. The results from this study offer several practical implications for trainers, boxers and sport psychology practitioners wishing to enhance the quality of the training experience for its participants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5999</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7932&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5999</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7932</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467664</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5999</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Craig A. Wrisberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>