<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Field Experience in Public Health Nutrition in Florida</title>
<publication-date>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Venable</lname>
<fname>Wanda</fname>
<mname>Meers</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis describes and analyzes the observations and experiences of the student nutritionist during eight weeks of field training with the Nutrition Section in the Division of the Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services. Supervision was provided by public health nutritionists in Jacksonville at the state level, in the region around Tallahassee, and in Escambia County. The field experience was planned to supplement the student&#39;s academic training. In addition, an opportunity was provided for the student to assess the role of nutrition in public health by participation in public health programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information was obtained on the history, organization, and programs of the Division of Health through conferences, selected readings, and observations. The student observed or took part in a variety of program activities at the state, regional, and local levels, contrasting the duties of the nutritionist at each level. The student observed nutritionists planning, coordinating, implementing, and evaluating programs, with professional and nonprofessional persons representing various agencies. Teaching and counseling patients strengthened professional skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participation in these program activities increased the student&#39;s confidence in her ability to apply her academic knowledge. Such participation was helpful in developing the professional attitudes and skills necessary for a public health nutritionist.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3850</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5330&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3850</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5330</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-12T12:29:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8969370</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3850</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William H. Oliver, Mary Jo Hitchcock</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>