<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of a glycosyphosphatidylinositol anchor transamidase in Arabidopsis thaliana and the function of GPI anchored proteins in stomatal development</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mbundy1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Bundy</lname>
<fname>Mark Gerald Ronald</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Stomata</keyword>
<keyword>GPI-anchor</keyword>
<keyword>TMM</keyword>
<keyword>ERECTA signalling pathway</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Developmental Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In plants stomata play a vital role for survival by allowing the gas exchange of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; [carbon dioxide] and water vapor to occur. A stoma is a central pore flanked by two kidney shaped guard cells and in wild type there is at least one pavement cell between each stoma. The &lt;em&gt;ERECTA&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(ER)&lt;/em&gt; gene family consisting of &lt;em&gt;ER, ERL1, ERL2&lt;/em&gt; is involved in regulation of stomata development, where a triple mutant of &lt;em&gt;er erl1 erl2&lt;/em&gt; displays an increased stomata index and clusters of stomata that disobey the one cell spacing rule. To better understand the pathway of stomata development, we performed an ethyl&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;methanesulfonate (EMS) screen in an enhancer &lt;em&gt;erl1 erl2 &lt;/em&gt;background and looked for mutants with stomata clustering. A mutant with a strong stomata clustering phenotype was found and through map-based cloning the gene was identified as At1g08750 (renamed &lt;em&gt;AtGPI8&lt;/em&gt;), a putative glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchor (GPI) transamidase (GPI-T). In mammals and yeast the GPI-T is responsible for the cleaving of the C-terminal end of a protein and the attachment of the GPI anchor. Here we report the characterization of the partially functional &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-1&lt;/em&gt; and the lethal knockout &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-2&lt;/em&gt;. We demonstrate how GPI anchored proteins (GPI-APs) play a role in fertility, growth, plasmodesmata permeability and stomata development. Furthermore, we investigate the involvement of a GPI-AP in the stomata development pathway. Genetic interactions have determined that the &lt;em&gt;er &lt;/em&gt;family acts synergistically with &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-1&lt;/em&gt;. A gain of function mutant of YDA has epistasis over &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-1&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Tmm&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-1&lt;/em&gt; share similar phenotypes in leaves but &lt;em&gt;tmm&lt;/em&gt; is epistatic over &lt;em&gt;atgpi8-1&lt;/em&gt; in stems. These results indicated that a GPI-AP protein functions upstream of YDA, and either downstream of or in concurrence with the ER family and TMM. Sequence analysis suggests that TMM could potentially be a GPI-AP in the stomata development pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2395</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2913&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2395</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2913</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-24T14:53:47-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2913/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4255591</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2395</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Elena Shpak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brad Binder, Albrecht Von Arnim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>