<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Seeing the World Differently: An Analysis of the Impact of a Sport-Related Study Abroad Program on Global Mindedness</title>
<publication-date>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>LeCrom</lname>
<fname>Carrie</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Greenhalgh</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Dwyer</lname>
<fname>Brendan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>global minded</keyword>
<keyword>study abroad</keyword>
<keyword>cultural differences</keyword>
<keyword>sport management</keyword>
<keyword>global</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research was to determine whether there is a difference in  the global mindedness of students who have participated in sport-related study  abroad opportunities and those who have not. While a vast amount of research  exists on the impact of studying abroad in other fields, no research has been published  in the sport management field on how study abroad experiences impact students.  The current study surveyed alumni of a graduate program at a mid-Atlantic  university over a 12-year time frame. The course examined, offered once per year,  is a two-week trip to Western Europe that focuses on sport administration in that  region of the world. Surveys assessed the global mindedness of alumni, comparing  the results of alumni who had attended the trip to those who had not. Results  indicate that there were no statistically significant differences in global mindedness  between the two groups. When further broken down into the five dimensions  of the global mindedness scale, (responsibility, cultural pluralism, efficacy,  globalcentrism, and interconnectedness), the only factor in which the difference  between the two groups was statistically significant was cultural pluralism, indicating  that students who study abroad have higher levels of cultural pluralism  than those who do not.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jasm/vol7/iss2/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1324&amp;amp;context=jasm&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1324</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-08T09:06:18-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Journal of Applied Sport Management</publication-title>
<context-key>20479268</context-key>
<submission-path>jasm/vol7/iss2/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>