<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Misinformation and Your Health: An Exploration of Where we Find Information Culturally</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-22T12:06:10-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>brannen@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Brannen</lname>
<fname>Michelle</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Venable</lname>
<fname>Megan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mack</lname>
<fname>Thura</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Other</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A 2019 article in the American Journal of Preventive Medicine Misinformation as a Misunderstood Challenge to Public Health, scientists explore how health misinformation arises in media and social media, how health information impacts people, and opportunities to rethink how we navigate the health information landscape. The presenters will present key concepts from the research and then facilitate activity and discussion aimed at self-examination and reflection. This conversation will allow presenters to reflect and share about their personal experiences seeking health information and consider the cultural contexts that factor into this process with the goal of improving ability to evaluate health information resources.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2021/session2/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1258&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1258</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-14T11:11:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>21088295</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2021/session2/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Michelle Brannen is the Head of the Scholars’ Collaborative at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville Libraries. Michelle received her Master’s in Information Sciences from the University of Tennessee and has a degree in Music Education from Florida State University. Her research interests include learning styles and the creative process; how library services can impact and support learning; library assessment; and the intersections of civility and diversity in communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thura Mack is a professor in University Libraries at the University of Tennessee. As the Coordinator of Community Learning Services and Diversity Programs, she leads the Libraries’ outreach to schools in Knoxville and the surrounding community. Community Learning Services teaches information literacy and library research skills to university-bound students in programs such as UT’s College Access and Persistence Services (CAPS) and Project GRAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Megan Venable is special events coordinator for the University of Tennessee, Knoxville Libraries. A Knoxville native, Megan earned her BS (broadcasting) from UTK in 1996. She returned to the university in 2005 as assistant to the director of development for the College of Communication and Information. During that time she began studying for her master&#39;s degree in communication studies, which she received in 2007. She is a past president of the Knoxville Nativity Pageant and former volunteer at the Humane Society of Sarasota County, Fla. In her spare time, she enjoys writing for VIP Knoxville, a social magazine for the city.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;UT Libraries Public Health Libguide &lt;a href=&quot;https://libguides.utk.edu/public_health&quot;&gt;https://libguides.utk.edu/public_health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southwell, N. (2019). Misinformation as a Misunderstood Challenge to Public Health. &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Preventive Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;57&lt;/em&gt;(2), 282–285. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2019.03.009&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Breakout Rooms</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will learn about the impact of health misinformation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will reflect on their health information practices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will gain insight into evaluating health information resources&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Evaluating health information is a critical skill for everyone. With a complex and overloaded information landscape, many people are overwhelmed when it comes to finding trustworthy health information. Our presentation is tied to health education and media culture in that participants will gain knowledge of misinformation issues and will be able to reflect on their personal practices.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>