<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Improved feed protein fractionation schemes for formulating rations with the Cornell Net Carbohydrate and Protein System</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>clanzas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Cornell</institution>
<lname>Lanzas</lname>
<fname>Cristina</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Broderick</lname>
<fname>G</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Fox</lname>
<fname>D</fname>
<mname>G</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Animal Nutrition</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Disease Modeling</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Adequate predictions of rumen-degradable protein (RDP) and rumen-undegradable protein (RUP) supplies are necessary to optimize performance while minimizing losses of excess nitrogen (N). The objectives of this study were to evaluate the original Cornell Net Carbohydrate Protein System (CNCPS) protein fractionation scheme and to develop and evaluate alternatives designed to improve its adequacy in predicting RDP and RUP. The CNCPS version 5 fractionates CP into 5 fractions based on solubility in protein precipitant agents, buffers, and detergent solutions: A represents the soluble nonprotein N, B1 is the soluble true protein, B2 represents protein with intermediate rates of degradation, B3 is the CP insoluble in neutral detergent solution but soluble in acid detergent solution, and C is the unavailable N. Model predictions were evaluated with studies that measured N flow data at the omasum. The N fractionation scheme in version 5 of the CNCPS explained 78% of the variation in RDP with a root mean square prediction error (RMSPE) of 275 g/d, and 51% of the RUP variation with RMSPE of 248 g/d. Neutral detergent insoluble CP flows were overpredicted with a mean bias of 128 g/d (40% of the observed mean). The greatest improvements in the accuracy of RDP and RUP predictions were obtained with the following 2 alternative schemes. Alternative 1 used the inhibitory in vitro system to measure the fractional rate of degradation for the insoluble protein fraction in which A = nonprotein N, B1 = true soluble protein, B2 = insoluble protein, C = unavailable protein (RDP: R(2) = 0.84 and RMSPE = 167 g/d; RUP: R(2) = 0.61 and RMSPE = 209 g/d), whereas alternative 2 redefined A and B1 fractions as the non-amino-N and amino-N in the soluble fraction respectively (RDP: R(2) = 0.79 with RMSPE = 195 g/d and RUP: R(2) = 0.54 with RMSPE = 225 g/d). We concluded that implementing alternative 1 or 2 will improve the accuracy of predicting RDP and RUP within the CNCPS framework.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>4881</fpage>
<lpage>4891</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/36</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1035&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>36</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1035</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-01T10:49:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2117193</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/36</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Journal of Dairy Science. Copyright American Dairy Science Association. Link to publisher version: http://www.journalofdairyscience.org/article/S0022-0302%2808%2970955-X/abstract</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Dairy Science</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>