<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Through a Glass Darkly: The State of the Campus from an LGBT Perspective July 2008</title>
<publication-date>2008-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hoemann@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hoemann</lname>
<fname>George</fname>
<mname>H</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>LGBT</keyword>
<keyword>Lesbian</keyword>
<keyword>Gay</keyword>
<keyword>Bisexual</keyword>
<keyword>and Transgender</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Gender and Sexuality</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, is not an island.  Rather, the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, co-exists with other institutions of higher learning and operates within the larger social and political context of early 21st century America.  To compete successfully for the highest quality faculty, students, staff and resources, the university must implement a vigorously inclusive policy of recruitment and retention.  Any university – but especially a university that has labored under nearly four decades of litigation to overcome its legacy of segregation and racial discrimination – also has a moral obligation to lead its constituent members as well as the larger community to the fullest possible understanding and manifestation of diversity and inclusion.  This report gauges the University of Tennessee, Knoxville’s, achievement of those allied  imperatives from the perspective of its lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender faculty, students and staff.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lgbtrepo/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_lgbtrepo&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-07-14T11:57:58-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_lgbtrepo/article/1000/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Commission for LGBT - Reports, Minutes, Events and Other Documents</publication-title>
<context-key>897207</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lgbtrepo/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2009-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>