<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Due Process and Equal Protection: A Constitutional Approach to Same-Sex Marriage</title>
<publication-date>2014-04-24T13:07:45-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Musselman</lname>
<fname>Ashley</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>same-sex</keyword>
<keyword>marriage</keyword>
<keyword>constitution</keyword>
<keyword>euqal protection</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;On July 6, 2006, the Court of Appeals of New York decided Hernandez v. Robles. At issue in that case was whether New York&#39;s Domestic Relations Law violated the Due Process Clause and the Equal Protection Clause of the New York constitution by limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples. The plaintiffs were members of forty-four same-marriage licenses in the State of New York. The case began as four separate lawsuits in which the plaintiffs sought a declaratory judgment against &quot;the license-issuing authorities of New York City, Albany, and Ithaca; the State Department of Health, which instructs local authorities about the issuance of marriage licenses; and the State itself,&quot; for refusing to issue marriage licenses to same-sex couples, while issuing licenses to opposite-sex couples. In the end, the Court of Appeals of New York held that &quot;the New York Constitution does not compel recognition of marriages between members of the same sex.&quot; The court emphasized that &quot;[w]hether such marriages should be recognized is a question to be addressed by the Legislature&quot; and not by the courts.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol5/iss1/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1079&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>policynotes</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1079</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-24T12:35:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5517770</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol5/iss1/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>A Constitutional Approach to Same-Sex Marriage</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>