<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of the Ability of Sevier County to Support its Schools</title>
<publication-date>1952-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Large</lname>
<fname>Dewey</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Purpose of the Study: The purpose of this study is to determine the ability of he people of Sevier County to support a program of education in its public schools. The available finances and possible sources of revenue for developing, maintaining and improving public education within the County will be investigated with the intention of clarifying the complete financial aspect of the educational situation. It is hoped that the report of findings in this study will be favorably accepted and used by the Quarterly Court and the Board of Education of Sevier County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The educational situation and financial conditions of the County will be shown with little attention to other county or city school systems. This writing will not be a detailed financial statement of debit and credit, and liabilities and assets, but will be an attempt to show, through a study of the existing financial conditions of Sevier County, the present ability to support and educational program and to perhaps determine ways of channeling that ability to more effectively meet the needs of the people in a total program of education.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3260</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4690&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3260</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4690</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-03-19T11:58:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6868885</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3260</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Orin B. Graff</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John W. Gilliland, Robert S. Fleming</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1952-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1952-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>