<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Retinoids synergized with insulin to induce Srebp-1c expression and activated its promoter via the two liver X receptor binding sites that mediate insulin action</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>R</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>W</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Y</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Zhang</lname>
<fname>Y</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Insulin</keyword>
<keyword>Metabolism</keyword>
<keyword>Primary hepatocytes</keyword>
<keyword>Retinoids</keyword>
<keyword>Srebp-1c expression</keyword>
<keyword>Retinoid X receptor</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We have reported that the rat liver lipophilic extract (LE) synergized  with insulin to induce Gck and Srebp-1c in primary rat hepatocytes.  After identification of retinol and retinal in LE, only their effects in  the absence or presence of insulin on Gck, but not that on Srebp-1c,  were investigated subsequently. The retinoid effects on the Srebp-1c  expression and the activation of its promoter were examined with  real-time PCR and reporter gene assays, respectively. In primary  hepatocytes, retinal and retinoic acid (RA) synergized with insulin to  induce Srebp-1c expression. This induction was followed by the elevation  of its target gene, fatty acid synthase. Activation of retinoid X  receptor, but not retinoic acid receptor, was responsible for the  induction of Srebp-1c expression. RA, but not retinal, also induced  Srebp-1c expression in a dose dependent manner in INS-1 cells. The RA  responsive elements in Srebp-1c promoter were determined as previously  identified two liver X receptor elements responsible for mediating  insulin action. We conclude that retinoids regulate hepatic Srebp-1c  expression through activation of retinoid X receptor. The RA- and  insulin-induced Srebp-1c expression converged at the same sites in its  promoter, indicating the roles of vitamin A in regulation of hepatic  gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/18</coverpage-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1018</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-05T07:14:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>2002546</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21316346</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>