<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Final Destination, Graduation: Increasing Retention Rates of African American Males Through Student-Faculty Interaction During Study Abroad</title>
<publication-date>2013-06-03T05:46:28-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lwilso59@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Leota Evett</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Bilingual, Multilingual, and Multicultural Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>International and Area Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; As many predominately White institutions continue to emphasize the importance of diversity and multiculturalism, the recruitment of African American students has increased.  However, many institutions struggle with retaining this particular student population to graduation, suggesting that they may require a different type of support to achieve degree completion.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extensive research shows that African American students who participate in leadership or educational enrichment experiences and establish faculty relationships are likely to demonstrate a greater satisfaction with their college experience.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study abroad offers a unique experiential learning environment that allows students to reinforce classroom knowledge, validate their career field, experience broader forms of diversity, and affirm their racial identity (Young, 2008).  Study abroad presents an opportunity for students to have a shared experienced with faculty in an intimate group setting, therefore enhancing their overall experience and increasing retention and graduation rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Discuss retention of African American students in higher education&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.&lt;strong&gt;  &lt;/strong&gt;Increase awareness surrounding benefits of study abroad to retention of African Americans and encourage faculty and staff to promote study abroad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Encourage students to consider studying abroad!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handout: &lt;/strong&gt;summary of presentation as well as Office of Programs Abroad and SOLD office contact information&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion questions to engage audience: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. How can student affairs professionals and faculty members increase the number of students of color who study abroad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.  What other initiatives can be used to engage students of color and encourage retention?&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2013/Session2/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1088&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1088</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-11T13:49:55-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1088/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3575715</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2013/Session2/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
<value>VCR/DVD/Monitor</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>