<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study to Evaluate the Suitability of a Centrifuge as a Dynamic Flight Simulator for F/A-18 Strike Fighter Mission Training</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rmmasica@mac.com</email>
<institution>UTSI</institution>
<lname>Masica</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>Michael</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Centrifuge-Based Flight Simulator</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to evaluate the suitability of using an existing 25-ft radius centrifuge as a dynamic flight simulator for “full mission” F/A-18 strike fighter mission training with respect to the representativeness of pilot-perceived motion and acceleration cues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology employed in this study consisted of analyzing F/A-18 mission tasks, collecting pilot opinion surveys of important sensory cues needed in simulator training, and conducting an analysis of human pilot perceptual problems caused by centrifuge motion constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study identified a number of issues indicating that a centrifuge-based flight simulator shows limited potential for use in “full mission” F/A-18 training scenarios.  Specifically, there is a fundamental mismatch between the 6 degree-of-freedom mission-representative acceleration environment experienced in the aircraft and the 3 degree-of-freedom acceleration environment the centrifuge is able to provide.  The centrifuge is not optimized for the typical acceleration environment experienced during F/A-18 missions and has significant limitations in “near one g” and “near zero g” flight conditions.  Additionally, the centrifuge causes a variety of undesired, unrealistic, and debilitating vestibular artifacts that are not consistent with what a pilot experiences in the aircraft when performing the same mission task, degrading the effectiveness of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its limited suitability as a “full mission” F/A-18 simulator, the centrifuge is an essential physiological training device, shows good potential as a part-task trainer for departure/spin training, and should continue to play a role in the F/A-18 training continuum.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/543</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>543</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1005</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-10-31T16:18:57-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1005/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1052192</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/543</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Ranaudo, Uwe P. Solies, Frank G. Collins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>