<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of novel optical imaging and therapeutic agents for the detection and treatment of bladder cancer.</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jbourn1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Bourn</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>Rose</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Bladder cancer</keyword>
<keyword>RTKIs</keyword>
<keyword>COX-2</keyword>
<keyword>targeted therapies response</keyword>
<keyword>optical imaging</keyword>
<keyword>fluorocoxib A</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Several types of cancer, including bladder cancer, overexpress multiple receptor tyrosine kinases (RTKs), such as the c-Kit receptor and platelet derived growth factor receptor (PDGFR). Inhibitors of RTKs (RTKIs) are therefore used as targeted treatment options for patients with cancers that overexpress RTKs. A challenge associated with targeted therapies is the activation of alternative pro-survival signaling pathways, such as the cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) pathway, resulting in drug resistance. Although COX-2 is over-expressed and promotes tumorigenesis in bladder cancer, it can be used as a biomarker for bladder cancer detection and treatment strategies.Conventional optical imaging technologies can detect advanced stages of bladder cancer; however, they have several limitations to detect early stages. Novel optical imaging agent, fluorocoxib A, is a rhodamine-conjugated analog of indomethacin, which selectively targets COX-2 expressing tissues. Fluorocoxib A can be used for the detection and monitoring of COX-2-expressing tumors during treatment.We evaluated the effects of RTKIs and COX inhibitors, alone and in combination, on human and canine bladder cancer cell lines &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt;. Despite inhibiting cellular proliferation and increasing apoptosis, tested RTKIs increased COX-2 expression. Co-treatment of RTKIs and COX inhibitors abrogated the RTKI-induced COX-2 expression, indicating co-treatment may be more effective than either treatment alone.To evaluate the ability of fluorocoxib A for the detection of bladder cancer in mice, we used the carcinogen (&lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-butyl-&lt;i&gt;N&lt;/i&gt;-4-hydroxybutyl nitrosamine, BBN) -induced bladder cancer mouse model that resembles human bladder cancer. The specific uptake of fluorocoxib A by the bladder tissues correlated with the progression of bladder carcinogenesis and increased COX-2 expression, in contrast to normal bladder urothelium where no fluorocoxib A uptake was detected.We also investigated the RTKI-induced upregulation of COX-2 by evaluating the effects of RTKIs &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt;. Treatment of K9TCC#5Lilly xenograft tumors with AB1010 and imatinib increased COX-2 levels in the tumors of treated mice compared to the control group. The specific uptake of fluorocoxib A correlated with the treatment-induced increased COX-2 expression.Our results suggest that fluorocoxib A is a valuable optical imaging agent that can be used for detecting and monitoring early responses to targeted therapies in patients diagnosed with COX-2-expressing bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5264</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6808&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5264</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6808</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T08:36:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>14342864</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5264</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Maria Cekanova</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Maitreyi Das, Robert Donnell, Katie Tolbert, Albrecht von Arnim</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Research article described in Chapter II is a slightly modified version of an article that was published in the Dove Press journal, Drug Design, Development, and Therapy, by Jennifer Bourn and Maria Cekanova in June 2018.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>