<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Experience of Place</title>
<publication-date>1995-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peacher</lname>
<fname>Rosemary</fname>
<mname>Kehoe</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate the human experience of place. A phenomenological approach was utilized employing an unstructured open-ended dialogical interview method. Twenty participants, including ten younger and older adults, were asked to describe places which were special to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interpretation of the interview transcripts revealed five themes descriptive of one&#39;s experience of place: Identity, Connection, Security, Possibilities, and Beauty/Awe. The experience of time was interwoven with all five themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of &lt;em&gt;Identity&lt;/em&gt; comprises the way in which a place can strengthen one&#39;s sense of self, provide continuity across the developmental life span, and trigger poignant memories from an earlier time in one&#39;s life. The loss of a special place was described as emotionally devastating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Connection&lt;/em&gt; to loved ones, some of whom may be deceased, as well as to something larger than oneself, such as a university or city, describes the second theme. Many participants expressed comfort at the recognition that a place may endure long after one&#39;s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Security&lt;/em&gt;, the third theme, embraces the ability of a place to provide a sense of permanence and tradition, ensure familiarity and safety, and to afford moments of relaxation, solitude, and brief escape from life&#39;s problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possibilities&lt;/em&gt; encompasses the way in which the participants experienced the environment as challenging their mental and physical abilities, stimulating their imagination, and enriching their opportunities for personal change and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beauty and Awe&lt;/em&gt;. the final theme, includes feelings of appreciation for the splendor of the earth, experiences of feeling alive, a sense of timelessness, and an awareness of a spiritual oneness with the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Present results were discussed in terms of their implications for clinical psychology, most notably the need to recognize the role of the non-human environment in providing stability, identity, and a sense of well-being. Theoretically, this emphasis suggests extending the conceptual meaning of &quot;object&quot; within the context of Object Relations Theory.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3003</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4500&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3003</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4500</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-30T11:05:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6308578</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3003</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leonard Handler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas L. Bell, Ronald E. Hopson, Howard R. Pollio</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1995-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>