<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&lt;em&gt;Beauveria bassiana&lt;/em&gt;, A Cotton Endophyte With Biocontrol Activity Against Seedling Disease</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Griffin</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Ruth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Earth Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beauveria bassiana&lt;/em&gt; isolate 11-98 is entomopathogenic, endophytic in tomato, and has biocontrol activity against &lt;em&gt;Rhizoctonia solani&lt;/em&gt; on tomato. The objectives of this study were to determine 1) if &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; is endophytic in cotton, following seed treatment; 2) if &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; can protect cotton against seedling pathogens; 3) if different conidial rates, applied to seed, alter effectiveness of &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt;; and 4) mechanisms of biocontrol used by &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; against plant pathogens. Cotton ‘Delta Pine 436’ seed was inoculated with isolate 11-98 conidia, sown in a gnotobiotic system, and then isolated from surfacesterilized seedlings on selective medium. Using scanning electron microscopy, hyphal penetration of epithelial cells was observed. Using ITS primers, polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and electrophoresis of PCR products, 11-98 was detected (single 421-bp band) in a dilution series of fungal and plant DNA, and from cotton seedlings endophytically colonized by 11-98. Biocontrol of &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; against &lt;em&gt;R. solani, Pythium myriotylum,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Thielaviopsis basicola&lt;/em&gt; was examined using several seed treatment rates (log 5 to log 11 CFU). Disease was suppressed and plant growth was increased in potting mix with &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; at log 7 and log 9 CFU/seed, and in sandy loam soil at log 7 CFU/seed. With low disease pressure from &lt;em&gt;P. myriotylum&lt;/em&gt;, seed treated with 11-98 or BotaniGard isolate GHA increased plant growth. Assays with &lt;em&gt;T. basicola&lt;/em&gt; were inconclusive. &lt;em&gt;Beauveria bassiana&lt;/em&gt; was evaluated for induced systemic resistance in cotton against &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas axonopodis&lt;/em&gt; pv. &lt;em&gt;malvacearum&lt;/em&gt;. Root drench treatments were &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; at log 5, log 7, and log 9 CFU/ml, untreated, 2,6-dichloro-isonicotinic acid (INA), and untreated without &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt;. After 13 days, primary leaves were wounded and challenge-inoculated with &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt;. Treatment with &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; (log 7 CFU/seed) had less disease than untreated controls and was as effective as INA. In antibiosis assays, &lt;em&gt;Beauveria bassiana&lt;/em&gt; out-competed &lt;em&gt;T. basicola&lt;/em&gt; on cotton agar, however no clear zone of inhibition was observed; &lt;em&gt;B. bassiana&lt;/em&gt; was outcompeted by &lt;em&gt;R. solani&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P. myriotylum&lt;/em&gt;, however it maintained its original colony diameter. &lt;em&gt;Beauveria bassiana&lt;/em&gt; hyphae coiled around &lt;em&gt;P. myriotylum&lt;/em&gt; hyphae in parasitism assays; no coiling was observed with &lt;em&gt;R. solani&lt;/em&gt;; results for &lt;em&gt;T. basicola&lt;/em&gt; were inconclusive.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/180</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1227&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>180</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1227</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-29T11:24:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1125585</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/180</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bonnie H. Ownley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kimberly D. Gwinn, William E. Klingeman III, Ernest C. Bernard</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/GriffinMaryRuth.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>