<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Computational Model to Predict &lt;em&gt;In Vivo&lt;/em&gt; Kinetics in Implanted and Non-Implanted Shoulders</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kubo</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Brennon-Kyle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering Science and Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to develop and implement a computational model designed to input &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; kinematic and predict &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; forces and torques for the shoulder, elbow, and wrist in normal, rotator cuff-deficient (RCD), reverse shoulder arthroplasty (RSA) and total shoulder arthroplasty (TSA) shoulder subjects. Twenty subjects, divided evenly amongst the four shoulder types, performed a box-lift activity while under fluoroscopic surveillance. Three dimensional (3D) &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; kinematics was determined for the subjects using implant models and bone models created from CT (computed tomography) scans in a 2D-to-3D registration process. The kinematics were used as input for an inverse dynamics mathematical model, and the subject-specific kinetics were derived. Average resultant shoulder forces were 78.3N (range: 70.4N to 117N, SD: 5.213), 102N (range: 90.2N to 180.2N, SD: 12.339), 94.9N (range: 84.9N to 149N, SD: 10.02), and 92.5N (range: 87.984N to 95.370N, SD: 1.848), for normal, RCD, RSA, and TSA subjects, respectively. Average resultant shoulder torques were 23.6Nm (range: 8.32Nm to 73.7Nm, SD: 11.227), 29.6Nm (range: 22.892Nm to 71.377Nm, SD: 7.581), 27.2Nm (range: 19.961Nm to 59.352Nm, SD: 6.664), 20.3Nm (range: 11.700Nm to 31.409Nm, SD: 6.496), for normal, RCD, RSA, and TSA shoulders, respectively. This study revealed that RCD subjects exhibited a decreased ROM (range of motion) of the humeral head with respect to the glenoid, as compared to the other groups. This study also showed that subjects having a rotator cuff-deficient shoulder and/or a replaced shoulder tend to use compensatory motions to perform the task of lifting a box, and, as a result, they experience greater forces at the glenohumeral joint. Paradoxically, the RCD subjects experienced the highest joint forces and torques among the different shoulder types.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4544</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6100&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4544</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6100</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-24T11:23:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10067313</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4544</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard D. Komistek</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mohamed R. Mahfouz, William R. Hamel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Engineering Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>