<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of 5-HT1A Receptors on the Development of Stress-Induced Changes in Behavior</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lbader@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bader</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Renee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>HAMSTER</keyword>
<keyword>SOCIAL DEFEAT</keyword>
<keyword>SEROTONIN</keyword>
<keyword>CONDITIONED DEFEAT</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biological Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Social defeat leads to both increased anxiety-like behavior and the formation of a fear memory for a specific opponent. We have shown that serotonin (5-HT) signaling, particularly in the basolateral amygdala (BLA), alters the acquisition of the conditioned defeat response in Syrian hamsters. While activation of 5-HT1A receptors impairs the acquisition of conditioned defeat, it is unclear whether these receptors alter the development of anxiety-like behavior or formation of fear memories. One method for investigating the formation of defeat-induced fear memories is to measure avoidance of former opponents, and many researchers have reliably used the open field as a measure of anxiety in rodents. In this study, we investigated whether activation of 5-HT1A receptors prior to social defeat would reduce subsequent avoidance of a former opponent but not alter anxiety-like behavior. We also investigated whether activation of 5-HT1A receptors prior to social defeat would reduce the expression of Arc immunoreactivity in the BLA. We administered 8-OH-DPAT (0.0, 0.25, 0.5 mg/kg), a 5-HT1A receptor agonist, prior to 3, 5-minute social defeats and 24- hours later exposed hamsters (&lt;em&gt;Mesocricetus auratus&lt;/em&gt;) to a social interaction test to measure the conditioned defeat response immediately followed by a Y-maze test to measure avoidance of a former opponent and an open field test to measure anxiety. In a separate experiment, we administered 8-OH-DPAT (0.0, 0.25 mg/kg) prior to 3, 5-minute social defeats and 2- hours later brains were perfused and removed for Arc immunohistochemistry. We found that administration of 8-OH-DPAT prior to social defeat reduced the acquisition of conditioned defeat compared to vehicle controls. We also found that administration of 8-OH-DPAT prior to social defeat reduced subsequent avoidance of former opponents but did not alter the classic measures of anxiety in the open field. 8-OH-DPAT administration prior to defeat also impaired Arc immunoreactivity in the BLA. These results suggest that 5-HT1A receptors modulate the fear memory associated with the social defeat experience. Furthermore, these results raise the possibility that 5-HT1A receptor activation disrupts Arc expression in the BLA and thereby impairs the development of a fear memory that is essential for the conditioned defeat response.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1589</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2638&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1589</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2638</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-28T12:11:06-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2638/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3808344</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1589</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Matthew A. Cooper</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Todd M. Freeberg, Jim Hall</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>