<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>University of Tennessee Library Lectures, 1979-1981 (no. 31-33)</title>
<publication-date>1981-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>AR.0281</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thirty-first lecture, delivered by Michael Gorman, joint editor of the Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, Second Edition, discussed the impact of the revised rules. Gorman predicted the new rules would, by restoring standardization of bibliographic control and acting as a catalyst in the process of change, inaugurate a new era of library cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard De Gennaro, in the thirty-second lecture, addressed the chronic fiscal crisis in libraries. He predicted that librarians will need to deal with the imbalance between commitments and resources by facing economic realities. Library goals must be shifted from building large local collections to developing physical and electronic access to a wide range of materials from a variety of sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances Neel Cheney reminded her audience that writers are generally also readers, and thus many of them have made use of academic and public libraries. Many writers have written of their experiences in libraries, and in the thirty-third lecture she shares with us these experiences, &quot;some happy, some unhappy,&quot; of writers and their reading.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libarcutlect/11</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1010&amp;amp;context=utk_libarcutlect&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1010</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-25T08:12:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>University of Tennessee Library Lecture Series</publication-title>
<context-key>1171102</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libarcutlect/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1981-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>