<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of low-dose naltrexone on feed intake, growth, endocrine and immune parameters in the recently-weaned pig</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>acarte30@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carter</lname>
<fname>Ashley</fname>
<mname>Christine</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Weaning is a stressful event for pigs and causes decreased feed intake, poor growth, and increased susceptibility to disease. Previous studies have shown that syndyphalin-33, a synthetic opioid, was effective in increasing feed intake, abrogating the changes in appetite regulating genes during weaning, and abrogating the effects of a salmonella challenge on immune cells in newly-weaned pigs. However, there are several concerns associated with the administration of an opioid in commercial swine operations. Low-dose naltrexone (an opioid antagonist) has been used to alleviate symptoms from fibromyalgia and Crohn’s disease in humans. As inflammation is a common factor in both auto-immune diseases in humans and weaning stress in pigs, a logical next-step would be to examine the effects of low-dose naltrexone on pigs at weaning. In this study, low-dose naltrexone administration was evaluated for its affects on feed intake, growth, endocrine, and immune parameters in newly weaned pigs. Four treatments of 0 mg/day (d), 1 mg/d, 5 mg/d, 10 mg/d naltrexone were administered orally daily beginning 2 wk prior to weaning to 48 commercial crossbred pigs. Each treatment group included 12 pigs. Body weights and blood samples were collected d 0 and at 1, 4, and 7 post-weaning. All animals treated with naltrexone had increased total gain as compared to the control animals (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.05). A decrease in feed intake was seen in animals treated with 5 mg/d naltrexone as compared to the control animals (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.05). Plasma cortisol concentrations were similar to previously published concentrations and increased 1 d post-weaning in the control animals (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.01). Animals treated with 10 mg/d naltrexone had higher plasma concentrations of cortisol relative to all other treatments (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.01). On 1 d post-weaning, animals treated with 1 mg/d and 5 mg/d naltrexone had lower plasma cortisol concentration than the controls (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.01), and by d 4 post-weaning, all animals treated with naltrexone had lower cortisol concentrations relative to the control animals (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; &lt; 0.01). As a non-opioid, oral low-dose naltrexone may be a promising therapy to decrease the growth lag associated with weaning.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3567</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4874&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3567</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4874</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-08-06T10:52:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7423972</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3567</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cheryl Kojima</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Henry Kattesh, Brian Whitlock</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>