<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Malcolm S. Knowles: His Contributions to the Theory and Practice of Adult Education</title>
<publication-date>1973-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jahenschke@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Lindenwood University</institution>
<lname>Henschke</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
<suffix>EdD</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Community College Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
<discipline>Online and Distance Education</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The central question of this study was: What are the contributions in theory and practice Malcolm S. Knowles has made to the emerging field of adult education? The nature of the study as contemporary history of a living person&#39;s educational work, required the findings to be preliminary. The source of information used to answer the central question were: interviews with and questionnaire responses of contemporaries of Knowles and Malcolm S. Knowles who served as &quot;prime information resource;&quot; writing so Knowles and others; and documents and proceedings of a variety of organizations influenced by Knowles. Sections were included on the influence that shaped him as an adult educator; his administrative role at Chicago Central YMCA and Adult Education Association of the U.S.A; his being professor of Education at Boston University; and his spin-off influence on total social systems and individuals, in addition to numerous students and graduates. His influence on more than forty social systems are described and his influence on forty-four individuals is described. George F. Aker&#39;s model of twenty-three essential adult educator behaviors was the tool used to determine areas of strength and weakness of Knowles as asserted by others. Three conclusions concerning Knowles seem warranted: (1) Only the activities and vocation which offered him the opportunity to pioneer and do what he perceived as socially useful could ultimately capture his efforts - adult education thus far has set this test; (2) Eduard C. Lindeman&#39;s book &quot;The Meaning of Adult Education&quot; formed the central overall perspective, inspiration, influence and foundation for Knowles&#39; contribution to the field of adult education; and (3) Knowles&#39; social science research base in his adult education contributions stem from Alvin Johnson and his book &quot;The Clock of History.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_IACE-browseall/385</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1389&amp;amp;context=utk_IACE-browseall&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>385</label>
<document-type>book</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1389</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-07-09T13:51:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>IACE Hall of Fame Repository</publication-title>
<context-key>7308597</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_IACE-browseall/385</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="class_year" type="date">
<value>1998-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>