<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thermal Characteristics of Ground &lt;em&gt;Pectoralis Secundus&lt;/em&gt; Turkey Muscle</title>
<publication-date>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lazure</lname>
<fname>Connie</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Thermal conductivity and diffusivity of ground turkey pectoralis&lt;em&gt; secundus &lt;/em&gt;muscle were investigated using a line-source apparatus modified to allow determinations upon the sample during transient heating.  Samples (51.5g) were heated in a water jacketed cylinder at and to end points of 77, 95, 113, 131, 149, 167, and 185&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F and subjected to holding times of 0 or 15 min.  The relationship between thermal properties and moisture factors including total moisture, cooking loss, and expressible moisture index was investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thermal conductivity values were similar for samples heated at and to temperatures between 77 and 167&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F but tended to decrease for those at 185&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F.  Holding times did not affect thermal conductivity values.  There tended to be close agreement among values for a given end point and these were within ranges reported in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total moisture gradually decreased for turkey heated to temperatures that ranged from 77 to 149&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F.  Thereafter a pronounced decrease in total moisture occurred as end points increased.  A significant increase in cooking loss was noted between samples heated to 77 and 95&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F (P &lt; 0.001) , to 113 and 131&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F or 149&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F (P &lt; 0.01) , and to 149 &lt; 167 &lt; 185&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F (P &lt; 0.05) .  Expressible moisture indexes for 77 and 95&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F samples were similar and decreased slightly at 113&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F.  A pronounced decrease occurred for samples at 131&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F.  With further increase in temperature, little difference was observed.  Expressable moisture indexes were similar for the 149, 167, and 185&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F end points.  Holding time had little if any effect on all parameters measured.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3875</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5359&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3875</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5359</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-18T13:22:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8999909</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3875</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Grayce E. Goertz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ada Marie Campbell, J. L. Collins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>