<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Case Study Exploring the Preservice Technology Training Experiences of Novice Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ssutton5@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sutton</lname>
<fname>Susan</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Integration of technology</keyword>
<keyword>Preservice teachers</keyword>
<keyword>Teacher preparation programs</keyword>
<keyword>Case study</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This qualitative study was designed to identify and explore the preservice technology training experiences of novice teachers and examine their perceptions of how well their teacher preparation program prepared them with the knowledge and skills necessary to fulfill the National Educational Technology Standards for Teachers (NETS•T). Data were collected by following an instrumental case study design utilizing semi-structured interviews, documents, and field notes. Simultaneous collection and analysis of the data helped the researcher to create a deeper understanding of the technology training experiences of novice teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings of this study revealed that novice teachers believe there was a lack of emphasis on technology integration in their teacher preparation program outside of the one required technology course. They expressed a need for technology training to be integrated across the curriculum. They wanted to be provided with authentic learning experiences so they could connect the theory to the practice in relation to technology integration. They wanted more time to practice, reflect, and plan student-centered, technology-rich lessons and they wanted to see all teacher education faculty modeling technology so connections could be made between the technology tools and the appropriate uses of these tools within their content areas. Last, they believe future preservice teachers need more hands-on experiences in creating student-centered, technology-rich lessons, not just within the one required technology course, but throughout their teacher preparation program. Furthermore, 90 percent of the participants expressed a need for more exposure to the technology standards. They stated the only place they were exposed to these technology standards was in the one required technology course and felt that one semester was not enough exposure for them to learn how to implement each of the standards with confidence. All stated they would have liked to have seen all faculty members throughout the teacher preparation program incorporate these technology standards into their teaching, so they would have been provided with adequate exposure to the technology standards.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/915</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1972&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>915</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1972</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-23T13:45:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1578331</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/915</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vincent A. Anfara, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Schuyler W. Huck, Russell L. French, Jay A. Pfaffman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>