<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modes of Social Justice Volume 6, Issue 1 - Full Issue for download</title>
<publication-date>2015-10-08T14:10:50-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>schamelc@hotmail.com</email>
<institution>Claremont Graduate University</institution>
<lname>Schamel</lname>
<fname>Craig</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;When the theme for this issue of Catalyst was conceived, it was imagined that contributions might present both defenses and critiques of liberal justice, that is, one might say, that these contributions would either promote reformist or revolutionary modes of justice. Instead, all of the submissions took a fairly decisive position of critique of liberal modes of justice, though they are not necessarily in agreement about what constitutes a revolutionary mode of social justice, and they do not always adopt the term &#39;revolution&#39; itself as a description of the critique they present and the direction in which they point. Not only did the spirit and letter of the submissions for this issue effectively endorse revolutionary modes of social justice, but these works hit the ground running, with most immediately moving into attempts to describe and help create a strategy of practice for a social justice which could be called revolutionary, and which rather decisively rejects liberalism and in some fundamental ways, conveying in spirit a sense of impatience even with justice as it is conceived and carried out by liberal systems. It is this spirit of the authors of these works and the feeling of eagerness to describe and participate in the effectuation of a revolutionary praxis which they convey, and also on the idea of liberalism as an ideology, on which I focus briefly in this introduction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol6/iss1/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1040&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>entireissue</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1040</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-08-27T22:05:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>3269237</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol6/iss1/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Roads to Reconciliation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>