<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Terrain Impacts from Vehicle Operations across Multiple Passes</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jkane3@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Kane</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Robert</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>vehicle dynamics</keyword>
<keyword>terramechanics</keyword>
<keyword>military</keyword>
<keyword>ITAM</keyword>
<keyword>Impacts</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Bioresource and Agricultural Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Environmental Indicators and Impact Assessment</discipline>
<discipline>Sustainability</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study, conducted on August 12th and 13th, 2008 at Fort Riley, Kansas on a clay loam soil, evaluated the terrain impacts of four commonly used tracked and wheeled military vehicles: the M1A1 Abrams Main Battle Tank, M998 High Mobility Multipurpose Wheeled Vehicle, M985 Heavy Expanded Mobility Tactical Truck, and M113 Armored Personnel Carrier. Disturbed width and impact severity were assessed along 14 spirals subjected to a maximum of eight consecutive passes for a total of 696 impact points. Data indicate that multiple passes produce increased vegetative impacts, with multipass coefficients ranging from 0.98 to 4.44 (compared to the commonly accepted value of 2.00) depending on vehicle type and turn severity. The widely-used MPC of 2.00 fits the M985 HEMTT and M113 at sharp turns, with an MPC of 1.00 fitting the straight and intermediate turning conditions of these vehicles, as well as all turning conditions for the M998 HMMWV. For the M1A1, a MPC of 2.00 is suitable for straight paths, a MPC of 3.00 is suitable for intermediate turns, while sharp turns can be represented by a MPC of 4.00. The data suggests that MPCs should be adjusted depending on the vehicle type and according to the turning radius of the vehicle, as tracked vehicles were found to have a higher multipass coefficient than wheeled vehicles, with multipass coefficients increasing with vehicle weight and the sharpness of turns.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/811</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1907&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>811</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1907</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-17T17:07:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1646547</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/811</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paul D. Ayers</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Freeland, Joanne Logan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biosystems Engineering Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>