<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Weaning Strategy on the Physiology and Performance of Beef Calves</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ccampist@utk.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Campistol</lname>
<fname>Cristina</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>weaning</keyword>
<keyword>calves</keyword>
<keyword>stress</keyword>
<keyword>well-being</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Two experiments examined growth performance and physiological measures of stress in pre- and postweaned Angus steers (313 ± 24.5 kg; n = 48/Exp.), where steers were fitted with (YD) or without (ND) an anti-suckling device (Exp. 1), or provided (YS) or not provided (NS) a grain supplement (Exp. 2) for 7 d and weaned by fenceline (FS) or total separation (TS). Steers in Exp. 1 were weighed and bled on d 0, 3, 7  10, 14, 21, and 42, and in Exp. 2, on d 0, 7, 10, 14, and 21 and provided a grain supplement on d 7-21. In Exp. 1, weight gain was not different (P = 0.74) between ND and YD steers during preweaning. The YD-FS steers lost weight (P = 0.01) by d 10 compared with YD-TS steers. Hematocrit (Hct) increased (P = 0.04) in YD but not ND steers on d 3. Neutrophil:lymphocyte ratio (N:L) increased (P &lt; 0.01) in all steers by d 7. Cortisol values in YD-FS steers were higher (P &lt; 0.05) compared with YD-TS steers on d 10 and 21. The ND-FS steers had higher (P = 0.04) interferon-gamma (IFN) concentrations on d 10 compared with all YD steers. Haptoglobin (HAP) values increased (P &lt; 0.01) in all steers by d 3. The FS steers had higher (P &lt; 0.01) ceruloplasmin (CER) values by d 10 than TS steers regardless of preweaning treatment. Ovalbumin-specific IgG increased (P &lt; 0.01) in all steers 10 d following its administration. In  Exp. 2, NS-TS steers lost weight (P &lt; 0.01) between d 7 and 10  compared with the remaining steers. The YS steers had higher cortisol, N:L and CER  on d 7 compared with NS steers. Moreover, NS steers had higher (P &lt; 0.01) Hct on d 10 than YS steers. Based upon physiological and growth  performance data, it may be concluded that use of an anti-suckling device prior to weaning does not improve the animals’ well-being and, providing a grain supplement beginning 7 d prior to weaning may temper the animals’ stress response due to weaning when total separation is employed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/780</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1877&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>780</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1877</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-10-24T17:42:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1615782</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/780</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Henry G. Kattesh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John C. Waller, Emmit Rawls, Gina M. Pighetti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>