<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Principals’ Roles in Supporting and Evaluating Teacher Use of Technology in Nonpublic Secondary Schools</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>swallis@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wallis</lname>
<fname>Susan</fname>
<mname>Byrkit</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Educational technology</keyword>
<keyword>technology integration</keyword>
<keyword>technology support</keyword>
<keyword>technology evaluation</keyword>
<keyword>nonpublic school technology leadership</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this qualitative, explanatory, multi-site study was to explore and better understand how high school principals support, and evaluate teacher use of technology for classroom instruction in nonpublic secondary schools.  The study was guided by the Role Identity theory theoretical framework as provided by McCall and Simmons (1966).  Literature was also reviewed related to administrative support of technology integration.  Limited research exists exploring how principals perceive they support technology use as well as how they evaluate technology integration in the classroom.  This study sought to address the gap in the literature.  Data were collected through interviews with six high school principals, field notes, and collected artifacts from each of the six schools.  Data revealed principals support teacher use of technology for classroom instruction within the constraints of available resources.  The study also revealed a lack in formal methods or instruments for evaluating technology use.  One solution is for heads of schools and accrediting agencies to establish distinct expectations for principals in leading technology integration using established NETS-A standards.  Such expectations can empower principals and transform successful integration of technology in nonpublic schools.  Additional implications for heads of school and policy makers regarding technology integration were explored.  Finally, suggestions were offered for future research projects.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5828</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7594&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5828</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7594</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-10T19:18:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20522221</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5828</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Pamela Angelle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Lynne Derrington, Karen Boyd, Joel Diambra</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/Susan Wallis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>