<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Observation of Baryon Number Violation via Cold Neutron Sources</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>frostmj@ornl.gov</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Frost</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>particle physics</keyword>
<keyword>baryon asymmetry</keyword>
<keyword>neutron sources</keyword>
<keyword>neutron optics</keyword>
<keyword>nanoparticles</keyword>
<keyword>anti-neutron oscillation</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Current models describing the fundamental nature of the universe suggest that Baryonnumber need not be conserved and would provide a valid argument as to the levelof matter-antimatter imbalance in the observable universe. The observation of anyneutron/antineutron or neutron/mirror-neutron oscillations would confirm BaryonNumber Violation (BNV), and thus reveal the fundamental nature of the universe.Experiments that would show the existence of such oscillations, or at least put anupper limit on their time constants, are unique. A push to further investigate thesephenomena would either discover a phenomenon that gives rise to the existence of theuniverse as we know it, or narrow the wide field of theories that attempt to explainthese Beyond Standard Model mechanisms. New experiments utilizing sources of coldneutrons such as a nuclear reactor or spallation source provide a means by which tosearch for these higher energy scale phenomena beyond that which can be achievedwith a collider. Contemporary experiment design utilizing these sources in addition tomodern neutron transport techniques can provide an improvement in experimentalsensitivity upwards of three orders of magnitude beyond what as been attemptedpreviously. However, these designs utilize a range of technologies that have notnecessarily been implemented in such a grand manner. This practical implementationis a concern that further complicates the overall design. Demonstrations of noveltransport concepts and simulations incorporating those results into the developmentof an experiment design to observe this type of oscillation are the main focus of thiswork. The developments have also been my main contribution to the collaborativeeffort towards the realization of a new experiment that would meet move thisendeavour forward.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5951</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7737&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5951</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7737</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-24T14:18:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>21246603</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5951</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Yuri Kamyshkov</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Geoffrey Freene, Stephan Spainer, Lawrence Townsend, Arthur Ruggles</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6821-170X</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>