<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Code Switching: The unfortunate but necessary key to opening doors for yourself and others to follow</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-12T15:06:46-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>Wallaceh@apsu.edu</email>
<institution>Austin Peay State University</institution>
<lname>Wallace</lname>
<fname>Harold</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Unifying the Black Community</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Inequality and Stratification</discipline>
<discipline>Multicultural Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Code Switching: The unfortunate yet necessary key to opening doors for yourself and others to follow&quot; this presentation touches on what &quot;Code Switching&quot; is, it&#39;s origin, and why it is simply a defense mechanism to make sure you are always able to feed yourself and your family. The more we become comfortable with the &quot;Why&quot; the more we can move forward on &quot;How&quot; it will help get others in the door. Ultimately finding the balance between being unapologetically and authentically you/black, and being the person you need to be to infiltrate the higher rankings of any industry, hopefully leave a path behind you for others to follow. Also with the hopes of breaking down the &quot;Crabs in a bucket/barrel&quot; mentality that has proven to be an abuse of our competitive spirit and need for survival.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1240&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1240</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-27T09:17:29-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1240/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16084192</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Harold Wallace III is the new Director of the Wilbur N. Daniel African American Cultural Center at Austin Peay State University. Harold is a proud Los Angeles, CA native and has served in higher education for 10 years. In his prior roles he worked as an advisor for 3 organizations including Black Student Association, Native American Student Association and Hispanics of Today. While advising, he created and implemented programming to enhance the atmosphere of diversity on campuses. Harold has an immense amount of experience starting and working with initiative programs aimed to guide our underrepresented populations with retention always at the forefront of his efforts. Harold is also a higher education speaker, who enjoys using his words to paint pictures of a World that we all deserve to live in and be a part of and inspire our future leaders. His educational background includes a B.A in Ethnic Studies, Business, and Sociology from Wichita State University, and a Master of Science in College Student Personnel from Arkansas Tech University. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NJy5yeBSQ7o&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NJy5yeBSQ7o&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Monitor</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;- Participants will understand the difference between being &quot;Fake&quot; and having a better understanding for the need for &quot;Code Switching&quot; due to White fragility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Participants will dig deeper into the &quot;By any means necessary&quot; resilience that it takes to lead into uncharted waters of higher ranking positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Participants will help understand  the need for unity in a world that is constantly having us compete for the same roles. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The program relates directly with the theme, by helping us people of color understand that we are stronger when unified. When one person works super hard, defying the odds to grab a role of power in any industry, they should be reaching back for others hopefully making the journey for them easier than their own, which is what our ancestors have sacrificed so much for us to be able to do. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>