<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Differences of Cycling Experiences and Perceptions between E-Bike and Bicycle Users in the United States</title>
<publication-date>2017-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ling</lname>
<fname>Ziwen</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>cherry@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cherry</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Portland State University</institution>
<lname>MacArthur</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Bosch eBike Systems Americas</institution>
<lname>Weinert</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
<mname>X.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>e-bike</keyword>
<keyword>conventional bicycle</keyword>
<keyword>difference</keyword>
<keyword>cycling experience and perception</keyword>
<keyword>online survey</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;E-bikes are bicycles that provide pedal-assistance to aid people in cycling. Because of the potential of promoting sustainable transportation, more attention has been focused on the e-bike market. This paper investigates the differences of the cycling experience and perceptions between e-bike and conventional bicycle users, using samples drawn from independent bicycle dealer customers. A total of 806 respondents in the United States took the on-line survey, including 363 e-bike-owning respondents. The results show that e-bikes play a more important role in utilitarian travel, such as commuting and running errands, compared to a conventional bicycle. Conventional bicycle-owning respondents use their bicycles more for recreation and exercise. Also, e-bike owners tend to bike longer distances and take more trips per week. Both e-bike respondents and bicycle respondents stated that improved health was a key factor for cycling, while Millennials and Generation X respondents cycle to save time and improve the environment. Finally, an ordered logit model is proposed for evaluating factors that influence interest in future e-bike ownership. Travel purpose, e-bike familiarity, annual household income, and education level are statistically significant factors in the model. These findings begin to provide insight and a profile of potential new markets for e-bikes in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_civipubs/22</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1029&amp;amp;context=utk_civipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1029</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-12-05T10:49:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>11200261</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_civipubs/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Ling, Ziwen, Christopher R. Cherry, John H. MacArthur, and Jonathan X. Weiner. “Differences of Cycling Experiences and Perceptions Between E-Bike and Bicycle Users in the United States.” Sustainability 9, no.9 (2017). https://doi.org/10.3390/su9091662.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.3390/su9091662</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Sustainability</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>