<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Local Government Relations in Knox County Executive Collaboration and its Impact</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jryansowell@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Sowell</lname>
<fname>J. Ryan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Political Science</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Government Relations</keyword>
<keyword>Executive Collaboration</keyword>
<keyword>Leadership</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The recent governmental history of Knoxville and Knox County represents an intriguing case study of interest-group-led referendums, corruption, and reform. Recent structural reforms were a direct response to the unethical behavior displayed by some members of the Knox County Commission, but indirectly the changes attempted to address a number of lingering community issues. When placed in the context of the community’s contemporary political history, the reforms&#39; significance becomes apparent. In the past twenty years the greater Knoxville community experienced intergovernmental court battles, a failed unification referendum, a sheriff with unprecedented political clout, and state legislative intervention. Executive leadership has had a major impact on the course of the community’s contemporary history and will continue to be an important factor in local debate to come.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol3/iss1/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1095&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1095</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-02T08:00:55-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>2384250</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol3/iss1/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Government Relations</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>