<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unintentional Injury Content Assessment in Undergraduate Personal Health and Wellness Courses</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kwinston@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Winston</lname>
<fname>Kiley</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Unintentional Injuries</keyword>
<keyword>Personal Health Courses</keyword>
<keyword>Injury Instrument</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Community Health and Preventive Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research study was to describe course content on unintentional injuries in undergraduate personal health and wellness courses at four year public and private colleges and universities identified by the Eta Sigma Gamma directory in the United States.  An instrument was created, validated and tested for reliability, and used to assess course content areas related to unintentional injuries in undergraduate personal health and wellness courses.  The sample for the study included 106 participants (N=106) from public and private colleges and universities in 36 states.  Chi-square analysis, ANOVA, factor analysis, and MANOVA tests were used to determine if significant differences existed in course content areas based on selected demographic characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results indicated that college and university faculty members report teaching about unintentional injuries.  Findings indicated that significant differences do exist in unintentional injury course content areas.  The top five content areas identified by faculty members include water-related injuries, firearm safety, motorcycle injuries, motor vehicle passenger safety, and motor vehicle impaired driving.   Factor analysis results revealed that unintentional injury course content areas can be categorized into three groups:  personal content, motor vehicle content, and injury content.   The level of statistical significance was set at 0.05.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/758</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1740&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>758</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1740</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-07T13:11:07-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1740/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1265249</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/758</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>June D. Gorski</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory Petty, Denise Bates, Rena Hallam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>