<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effective Education on Consumers&#39; Food Safety Knowledge, Perceptions, and Behaviors at Local Area Farmers&#39; Markets</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>malbin1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Albin</lname>
<fname>Molly</fname>
<mname>Louise</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>food safety</keyword>
<keyword>education</keyword>
<keyword>farmers&#39; markets</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although extensive research has been conducted to understand consumers’ knowledge of food safety risks, there is a lack of research on consumers’ knowledge, perceptions, and behaviors towards risks associated with locally grown, processed, and manufactured foods sold at farmers’ markets. Recently, there has been a movement toward purchasing local foods to support local economies, out of concern for food miles, or because of a perception of higher quality goods. In Tennessee, the number of farmers’ markets has doubled in five years. Furthermore, previous research determined food safety education is most effective if developed with input from the target audience. The purpose of this research was to determine what, if any, food safety concerns, misconceptions, and current practiced behaviors exist amongst a targeted population of consumers who purchase locally grown, processed, and/or manufactured food commodities in a farmers’ market setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instrument was developed and tested at a separate farmers’ market location. Screener questions were included for demographics and shopping frequency. Purchasing habits of perishable foods were used to determine participant qualification for the full survey. The survey instrument addressed commonly purchased goods, reasons for shopping at farmers markets, food safety knowledge, common misconceptions, and general disposition towards food safety. Data were collected during 6 markets from July-­‐October (n=27) and analyzed to determine misconceptions. Eighty-­‐nine percent of consumers believed “it is important or very important to purchase goods at farmers markets to avoid pesticides and other chemicals”. Additionally, 88.8% thought harmful bacteria grows in ≤2 hours in foods held between 40-­‐140oF, yet only 13.0% of the 85.2% who planned on purchasing perishable goods brought a cooler or insulated bag indicating a knowledge gap exists on the relationship between harmful bacterial growth and how long perishable goods are left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this study suggest that even though food safety educational material exists, somehow the material is not reaching some consumers. Consumers at farmers’ markets need to be further studied to improve their understanding of safe food handling at farmers’ markets, organic classification, pesticide use, the relationship between time and temperature, and proper planning for perishable food purchases.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3342</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4769&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3342</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4769</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-17T13:07:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7002992</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3342</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jennifer K. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sarah Colby, Faith Critzer, H. Dwight Loveday</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>