<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Design and Synthesis of Biotinylated Tylophorine Analogues for use as Affinity Probes in the Elucidation of the Cellular Targets of DCB-3503</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Francis</lname>
<fname>Samson</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The tylophorine analogue, DCB-3503 (&lt;strong&gt;1-62b&lt;/strong&gt;, NSC-716802), has been found to exhibit broad spectrum activity &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; in the National Cancer Institute’s (NCI) panel of 60 human-derived cell lines. Recent studies involving HepG2, a human hepatocellular carcinoma cell line, and two pancreatic ductal carcinoma cell lines (PANC-1 and HPAC), have suggested that DCB-3503 (&lt;strong&gt;1-62b&lt;/strong&gt;) exerts its unique growth inhibition properties by modulating nuclear factor kappa B activity as well as through the inhibition of nuclear protein synthesis. However, the physiologically relevant protein binding partner(s) of DCB-3503 (&lt;strong&gt;1-62b&lt;/strong&gt;) have not been identified. Herein, the design and synthesis of two biotin conjugates of DCB-3503 are described. In both cases, attachment of the biotin moiety to the active core was achieved through a Cu(I)- catalyzed 1,3-dipolar Huisgen cycloaddition (“click”) coupling reaction. Additionally, 3D QSAR studies were performed using comparative molecular field analysis (CoMFA) on a set of phenanthrolizidine alkaloids with inhibitory activities against the HepG2 cell line. A satisfactory CoMFA model was obtained with LOO cross-validation &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and noncross- validated &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; values of 0.567 and 0.935, respectively. The developed model demonstrated promising predictive abilities as discerned by the results of the external test set.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/600</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1668&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>600</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1668</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-23T12:02:38-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1165466</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/600</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Baker</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael D. Best, George K. Schweitzer, Jeffery M. Becker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>