<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effects of nursing home organizational culture and climate on employee and resident outcomes</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Cassie</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
<mname>McClure</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Social work</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The organizational context of nursing homes is examined through a comprehensive review of scholarly literature and an original study of the association between organizational social context and outcomes in a sample of 27 nursing homes, 1,114 nursing home employees, and 3,927 nursing home residents. The study hypothesizes that nursing homes with more positive cultures and climates will have: 1) better employee morale; 2) less staff turnover; and 3) better resident health and psychosocial functioning. This research confirms the existence of particular culture and climate profiles in the nursing home industry. Results of Hierarchical Linear Modeling analyses reveal that nursing homes with more positive climates enjoy higher employee morale and better resident outcomes. Findings from this study have implications for organizational change strategies to create organizational social contexts that contribute to improved services for nursing home staff and residents.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6051</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7984&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6051</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7984</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467843</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6051</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles Glisson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>