<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Perceived Confidence Level of 5th and 6th Grade Teachers in Sevier County, Tennessee Using Technology in the Classroom</title>
<publication-date>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Baxter</lname>
<fname>Jerry</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Throughout history many devices, inventions and gadgets have been advocated as items that would revolutionize the way people live, work and play. As we begin the new millennium, the sheer number of these items being considered or developed has skyrocketed. For the most part people can look around anywhere they happen to be and point to the successes while the failures are soon forgotten. This is especially true in education. Items such as televisions, calculators, overhead projectors, etc. have truly revolutionized education through their wide use in the classroom. Some of the items on the list of inventions may appear outlandishly silly or common place in the 21st century; however, they are all a part of the recipe that makes-up the educational system of today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educational systems across the country have been burdened, in the last three decades, with the evolution of the expanding role school systems are responsible for in order to educate the nation&#39;s children. Enormous amounts of resources have been allocated to address areas such as school safety, illegal drugs, nutrition, teen pregnancy, student achievement, etc. The nation is now struggling with the issues that surround the rapid explosion of technology. The technology revolution has profound and far-reaching implications for all aspects of our culture. The technology revolution has the potential to rival the industrial revolution in the magnitude of impact on people&#39;s daily lives&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6367</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8320&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6367</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8320</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-13T11:46:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23808970</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6367</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas N. Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles Chance, George Harris, C. Glennon Rowell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>