<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hunter Harvest of Pen-Reared Northern Bobwhites Released From the Surrogator</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:50:10-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Georgia Department of Natural Resources</institution>
<lname>Thackston</lname>
<fname>Reggie</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station</institution>
<lname>Crouch</lname>
<fname>Tyson</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Kentucky Department of Fish and Wildlife Resources</institution>
<lname>Baxley</lname>
<fname>Danna</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Kentucky Department of Fish and Wildlife Resources</institution>
<lname>Robinson</lname>
<fname>Ben</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Alabama</keyword>
<keyword>bobwhite chicks</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>Georgia</keyword>
<keyword>hunter harvest</keyword>
<keyword>Kentucky</keyword>
<keyword>Surrogator</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;There has been increased interest in releasing pen-reared northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) to meet quail hunting and shooting objectives as populations have declined. The Surrogatort is a commercially available product for rearing and releasing gamebirds into the wild and is promoted as a method to enhance bobwhite survival, improve hunting, and increase recruitment from natural reproduction. We used return-to-hunter bag data from 3 properties in Alabama, Georgia, and Kentucky to evaluate the Surrogatort as a pre-hunting season release technique for pen-reared bobwhites. Across all sites, 3,859 5-week old banded bobwhite chicks were released at varying times during June through October, 2005–2010. Ninety-three quail hunts were conducted during November through January 2005–2011 comprising 431 hunt party hours which resulted in 19 banded bobwhites being harvested. The return-to-hunter bag for all sites combined was 0.005 (range 1⁄4 0.000 to 0.008). This was considered unsatisfactory at each site and across all sites combined for a quality hunting/shooting experience. The mean cost per chick released was $3.41 (range 1⁄4 $2.74 to $3.88) including the costs of quail chicks, Surrogatort units, propane, and feed across all sites. The mean cost per bird returned-to-hunter bag (Alabama and Georgia) was $655.80 (range 1⁄4 $489.91 to $821.68). These costs did not include economic depreciation of Surrogatort units.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/63</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1390&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>63</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_artificial_management_research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1390</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:44:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472197</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/63</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>