<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Physical Activity Assessment in Wheelchair Users</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>congerscotta@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Conger</lname>
<fname>Scott Alexander</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>energy expenditure</keyword>
<keyword>power</keyword>
<keyword>accelerometer</keyword>
<keyword>propulsion</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; To examine the relationship between hand rim propulsion power and energy expenditure during wheelchair locomotion.  &lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; Fourteen individuals who used manual wheelchairs were included in this study.  Each participant performed five different locomotion activities in a wheelchair with a PowerTap hub built into the rear wheel.  The activities included wheeling on a level surface that elicited a low rolling resistance at three different speeds (4.5, 5.5, and 6.5 km∙hr&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;), wheeling on a rubberized 400m track that elicited a higher rolling resistance at one speed (5.5 km∙hr&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;), and wheeling on a sidewalk course that included uphill and downhill segments at their self-selected speed.  Energy expenditure was measured using a portable indirect calorimetry system.  In addition, each subject wore an Actical and a SenseWear activity monitor on the right wrist and upper arm, respectively.  Stepwise, linear regression was performed to predict energy expenditure from power output variables.  A repeated measures ANOVA was used to compare the measured energy expenditure to the estimates from the power models, the Actical, and the SenseWear.  Bland-Altman plots were used to assess the agreement between the criterion values and the predicted values.  &lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; The relationship between energy expenditure and power was significantly correlated (r = 0.694, p &lt; 0.001). Stepwise, linear regression analysis yielded three significant prediction models utilizing measured power; measured power and speed; and measured power, speed, and heart rate.  A repeated measures ANOVA demonstrated a significant main effect between measured energy expenditure and estimated energy expenditure (p &lt; 0.01).  There were no significant differences between the criterion method and the power models or the Actical.  The SenseWear significantly overestimated energy expenditure when wheeling at 4.5 km·hr&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, 5.5 km·hr&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, 6.5 km·hr&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, and during self-paced sidewalk wheeling (p &lt; 0.05).  &lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; Energy expenditure can be accurately and precisely estimated based on wheelchair propulsion power.  These results indicate that wheelchair power could be used as a method to assess physical activity in people who use wheelchairs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1069</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2293&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1069</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2293</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-04T14:05:59-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2293/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2133241</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1069</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson, Eugene C. Fitzhugh, Gene A. Hayes, Paul C. Erwin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>