<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Social and Economic Effects Produced Upon Small Towns by Rapid Industrialization</title>
<publication-date>1938-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Holly</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Fred</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The introduction of an industry into rural areas or small towns, unless they are mill centers, and the absorption of rural peoples into these industries involve many changes of social and economic significance. The shift from an agricultural to an industrial economy has by its very nature many consequences. This study is an attempt to measure, as far as is possible, the effects of such changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The City of Elizabethton, Tennessee underwent a very rapid change beginning in 1925 when the American Bemberg Corporation located a rayon establishment there. With the shift of economy many significant changes occurred. Therefore, Elizabethton, Tennessee was chosen as the setting for this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For purposes of comparison and suggestion a study of similar developments in Kingsport, Tennessee has been included. Kingsport&#39;s industrial history extends over a longer period of time and presents a much more stable situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurement of such social and economic changes is unusually difficult; however, data have been compiled which will point out many of the basic changes occurring with the rapid industrialization of rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various methods were used in the collection of the data. As far as was possible original data were used. Such data were obtained from County and City Officials, records of private concerns, and County and Federal records. In many cases where measurement was necessary data were not available. To overcome this inadequacy various techniques were relied upon. Interviews, observations, and actual experiences (the writer is a native of Elizabethton, Tennessee) were relied upon.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1772</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3124&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1772</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3124</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-29T12:00:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4524309</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1772</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles P. White</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hiram E. Cole, Harry G. Meyer</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;(large file - 62 MB)&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1938-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1938-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>