<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tracking Flanker Task Dynamics: Evidence for Continuous Attentional Selectivity</title>
<publication-date>2020-04-13T07:05:30-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>clevi2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Levi</lname>
<fname>Cody</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kpeter33@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peterson</lname>
<fname>Katherine</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kkinder5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kinder</lname>
<fname>Kaleb</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ctas1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tas</lname>
<fname>Caglar</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>abuss@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Buss</lname>
<fname>Aaron</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Cognitive Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A central research goal in the cognitive sciences has been to understand the processes that underlie selective attention, or the ability to focus on goal-relevant information. Two opposing theories have been proposed in an effort to explain how selective attention emerges: one suggests that attention improves continuously over time, whereas the other proposes that attention improves at a discrete time point. While outcome-based data (e.g., reaction time) have successfully provided evidence for both accounts, there has been no empirical evidence to differentiate them. In this study, we used mouse-tracking in a flanker task that provided time sensitive measures associated with selective attention. Specifically, we recorded the path of real-time movement trajectories to assess characteristics of continuous and discrete shifts in selective attention. Our results strongly suggested that selective attention increased gradually over time, as opposed to at a discrete point, thus providing support for a continuous account of selective attention.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_psycpubs/19</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=utk_psycpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>19</label>
<document-type>poster</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1036</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-04-10T14:57:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Psychology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>17334898</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_psycpubs/19</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>