<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Brand Communication in a Large Consumer Goods Company:  A Case of The Coca-Cola Company</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:56:46-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmac110495@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Deal</lname>
<fname>Julianna</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to better understand the flow of communication among the multitude of different bottles within a large consumer goods company, the Coca-Cola Company. This qualitative study conducted several interviews, both with lower and middle level employees, and with executives. Interviews were either conducted in-person or through email communication. Prior to interviewing employees, an informed consent form was signed by each participant, which ensured their privacy. The study applied thematic analysis to determine trends surrounding brand communication within the Coca-Cola Company and strategic methods that employees found both effective and unsuccessful. Results show successful communication themes such as: avoiding micromanagement, creating diversity within teams, using the core values in all decision making, creating a positive office environment, providing helpful critique without hurtful criticism, and collaborating among all departments within the company.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/education/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1159&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1159</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-10T18:06:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11942230</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/education/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Department of Retail, Hospitality, and Tourism Management</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Michelle Childs</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>