<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spiritual architecture and the everyday</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Waring</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis investigates the way architecture can be spiritually engaging as well as perform functionally in a non-religious program. Spiritual sensitivity and intent in architecture may seem somewhat counter to the act of architecture itself. Architecture is a physical manifestation of the designer&#39;s idea, and the fulfillment of the patrons functional needs and/or desires. The spiritual may seem to be the ephemeral rather than the tangible, the philosophy rather than the action, or the metaphysical rather than the physical. However, architecture may be derivative or inclusive of many outside influences, such as the context, topography, function, and in this proposal the spiritual. Architecture has dealt well with the spiritual engagement in relation to the sacred. However, it has not been as deliberate in providing an engaging experience spiritually in everyday architecture. To study the way architecture might be engaging spiritually there are characteristics and qualities that have the capacity to bridge the tangible and the ephemeral. These characteristics begin to define the essence of the spiritual experience through varying scales from the individual to the collective. The conscious design of spaces that breath life into the project will be those moments conceived as meditative, quiet, centered spaces and will be contrasted to the more physically engaged collective spaces. This thesis of spiritual engagement of the everyday will be explored through the design of a transitional residential community and neighborhood community center in Memphis, Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6009</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7642&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6009</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7642</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467671</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6009</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jon Coddington</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Adam Drisin, Mark DeKay</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>