<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The influence of storage time and temperature on propofol concentrations in canine blood and plasma.</title>
<publication-date>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>Sherry</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Propofol is an intravenous anesthetic commonly used due to its favorable pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile. There are discrepancies in the literature about the most appropriate sample for determining propofol concentrations. Although plasma has been used for determining propofol concentrations, whole blood has been the preferred sample. There is also a lack of consistency in the literature on the effect of storage time and temperature on propofol concentrations and this may lead to errors in the design of pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamics studies. The purpose of this study was to determine the difference in propofol concentrations in whole blood versus plasma and to evaluate the influence of storage time (56 days) and temperature (4 °C, -20 °C, -80 °C) on the stability of propofol concentrations in blood and plasma samples. Results from the study indicate that whole blood and plasma samples containing propofol stored at -80 °C have concentrations as high as or higher than those stored at 4 °C or -20 °C for 56 days; thus, -80 °C is an appropriate temperature for propofol sample storage. Plasma propofol concentrations were consistently higher than whole blood for all three storage temperatures. Consequently, plasma is the most appropriate sample for propofol analysis due to its consistent determinations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/149</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1148&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>149</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1148</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-04-14T08:32:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>17362459</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/149</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.7717/peerj.3476</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>PeerJ</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>