<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>American Daoism: A New Religious Movement in Global Contexts</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chan</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>San-Hu</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis explores the phenomenon of American Daoism. It assumes that American Daoism is a New Religious Movement, and argues that it has roots in counterhegemonic religious movements of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. I will explore these roots and describe how they are counter-hegemonic. Furthermore, I will build upon Elijiah Siegler’s doctoral dissertation, “The Dao of America: The History and Practice of American Daoism,” by using post-modern theories of identity to discuss how American Daoist identity is formed. This thesis argues that American Daoist identity is a combination of Chinese and American cultural objects that form a hybrid religious identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American Daoism has largely been influenced by globalization and consumer culture. I will argue that there is some degree of commodification in American Daoism. The process of commodification is not negative, rather it facilitates American Daoism’s spread into new markets. I also discuss the negative aspects of commodification in relation to Daoism, and the problems encountered when differentiating between the two.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3652</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5005&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3652</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5005</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-10T10:47:59-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8125154</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3652</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Miriam Levering</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Mark Hulsether, Dr. Rachelle Scott</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>