<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Verbal Judo Training Module for Law Enforcement: An Ethnographic Perspective</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T18:55:58-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lornak@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Keathley</lname>
<fname>Lorna</fname>
<mname>F</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ginger1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Communication Studies at The University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Kupritz</lname>
<fname>Virginia</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jhaas1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Communication Studies at The University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Haas</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Interpersonal and Small Group Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined Verbal Judo non-verbal and verbal communication tactics in a compliance-gaining context between a police officer and an individual who had been stopped by the officer. Verbal Judo emphasizes the use of both verbal and non-verbal communication by the officer with specific discourse structures aimed at the individual to obtain goals in compliance-gaining contexts. Verbal Judo incorporates the &lt;em&gt;principle of nonresistance&lt;/em&gt; deflecting the other’s energies to obtain goals within a context. This study determined that Verbal Judo compliance-gaining procedures used in training videos should be tailored by law enforcement to the specific context and type of person (&lt;em&gt;easy, difficult, sneaky&lt;/em&gt;). Successive repetition by officers (with matching non-verbal tone) of strategic Verbal Judo language when dealing with a &lt;em&gt;difficult person &lt;/em&gt;is the key in diminishing conflict and minimizing escalation of conflict within the compliance-gaining context. Minimizing conflict in compliance-gaining situations between officers and individuals benefits law enforcement agencies, law enforcement officers, city and state governments, and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keywords:  &lt;em&gt;Law Enforcement, Verbal Judo, Visual Ethnography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/session2/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1028&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1028</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-12T05:44:09-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1028/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2010799</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/session2/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>