<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extraction of Proteins by Winsor III Microemulsion Systems</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gomez del Rio</lname>
<fname>Javier</fname>
<mname>Alejandro</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Purification of proteins by microemulsion was improved through use of a 3-phase (“Winsor-III”) microemulsion system instead of the traditionally employed 2-phase (“Winsor-II”) water-in-oil microemulsion system. As a consequence, two of the main problems of the traditional method were improved: the low and slow rate of recovery of proteins encapsulated by the microemulsions and the low protein solubilization capacity of the microemulsions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microemulsion systems employed a mixture of surfactants, two pH-degradable “cyclic ketal” alkyl ethoxylates (O-[(2-tridecyl, 2-ethyl-1,3-dioxolan-4-yl) methoxy]–O’- methoxy poly(ethylene glycol)&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; , where n, the average degree of polymerization for the ethoxylate group, equaled 3.0 or 5.45, CK3 and CK7, respectively) and Aerosol-OT (AOT). CK7’s ethoxylate size has broad molecular weight distribution. Partitioning behavior of CK7 molecules as a function of their ethoxylate size, temperature, and the addition of a second surfactant (AOT, CK3, or octyl β-D-glycoside) were investigated. A semi-empirical thermodynamic mathematical model was developed to calculate the phase inversion temperature (PIT) for a surfactant mixture of a specified composition. This information is useful to find the optimal Winsor-III for protein extraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally different Winsor-III systems formed by water, isooctane and surfactant mixtures of CK7, CK3 and AOT were tested in forward extraction of α-chymotrypsin, cytochrome-c, lysozyme, BSA and pepsin. Three approaches were used to obtain Winsor- III systems suitable for forward extraction: employment at 40°C, addition of a more hydrophobic surfactant (CK3, 25°C), and the addition of 1.5 wt. % NaCl (aq) to increase the ionic strength (25°C). Protein concentrations achieved in microemulsion phase were 10 times higher than values reported in the literature for extraction by Winsor-II microemulsion systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back extraction was tested for α-chymotrypsin, cytochrome-c, and lysozyme. Aqueous striping solutions used for back extraction contained either a high ionic strength (5 wt. % NaCl) or a high pH (12.0). Back-extraction was fast and total recovery of the activity for α-chymotrypsin was achieved. Other proteins have smaller percentage of mass recovery in the conditions tested but comparable with yields reported in the literature for microemulsion-based extraction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/439</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1500&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>439</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1500</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T11:17:28-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1151061</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/439</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Douglas Gordon Hayes</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Paul D. Frymier, Tsewei Wang, Qixin Zhong</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/GomezdelRioJavierAlejandro.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>