<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SIMULATING MICROBIAL ELECTROLYSIS FOR RENEWABLE HYDROGEN PRODUCTION INTEGRATED WITH SEPARATION IN BIOREFINERY</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cwilso76@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Christian</fname>
<mname>James</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>microbial electrolysis</keyword>
<keyword>biorefinery</keyword>
<keyword>hydrogen production</keyword>
<keyword>simulation</keyword>
<keyword>bio-oil separation</keyword>
<keyword>steam reforming</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemical and Biomolecular Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Catalysis and Reaction Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Membrane Science</discipline>
<discipline>Process Control and Systems</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Biomass conversion to hydrocarbon fuels requires significant amounts of hydrogen. Fossil resources typically supply hydrogen via steam reforming. A new technology called microbial electrolysis cells (MECs) has emerged which can generate hydrogen from organic sources and biomass. The thermochemical route to fuels via pyrolysis generates bio-oil aqueous phase (BOAP) which can be used to make hydrogen. A process engineering and economic analysis of this technology was conducted for application in biorefineries of the future. Steam methane reforming, bio-oil separation and microbial electrolysis unit operations were simulated in Aspen Plus to derive the mass and energy balance for conversion of biomass. A process scheme using MEC to generate hydrogen, while minimizing use of natural gas was developed. A process design developed by Pacific Northwest National Laboratory was used as baseline biorefinery flowsheet. The results show that hydrogen production at a rate of 1,723 lb/hr can be derived using 19.5 % of the bio-oil as the substrate BOAP, while eliminating the need for natural gas. A two-step quench system allows separation of an aqueous stream containing about 23,000 lb/hr of organic substrate, sufficient for hydrogen generation, besides that generated from off-gas, so as to meet the total biorefinery hydrogen needs. The techno-economic analysis (TEA) showed that hydrogen can be generated for a minimum hydrogen selling price of $ 3.35/kg-H₂. The results of this study show that hydrogen can be practically derived from an aqueous soluble bio-oil stream, while majority of the bio-oil is used for hydrocarbon production, using a wholly biomass-sourced hydrogen. This alternative has potential to reduce greenhouse gas emissions from the biorefinery.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4914</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5832&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4914</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5832</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-24T11:25:44-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/5832/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9745477</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4914</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Abhijeet Borole</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert M. Counce, Sankar V. Raghavan, Paul D. Frymier</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>