<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Population Dynamics of the Louisiana Black Bear in the Upper Atchafalaya River Basin</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>koconne4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>O&#39;Connell</lname>
<fname>Kaitlin</fname>
<mname>Christine</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>mark-recapture</keyword>
<keyword>multi-state</keyword>
<keyword>Louisiana</keyword>
<keyword>black bear</keyword>
<keyword>population dynamics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Louisiana black bear (&lt;em&gt;Ursus americanus luteolus) &lt;/em&gt;is listed as Threatened under the Endangered Species Act as a result of habitat loss and human-related mortality. Two of the 3 sub-populations must be viable for delisting to occur. I collected hair samples from 2010 to 2012 in a DNA mark-recapture study to augment data collected from 2007 to 2009 in the Upper Atchafalaya River Basin (UARB) to estimate abundance (&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;), growth rate (λ), and apparent survival rates (φ)&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;to ultimately be used in a population viability analysis. In addition, I evaluated the effects of the opening of the Morganza Spillway in 2011 which flooded &gt;50% of the UARB study area. I used a Multi-state model to estimate changes in transition rates (ψ) from the flooded area to non-flooded area before (2007–2010), during (2011), and after (2012) the flooding event. Finally, I evaluated a 2-wire hair sampling system that was implemented in 2010 to increase capture probabilities (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) for males. Average &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; from 2010 to 2012 was 62.1 (SE = 3.6) and averaged across all years of study (2007–2012) &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; was 57.6 (SE = 2.2), excluding the year of the flooding event. Population growth rate indicated an increasing population, averaging λ = 1.11 across all 6 years of the study and mean φ was 0.83 (SE = 0.01). Estimates of ψ from the flooded to non-flooded areas increased slightly during the flood year indicating that some bears left the floodway but most did not. Apparent survival did not change for flooded or non-flooded areas during the period of flooding. Finally, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; for males increased and decreased for females as predicted for a wire effect, but models with constant &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; were more parsimonious. The 2-wire system increased capture probabilities but the effect was not significant. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2631</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2880&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2631</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2880</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-21T10:20:23-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2880/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4250244</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2631</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph D. Clark</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank T. van Manen, Arnold Saxton, Lisa Muller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>