<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Action as Essential Metaphysical Dependence</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Baker</lname>
<fname>Jordan</fname>
<mname>Timothy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>philosophy of action</keyword>
<keyword>non-causal</keyword>
<keyword>grounding</keyword>
<keyword>metaphysical dependence</keyword>
<keyword>emergence</keyword>
<keyword>agency</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;What makes an event &lt;i&gt;count&lt;/i&gt; as an action? The standard answer to this question—causalism—claims that if an event is caused &lt;i&gt;in the right way&lt;/i&gt; it counts as an action. Causal deviance objections, however, undermine the explanatory power of causalist accounts. Non-causal theories of action offer a promising alternative; however, they &lt;i&gt;also&lt;/i&gt; raise a myriad of difficulties. Many non-causal arguments against causalism unintentionally lead to dialectical stalemates, which are methodologically undesirable and should be avoided whenever possible. I offer a theory between these two inadequate accounts that synthesizes the strengths of non-causalism with insights from agent-causal theories. I agree with traditional non-causalist that action explanations cannot be causally reduced; however, I also agree with causal theories that an &lt;i&gt;extrinsic&lt;/i&gt; relation between the agent and the event makes the difference between mere events and actions. I call this account an “agency-first” theory of action since it neither reduces agency—as in causalism—nor does it ignore agency to focus on the intrinsic features of actions—as in non-causalism. Instead, I claim we must not lose sight of the &lt;i&gt;agent&lt;/i&gt; when analyzing action and thus posit the non-causal, yet extrinsic, relation of essential metaphysical dependence to explain action &lt;i&gt;in terms&lt;/i&gt; of agency without losing the distinctive character of either concept.To this end, I claim that &lt;i&gt;essential metaphysical dependence&lt;/i&gt; explains what makes an event count as an action by explaining how actions are grounded in agency. I first set-up the dialectic between causalists and non-causalists and raise objections to both views. I then describe the essential metaphysical dependence relation in detail and defend this account from several objections. Finally, the relation of dependence is commonly thought to be transitive, which entails a final significant objection—if actions depend on agency, and agency depends on non-agential forces, then actions are not &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; explained by dependence on agency. I argue, however, that plausible accounts of agency’s metaphysical emergence blocks the transitivity objection. I conclude that my agency-first theory adequately addresses what makes an event count as an action, while at the same time keeping the agent in view.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5345</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6881&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5345</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6881</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545340</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5345</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David Palmer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nora Berenstain, Eldon Coffman Jr., Bruce MacLennan</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5875-8135</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>