<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Does Sarbanes-Oxley Foster the Existence of Ethical Executive Role Models in the Corporation?</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sarbanes-Oxley</keyword>
<keyword>corporate governance</keyword>
<keyword>role model</keyword>
<keyword>ethics</keyword>
<keyword>corporate culture</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Ethics and Political Philosophy</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Ethics and Professional Responsibility</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;If  compliance with, or the efficacy of, Sarbanes-Oxley and other corporate  governance initiatives requires that executives (or other firm leaders)  be good ethical role models, then it is important to ask whether  Sarbanes-Oxley - or any other attribute of existing corporate governance  regulation - in fact promotes or permits the production or preservation  of ethical role models in the executive ranks of public companies. An  absence of support for ethical role models in public companies may  signal the failure of broad-based federal corporate governance  initiatives like Sarbanes-Oxley. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;This Article assumes that  ethical roles models may be important to the maintenance of good  corporate governance (in general) and the success of Sarbanes-Oxley as a  corporate governance initiative (in specific). With that in mind, the  Article preliminarily analyzes, using legal and social sciences  literature, whether Sarbanes-Oxley may encourage or discourage the  existence of ethical role models in the corporation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/15</coverpage-url>
<label>15</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T09:30:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035209</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/15</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Does Sarbanes-Oxley Foster the Existence of Ethical Executive Role Models in the Corporation?. Journal of Business &amp; Technology Law, Vol. 3, p. 221, 2008; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 33. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1130647</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1130647</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>