<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Student-Athlete Awareness of Athletic Career Transition and Transferable Skills</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mwoods34@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Woods</lname>
<fname>Michelle</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>student-athlete</keyword>
<keyword>awareness</keyword>
<keyword>intercollegiate athletics</keyword>
<keyword>transferable</keyword>
<keyword>skills</keyword>
<keyword>transition</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Sports Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to measure student-athlete’s awareness of transferable skills, identify what skills are most transferable, and identify the resources available to aid student-athletes in the transition from athletic career retirement to a non-athletic career setting. A modified version of McKnight’s (2007) survey was used to collect data regarding student-athlete awareness of career transition and transferable skills. One hundred and sixty student-athletes participated in the survey, which was comprised of three parts: (a) transferable skills, (b) career transition, and (c) demographic information. A quantitative approach utilized descriptive statistics to identify student-athlete’s awareness of transferable skills, the most frequently reported transferable skills, and the resources that aid in the acquirement of transferable skills and transition from athletic career retirement to a non-athletic career setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theoretical framework of the Model of Transition (Schlossberg, 1981) and Life Development Intervention (LDI) (Mayocchi and Hanrahan, 2000) was used to explain the factors that influence transition and role of transferable skills while transitioning out of sport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings are consistent with previous research stated in the literature, indicating student-athletes are highly aware of transferable skills. The student-athletes who participated in this study also determined strong work ethic as the most frequently reported transferable skill. Family members and athletics department personnel such as coaches and student-athlete development staff were identified as the most useful resources for aiding in the acquirement of transferable skills and transition from athletic career retirement to a non-athletic career setting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4790</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5790&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4790</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5790</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-23T13:06:48-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9740069</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4790</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James Bemiller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robin Hardin, Sylvia Trendafilova</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>