<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Influence of Dietary Calcium to Phosphorus Ratio on Bone Density of Vegetarian and Non-Vegetarian Older Women</title>
<publication-date>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davis</lname>
<fname>Teresa</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study were: to investigate the influence of dietary calcium, dietary phosphorus, and their ratios as observed in vegetarian and non-vegetarian subjects on their bone densities and to compare bone density, the dietary intakes of calcium and of phosphorus, and the ratio of calcium to phosphorus in vegetarian and non-vegetarian subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After obtaining informed consent, data were collected on 43 vegetarian and 36 non-vegetarian women, 40 to 92 years old, who consumed self-selected diets. Dietary information was obtained from 7-day dietary records. Dietary supplements were also recorded. Measurements of height, weight, and bone density of the radius, ulna, and finger were made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nutrient intakes were calculated by computer using food composition values from U.S.D.A. Handbook Nos. 456 and 8 and information obtained from Worthington and Loma Linda Foods. Bone density values of the radius and ulna were obtained using a bone mineral analyzer developed by Norland-Cameron Company. A bone densitometer developed by the Department of Nutrition, The University of Tennessee, was used to determine bone density of the finger (left phalanx 5-2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mean age of 57.1 years in the vegetarian group (Veg) was not significantly different from that of 58.8 years in the non-vegetarian group (Non-veg) (P &gt; 0.05). There was no significant difference in weight (Veg = 137.7 lb.; Non-veg = 141.6 lb.) and in height (Veg = 63.5 in; Non-veg = 63.5 in) between groups· (P &gt; 0.05). Mean values for height and weight were not significantly different between the Veg and Non-veg groups when adjusted for the mean age of both groups (57.9 years). There was a significant decrease in height with age but not weight with age in both groups. The differences in decreased height with age between groups was not statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mean calcium and phosphorus intakes from food (Ca = 1017 mg; P = 1325 mg) and from food plus supplements (Ca = 1106 mg; P = 1346 mg) in the Veg group surpassed the RDA. In the Non-veg group, the phosphorus intakes from food (1114 mg) and from food plus supplements (1131 mg) were greater than the RDA. The RDA for calcium was also met from food plus supplements (838 mg) but not from food alone (784 mg) in the Non-veg group. There was a tendency for a decrease in calcium and phosphorus intakes with age in both groups. When the intakes were either adjusted or unadjusted for age, the Veg group generally consumed significantly greater amounts of calcium and phosphorus from food alone and from food plus supplements than did the Non-veg group. The calcium to phosphorus ratios from food (Veg = 0.74; Non-veg = 0.70) and from food plus supplements (Veg = 0.78; Non-veg = 0.72) unadjusted and adjusted for age were not significantly different between groups. No significant relationship between the calcium to phosphorus ratio and age in both groups was obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no significant difference in the mean bone density measurements of the radius, ulna, and finger between the Veg and Non-veg groups unadjusted and adjusted for the mean age of both groups. A highly significant negative correlation between bone densities of the radius, ulna, and finger and age was obtained (P &lt; 0.0005). There was no significant difference in the slopes of the regression lines of bone density of the radius on age between Veg and Non-veg groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both the Veg and Non-veg groups, there was a significant positive correlation between bone density of the radius and height, and also between bone density of the radius and weight. However, when adjusted for age, these correlations were not statistically significant. There were also no significant differences in the slopes of the regression lines of bone density on height and bone density on weight between Veg and Non-veg groups unadjusted and adjusted for age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Veg group, the phosphorus intake from food alone was positively related to bone density of the radius. Regression coefficients on other nutrient intakes were non-significant in the Veg group. In the Non-veg group, there was a significant positive relationship between bone density and the intakes of calcium and phosphorus from food and also the intakes of calcium, phosphorus, and their ratio from food plus supplements. When adjusted for the influence of age, however, there was no significant correlation between bone density of the radius and each of the nutrient intakes of both groups. The slopes of the regression lines for bone density on the calcium intake and the calcium to phosphorus ratio from food plus supplements were significantly different between groups. There were no significant differences between any of the regression lines of bone density on nutrient intake between Veg and Non-veg groups adjusted for age.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4111</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5518&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4111</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5518</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-30T08:36:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9214995</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4111</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Roy E. Beauchene</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Rossie L. Mason, Ada Marie Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>