<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Study Of Mechanical Behaviors and Structures of Bulk Metallic Glasses with High-energy Synchrotron X-Ray Diffraction</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>fjiang3@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jiang</lname>
<fname>Feng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Bulk metallic glass</keyword>
<keyword>amorphous</keyword>
<keyword>mechanical behavior</keyword>
<keyword>structure</keyword>
<keyword>x-ray</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Metallurgy</discipline>
<discipline>Other Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation addresses two critical issues in the mechanical behaviors and structures of bulk-metallic glasses (BMGs): (1) the effect of composition, fabrication method, and pretreatment of plastic deformation on mechanical properties and structures of BMGs; (2) the mechanical response and structural evolution of BMGs in the elastic and plastic region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Cu&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;Zr&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;94&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; and (Cu&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;Zr&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;92&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; amorphous alloys were used to study the effect of composition on mechanical properties and structures of BMGs. The (Cu&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;Zr&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;94&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; alloy exhibits lower yield stress and Young’s modulus, higher Poisson’s ratio, worse thermal stability, and better plasticity than (Cu&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;Zr&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;92&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;. Both the topological and chemical effects of Al addition account for the differences of mechanical and physical properties between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Zr&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;Ni&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;30&lt;/sub&gt; glass-forming alloy with injection casting (the melting temperatures are 1,550 K and 1,250 K, respectively) and with suction casting was fabricated. The results indicate that despite their amorphous structures, the suction-casting samples exhibit a lower yield stress, lower Young’s modulus, and larger plastic strain than the injection-casting samples (the melting temperature is 1,550 K) due to more quenched-in free volumes in suction casting, which results from the higher cooling rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inhomogeneous plastic deformation in Zr&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;40&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;BMG samples was introduced by four-point-bend fatigue. There is almost no difference of the stress-strain behaviors between the deformed and undeformed samples. Elastostatic compression was used to introduce homogeneous deformation in Zr&lt;sub&gt;70&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;Ni&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; BMG samples.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;The preloaded samples are softer with decreases of yield strength and Young’s moduli. Anisotropy was observed in the preloaded samples despite their small magnitudes, which even occurred at a relatively low temperature and applied stress level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structural evolution of Zr&lt;sub&gt;70&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;Ni&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8 &lt;/sub&gt;BMG in the elastic region was analyzed with anisotropic pair density function. The analysis of the first shell of Zr&lt;sub&gt;70&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;Ni&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; glass confirms the structural changes in the elastic region. The bond reorientation leads to direction dependent changes in the chemical short-range order. The structural evolution in the plastic region of Zr&lt;sub&gt;70&lt;/sub&gt;Cu&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;Ni&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;Al&lt;sub&gt;8 &lt;/sub&gt;BMG is investigated as well. The serrations were observed for both the stress-displacement and full width at half maximum-displacement curves. The excess free volume was measured, which increases with increasing the displacement.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1049</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2183&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1049</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2183</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-10T09:19:11-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2183/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2008168</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1049</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hahn Choo, Takeshi Egami, John D. Landes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>