<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Women and the Environment: Mediating and Moderating Effects of Gender and Demographic Characteristics of Environmental Concern</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cprice14@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Price</lname>
<fname>Carmel</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Environmental sociology</keyword>
<keyword>environmental concern</keyword>
<keyword>ecogender</keyword>
<keyword>environmental demography</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Place and Environment</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study I examine the relationship between environmental attitudes and gender.  First, I explore variations across previous studies to determine patterns regarding gender differences in levels of environmental concern. Second, I look at the mediating effects of gender and several socio-demographic characteristics (age, race, class, education, political orientation, residence, martial status, number of children, religious identification, and scientific knowledge) on a variety of measures of environmental concern to assess the extent to which gender operates through other variables as it predicts levels of environmental concern. Third, I look at the moderating effects of gender on the same list of socio-demographic characteristics to determine the extent to which gender intersects with other variables to shape environmental attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I conduct a systematic review of literature using 22 peer reviewed journal articles, which include 128 measures of environmental concern, published between 1995 and 2010. I also test for mediating and moderating effects of gender and various socio-demographic characteristics on 14 measures of environmental concern using data from two sources: the General Social Survey Environment II: 2000 questionnaire and the American National Election Study 2008 Times Series Pre-election Survey. To test for mediating and moderating effects I employee several methodological techniques including principal component analysis, model building, linear regression techniques, and non-parametric regression methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this study show that, in general, women do express a greater concern for the environment than men. However, gender in conjunction with other socio-demographic characteristics has the potential to produce different effects than when gender is considered alone. This study supports the idea that the intersectionality of gender and other socio-demographic characteristics is of great importance and should not be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1116</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2197&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1116</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2197</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-25T10:29:01-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2197/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2030628</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1116</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stephanie A. Bohon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert E. Jones, R. Scott Frey, Damayanti Banerjee, Priscilla Blanton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>