<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Phylogenetic systematics and zoogeography of the nearctic members of the minnow genus Phoxinus (Cyprinidae: Cypriniformes) with a description of a new species from the Tennessee River drainage, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Skelton</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>Eugene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Questions regarding the taxonomy and systematics of the Nearctic Phoxinus (Cyprinidae: Cypriniformes) were investigated in this study. First, a new member of the genus, Laurel Dace, was described from the Tennessee River drainage, Tennessee. This distinctive minnow is one of seven described North American Phoxinus species and one of four that occurs in Tennessee. It differs from all congeners by having the combination of two uninterrupted black lateral stripes, and development of black pigment on the underside of the head of nuptial males. Based on coloration and tuberculation patterns, the Laurel Dace is hypothesized to be part of a monophyletic group comprised of P. areas, P. tennesseensis, and P. cumber/andensis. The Laurel Dace appears to be very rare; it is currently known from only six localities on the Walden Ridge portion of the Cumberland Plateau. Human activities such as coal mining, agriculture, and timbering threaten its future existence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6435</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8409&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6435</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8409</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075109</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6435</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Etnier, Thomas G. Hallam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Arthur C. Echternacht, Gary F. McCracken, Paul W. Parmalee</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>