<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Teachers&#39; Attitudes and Perceptions of Multicultural and Diversity Awareness in Elementary Schools</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>James</lname>
<fname>Joy</fname>
<mname>Lynne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine how teachers perceived teaching multicultural students and their own training toward teaching multicultural children. The aim of this study was to determine whether to what extent those perceptions could be attributed to teacher training, multicultural curriculum, and teacher attitudes and perceptions of multicultural and diversity awareness. The research design included a quantitative inquiry. A questionnaire was given to 50 elementary teachers from 5 schools who taught second and fifth grade. The questionnaire attempted to measure teachers attitudes and perceptions of cultural and diversity awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While teachers&#39; general attitudes toward cultural diversity were positive, this study revealed that teachers&#39; felt that they were insufficient with pre-service experiences and training to work with culturally diverse students. They also felt that in-service training was insufficient in this area. Teachers showed a desire to provide experiences for their students to help them understand multicultural studies. Considering the increasing emphasis on working with multicultural populations worldwide, there is only a modest amount of research dealing with the preparation of teachers in this area. The recommendations for additional research addressed this issue. Among the recommendations, the researcher suggested further study related to teachers&#39; attitudes and perceptions of multicultural and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3041</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4475&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3041</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4475</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-28T08:04:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6296289</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3041</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Thomas Noel Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Asafa Jalata, Dr. Lester Knight</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Teacher Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>