<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mental Health among Afro-centric people; Every piece is vital to the puzzle</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-12T15:06:49-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>drjason.stubbs@hotmail.com</email>
<lname>Stubbs</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Mental Health</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Community Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The workshop will discuss the state of mental health in general amongst minority groups in particular black afro-centric people. The workshop will present the problem that still exist regarding health care for minority groups and focus in on mental health. Participants will engage in the issue of mental health from the lack of information and understanding of mental illness, The God/Faith factor, the reluctance and inability of the people to engage and access care. The workshop will integrate the old concept of the village having a vital part in the cultivation of the mental state of afro-centric people and how each person in the village is a valuable and vital part of the mental well being of each member of the village. Just as a puzzle has pieces that are uniquely shaped and made coupled with the intricate process of pairing with the other puzzle pieces, in the end it will make the masterpiece. If the value of unity and finding the fit one with another is realized it will strengthen the social fabric that will influence the mental health of the community. This will take participants on a journey of the afro-centric people from denial, deflection and decision regarding mental health drawing on research statistics and information and evidence based resources and solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1252&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1252</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-06T13:22:28-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1252/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16120041</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jason Stubbs, was born and raised in Nassau Bahamas and enjoys spending quality time with family and friends. Dr. Stubbs has a lifelong desire to keep learning and growing as a leader, coach and trainer. He lives by the quote of his world renown mentor Dr. Myles Munroe that says “The greatest tragedy in life is not death but to have lived a life without fulfilling your purpose.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a professional he is a certified human behavior consultant, Certified with the John Maxwell team as a speaker, coach and trainer. Numerous academic degrees but most of all he has a love for people and seeing them identify develop and fulfill their full life’s potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree. Jason continued his educational pursuit and completed his first Doctor of Philosophy with an emphasis in Adolescent Psychology. Jason has a passion and love for education completed his second Doctoral degree in Leadership &amp; Administration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason is Certified Human Behavior Consultant with the ability to perform DISC assessments with individuals and teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason is a Certified John Maxwell Coach, Teacher and Speaker with the world renowned Dr. John Maxwell. Jason is currently completing his certification as a Talent Management specialist through HRM (Human Resource Management) He currently serves as Pastor of Leadership Development (Talent Management Specialist) at a local church in Knoxville TN.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Monitor</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will practice specific knowledge regarding the state of mental health among minorities specifically African Americans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will leave with tangible resources for future reference, including community participation and engagement in mental wellness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will gain knowledge in basic mental health awareness and identification for intervention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participants will evaluate the strengths and challenges of their personal beliefs regarding mental health stigma, well-being, and intervention as a community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The theme of breaking the cycle of a people divided in that it will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) address the stigma of Mental Health in the Black community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Present practical tools on how to be a vital part of the mental health of the community whether it is family, friends or colleagues&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) Presenting the value in communal engagment regarding mental well-being &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>