<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effect of midazolam on end-tidal concentration of isoflurane necessary to prevent movements in dogs</title>
<publication-date>2011-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mrsed@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Seddighi</lname>
<fname>Reza</fname>
<suffix>DVM, MS, PhD, Dip ACVA</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anesthesiology</discipline>
<discipline>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Objective To determine the possible additive effect of midazolam, a GABAA agonist, on the end-tidal concentration of isoflurane that prevents movement (MACNM) in response to noxious stimulation.   Study design Randomized crossover experimental study.  Animals Six, healthy, adult intact male, mixed-breed dogs.  Methods After baseline isoflurane MACNM (MACNM-B) determination, midazolam was administered as a low (LDS), medium (MDS) or high (HDS) dose series of midazolam. Each series consisted of two dose levels, low and high. The LDS was a loading dose (Ld) of 0.2 mg kg-1 and CRI (2.5 μg kg-1 minute-1) (LDL), followed by an Ld (0.4 mg kg-1) and CRI (5 μg kg-1 minute-1) (LDH). The MDS was an Ld (0.8 mg kg-1) and CRI (10 μg kg-1 minute-1) (MDL) followed by an Ld (1.6 mg kg-1) and CRI (20 μg kg-1 minute-1) (MDH). The HDS was an Ld (3.2 mg kg-1) and CRI (40 μg kg-1 minute-1) (HDL) followed by an Ld (6.4 mg kg-1) and CRI (80 μg kg-1 minute-1) (HDH). MACNM was re-determined after each dose in each series (MACNM-T).  Results The median MACNM-B was 1.42. MACNM-B did not differ among groups (p &gt; 0.05). Percentage reduction in MACNM was significantly less in the LDS (11 ± 5%) compared with MDS (30 ± 5%) and HDS (32 ± 5%). There was a weak correlation between the plasma midazolam concentration and percentage MACNM reduction (r = 0.36).  Conclusion and clinical relevance Midazolam doses in the range of 10-80 μg kg-1 minute-1 significantly reduced the isoflurane MACNM. However, doses greater than 10 μg kg-1 minute-1 did not further decrease MACNM indicating a ceiling effect.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>195</fpage>
<lpage>202</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/94</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1093&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>94</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1093</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-22T12:20:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>3781178</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/94</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Veterinary Anesthesia and Analgesia</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>