<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Crystal Growth and Physical Property Characterization of Complex Perovskite Oxides</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lli35@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Ling</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Crystal growth</keyword>
<keyword>structural phase transition</keyword>
<keyword>elastic moduli</keyword>
<keyword>magnetic property</keyword>
<keyword>physical property</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Ceramic Materials</discipline>
<discipline>Condensed Matter Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Bulk EuTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; [europium titanate], a quantum paraelectric antiferromagnet, is shown to exhibit multiferroic behavior in strained thin film form, which highlights the spin-phonon coupling in this system. We have investigated the structural, elastic, magnetic, thermal and transport properties of single crystals of EuTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; as well as doped system EuTi&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;B&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (B = Zr, Nb) [Zr and Nb doped europium titanate] utilizing various experimental techniques and theoretical calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cubic to tetragonal structural transition in pure EuTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; is characterized by a pronounced step-like softening of the elastic moduli near 288 K [kelvin], which resembles that of SrTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; [strontium titanate] and can be adequately modeled using the Landau free energy model employing the same coupling between strain and octahedral tilting order parameter as previously used to model SrTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Zr doping pushes the antiferromagnetic transition to lower temperatures while maintaining the insulating behavior. Intriguingly, Nb doping shifts the structural phase transition in EuTiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; to higher temperatures, accompanied by a weakening of octahedral tilting. Furthermore, Nb doping destabilizes the antiferromagnetic ground state of the parent compound and long range ferromagnetic order is observed in the samples containing more than 5% Nb, which is most likely accounted for in terms of the ferromagnetic interaction between localized Eu 4&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; spins mediated by itinerant electrons introduced by Nb doping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have also investigated the magnetoelastic coupling eect in 5d Re-based double perovskites Ba&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;FeReO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; [barium two iron rhenium oxygen six] and Ca&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;FeReO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; [calcium two iron rhenium oxygen six]. A large softening in C&lt;sub&gt;44&lt;/sub&gt; [shear modulus] over a wide temperature range is observed for Ba&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;FeReO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; below its Curie temperature, which is indicative of a structural distortion. For Ca&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;FeReO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;, both the longitudinal and shear modulus show a softening starting at 160 K. In addition, magnetoelastic coupling constants have been estimated from elastic constants and magnetostriction data, which provide direct evidence of pronounced coupling between magnetism and the lattice degrees of freedom present in both compounds.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3437</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4875&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3437</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4875</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-12T15:12:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7212251</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3437</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Veerle M. Keppens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David G. Mandrus, Haidong Zhou, Mariya Zhuravleva</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>