<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Save Martha Stewart? Observations About Equal Justice in U.S. Insider Trading Regulation</title>
<publication-date>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Insider Trading</keyword>
<keyword>Equal Justice</keyword>
<keyword>Enforcement Discretion</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Jurisprudence</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Gender</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Politics</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Ethics and Professional Responsibility</discipline>
<discipline>Other Feminist, Gender, and Sexuality Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Martha  Stewart is the subject of a civil enforcement action alleging  violations of U.S. securities laws and regulations governing insider  trading. The facts, as we now know them, suggest that the considerable  governmental resources spent in pursuit of Martha Stewart (which are out  of proportion to the apparent financial magnitude of any illegal  trading activity) result from an express decision to single her out for  potential criminal prosecution or civil enforcement based on some  personal characteristic or characteristics. After describing the basic  structure of insider trading regulation in the United States, this paper  identifies potential structural sources of selective enforcement in the  regulation of insider trading and isolates certain easily recognizable  bases for enforcement bias in the application of that regulation, using  the Martha Stewart insider trading investigation as an example.  Ultimately, the paper recommends more rigorous investigation into  possible sources of selectivity and bias in insider trading enforcement  and offers preliminary suggestions for ways in which the identified  potential for bias may be obviated or overcome, consistent with the  current federal regulatory and political environment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/26</coverpage-url>
<label>26</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1034</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-01T14:04:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2042263</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/26</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Save Martha Stewart? Observations About Equal Justice in U.S. Insider Trading Regulation. Texas Journal of Women and the Law, Vol. 12, No. 247, 2003. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=489005</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=489005</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>