<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nutrition Field Observations and Experiences in the State of New Mexico</title>
<publication-date>1969-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McRae</lname>
<fname>Vera</fname>
<mname>Geraldine</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report describes and analyzes the observations and experiences of the author during eight weeks of field experience with the Nutrition Consultant in the Maternal and Child Health Section, New Mexico Health and Social Services Department. The field experience provided an opportunity for the application of theories and principles to the actual practice of public health nutrition while working under the supervision of a nutritionist. The experience was designed to strengthen the author&#39;s understanding of public health by furthering her knowledge of the practice of public health in the community, of the role of nutrition within these public health programs and within the community, and of the functions of a public health nutritionist. The author observed and participated in the nutrition program within the health agency as well as with other community agencies and professional groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience provided the author with an overview of the public health program within the state of New Mexico, the role of nutrition in the program, and an opportunity to observe and participate in activities with the nutritionists and other health personnel. Her understanding of the role of the public health nutritionist within the total health program was strengthened by the opportunity for observing the different ways in which health agencies strive to meet the nutritional needs of the population. Observation of another nutritionist&#39;s methods of providing services effectively demonstrated to the author that there is no one method that is right in every situation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3840</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5316&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3840</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5316</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-10T12:49:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8959104</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3840</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roy E. Beauchene, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1969-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1969-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>