<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Case for an Aerial Refueling Capability for the United States Marine Corps UH-1Y Helicopter</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Suckow</lname>
<fname>Scott</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aviation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this thesis is to generate interest discussion, examination and ultimately installation of in-flight refueling capability on the UH-1Y, to enhance the utility of the UH-1Y in support of Marine Corps strategic and operational concepts.  Material presented herein was acquired from numerous reference documents and publications to include aircraft flight manuals; tactics, techniques and procedures manuals; program office documents; contractor literature; and the author’s experiences as a Fleet Marine Force UH-1N pilot.  Air-to-Air Refueling (AAR) systems are presented using currently fielded equipment in both tested and untested configurations, incorporating empirical data, tactics and past experiences.  The resultant conclusions to the data, as presented, clearly indicate the need and highlight the intrinsic value of AAR at the strategic and operational level in order to maximize capability and efficiently support the strategic and operational requirements of the Marine Corps.  Additionally there is an obvious tactical level utility of the system for an air-to-air refueling mission kit for the UH-1Y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2000, then Commandant of the Marine Corps, General James L. Jones, outlined his vision for how the Corps should be organized, equipped, and prepared to fight and win conflicts in &lt;em&gt;USMC 21. &lt;/em&gt; In October 2001, then Chief of Naval Operations, Admiral Vernon Clark, outlined his vision for how the USN and USMC should work together to organize, integrate, equip, and transform their forces to meet the emerging threats of the future in &lt;em&gt;Sea Power 21.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis will examine the larger scope and scale of how this AAR capability can better support this Marine Air Ground Task Force within the operational, tactical and strategic visions of &lt;em&gt;USMC 21 &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Sea Power 21 &lt;/em&gt;requirements.  USMC rotary wing assets still have a few aircraft that are not AAR capable.  As long as the Marine Corps have even one aircraft that can’t air-to-air refuel, it is limited by a most restricted capability and must continue to rely on land and sea based facilities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4491</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6017&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4491</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6017</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-12T11:31:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10011232</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4491</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George W. Masters, U. Peter Solies</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>