<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Gene Expression Analysis of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 at 10 and 37°C and Under Acidic Conditions Using High Density Oligonucleotide Microarrays</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carter</lname>
<fname>Kristina</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This purpose of this investigation was to use DNA microarrays to study gene expression in &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 under refrigerated and acidic conditions. Total RNA from &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 grown to 7 log CFU/mL under control (37 °C, pH 7), refrigerated (10°C, pH 7), acid adapted (37°C, pH 5.5, then lowered to 3.5), and acid shocked (37°C, pH 7, then lowered to 3.5) conditions was extracted using an optimized Qiagen RNeasy procedure. Total RNA was converted to cDNA, labeled, and hybridized onto an Affymetrix GeneChip® &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; Genome 2.0 Array. Results were analyzed using Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) and a t-test with significance set at p&lt;0.01 and an expression cut-off of 2-fold difference in gene expression. Expression of selected genes, including an internal control (&lt;em&gt;hemX&lt;/em&gt;) was confirmed using real time reverse transcriptase PCR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microarray results revealed 293 down-regulated and 375 up-regulated genes. Cold shock genes &lt;em&gt;cspE, cspA, cspG,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cspH&lt;/em&gt; were down-regulated; &lt;em&gt;recA&lt;/em&gt; and SOS DNA repair genes &lt;em&gt;uvrB, yebG, ruvA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B, lexA,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dinl&lt;/em&gt; were up-regulated. Expression of &lt;em&gt;fhuA&lt;/em&gt; (outer membrane protein) and &lt;em&gt;napG&lt;/em&gt; (electron transport) genes was 115- and 70-fold greater under refrigeration. Microarray analysis revealed that genes involved in DNA binding, biosynthesis, iron, transport and cellular metabolism were significantly up-or down-regulated in acid adapted cells. Genes related to iron uptake and transport (&lt;em&gt;cyo, ent, fhu, fep,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;feo&lt;/em&gt; operons) were up-regulated under acid shocked conditions. For acid adapted conditions, expression of &lt;em&gt;cfa&lt;/em&gt; (cyclopropane fatty acid biosynthesis; decreases membrane fluidity and increases acid resistance) and genes involved in the glutamate decarboxylase acid resistant systems were significantly up-regulated. The virulence genes eae, stx1, and stx2 were not differentially expressed under either condition.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/134</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1180&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>134</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1180</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-27T10:27:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1123237</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/134</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael Davidson, Doris D’Souza, Todd Reynolds, Arnold Saxton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/CarterKristina.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>