<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Exploring the Effectiveness of Online Instructional Technology in Higher Education: Professors’ Perspective</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T19:16:21-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gshaw@mailbox.sc.edu</email>
<institution>University of South Carolina - Columbia</institution>
<lname>Shaw</lname>
<fname>George</fname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Science and Technology Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Technology has drastically changed the landscape of how, when, and where we can access information.  As a result of technological advancements, delivery methods for classroom lectures has also change.  In higher education, 21st century technology allows professors to deliver lectures face-to-face or online and synchronous or asynchronous within the online education environment.  This pilot study interviewed four faculty members and one instructor at a major university in South Carolina in a one-on-one interview session to explore the effectiveness of online instructional technology.  Understanding how open source software help professors make online instructional technology more conducive to the learning and knowledge process, in addition to what factors make online instructional technology within the online educational environment effective, were the focus of this study.  Preliminary results from content analysis show more emphasis needs to be placed on the choice of technology for each class taught, every semester. Five  themes were identified from this pilot study. The pilot study has shown a need for further investigation in online instructional technology and its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/poster/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1055&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1055</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-14T19:23:32-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1055/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2405235</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/poster/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>