<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Antecedents and Consequences of Supply Chain Resilience: A Dynamic Capabilities Perspective</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sponomar@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Ponomarov</lname>
<fname>Serhiy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>supply chain resilience</keyword>
<keyword>dynamic capabilities</keyword>
<keyword>supply chain capital</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Supply chain resilience is a comparatively unexplored area of supply chain research, that is related to risk management, but at the same time differs from traditional risk management approaches in that it focuses on firms’ ability to absorb disruptions or enables the supply network to return to stable conditions faster. The increased risks that are the result of complex and geographically disperse global supply chains necessitate that companies gain a better theoretical understanding of this emerging critical topic in order to be sustainable in the long term and effectively operate in turbulent business environment. Thus, a better understanding of supply chain resilience, its major antecedents and consequences is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employing a multi-disciplinary approach, this dissertation was exploring antecedents and value-based consequences of supply chain resilience from a firm perspective. A dynamic capabilities extension of the resource-based view was combined with several related theoretical perspectives to build a comprehensive conceptual framework filling the gaps in previous research. A combination of survey methodology and structural equation modeling was employed to collect and analyze the data drawing from a sample of supply chain and logistics managers. Quantitative data analysis resulted in significant theoretical and practical research implications. Finally, the directions for future research that have the potential to make a significant contribution to both business practice and academic research were proposed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1338</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2526&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1338</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2526</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-31T20:10:05-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2526/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2715992</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1338</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Collins Holcomb, Theodore P. Stank</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Chad W. Autry, Terry L. Esper, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>