<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Breaking the Cycle of Inequity in the Workplace</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-12T15:06:37-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>brittany@careerthrivers.com</email>
<institution>N/a</institution>
<lname>Cole</lname>
<fname>Brittany</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Other</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Business</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Forbes recently highlighted a new study by LeanIn.Org and McKinsey &amp; Co. which paints a troubling picture about the treatment of black women in the workplace. According to the Women in The Workplace 2018 survey, &quot;women of color are not only significantly underrepresented, they are far less likely than others to be promoted to manager, more likely to face everyday discrimination and less likely to receive support from their managers.&quot; This workshop will provide insights, resources and hands on exercises to help black talent create a strategic leadership development plan around their career brand in order to advance despite barriers in their career.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1251&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1251</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-31T09:03:38-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16095009</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Every experience is an opportunity for continuous improvement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brittany Cole lives by this motto as a speaker, coach and consultant that is passionate about equipping women and diverse millennials to thrive in the workplace!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to her corporate successes, Brittany has built Career Thrivers which is a leadership development firm that partners with organizations to help engage, develop and retain diverse talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a former sales and marketing leader at Pfizer, Brittany has experienced how intentional leadership development increases colleague engagement, accelerates career achievements and drives business results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brittany studied Political Science and Communications at The University of Tennessee, Knoxville and earned a certification in Strategies for Building and Leading Diverse Organizations from The Harvard Kennedy School of Public Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond her work with Career Thrivers, Brittany and her husband Joseph enjoy hiking, concerts and exploring their hometown of Nashville, TN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to bring a speaker to your organization that can engage and empower your audience with dynamic energy and polished execution then you are in the right place! Let’s thrive, together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more about Brittany, please view her video at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.careerthrivers.com/our-purpose&quot;&gt;https://www.careerthrivers.com/our-purpose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Please see attached file for a detailed overview of the 2 proposed workshops. To check out speaker reel videos or hear testimonials from clients I&#39;ve worked with, please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.careerthrivers.com/speaker&quot;&gt;https://www.careerthrivers.com/speaker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the difference between diversity, inclusion and equity in the workplace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify who they need to connect with in order to build a strategic network of career advisers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a plan to begin implementing to show up and add value from the classroom to the workplace in order to thrive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Both topics are directly related to the theme as they provide strategies for black students, black professional and allies to overcome inequities in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>