<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Congressional Campaigns of James K. Polk, 1824-1837</title>
<publication-date>1977-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jpukl@sc.rr.com</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pukl</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>James K. Polk</keyword>
<keyword>Tennessee history</keyword>
<keyword>Jacksonian era</keyword>
<keyword>Congressional campaigns</keyword>
<keyword>Tennessee Congressmen</keyword>
<keyword>United States Congress</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
<discipline>Political History</discipline>
<discipline>United States History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this thesis is to expose the actions of James K. Polk in his efforts to obtain a seat in the national House of Representatives. The narrative answers this general question: just what did Polk do to gain his initial victory (1825), and in his subsequent successful bids for office. What tactics did he and his opponents use? Was Polk the best candidate, or was he just a better politician? Did issues or personalities influence the election result? If issues, were they local, state, or national in nature, or a combination? And did these issues change over the years, either in their nature or substance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study covers Polk&#39;s seven Congressional campaigns and since both issues and candidates changed from year to year, a comprehensive set of specific conclusions cannot be drawn. Polk, as illustrated throughout this thesis, adjusted his strategy to suit his various opponents and to changing issues. Characteristic of all his campaigns, however, were speeches and printed circular letters, extensive travels, frequent use of the newspapers, and even various underhanded schemes. Polk undoubtedly used his incumbent status to win votes. He granted political favors, performed services, and franked mail into his district. All extant election results are included in tabular form and the results of a census study of Polk&#39;s district are revealed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3425</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4807&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3425</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4807</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-16T11:52:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7224048</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3425</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paul H. Bergeron</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>LeRoy P. Graf, Ralph W. Haskins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1977-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1977-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>