<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Revitalization Through Rehabilitation: Enhancing Communities Through Re-use</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jpimsler@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Pimsler</lname>
<fname>Jason Stuart</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>BeltLine</keyword>
<keyword>re-use</keyword>
<keyword>sustainability</keyword>
<keyword>architecture</keyword>
<keyword>planning</keyword>
<keyword>preservation</keyword>
<keyword>Goat Farm</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Historic Preservation and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The densification of an existing community through the implementation of sustainable design principles, such as adaptive reuse, promotes revitalization. The re-inhabitation of the proposed abandoned structure along the BeltLine can lead to further development of the existing arts complex. As part of this revitalization, linkages established along a citywide master-planned path provide nodal connections between the local art district and the artists of the Goat Farm and educate visitors of the significant industrial history of the area. The purpose of this thesis is to investigate the positive impact that sustainable architecture, adaptive reuse and proper planning can have on a community and the people who reside there. The goal of sustainable planning is to determine what a community is missing, then ultimately implementing a strategy that meets the needs of the people living in these areas. A successful strategy will employ the resources that already exist and use them in a beneficial and waste less wasteful manner. My hope is that by re-purposing existing historic structures that are vacant or under utilized, the improvements to the existing architecture will educate visitors about sustainable practices and promote collaboration amongst people.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1670</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2584&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1670</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2584</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-31T11:52:39-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3633044</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1670</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John S. Rabun</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer A. Akerman, Scott W. Wall</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>