<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of Administrative and Supervisory Practices Affecting the Induction and Orientation of Beginning Teachers</title>
<publication-date>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Breeding</lname>
<fname>Paul</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;) Despite the abundance of educational research, little material of outstanding significance is available on the relation of administration and supervision to the induction and adjustment of beginning teachers. While scattered materials are available, such as a few master&#39;s thesis, and occasional articles in periodicals, there seems no comprehensive study available dealing with this challenging problem in .American education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World War II, and particularly the years immediately following the War, have given vigorous impetus to this problem. This study seeks to analyze and synthesize the literature now available in many books, periodicals, and bulletins; and thus determine what should constitute acceptable administrative and supervisory practices in relation to the induction and adjustment of new teachers. It seeks to determine present practices in the secondary schools of Virginia, and to evaluate those practices in the light of criteria established as acceptable. Finally, recommendations for more effectively meeting the problem of induction and adjustment of new teachers in Virginia will be projected.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4393</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5885&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4393</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5885</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-07T07:39:16-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9801787</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4393</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>B. H. Story</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dale Wantling, Martin E. Little</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>