<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relationships of Self-Direction and Attitude toward Continuing Education in Community College Allied Health Programs</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jhenline@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hall</lname>
<fname>Julie</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>self-directed learning</keyword>
<keyword>self-direction</keyword>
<keyword>attitude toward continuing education</keyword>
<keyword>allied health</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Continuing education is a vital component in health care because professionals operate in a complex discipline that is continuously evolving. Ongoing social, technological, and medical changes present many trials and challenges to professionals in health care (Cadorin, Suter, Dante, Williamson, Devetti, &amp; Palese, 2012). Additionally, health care professionals who acknowledge continuing education as a lifelong exercise are well suited to remain well-informed of innovative developments (Cadorin et al., 2012; Evans, Gallatin, Taylor, &amp; Brodnik, 2008; El-Gilany &amp; Abusaad, 2013; Levett-Jones, 2005). In health care, self-directed learning can contribute to increased confidence, independence, inspiration, and growth of skills (O’Shea, 2003; Yuan et al., 2012). Individuals with the capability to be highly self-directed can utilize this to discern any level of personal weakness then work to rectify the deficiency (Avdal, 2013; Yuan et al., 2012).The study’s purpose was to explore relationships among self-directed learning and attitude toward continuing education among students participating in community college Allied Health programs. For this study, 113 students in Allied Health degree programs at a southeastern community college participated. Respondents completed Stockdale’s (2003) Personal Responsibility Orientation-Self Directed Learning Scale (PRO-SDLS), Blunt and Yang’s (2002) Revised Attitude toward Continuing Education Scale (RAACES), as well as answered two demographic questions (age and class rank).The results revealed that level of self-direction has a significant relationship between several factors and items related to attitude toward continuing education. One of the strongest findings was that participants with high levels of self-direction viewed adult education as a way to make better use of their lives. The information resulting from this study will enhance the current literature and allow for better understanding of self-directed learning principles and their relationship with attitude toward continuing education. Applying this information in Allied Health programs may have a substantial effect on how faculty facilitates self-directed learning principles in their area of study (El-Gilnay &amp; Abusaad, 2013). Future recommendations for research comprise of a duplication of the study using a more diverse and increased sample size across multiple community colleges and conducting other studies that would examine introducing self-directed learning principles into Allied Health programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5280</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6824&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5280</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6824</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T08:36:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>14342958</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5280</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kathleen C. Brown, Joel F. Diambra, Gary J. Skolits</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>