<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Preferences among White College Students Regarding Ethnicity of University Counseling Center Therapists</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jricha30@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Richardson</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>David</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Ethnic matching</keyword>
<keyword>University counseling center</keyword>
<keyword>Client prejudice</keyword>
<keyword>Personality</keyword>
<keyword>Client attrition</keyword>
<keyword>International therapists</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This 2-study research project explored whether the ethnicity of university counseling center therapists affects White clients’ therapy attendance rates and perception of counselors’ trustworthiness and level of expertise. Study 1 examined attendance rate differences of the clients of White therapists versus ethnic minority therapists in a university counseling center to determine if the minority therapists have lower client attendance rates than clients of White counselors. Study 2 examined White undergraduate participants’ ratings of profiles of White, African American and non-US Indian counselors portrayed in a mock university counseling center brochure on factors of trustworthiness and expertise. It also examined Big 5 personality traits as covariates to determine if the trait of Openness to Experience positively influences White participants’ ratings of ethnic minority therapists. Results for Study 1 showed that practicum-level ethnic minority trainees had significantly lower client attendance rates when compared with practicum level White therapists; no significant differences in client attendance rates were found among intern-level minority and White therapists. Study 2 found that non-US Indian counselors were rated more negatively than White or African American counselors by White participants. However, the trait of Openness did not show a significant interaction with ethnicity of counselor among participants. The article concludes with a discussion of the main findings, future research ideas, and practical implications for university counseling centers regarding assigning clients to ethnically/culturally different counselors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1120</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1819&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1120</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1819</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-17T18:39:20-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1819/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1315786</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1120</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brent S. Mallinckrodt</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael A. Olson, John W. Lounsbury, Asafa Jalata.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>