<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Survival and Flight Characteristics of Captive-Reared and Wild Northern Bobwhites in Texas</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:39:06-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Texas Parks and Wildlife Department</institution>
<lname>Perez</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas Parks and Wildlife Department</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Don</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas Parks and Wildlife Department</institution>
<lname>Gruen</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>direction of departure</keyword>
<keyword>first generation</keyword>
<keyword>flight speed</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>south Texas</keyword>
<keyword>survival</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introductions of captive-reared northern bobwhite (Colinus virginianus) to bolster native populations have been largely unsuccessful. We compared the survival and flight characteristics of game-farm (n 46), first-generation (F1) (n = 48), wild translocated (n = 45), and wild native (n = 50) northern bobwhites. In November 1993, all birds were radio-collared, leg banded, sexed, and aged. Birds were then released on a study area in Brooks County, Texas in groups of about 15, 1 bird at a time. Upon release, the direction of departure, speed, and time required to reach cover were recorded. The mean flight speed and distance flown for wild bobwhites was significantly greater (P &lt; 0.01) than captive-reared bobwhites. Wild native, wild translocated, and F1 groups were non-randomly distributed in direction of departure at release site (P &lt; 0.01). Survival of wild groups was significantly higher than captive-raised groups (P &lt; 0.05). The major cause of mortality in all groups was mammalian depredation. Fifteen F1 quail and 1 game-farm quail integrated into wild coveys. Our results re-confirm the inability of game-farm and first-generation northern bobwhites to survive in the wild, and we offer flight speed as one potential causal factor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol5/iss1/14</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1269&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>14</label>
<document-type>penreared_quail</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1269</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472016</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol5/iss1/14</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>