<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Calpain on the Degradation of Amyloid Beta (Aβ) Protein</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lu</lname>
<fname>Xin</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Abnormal accumulation of amyloid beta-peptide (A-beta) is believed to be the primary event in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer’s disease (AD). Two cellular mechanisms could contribute to the abnormal accumulation of Aβ in the brain: over production and/or failure in clearance of this A-beta peptide. In an effort to identify the cellular system that is involved in A-beta clearance, we conducted experiments to investigate the effects of calpain inhibitors on the production of secreted A-beta and the intracellular accumulated derivatives of APP, using a culture cell model. Our results revealed that at low concentration, calpain inhibitors caused an increase in the accumulation of both A-beta 40 and A-beta 42. At high concentration, calpain inhibitors led to a decline in A-beta accumulation toward the basal level and an increase in intracellular accumulation of C-terminal fragments, including CTF-beta, CTF-alpha, generated by beta– and alpha-cleavage, respectively. These results suggest that calpain enzymes, which are a highly conserved superfamily of calcium dependent papain-like cysteine proteases, are involved in the metabolism of APP and the formation and accumulation of A-beta. To further identify the enzyme(s) that is responsible for calpain inhibitor-regulated A-beta formation and accumulation, we employed the small interference RNA (siRNA) approach to investigate the effect of knockdown of calpains on the formation and accumulation of A-beta. Our results suggest that different isoforms of calpain enzymes may function differently in A-beta production and accumulation. This information may lead to a better understanding of the mechanism underlying the abnormal accumulation of A-beta peptide in the Alzheimer’s disease brain and provide new insight into the pathogenesis of this disease.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3655</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5002&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3655</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5002</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-10T10:28:18-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8124935</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3655</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Xuemin Xu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Meizhen Cui, Hildegard Schuller, Karla Matteson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>