<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Changes to Primary Education to Increase Postsecondary Hispanic Enrollment Rates in TN</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-19T07:48:33-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>smoses8@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Moses</lname>
<fname>Shelby</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Modern Languages</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In Tennessee, the Hispanic enrollment rate in higher education is statistically lower than other racial demographics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand the current demographics and to illustrate where the problem lies, this paper first focuses on the immigration, demographic, and postsecondary enrollment trends nationally as well as in Tennessee. By focusing on which ways primary education can better prepare Hispanic children for higher education, which in turn improves the long term postsecondary education enrollment, the paper centers on three general methods. These methods are providing specialized assistance within elementary schools for the children, providing home assistance for the families, and using community outreach methods to aid newly immigrated families with young children. Research showed these methods to have strong potential in improving early academic success that will lead to higher postsecondary enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2016/artsandsciences/8</coverpage-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1116</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-14T13:11:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>8478325</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2016/artsandsciences/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Modern Foreign Language and Literature</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Lisa Parker</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>