<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>St. George Tucker&#39;s Second Amendment: Deconstructing &quot;The True Palladium of Liberty&quot;</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-06T11:54:09-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Halbrook</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Bill of Rights, according to the above view, is designed to inform ordinary citizens of their rights. Its meaning is not a monopoly of the governmental entities whose powers the Bill of Rights was intended to limit. By knowing when their rights are violated, the citizens may signify their displeasure through mechanisms, such as the ballot box and the jury box, and may resort to speech, the press, assembly, and petition to denounce the evil. The Second Amendment &quot;right of the people to keep and bear Arms&quot; was intended to serve as the ultimate check, which the Founders hoped would dissuade people at the helm of state from seeking to establish tyranny.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol3/iss2/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1052&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1052</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-06T11:17:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5281133</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol3/iss2/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Attorney at Law, Fairfax, Va.; Ph.D. Florida State University, J.D. Georgetown University; former philosophy professor, Tuskegee University, Howard University, George Mason University. Books include A RIGHT TO BEAR ARMS: STATE AND FEDERAL BILLS OF RIGHTS AND CONSTITUTIONAL GUARANTEES (1989); FIREARMS LAW DESKBOOK (2007); FREEDMEN, THE FOURTEENTH AMENDMENT, AND THE RIGHT TO BEAR ARMS, 1866 -1876 (1998); THAT EVERY MAN BE ARMED: THE EVOLUTION OF A CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT (1984, 2000); THE FOUNDERS&#39; SECOND AMENDMENT (forthcoming). Argued Printz v. United States, 521 U.S. 898 (1997), and other Supreme Court cases. See further www.stephenhalbrook.com. © Copyright 2007 by Stephen P. Halbrook. All rights reserved. 2 ST. GEORGE TUCKER, View of the</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Palladium of Liberty</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>