<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Universality : exploring work value differences in the transitional economy of China</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Geren</lname>
<fname>Brenda</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The universality issue of work value differences is explored in this research study which takes place in the transitional economy of China. Chinese organizations are searching for new methods of management to compete in the global market, as former state-run enterprises convert to performance-based organizations. In addition, their entry into The World Trade Organization in 2001 will accelerate opportunities for foreign trade and investment, both for China and other countries as well. This transitional status presents a myriad of opportunities for researchers to analyze the universality of their methods, models and theories on both a micro (individual) and macro (cultural) level, as well as in the organizational context. This research, which is set in Shanghai, examined work value differences on the micro (individual) and macro (cultural) level through a factor analysis and comparison with U. S. data. A MANOVA analyzed demographic variables (managerial level (supervisory v. task, work tenure, educational level, gender and age) assessing various groups&#39; traits in an organizational environment. Finally, using these findings, the universality of motivation models was conceptually developed. The Chinese work values were found to be of a collective nature with the concern of the group as an end goal. No significant differences were found in the demographic variables on the work values as the Confucian tradition and guanxi roles play an important part in the organization. Because of these findings, Western motivation models are unlikely to be an effective approach, as they are directed toward an individualist end goal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6234</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8186&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6234</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8186</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450328</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6234</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James Moran III</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>