<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Education and the Black Community: What are we missing?</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-12T15:06:52-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>EvettyS@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Knox County Schools</institution>
<lname>Satterfield</lname>
<fname>Evetty</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>katherine.mencer@knoxschools.org</email>
<institution>Knox County Schools</institution>
<lname>Mencer</lname>
<fname>Katherine</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Education and the Black Community</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Assessment, Evaluation, and Research</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
<discipline>Urban Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Teachers of Color in the state of Tennessee comprise only 13% of overall teachers in the workforce*. As Tennessee&#39;s student body becomes increasingly diverse, recruiting and retaining teachers of color, as well as providing cultural relevant content, is paramount. This session will provide an interactive presentation that will allow community voices to shape education priorities among Black and Brown students in Knox County Schools. Led by Knox County School Board Member, Evetty Satterfield and 2018 Teacher of the Year, Katherine Mencer, participants will engage in an action lab. Action labs are problem solving platforms that engage citizens to create solutions for a specific issue. Teachers of Color shortage and culturally related content are two areas we will address in our lab. Best solutions to the issue will be shared with Knox County Schools Superintendent, Bob Thomas.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1233&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1233</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-17T12:27:54-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16026450</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evetty Satterfield &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A proud Knoxville native! She holds a Special Education degree from Alabama A&amp;M University and a Master of Social Work from Washington University in St. Louis. Evetty understands the importance of mastering your craft in order to serve your community with passion and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her short, yet fulfilled lifespan, Evetty has committed service years as a Founding Corps Member for City Year Denver and an Ella Baker Trainer for the Children’s Defense Fund - which has allowed her to continue to spread the movement by co-launching East Tennessee Freedom School in 2017. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evetty returned to Knoxville, TN after sharing her talents internationally as the Director of Student Services at Manor International in Abu Dhabi, UAE. She currently serves on the Knox County School Board and outside of her many responsibilities, she finds the most joy by mentoring emerging adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Katherine Mencer &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Accomplished Educator with 8 years’ experience; solid foundation in all curriculum areas and demonstrated leadership skills. Dedicated and devoted educator committed to the academic success of all students. Extensive training in educational strategies and intervention techniques for beginning and struggling readers and mathematicians. Self-motivated, goal oriented, and a strategic thinker that is capable of developing and accomplishing big picture objectives. Creates and sustains a supportive classroom environment where students are encouraged and empowered to take ownership of their learning and set goals.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Monitor</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Participants will practice specific skills of identifying barriers within public education and creating tangible solutions to promote change to better serve Black students &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will gain knowledge in how to decipher systematic policies that hinder progression for Black students &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will evaluate the strengths and challenges of recruiting educators and changing the landscape of public education to better serve Black students&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&quot;...And How Are The Children?...All the children are well.&quot; A greeting that is passed amongst the Members of the Massai Warriors of Kenya. Meaning peace and safety prevail; the priorities of protecting the young, the powerless are in place. So how do we break the cycle of our divided people?Breaking the Cycle of People Divided begins when we understand where the division lies. A society is as successful as the children it produces. In all public education systems across America, there are feasible divides between the educator and the scholars. Our public education system has yet to figure out how to educate our Black and Brown students which ultimately continues the cycle of ill-prepared generations of Black and Brown communities. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>