<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nitrogen Concentration Affects Nutrient and Carotenoid Accumulation in Parsley</title>
<publication-date>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>Dean</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of New Hampshire - Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Chenard</lname>
<fname>Christin</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of New Hampshire - Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Kopsell</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>β -carotene; chlorophyll; human health; lutein; zeaxanthin; macronutrient; micronutrient</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Horticulture</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Breeding and Genetics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Previous research has suggested that the herbal crop parsley (&lt;em&gt;Petroselinum crispum&lt;/em&gt; Nym.) has a relatively high concentration of nutritionally important carotenoid phytonutrients, such as lutein-zeaxanthin and β -carotene. Nitrogen (N) has the most direct impact on plant growth, but influence of N on phytonutritional quality is contradictory. Therefore, the objectives of this study were to measure the effects of different concentrations of N on growth, elemental accumulation, and carotenoid production in parsley. &#39;Dark Green Italian&#39; parsley was greenhouse-grown in a nutrient solution with 6.0, 13.1, 26.3, 52.5, or 105.0 mg N L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. After 8 weeks, plants were harvested and analyzed for biomass production, micro- and macronutrient concentrations, and lutein-zeaxanthin and β -carotene levels. Increasing N in the nutrient solution increased plant biomass, leaf tissue N, phosphorus (P), potassium (K), lutein-zeaxanthin, β -carotene, and chlorophyll. Leaf iron (Fe), manganese (Mn), and molybdenum (Mo) decreased with increases in N in nutrient solutions. Quadratic increases in response to increasing solution N occurred for leaf calcium (Ca), magnesium (Mg), sulfur (S), boron (B), copper (Cu), and zinc (Zn). Increasing the elemental and carotenoid concentrations in parsley through N fertility modification would be expected to increase the nutritional value of this culinary herbal crop.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/24</coverpage-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1024</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-30T08:11:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1587277</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Chenard, C. H., Kopsell, D. A. &amp; Kopsell, D. E. (2005). Nitrogen Concentration Affects Nutrient and Carotenoid Accumulation in Parsley. Journal of Plant Nutrition, 28(2), 285-297.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~db=all~content=a714843096~frm=abslink</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>