<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rose Eriophyid Mites: an ecological study of &lt;i&gt;Phyllocoptes fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt; Keifer (Acari: Eriophyidea), vector of rose rosette virus, and its relationship with &lt;i&gt;Rosa&lt;/i&gt; species</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kbaker46@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Solo</lname>
<fname>Katherine</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Rose rosette disease (RRD) is an epidemic that is lethal to roses. The causal agent for this disease is thought to be rose rosette virus (RRV) which is vectored by an eriophyid mite, &lt;i&gt;Phyllocoptes fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt;. Our research was aimed at answering fundamental ecological aspects of the relationship this mite shares with its rose hosts. In Chapter I, &lt;i&gt;Rosa&lt;/i&gt; species were evaluated for levels of residential populations of &lt;i&gt;P. fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt;. Statistical differences for year and rose species (α = 0.05) were observed. However, the resolution of the statistical tests was low due to loss of replications from destructive sampling of slow growing plants, development of symptoms of RRD, differential rates of mite populations on symptomatic vs asymptomatic plants of the same &lt;i&gt;Rosa&lt;/i&gt; species, and variable tolerance of &lt;i&gt;Rosa&lt;/i&gt; species to RRV. Chapter II involved a survey in Alabama, Georgia, and Mississippi for both vector and virus. A line was found through the middle of the three states where RRV was not detected south of the line. The southern border for &lt;i&gt;P. fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt; was much farther south than the RRV line in each state. Many sites contained eriophyid mites other than &lt;i&gt;P. fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Eriophyes eremus&lt;/i&gt; was observed in all three states and is a new report for Alabama and Mississippi. The reasons for the lack of RRV and low populations of &lt;i&gt;P. fructiphilus&lt;/i&gt; in the parts of these states are unclear. In Chapter III, the importance of floral cuts for maintaining eriophyid mite populations on field samples was evaluated. There were no significant effects of floral cuts or rose species observed. Rose rosette virus infected rose cuttings had an average of 46 times more eriophyid mites per gram of tissue than did cuttings from non-infected plants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5175</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6582&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5175</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6582</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415154</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5175</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark T. Windham</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mohammad Reza Hajimorad, Frank A. Hale, John B. Wilkerson, Alan S. Windham</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Entomology and Plant Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>