<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Systematic Study of &lt;em&gt;Trillium&lt;/em&gt; subgenus &lt;em&gt;Delostylis&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Farmer</lname>
<fname>Susan</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study focused on the systematics of &lt;em&gt;Trillium &lt;/em&gt;subg. &lt;em&gt;Delostylis, &lt;/em&gt;an enigmatic group endemic to the southeastern United States.  Phylogenetic analysis of DNA sequence data was used to examine the circumscription and phylogenetic placement of &lt;em&gt;Delostylis.  &lt;/em&gt;The results of the phylogenetic analysis of data from the ITS, &lt;em&gt;mat&lt;/em&gt;K, and &lt;em&gt;psb&lt;/em&gt;A-&lt;em&gt;trn&lt;/em&gt;H sequence data suggested that the circumscription of &lt;em&gt;Delostylis &lt;/em&gt;be narrowed to consist of &lt;em&gt;T. persistens, T. catesbaei, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. pusillum sensu lato.  &lt;/em&gt;A revised &lt;em&gt;Delostylis &lt;/em&gt;was characterized by the presence of a style with three slender stigmatic branches in those plants whose flowers are either white-fading-to-pink or pink.  Results of the phylogenetic analysis showed &lt;em&gt;Delostylis &lt;/em&gt;to be one of four innermost clades in &lt;em&gt;Trillium &lt;/em&gt;(the other three being &lt;em&gt;T. ovatum &lt;/em&gt;[bootstrap 100%; posterior probability 1.0], &lt;em&gt;T. &lt;/em&gt;subg. &lt;em&gt;Phyllantherum &lt;/em&gt;[100%; 1.0], and sister taxa &lt;em&gt;T. grandiflorum &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. nivale &lt;/em&gt;[86%; 1.0]).  Phylogenetic analyses of DNA sequence data as well as statistical analysis of quantitative morphological characters in conjunction with geographic distribution, physiography, and habitat preference were used to address the questions of species-level taxonomy.  Molecular evidence suggested that the narrowly endemic &lt;em&gt;Trillium persistens &lt;/em&gt;was monophyletic, but &lt;em&gt;T. catesbaei &lt;/em&gt;was not.  The remaining members of &lt;em&gt;Delostylis &lt;/em&gt;form the Pusillum Complex which was found to be composed of ten species (four of them new) in three groups rather than a single species with one or more varieties.  The Pusillum Cluster included &lt;em&gt;T. pusillum, T. texanum, T. georgianum (sp. nov.), &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. telmacola (sp. nov.)&lt;/em&gt;; the Ozarkanum Cluster included &lt;em&gt;T. ozarkanum &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. alabamicum (sp. nov.); &lt;/em&gt;and the Virginianum Cluster included &lt;em&gt;T. virginianum, T. monticola (stat. nov.), T. carolinianum (sp. nov.), &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. palustris (sp. nov.).  &lt;/em&gt;Five of the 10 species that are included within the Pusillum Complex are known from five counties or less (&lt;em&gt;T. telmacola, T. carolinianum, T. georgianum, T. monticola &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;T. pusillum&lt;/em&gt;) and should certainly be considered for protection.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4235</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5938&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4235</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5938</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-30T12:33:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9948906</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4235</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward E. Schilling, Christine R. B. Boake</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Randy Small, Gene Wofford, Sally Horn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>