<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Utilizing Cover Crops to Improve Sustainability of Conventional Weed Management Programs</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>garbmont@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Montgomery</lname>
<fname>Garret</fname>
<mname>Brown</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>weed control</keyword>
<keyword>Palmer amaranth</keyword>
<keyword>cover crop</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Weed Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research was conducted from the fall of 2014 to the fall of 2016 to evaluate the optimal utilization of cover crops for weed control in no-till environments. Studies included a corn (&lt;em&gt;Zea mays&lt;/em&gt; L.) termination timing study to evaluation different termination intervals of cereal rye (&lt;em&gt;Cereal rye&lt;/em&gt; L.), hairy vetch (&lt;em&gt;Vicia villosa&lt;/em&gt; Roth.), and a combination of cereal rye and hairy vetch cover crops on corn growth and development, an evaluation of a roller crimper for cover crop termination prior to corn study, an evaluation of a roller crimper for cover crop termination prior to soybeans [&lt;em&gt;Glycine max&lt;/em&gt; (L.) Merr.], an evaluation of glyphosate + dicamba tolerant (GDT) soybean utilization in a cover cropping system, and a study to evaluate the effects of fall applied herbicides on four cover crop species from controlling Italian ryegrass (&lt;em&gt;Lolium perenne&lt;/em&gt; ssp. &lt;em&gt;multiflorum&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from this research indicate that a cover crop termination interval prior to corn planting can influence corn growth, development, and yield, a roller crimper is not currently a viable tool for cover crop termination prior to planting corn, a roller crimper can be effectively used for cover crop termination prior to soybeans, GDT soybeans can be readily utilized into a cover cropping system, and that fall applied herbicides can be used with cover crops and aid in controlling Italian ryegrass.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4153</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5560&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4153</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5560</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-05T15:17:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9237001</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4153</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence E. Steckel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Angela T. McClure, Robert M. Hayes, Forbes R. Walker, Scott A. Senseman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>