<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Acute Lying and Sleep Deprivation on the Behavior and Immune Function of Lactating Dairy cows</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jkull@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Kull</lname>
<fname>Jessie</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objective of the study was to determine the effects of sleep or lying deprivation on the behavior, production, metabolism and immune function of dairy cows. Data were collected from 8 multi- and 4 primi-parous cows (DIM = 199 ± 44 (mean ± SD); days pregnant = 77 ± 30). Each cow experienced: 1) 24 h sleep deprivation implemented by noise or physical contact and 2) 24 h lying deprivation imposed by a wooden grid placed on the pen floor that prevented a recumbent position. An 11-d collection period (from 2 d before the first treatment (trt) to 8 d after trt) was followed by 12-d washout periods. Study days were organized from 2100 to 2059. During habituation (d -2 and -1 before trt), baseline (d 0), and trt (d 1), housing was individual stalls (mattress with no bedding). After trt, cows returned to sand-bedded freestalls for a 7-d recovery period (d 2 to 8). Lying behaviors were recorded by accelerometers attached to the hind leg. Milk yield was recorded 2× daily. NEFA and glucose concentrations were evaluated from serum sampled at 0300, 0900, 1500, and 2100 on d 1 and 2. Data were analyzed using a mixed model in SAS including fixed effects of trt, day, and their interaction with significant main effects separated using a PDIFF statement (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; ≤ 0.05). Lying time decreased during trt and increased on the first day of recovery for lying deprivation compared to sleep deprivation (d 1: 1.9 vs. 8.4 ± 0.7 h/d (mean ± pooled SE); &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; &lt; 0.001; d 2: 16.8 vs. 13.6 ± 0.7 h/d; &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.002). Milk yield decreased during lying deprivation compared to sleep (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.002). NEFA and glucose varied by time (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; ≤ 0.03). IL-1β and TNF-α were higher during trt, compared to baseline for both treatments (day: &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.04 and &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.004, respectively). Collectively, this suggests, lack of access to resting resources rather than the relative comfort of that resource, may have greater long-term effects on the welfare of dairy cows.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5089</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6496&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5089</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6496</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:06:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414858</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5089</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter D. Krawczel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Helen A. Baghdoyan, Gina M. Pighetti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>