<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular and Physiological Basis for Hair Loss in &lt;em&gt;Near Naked Hairless&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oak Ridge Rhino-like&lt;/em&gt; Mouse Models: Tracking the Role of the &lt;em&gt;Hairless&lt;/em&gt; Gene</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Yutao</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Hairless mice have been widely used in basic research and clinical trials. Two new mouse mutants with hair loss arose spontaneously in the breeding colony of Oak Ridge National Laboratory. The first homozygotes mutant, called &lt;em&gt;near naked hairless&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), never develops a normal coat, while heterozygotes display a sparse coat and become completely nude as they age. The &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;/Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutant mice are significantly smaller in body size and have very short, curly, and few vibrissae. Histological analysis revealed premature keratinization in the precortical region of hair follicles, formation of mineralized dermal cysts, and loss of hair follicles. Adult heterozygotes display pili multigemini (i.e. more than one hair from one piliary canal) after the first hair cycle, suggesting abnormal regulation of hair shaft formation by the mutation. A mutation was not identified in the coding region of &lt;em&gt;Hr &lt;/em&gt;nor in candidate genes around&lt;em&gt; Hr&lt;/em&gt;, suggesting a possible regulatory mutation of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt;. Microarray analysis was used to survey the gene expression profile and to identify the molecular mechanisms altered by the &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutation. Several pathways including Wnt/β-catenin, TGF-β, and apoptosis are significantly altered in &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutants, indicating the involvement of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in these pathways. &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutant mice are also suggested to be a research model for human MUHH (Marie Unna Hereditary Hypotrichosis).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second mouse mutant, called &lt;em&gt;rhino-like&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), displays progressive and random hair loss and wrinkling skin, leading to a rhinocerotic appearance. Histological analysis revealed the formation of utricles at as early as 10 days of age, the formation of dermal cysts, and the destruction of hair follicles. Since the phenotype in the homozygous mutants is very close to that in &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rh&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutant mice, the genomic DNA of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; gene was directly sequenced. A nonsense mutation was identified in the exon 12, leading to significantly reduced &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; expression, probably due to nonsense-mediated decay. The allele was named as rhino in Oak Ridge with the symbol &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (R for Oak Ridge). Microarray analysis of skin from mice at 7, 10, and 35 days was applied to identify the downstream events of the &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutation. Several genes including &lt;em&gt;Krt1-10&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Krt2-1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;IL-17&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Itgb4&lt;/em&gt;, were identified as the potential targets of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Wnt/β-catenin, apoptosis, and ERK/MAPK signaling pathways were altered in &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;sup&gt;rhR&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; mutant mice, suggesting a possible role of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; to regulate these pathways. Microarray analysis also shows many immune-related genes with differential expression, indicating the possible involvement of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; in immune response. Identification of this new &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; allele and its related research allows further understanding about the function of &lt;em&gt;Hr&lt;/em&gt; and the mechanisms of alopecia, i.e. hair loss.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1824</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3246&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1824</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3246</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-20T12:03:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4470207</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1824</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brynn H. Voy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Naima Moustaid-Moussa, Yisong Wang, Rogert Hettich</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>