<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Protease-Dead Separase Is Dominant Negative in the C. elegans Embryo</title>
<publication-date>2014-09-22T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mitchell</lname>
<fname>Diana</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Uehlein-Klebanow</lname>
<fname>Lindsey</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>bembenek@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bembenek</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>N.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Separase is a protease that promotes chromosome segregation at anaphase by cleaving cohesin. Several non-proteolytic functions of separase have been identified in other organisms. We created a transgenic &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; line that expresses protease-dead separase in embryos to further characterize separase function. We find that expression of protease-dead separase is dominant-negative in &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; embryos, not previously reported in other systems. The &lt;em&gt;C. elegans&lt;/em&gt; embryo is an ideal system to study developmental processes in a genetically tractable system. However, a major limitation is the lack of an inducible gene expression system for the embryo. We have developed two methods that allow for the propagation of lines carrying dominant-negative transgenes and have applied them to characterize expression of protease-dead separase in embryos. Using these methods, we show that protease-dead separase causes embryo lethality, and that protease-dead separase cannot rescue separase mutants. These data suggest that protease-dead separase interferes with endogenous separase function, possibly by binding substrates and protecting them from cleavage.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/90</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1096&amp;amp;context=utk_biocpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>90</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1096</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-06T06:15:30-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>9238531</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/90</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Mitchell DM, Uehlein-Klebanow LR, Bembenek JN (2014) Protease-Dead Separase Is Dominant Negative in the C. elegans Embryo. PLoS ONE 9(9):
e108188. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0108188</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1371/journal.pone.0108188</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-09-22T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>PLOS One</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>