<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Taking Responsibility</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-12T13:11:03-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>The Dickinson School of Law</institution>
<lname>Ackerman</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Communitarians have suggested that a balance must be struck between individual rights and the public welfare, and that our self-seeking tendencies must sometimes be set aside in pursuit of the common good. Government is often (although not always) the mechanism through which common interests are advanced. An abdication of government responsibility may result in disaster, as was the case with respect to Hurricane Katrina and its aftermath. At the other extreme, the accumulation of too much power in government can also bring about catastrophic consequences, as in the case of the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear plant disaster in the Soviet Union. A balance must be struck between the extremes of government passivity and &quot;all government, all the time. &quot; Traditionally, this tension has been framed as one of libertarianism versus collectivism; in current American political parlance, that of liberalism versus conservatism. But communitarians are more likely to view these issues in terms of an adjustment of interests, to be determined in the political arena, than as a clash of rights, to be adjudicated in the courtroom. This essay suggests a communitarian framework for analyzing the boundaries of government power and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1058&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1058</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-06T11:47:51-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5281473</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-06T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Taking Responsibility</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>