<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Does group feeding by toxic prey confer a defensive benefit?  Aristolochic acid content, larvae group size and survival of pipevine swallowtail (Battus philenor) larvae.</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lwisner1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wilmoth</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Wisner</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Gregariousness</keyword>
<keyword>Trade-off</keyword>
<keyword>Hippodamia convergens</keyword>
<keyword>Aggregation</keyword>
<keyword>Battus philenor</keyword>
<keyword>Aristolochic acid</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavior and Ethology</discipline>
<discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Aggregative feeding is widespread in Lepidopteran larvae suggesting that this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;behavior serves on adaptive function. Many studies of the potential benefits of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aggregative feeding in Lepidopteran larvae have been conducted. However, no studies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;have directly examined the benefits of cryptic larvae being both chemically defended and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;gregarious. Group feeding occurs disproportionately more in chemically defended&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;larvae than in larvae that have no chemical defense. Most of these larvae are cryptic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;when they are most highly aggregated and most vulnerable to predation. In this study,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the benefits of group feeding in terms of decreased predation were explored in first instar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;larvae of pipevine swallowtail larvae, &lt;em&gt;Battus philenor, &lt;/em&gt;a species that exhibits chemical&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sequestration. Contrary to our expectation, we found that groups of larvae fed a diet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with high levels of the toxin aristolochic acid, which they sequester naturally and use as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a defense against natural enemies, had significantly lower survivorship due to predation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in both the field and in the laboratory experiments compared to groups of larvae fed a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;diet with low aristolochic acid content. We also found that aristolochic acid does not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;deter the generalist predator &lt;em&gt;Hippodamia convergens, &lt;/em&gt;the ladybird beetle, suggesting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that this compound is not a universal predator deterrent as previously assumed. Thus,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;instead of finding a benefit to group feeding and chemical defense in cryptic larvae, we&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;have found a negative impact of group feeding in this population of &lt;em&gt;B. philenor&lt;/em&gt;. Based&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on this evidence, we speculate that other benefits of group feeding might be outweighing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the negative consequences of increased predation during the first instar. Future&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;research on chemical defense, aposematism, and aggregative feeding should take into&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;consideration that chemical defenses might not be universally effective against all&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;natural enemies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/924</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1991&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>924</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1991</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-13T10:58:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1938982</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/924</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James A. Fordyce</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Susan E. Riechert, Benjamin M. Fitzpatrick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>