<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Investigation of How Students Experience Corporate Advertising in Public Schools</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Gail</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In order to discover the experiences of public school students with the presence of corporate advertising available in their schools, data was collected from a public elementary, middle, and high school. This included a walkthrough of the schools to make note of advertisements available to students on a regular basis; informal interviews with school staff; and collection of classroom materials from teachers. Also, a total of ten students representing three different grade levels were interviewed in three focus groups, one per grade level. This study is a qualitative analysis conducted from a critical and phenomenological standpoint. The impetus for the study was an interest in the influence(s) of corporate presence in public schools, and a concern for what implications that may/may not have on democratic ideals in American society in general and American educational systems in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are presented as a literary journey of what students experience in terms of corporate advertising in their schools. Using Hatch’s interpretive analysis as a guide led to the development of five common themes that permeated the focus group discussions. Those include an understanding of the basic concept of advertising; a rejection of the idea that corporations employ the use of manipulative practices within the school; varying levels of awareness and abilities to recollect corporate names present within the school; the presence or lack of student agency; and evidence of “successful” manipulations of the students with regard to corporate agendas. Also noted was the presence in schools of practices that do not concur with school goals.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/219</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1251&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>219</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1251</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-10T10:11:48-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1139072</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/219</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Diana Moyer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Trena Paulus, Barbara Thayer-Bacon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Instructional Technology and Educational Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/WilsonAmanda.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>