<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>New Electrochemical and Optical Detection Methods for Biological and Environmental Applications</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rdansbys@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Dansby-Sparks</lname>
<fname>Royce</fname>
<mname>Nicholas</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Electrochemistry</keyword>
<keyword>Optical Sensors</keyword>
<keyword>Sol-gels</keyword>
<keyword>Catalytic Adsorptive Stripping Voltammetry</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Analytical Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Environmental Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Inorganic Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Detection of chromium and vanadium is of interest for biomedical and environmental applications.  The two metals have narrow limits between being essential and toxic for humans.  Ultra-sensitive techniques have been studied to measure Cr and V at low concentrations found in human blood and environmental samples.  Bismuth film and mercury-alloy electrodes have been developed as alternatives to traditional Hg-based electrodes for Cr and V detection.  While catalytic adsorptive stripping voltammetry (CAdSV) has been used to detect Cr and V, little is known about the process.  The mechanisms of CAdSV have been probed to provide a better understanding of its exceptional sensitivity and selectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near-real time monitoring of plume gas constituents is desired as a diagnostic tool for combustion efficiency, ensuring safe testing conditions and observing releases of green house gasses.  Ground testing rockets is a crucial preliminary step that ensures their performance during critical space missions.  Optical sol-gel sensors for carbon dioxide have been developed for remote sensing applications.  They are inexpensive and are compatible with the harsh environments encountered during rocket plume tests.  The sensors are a viable approach to compliment current infrared (IR) measurements for real-time carbon dioxide detection.  Additional work on kerosene and isopropyl alcohol sensing has been explored for incorporation into a multi-analyte sensing platform.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/788</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1883&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>788</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1883</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-05T14:15:27-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1883/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1382219</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/788</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Zi-Ling (Ben) Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael D. Best, Michael J. Sepaniak, Hong Guo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>