<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A preliminary account of a new genus to accommodate &lt;em&gt;Cosmospora vilior&lt;/em&gt; and related species</title>
<publication-date>2012-04-14T15:25:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Maryland</institution>
<lname>Herrera</lname>
<fname>Cesar</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>United States Department of Agriculture</institution>
<lname>Rossman</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
<mname>Y.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>United States Department of Agriculture</institution>
<lname>Samuels</lname>
<fname>Gary</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Maryland</institution>
<lname>Chaverri</lname>
<fname>Priscila</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cosmospora&lt;/em&gt; sensu Rossman (Ascomycota, Hypocreales, Nectriaceae) was erected to accommodate nectroid fungi with small, reddish, KOH+, smooth, thin-walled, laterally collapsing when dry, non- or weakly stromatic perithecia. Recently, the group was found to be polyphyletic based on molecular data, and has been segregated into multiple genera. However, not all &lt;em&gt;Cosmospora&lt;/em&gt;-like fungi have been treated systematically. Some of these species include &lt;em&gt;C. vilior&lt;/em&gt; (Starbäck) Rossman &amp; Samuels and many species often labeled as “&lt;em&gt;Cosmospora&lt;/em&gt; sp.” The objectives of this research were to designate an epitype for &lt;em&gt;C. vilior&lt;/em&gt;, which has been misapplied based on examination of the type specimen, and determine its phylogenetic position within &lt;em&gt;Cosmospora&lt;/em&gt; sensu lato and the &lt;em&gt;Nectriaceae&lt;/em&gt;. A multilocus phylogeny was constructed based on six loci (ITS, LSU, RPB1, MCM7, TEF1, and TUB) to estimate the species tree. Results from the phylogenetic analyses indicated that &lt;em&gt;C. vilior&lt;/em&gt; forms a monophyletic group with other &lt;em&gt;Cosmopora&lt;/em&gt;-like fungi that have an acremonium-like anamorph and that parasitize &lt;em&gt;Eutypa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Eutypella&lt;/em&gt; (Diatrypaceae). The group is phylogenetically distinct from other previously segregated genera, and for that reason, a new is described to accommodate these species.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/masmc2012/2012/April14/10</coverpage-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1009</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-07-05T12:17:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Middle Atlantic States Mycological Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3057786</context-key>
<submission-path>masmc2012/2012/April14/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T15:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Toyota Auditorium, Howard H. Baker Jr. Center for Public Policy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T15:25:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T15:25:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>