<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Microscopic Enamel Defects in a Contemporary Population: Biological and Social Implications</title>
<publication-date>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mifsud</lname>
<fname>Lise</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, the frequency of microscopic defects in enamel, termed Wilson bands, are analyzed according to socioeconomic affiliation, the sex, and ethnicity of the individual. The sample consists of 193 anterior teeth collected from private practice and public health oral surgeon&#39;s offices. These defects have been studied in great detail by dental researchers, dental anthropologists, and bioarchaeologists to ascertain: etiology, morphology, inter- and intra- population differences, prehistoric diet and health, and dietary and morbidity conditions of underprivileged contemporary populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this study are compared to results of previous researchers and similarities and differences in findings are discussed. Of particular interest is the applicability of Wilson bands to the stresses incurred during the weaning process, and the relationship of socioeconomic affiliation to the occurrence of Wilson bands. The social ramifications of these findings are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4222</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5686&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4222</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5686</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-07T09:50:34-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9448727</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4222</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Murray K. Marks</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Walter E. Klippel, Lyle Konigsberg, Mike Elam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>