<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Expression of inwardly rectifying potassium channels (GIRKs) and beta-adrenergic regulation of breast cancer cell lines</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hplummer@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Plummer</lname>
<fname>Howard</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yu</lname>
<fname>Qiang</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cakir</lname>
<fname>Yavuz</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>hmsch@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schuller</lname>
<fname>Hildegard</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Oncology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous research has indicated that at various organ sites there is a subset of adenocarcinomas that is regulated by beta-adrenergic and arachidonic acid-mediated signal transduction pathways. We wished to determine if this regulation exists in breast adenocarcinomas. Expression of mRNA that encodes a G-protein coupled inwardly rectifying potassium channel (GIRK1) has been shown in tissue samples from approximately 40% of primary human breast cancers. Previously, GIRK channels have been associated with beta-adrenergic signaling.  &lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breast cancer cell lines were screened for GIRK channels by RT-PCR. Cell cultures of breast cancer cells were treated with beta-adrenergic agonists and antagonists, and changes in gene expression were determined by both relative competitive and real time PCR. Potassium flux was determined by flow cytometry and cell signaling was determined by western blotting.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breast cancer cell lines MCF-7, MDA-MB-361 MDA-MB 453, and ZR-75-1 expressed mRNA for the GIRK1 channel, while MDA-MB-468 and MDA-MB-435S did not. GIRK4 was expressed in all six breast cancer cell lines, and GIRK2 was expressed in all but ZR-75-1 and MDA-MB-435. Exposure of MDA-MB-453 cells for 6 days to the beta-blocker propranolol (1 μM) increased the GIRK1 mRNA levels and decreased beta&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-adrenergic mRNA levels, while treatment for 30 minutes daily for 7 days had no effect. Exposure to a beta-adrenergic agonist and antagonist for 24 hours had no effect on gene expression. The beta adrenergic agonist, formoterol hemifumarate, led to increases in K&lt;sup&gt;+ &lt;/sup&gt;flux into MDA-MB-453 cells, and this increase was inhibited by the GIRK channel inhibitor clozapine. The tobacco carcinogen 4-(methylnitrosamino)-1-(3-pyridyl)-1-butanone (NNK), a high affinity agonist for beta-adrenergic receptors stimulated activation of Erk 1/2 in MDA-MB-453 cells.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our data suggests β-adrenergic receptors and GIRK channels may play a role in breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biolpubs/18</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;amp;context=utk_biolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1017</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-12T08:59:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- General Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4309178</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biolpubs/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>BMC Cancer 2004, 4:93 doi:10.1186/1471-2407-4-93</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>