<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Read-across to rank skin sensitization potential: subcategories for the Michael acceptor domain</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schultz</lname>
<fname>Terry</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Rogers</lname>
<fname>K</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Aptula</lname>
<fname>A</fname>
<mname>O.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: Eliminating animal testing for skin sensitization is a significant challenge in consumer safety risk assessment. To be able to perform resilient risk assessments in the future, one will need alternative approaches to fill the data gaps. OBJECTIVES: To this end, we propose a subcategory-based read-across approach to estimate and rank skin sensitization potential of chemicals. The example described here is for the mechanism of Michael-type nucleophilic addition with subcategories being limited to carbonyl-containing compounds. PATIENTS/METHODS: In this approach, in silico tools based on structural alerts were used to determine both the mechanism of protein binding and the relative subcategories within that mechanism. RESULTS: Fifty compounds previously evaluated in the in vivo mouse local lymph node assay (LLNA) were placed in 10 subcategories defined by their polarized alpha,beta-unsaturated substructure. To offset the limitations and skewness of the published in vivo data, in chemico glutathione (GSH) depletion data also were included. CONCLUSIONS: It was shown that the read-across approach can be successfully used to rank qualitatively skin sensitization potential of an untested carbonyl-containing Michael acceptor chemical by using subcategories. Moreover, the use of the more resilient in chemico GSH depletion data added further support to the read-across result.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/22</coverpage-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1021</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-27T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1288715</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Terry W. Schultz, K Rogers, and A O. Aptula. &quot;Read-across to rank skin sensitization potential: subcategories for the Michael acceptor domain&quot; &lt;em&gt;Contact dermatitis&lt;/em&gt; 60 (2009): 21-31.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/121619063/abstract</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Contact dermatitis</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>