<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thermodynamic and Neutron Structural Studies of Hydrocarbon Adsorption on MgO Nanocubes</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cook</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Presented is a series of thermodynamic and neutron scattering experiments used to probe the nature of the hydrocarbon - MgO (100) interaction. High-resolution volumetric isotherms are used to probe the wetting, layer transitions, heats of adsorption, two-dimensional compressibilities, and identify possible phase transitions of thin films of benzene, ethane, and n - pentane on MgO powders. Neutron diffraction experiments were used to probe the structure and identify any phase transitions within monolayer films of ethane, butane and n -pentane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benzene adsorption, while showing no visible layering steps, shows a shift in the shape of the isotherm &lt;em&gt;for p/p&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &gt; 0.7. The change in isotherm behavior can be analyzed through use of the BET constant from fits to the experimental data. Ethane and n -pentane both show incomplete wetting with three and two distinct steps in their respective isotherms. Phase transitions from a two-dimensional liquid to a two-dimensional vapor were determined by examining the trend in the two-dimensional compressibilities for the first two layers of ethane (127 ± 1K) and the second layer of pentane (183.8 ± 4K). Neutron diffraction was used to study the structure of the ethane monolayer and determine that the structure of a monolayer of butane forms a commensurate 7√2 x√2R45° structure with &lt;em&gt;p2gg&lt;/em&gt; symmetry and 4 molecules in the unit cell. By use of temperature dependent diffraction scans, the melting of the ethane (60K ≤ T&lt;em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ≤ 75K) and pentane (99K ≤ T&lt;em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; ≤ 107K) were observed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining the data sets from these two experimental techniques, preliminary two- dimensional phase diagrams can be proposed, the first step in characterizing the overall nature of the hydrocarbon-MgO interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1938</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3369&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1938</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3369</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-18T12:53:12-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4598934</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1938</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Z. Larese</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert J. Hinde, Takeshi Egami, Ziling Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>