<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of F/A-18 Spin Departure Demonstration Procedure with Departure Resistant Flight Control Computer Version 10.7</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Park</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to evaluate the capability to demonstrate F/A-18 Hornet departure characteristics, mainly the spin, with Flight Control Computer (FCC) Operation Flight Program (OFP) Version 10.7 (v10.7).  Version 10.7 was released to the Navy and Marine Corps F/A-18A/B/C/D fleet in 2003.  Version 10.7 was developed based on the existing FCC OFP (v10.5.1) to minimize out-of-control flight or departure related mishaps.  Version 10.7 was only a software upgrade and no hardware change to the existing F/A-18 was made.  Version 10.7 was remarkable since most of the known F/A-18 departure prone flight envelopes were rendered departure free by software change alone.  Although v10.7 eliminated most of the F/A-18 departure prone areas, it did not eliminate F/A-18 departures completely.  Therefore, there still exists a need to train pilots in F/A-18 departures and a need for Departure Demonstration Syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of departure resistant features of the new FCC OFP, significant portion of the F/A-18 Departure Demonstration Syllabus had to be changed.  Several test flights were conducted to re-develop the syllabus.  These flight test results revealed that existing spin entry procedure would not be sufficient to enter and sustain the spin.  Most of the flight tests to re-develop the syllabus were spent on fine tuning the repeatable spin entry procedure and sustaining the spin long enough for instructional purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended procedure proved to be the best repeatable spin entry procedure.  This procedure allowed sustained spin for one turn after the pro-spin flight control inputs were removed.  This one turn was necessary for pilots to evaluate the spin characteristics of the F/A-18 and train them to use proper procedures to recover from sustained spins.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2312</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3738&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2312</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3738</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-16T13:18:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4729409</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2312</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert. B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles T. N. Paludan, Richard J. Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>