<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Bounded Geometry and Property A for Nonmetrizable Coarse Spaces</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bunn@math.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Bunn</lname>
<fname>Jared R</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>coarse spaces</keyword>
<keyword>bounded geometry</keyword>
<keyword>Property A</keyword>
<keyword>metrizability</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Geometry and Topology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We begin by recalling the notion of a coarse space as defined by John Roe. We show that metrizability of coarse spaces is a coarse invariant. The concepts of bounded geometry, asymptotic dimension, and Guoliang Yu&#39;s Property A are investigated in the setting of coarse spaces. In particular, we show that bounded geometry is a coarse invariant, and we give a proof that finite asymptotic dimension implies Property A in this general setting. The notion of a metric approximation is introduced, and a characterization theorem is proved regarding bounded geometry. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chapter 7 presents a discussion of coarse structures on the minimal uncountable ordinal. We show that it is a nonmetrizable coarse space not of bounded geometry. Moreover, we show that this space has asymptotic dimension 0; hence, it has Property A.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, Chapter 8 regards coarse structures on products of coarse spaces. All of the previous concepts above are considered with regard to 3 different coarse structures analogous to the 3 different topologies on products in topology. In particular, we see that an arbitrary product of spaces with any of the 3 coarse structures with asymptotic dimension 0 has asymptotic dimension 0.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/953</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2109&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>953</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2109</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-25T12:51:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1901323</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/953</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jerzy Dydak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nikolay Brodskiy, Stefan Richter, Mark Hector</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>