<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Nutrition Field Experience with the Kentucky Department for Human Resources</title>
<publication-date>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Baxter</lname>
<fname>Jane</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis reports and analyzes the seven-week field experience in public health nutrition spent by the student nutritionist with the Kentucky Department for Human Resources. The purpose of this field experience was to apply the scientific principles learned at the university to &quot;real world&quot; problems encountered in the practice of public health nutrition. Further, the purpose of participation in a federal supplemental foods program was to explore the various roles and functions of the public health nutritionist in a defined program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The period of the field experience provided many opportunities for experiences that combined to accomplish the objectives. A major part of the student nutritionist&#39;s time was spent in Morehead, Kentucky; the remainder of the period in April, 1974, was spent with nutritionists in the Nutrition Office, Bureau for Health Services. She was able to explore the role and function of the public health nutritionist as administrator, educator, counselor, and consultant through observation of and participation in nutrition services. Through the analysis of her performance in these functions, she could examine the role and evaluate her skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiences in the county and at the state office strengthened the student nutritionist&#39;s philosophy of public health, that is the promotion of comprehensive health care for all citizens and the support of individual responsibility for health maintenance. She sees the public health nutritionist as a health professional who can conduct effective program planning and serve as a link in the health delivery system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student nutritionist has observed the changing structure of a state public health organization and has observed how this process sharpens the basic dedication to service required by the public health professionals. The frustrations of this process call for leaders and staff who can see the real purpose of their work and relate their objectives to emerging structure and programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3980</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5450&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3980</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5450</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T06:53:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9123264</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3980</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Robert H. Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>