<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nontarget host utilization of thistle species by introduced biological control agents and spatial prediction of non-target feeding habitats</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wiggins</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhinocyllus conicus&lt;/em&gt; Fröelich and &lt;em&gt;Trichosirocalus horridus&lt;/em&gt; (Panzer) were introduced from Europe into North America as biological control agents of the exotic weed species &lt;em&gt;Carduus nutans&lt;/em&gt; L. Concern exists over the feeding of these weevils on at least 25 species of native &lt;em&gt;Cirsium&lt;/em&gt; thistles. Research was conducted to 1) estimate phenological synchrony of the eight thistle species in Tennessee with &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt;, 2) investigate naturally-occurring populations of the five native &lt;em&gt;Cirsium&lt;/em&gt; thistle species for non-target activity by &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt;, 3) quantify the impacts to plants of each thistle species to feeding of  &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt;, and 4) identify potential areas of non-target feeding by the weevils using spatial analysis. Phenologies of two native species, C. &lt;em&gt;carolinianum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;C. horridulum&lt;/em&gt;, are synchronous with &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; reproduction, and all eight thistle species are phenologically synchronous with the reproduction of &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt;.  No non-target activity by &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; was observed in naturally-occurring populations of &lt;em&gt;Cirsium&lt;/em&gt; thistles, but adults of &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt; were documented for the first time on the native species &lt;em&gt;C. carolinianum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;C. horridulum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;C. muticum&lt;/em&gt;.  In caged plant studies, larvae of &lt;em&gt;R. conicus&lt;/em&gt; completed development in heads of &lt;em&gt;C. carolinianum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;C. horridulum&lt;/em&gt; and reduced seed numbers of both native species. Basal meristems of all eight thistle species exposed to &lt;em&gt;T. horridus&lt;/em&gt; were damaged at varying levels in caged plant studies, but no other impacts to plants were observed. Spatial analyses showed associations between Mahalanobis distance values and plant counts of &lt;em&gt;Carduus nutans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cirsium carolinianum&lt;/em&gt; in predicted habitats, and the occurrence of &lt;em&gt;Carduus nutans&lt;/em&gt; was associated with the occurrence of both weevil species in these habitats. About 12% of the total study area consisted of habitats where &lt;em&gt;C. nutans&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cirsium carolinianum&lt;/em&gt; overlap. The potential exists for these weevils to utilize native &lt;em&gt;Cirsium&lt;/em&gt; species found in Tennessee as plant hosts. The spatial model developed during this study not only allows potential monitoring of populations of &lt;em&gt;C. carolinianum&lt;/em&gt; to be more targeted, but also may be modified to apply to other systems involving interactions among introduced and native species.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/641</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1710&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>641</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1710</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-24T09:57:57-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1168129</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/641</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jerome F. Grant</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Paris L. Lambdin, Jack W. Ranney, John B. Wilkerson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>