<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Farm-to-Preschool in East Tennessee: Evaluation of a Small-scale Farmer’s Market at a Childcare Center on Household Fruit and Vegetable Availability and Preschoolers’ Consumption of Fruits and Vegetables</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jparry@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parry</lname>
<fname>Jade</fname>
<mname>Morgan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Farm to preschool</keyword>
<keyword>Farm to childcare</keyword>
<keyword>Farm to school</keyword>
<keyword>Farmer&#39;s market</keyword>
<keyword>Early childhood</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>International and Community Nutrition</discipline>
<discipline>Maternal and Child Health</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Most&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;preschool-aged children do not consume an adequate amount of fruits and vegetables (F&amp;V). Accessibility to F&amp;V and parental influence are important factors in determining fruit and vegetable consumption in preschool-aged children. The incorporation of farmer’s markets at childcare centers as part of a farm-to-preschool program provides an opportunity to increase access to F&amp;V and engage parents in supporting positive changes in their children’s dietary behaviors. Gaps in the farm-to-preschool literature include a lack of well-designed intervention trials that include a control group and rigorous evaluation tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;This was a pilot study with a quasi-experimental, pre-test, post-test design with an intervention and control group. Children and parents participated in a 12-week nutrition program at both the intervention and control childcare centers. Additional farm-to-preschool activities were provided at the intervention site including a small-scale farmer’s market for two hours once per week for eight weeks at the childcare center. Parents were asked to complete a home food inventory (HFI) to assess F&amp;V availability and a food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) to evaluate their preschooler’s usual consumption of F&amp;V. Paired-samples t-tests were used to analyze data.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Results indicated that there were no significant differences between pre and post scores for fruit availability (7.57 to 7.0 P = 0.34), vegetable availability (11.79 to 11.07 P = 0.30), preschoolers’ consumption of fruit (4.21 to 3.78 P = 0.36), and consumption of vegetables (4.86 to 5.5 P = 0.18), despite parents at the intervention facility spending an average of $6.04 per week on fresh produce at the preschool farmer’s market. Similarly no significant results were found for the control group.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discussion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The number of F&amp;V in the home did not significantly change at post evaluation for either group, potentially indicating that the parents in the intervention group were purchasing their usual F&amp;V at the small-scale farmer’s market, and displacing what they usually purchased elsewhere.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Future farm-to-preschool research may benefit from a mixed methods approach that captures how having local produce available at a childcare center could influence families in a variety of positive ways.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4014</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5060&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4014</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5060</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-21T19:25:52-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8186849</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4014</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marsha L. Spence</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sarah Colby, Katie Kavanagh</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>