<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>BiBeam Specimen Design for investigating Stress Corrosion Cracking in Brittle Materials</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>saduloju@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Aduloju</lname>
<fname>Sunday</fname>
<mname>Christopher</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Stress Corrosion cracking</keyword>
<keyword>Brittle specimens</keyword>
<keyword>Stress intensity factors</keyword>
<keyword>velocity</keyword>
<keyword>beam</keyword>
<keyword>Soda lime glass</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The existing method for testing and collecting Stress Corrosion data requires application of externally applied load on the specimen in the corrosive media. We propose a new type of specimen consisting of a bi-beam where two materials having slightly different coefficient of thermal expansions are bonded together and cooled to room temperature such that a self-loaded specimen is produced because of the presence of residual stress. This creates a very stable stress field that is ideal for long-term toughness experiments. A finite element model was developed to design such specimens while ensuring that the crack propagates at a steady state across the specimen. The model was first verified against analytical results for a thin film on a substrate. Then, since non-constant stress intensity factor are desirable for recording a spectrum of response, specimen geometries were investigated to determine the best geometry suitable for such experiments. The results obtained were validated by performing a stress corrosion cracking experiment using Schott B/Soda-lime glass bi-beam in water and the numerical data compares well with the experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5054</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6461&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5054</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6461</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:06:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414739</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5054</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Timothy J. Truster</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark D. Denavit, Zhongguo John Ma</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9359-0641</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Portions of this document were previously published in Fracture, Fatigue, Failure and Damage Evolution, Volume 7 pp 25-33</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>