<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Heuristic Procedures to Solve Sequencing and Scheduling Problems in Automobile Industry</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>He</lname>
<fname>Jingxu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Industrial Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the growing trend for greater product variety, mixed-model assembly nowadays is commonly employed in many industries, which can enable just-in-time production for a production system with high variety. Efficient production scheduling and sequencing is important to achieve the overall material supply, production, and distribution efficiency around the mixed-model assembly line. This research addresses production scheduling and sequencing on a mixed-model assembly line for products with multiple product options, considering multiple objectives with regard to material supply, manufacturing, and product distribution. This research also addresses plant assignment for a product with multiple product options as a prior step to scheduling and sequencing for a mixed-model assembly line. This dissertation is organized into three parts based on three papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction and literature review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1.&lt;/strong&gt; In an automobile assembly plant many product options often need to be considered in sequencing an assembly line with which multiple objectives often need to be considered. A general heuristic procedure is developed for sequencing automobile assembly lines considering multiple options. The procedure uses the construction, swapping, and re-sequencing steps, and a limited search for sequencing automobile assembly lines considering multiple options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2.&lt;/strong&gt; In a supply chain, production scheduling and finished goods distribution have been increasingly considered in an integrated manner to achieve an overall best efficiency. This research presents a heuristic procedure to achieve an integrated consideration of production scheduling and product distribution with production smoothing for the automobile just-in-time production assembly line. A meta-heuristic procedure is also developed for improving the heuristic solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3.&lt;/strong&gt; For a product that can be manufactured in multiple facilities, assigning orders to the facility is a common problem faced by industry considering production, material constraints, and other supply-chain related constraints. This paper addresses products with multiple product options for plant assignment with regard to multiple constraints at individual plants in order to minimize transportation costs and costs of assignment infeasibility. A series of binary- and mixed-integer programming models are presented, and a decision support tool based on optimization models is presented with a case study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary and conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/385</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1446&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>385</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1446</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T08:12:14-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1150077</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/385</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Fong-Yuen Ding</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Denise Jackson, Funda Sahin, Dukwon Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/HeJingxu.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>