<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Porotic Hyperostosis and Artificial Cranial Deformation in Dallas Society</title>
<publication-date>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Langdon</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
<mname>Patrick</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to evaluate, test, and amplify Lewis and Kneberg&#39;s (1946) observation that the severity of porotic hyperostosis at Hiwassee Island is related to the degree of cranial deformation. Statistical tests indicate a moderate, although non-significant, correlation between the two conditions. It is believed that this correlation may be explained by the differential treatment of infants, rather than a direct causality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sample of 364 crania from four Dallas Phase sites are examined. Age, sex, and status distributions of porotic hyperostosis, cribra orbitalia, and cranial deformation are examined in a biocultural framework that emphasizes the interaction among biology, culture, diet, and disease. Porotic hyperostosis and cribra orbitalia are evaluated by severity and activity, and cranial deformation is scored by degree and type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High incidences of both cribra orbitalia and porotic hyperostosis indicate endemic iron deficiency anemia in Dallas society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, high status individuals exhibit lower frequencies of both conditions, suggesting preferential access to iron- and protein-rich food sources. Cribra orbitalia (representing infant anemia) is least common in mound males, suggesting prolonged or more frequent access to mother&#39;s milk and other dietary supplements. Early childhood anemia (represented by calvarial porotic hyperostosis). however, is less frequent in females, suggesting preferential access to foods by virtue of sex role initiation and proximity to cooking pots, or that females are less susceptible to dietary stress. Another possibility is that females are weaned earlier than males and suffer anemic stress at an earlier age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial cranial deformation resulting from cradleboard use is virtually omnipresent. Both intentional and unintentional types are more common in village individuals, indicating increased use of the cradleboard by low status laborers. The higher frequency of intentional deformation in village individuals, especially males, suggests the use of different cradling apparatus for different infants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because porotic hyperostosis, cribra orbitalia, and cranial deformation are conditions most frequently occurring in childhood, differences based on status strongly suggest that status in Dallas society is largely ascribed. Intentional deformation in a few high status males, however, suggests achievement of status occurred among males.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4220</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5688&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4220</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5688</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-07T10:50:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9449002</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4220</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>P. S. Willey</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. L. Jantz, Maria O. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>