<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Macrobotanical Analysis of the Topper Site (38AL23)</title>
<publication-date>2017-04-19T17:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sroark1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Roark</lname>
<fname>Sierra Snively</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Archaeological Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Topper Site (38AL23) is a multicomponent precontact site located along the Savannah River in central South Carolina. Recent excavations conducted by the University of Tennessee have resulted in the identification,mapping, excavation, and processing of over 357 features of possible pits, postholes, and other traces of human activity. Fill from each feature was individually excavated and processed via drum flotation. This poster presents a detailed macrobotanical identification and analysis of the contents of a selection of these features using paleoethnobotanical standards. This project provides insight into Native American foodways, structure locations, and overall daily practices which occurred in the Woodland period portion of the site. Usually associated with the later Mississippian period, maize remnants have been identified and will be submitted for radiocarbon dating. Dates obtained from the botanical remains will allow for a more detailed examination of the chronologies of both ceramic technology and the spread of maize within the Southeastern United States. The results from this project have assisted in the planning for the 2017 continuation of the project and field school.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/artsandsciences/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1153&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1153</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-23T11:34:24-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1153/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10063549</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/artsandsciences/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Kandace D. Hollenbach</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-04-19T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>