<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>There Arises Light: A Work for Orchestra in One Movement</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Taylor</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Music</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There Arises Light&lt;/em&gt; is a work for orchestra in one movement. It was written in part to fulfill the requirements for the Master s degree in music composition, and is the primary subject of this thesis. Inspiration for the work was drawn from the composer&#39;s own experiences as well as from &lt;em&gt;Psalm 112&lt;/em&gt;. The composition was completed in February, 2001 by Michael S. Taylor, using a KORG N264 Music Workstation, an iMac™ G3 computer, and Mark of the Unicorn s Digital Performer™ version 2.7. The orchestration and notation of the score were completed in March 2002, using Coda®&#39;s Finale®, version 2002. It is approximately twelve minutes in duration and is scored for a conventional orchestra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to place the composition in historical perspective, examine its structural elements within the context of similar genres, and explain the compositional procedures used. Specifically, the study of &lt;em&gt;There Arises Light&lt;/em&gt; will involve a discussion of elements such as form, melody, harmony, rhythm, and texture in the work and the similar use of these elements in works by prominent composers of the twentieth century. The compositions to be examined are: &lt;em&gt;Third Symphony in One Movement&lt;/em&gt; by Roy Harris, &lt;em&gt;Symphony No. 2&lt;/em&gt; by Howard Hanson, &lt;em&gt;Symphony No. 3&lt;/em&gt; by Paul Creston, &lt;em&gt;Symphony No. 5&lt;/em&gt; in D Major by Ralph Vaughan Williams, &lt;em&gt;Dance Suite&lt;/em&gt; by Béla Bartók, &lt;em&gt;Symphony in Three Movements&lt;/em&gt; by Igor Stravinsky, and &lt;em&gt;Gloria&lt;/em&gt; by Francis Poulenc.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2186</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3570&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2186</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3570</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-09T12:02:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4689538</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2186</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kenneth A. Jacobs</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barbara Murphy, Walter W. Hawthorne</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Music</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Music</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>