<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hot Topic: National Guard&#39;s Weekend Drills are Considered Training</title>
<publication-date>1998-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>Richard.Stokes@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</institution>
<lname>Stokes</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>national guard</keyword>
<keyword>training</keyword>
<keyword>city employees</keyword>
<keyword>armed forces</keyword>
<keyword>military leave</keyword>
<keyword>MTAS online</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This Hot Topic discusses the Attorney General&#39;s Opinion No. 98-155, which addresses whether National Guard weekend drills are considered training under the law and subject to the military leave provisions of the Tennessee Code Annotated (T.C.A.). According to the Attorney General&#39;s opinion, &quot;Weekend training appears to be within the statutory terms of the T.C.A.&quot; The term &quot;training&quot; ordinarily would encompass the term &quot;drill.&quot; Drill is defined by Webster&#39;s dictionary as &quot;the act of training soldiers in the military art ... a kind or method of military exercises.&quot; The A.G. cited an Alabama case, Britton vs. Jackson, 414 So.2d 966 (Ala. App. 1981), in which the court held that &quot;weekend drill&quot; was within the definition of &quot;other training&quot; for purposes of that state&#39;s military leave statute. Therefore, the Tennessee statute covers both military duty as well as military training and appears to apply to weekend drills that are conducted in accordance with military orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Hot Topic also announces the launch of the MTAS website at http://www.mtas.utk.edu .&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtastop/210</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1216&amp;amp;context=utk_mtastop&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>210</label>
<document-type>bulletin</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1216</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-13T11:42:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Hot Topics</publication-title>
<context-key>3898304</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtastop/210</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;#41&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-03-13T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>