<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Chemical Disinfectants for Inactivation of Human Norovirus Surrogates</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ccao2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Cao</lname>
<fname>Cong</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>feline calicivirus FCV-F9</keyword>
<keyword>murine norovirus MNV-1</keyword>
<keyword>benzalkonium chloride</keyword>
<keyword>potassium peroxymonosulfate</keyword>
<keyword>sodium metasilicate</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Human noroviruses (HNoVs) are considered the leading cause of acute non-bacterial gastroenteritis worldwide. Effective chemical disinfectants to inactivate HNoVs are needed. Since HNoVs cannot be cultivated in the lab, cultivable surrogates, feline calicivirus (FCV-F9) and murine norovirus (MNV-1), are used to determine inactivation using infectivity plaque assays. This study aimed to: 1) determine the ability of benzalkonium chloride (BAC) and potassium peroxymonosulfate (KPMS) to inactivate FCV-F9 and MNV-1 &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; using suspension and carrier tests under clean and simulated dirty (5% fetal bovine serum) conditions over 1 h at room temperature; 2) determine inactivation of FCV-F9 and MNV-1 in suspension and carrier tests over 1 h at room temperature by sodium metasilicate (SMS). In suspension tests, BAC caused 1.94 and 2.59 log reductions of low and high FCV-F9 titers after 1 h, respectively. MNV-1 at low and high titers was reduced by &gt; 3and 1.47 logs with BAC after 1 h, respectively. KPMS at 5 and 10 mg/mL reduced low titers of both viruses to non-detectable levels within 30 s. High FCV-F9 titers were non-detectable after 2 min with 5 mg/mL and within 30 s with 10 mg/mL of KPMS. KPMS at 5 mg/mL had little effect against high titers of MNV-1, but caused a 4.61 log reduction after 5 min with 10 mg/mL of KPMS. Using clean carrier tests, KPMS at 5 and 10 mg/mL reduced both tested viruses at low titers after 30 s and only high FCV-F9 titers after 10 min to undetectable levels. MNV-1 at high titers were reduced to non-detectable levels after 15 min with 10 mg/mL KPMS. BAC reduced low titers of both viruses to undetectable levels after 1 h using carrier tests with no significant reduction of high titers even after 2 h. The antiviral effect of both chemicals decreased under simulated dirty conditions. Both viruses were reduced within 15 s by 5% and 10% SMS using suspension tests. FCV-F9 and MNV-1 at high titers were reduced to undetectable levels after 2 min and 15 s, respectively with 2% SMS. KPMS and SMS appear suitable for the rapid control of HNoV transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1600</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2745&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1600</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2745</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-17T11:32:26-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2745/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4038821</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1600</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Doris H. D&#39;Souza</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Svetlana Zivanovic, Irene Hanning</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>