<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Computer Simulation as a Medium for Teaching Inventory Management in Food Systems Administration</title>
<publication-date>1976-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>West</lname>
<fname>Joyce</fname>
<mname>Willene Fleming</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A conceptual framework was developed incorporating computer simulation as an instructional medium for teaching conceptual thinking and techniques for decision making and problem solving needed for inventory management. With this framework as a guide, an individualized instruction unit was designed and implemented for teaching cognitive learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifty-two food systems administration students at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, evaluated the effectiveness of the individualized study unit (experimental method) as opposed to the traditional lecture (control) method in teaching inventory management principles. A pretest was administered to each student in selected junior and senior courses prior to the teaching unit. A posttest was given three weeks after the pretest and following the teaching unit; then again, as a retention test, five weeks later. The student&#39;s prior exposure to inventory management principles, evaluation of teaching method and amount of time spent in the learning process were analyzed in relation to test scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test scores indicated that the vertical transfer of cognitive knowledge from the recall level to the problem solving level for inventory management principles was evident for students using the experimental method. These scores also showed that students in the senior course utilized the experimental method more effectively for achieving cognitive learning than did students in the junior courses. Posttest scores compared to retention test scores showed that the experimental method did influence student retention for the recall of inventory management principles as well as for the application of these principles towards solving a problem. The student&#39;s prior exposure to inventory management principles, evaluation of teaching method and time spent in the learning process did not affect cognitive learning or retention of knowledge for the principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study does show that the individualized instruction unit with computer simulation could be used for teaching conceptual thinking and techniques for decision making and problem solving needed for inventory management.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3787</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5449&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3787</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5449</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-15T14:25:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8978805</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3787</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Betty L. Beach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Jo Hitchcock, Grayce Goertz, Ohmer Milton, Ada Marie Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1976-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>