<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Colonizing Cyberspace: The Formation of Virtual Communities</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The topic of this thesis is the electronic bulletin board systems that existed in Memphis, TN from the early 1980s until around 1999.  Although initially a fringe hobby limited to computer enthusiasts, the declining cost of computers, and their subsequent proliferation, allowed those without technical proficiency to dial in.  Over time, those who connected to the BBSes developed into a close-knit, emotionally involved community. The dynamics of the communities that arose on BBSes differed based on numerous factors, particularly age. This thesis attempts to examine those interactions, as well as challenge the notion that community is wedded to geography, an idea prevalent among historians. &lt;br /&gt;    In order to accomplish this goal, I have relied on interviews with those who participated in the Memphis BBS scene, as well as a survey questionnaire for those unable to schedule meetings. In addition, many users retained log files, message base archives, and a host of other relevant materials which were also utilized as primary sources. A great wealth of data was also found on the World Wide Web, particularly among sites devoted to the BBSes.&lt;br /&gt;    Computer-mediated communication is rapidly changing how individuals interact. Email, chat rooms, and instant messaging have already impacted how people build and maintain social networks. These changes are not as new as many thing, however. Well before the Internet, the BBSes altered those who participated in similar ways. Thus, this thesis examines the BBS community in order to broaden understanding of computer-mediated interaction in general.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2039</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3398&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2039</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3398</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-01T08:47:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4651831</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2039</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Janis Appier</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kathleen Brosnan, Vejas Liulevicius</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>