<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A computational approach to understanding material system : infrared coating of Ni-P on steel</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Engleman</lname>
<fname>Peter</fname>
<mname>Gregory</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;It is thought that Ni-P can be used as a binder for ceramics (WC, TiC, etc.) used in coating applications such as those for corrosion and wear resistance. It is the intent of this study to use existing, commercially available models, such as Thermo-Cale® and Dictra®, to predict what phases will be present, in what quantities, and where, with respect to the interface, these phases can be found for Ni-P coatings fused on steel using high-density infrared processing techniques. It is also the goal of this study to attempt to predict the amount of co-diffusion that will occur between the coating and substrate materials and what effect(s) this will have on the material properties. High-density infrared processing offers a method for close process control. Since it is a cold-wall technique, the specimen is heated directly and begins cooling immediately when the furnace is shut down. Using infrared processing also allows close control of time and temperature parameters providing the ideal environment for exploring diffusion controlled experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5219</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6627&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5219</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6627</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847063</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5219</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Narendra Dahotre</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>