<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>When One Should Forgive: Eirenistic Responses to Wrongdoing</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dlewis14@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Lewis</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>Court</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Philosophy</keyword>
<keyword>Ethics</keyword>
<keyword>Forgiveness</keyword>
<keyword>Rights</keyword>
<keyword>Nicholas Wolterstorff</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Ethics and Political Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In my dissertation I use Nicholas Wolterstorff’s conception of the good life (eirenéism), which serves as the foundation for his theory of rights, to argue for a new ethics of forgiveness that incorporates the necessary relational features of forgiveness, while at the same time providing substantive normative guidance in regards to &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; one should forgive. I, then, show that eirenistic forgiveness implies there is an obligation to forgive: a repentant wrongdoer has a right to be forgiven that creates certain obligations for victims to forgive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, like Wolterstorff, find such an implication repugnant, and so I spend the majority of my dissertation addressing this implication. I address the obligation to forgive by developing and responding to Wolterstorff’s claim that forgiveness is a non-obligation-producing third-party obligation, and I argue that because forgiveness is like all other obligations, the acceptance of such a position implies that all obligations are third-party obligations. To avoid this conclusion, I provide an argument that shows that the two-party obligation to forgive is not repugnant, or at least not as repugnant as first seems. I spend the remainder of my dissertation showing how one can apply eirenistic forgiveness to a wide-range of difficult cases, that the right to seek punishment does not compete or override the obligation to forgive, and by examining whether or not eirenéism is a religious ethic or if it is an ethical system amenable to both theists and non-theists.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1321</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2428&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1321</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2428</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-02-11T12:24:01-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2428/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2513112</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1321</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Glenn Graber</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Nolt, E.J. Coffman, Alfred Beasley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>