<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Propulsion/airframe Integration Study of an Ultra High Bypass Ratio Turbofan and a Slotted, Natural-Laminar-Flow Wing</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Next-generation aircraft concepts such as the transonic truss-braced wing, integrate ultra-high- bypass-ratio turbofan engines and natural-laminar-flow wings. Slotted, natural-laminar-flow technology shows the potential to further reduce fuel burn. Currently, propulsion/airframe integration effects between the engine and wing are not well characterized. A representative N+3 turbofan engine model was created by scaling a NASA reference engine to the fan diameter and cruise thrust requirements of the transonic truss-brace wing. NASA’s OVERFLOW computational fluid dynamics code was used to characterize a semi-infinite slotted, natural- laminar-flow wing and a representative N+3 turbofan both installed and in isolation to quantify the influence of propulsion/airframe integration on interference drag. Four engine positions were investigated: trailing-edge/over-wing, leading-edge/over-wing, leading-edge/under-wing, and trailing-edge/under-wing. It was determined that leading-edge/over-wing and trailing-edge/under- wing mounted nacelles created similar or less interference drag than conventional leading- edge under-wing nacelles at cruise conditions. The trailing-edge/under-wing had the minimum interference drag of all configurations considered. These findings show the need for full 3-D wing integration testing to accurately place the engine.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5528</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7001&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5528</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7001</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914330</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5528</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James Coder Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stephanie Termaath Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>