<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Experimental Study On The Production Of Negative Ion Copper Clusters And Applications</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rchu@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chu</lname>
<fname>Ran</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Copper cluster</keyword>
<keyword>metral cluster</keyword>
<keyword>negative ion</keyword>
<keyword>sputtering source</keyword>
<keyword>application of copper cluster</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Nuclear</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;At the Holifield Radioactive Ion Beam Facility (HRIBF) at Oak Ridge National Laboratories (ORNL), we investigated the formation, production and potential application of negative-ion copper clusters using mass distributions of negative-ion copper clusters obtained by bombarding various copper samples with Cs ions. The Cu samples – in very large mass-selected clusters Cu (e.g. n=54) – included natural Cu, isotopically enriched copper-63 and copper-65, and electroformed ultra-clean Cu. Mass spectra of negative copper cluster produced by Cs sputter source size up to 50 are shown for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three main features were observed for all four copper samples: the intensity of copper cluster ion exhibit an even-odd alternation because of electron pairing in the highest occupied molecular orbitals ; a discontinuity in the ion intensity at magic number n = 2, 8, 20, 40 due to close of shell in the shell model; the abundance of a copper cluster has a power-law dependence on its size n. The exponent we measured for the copper cluster was ~ 3. It’s for the first time to report experimental power-law exponent of copper cluster low to 3 which consists of the thermodynamic model and shock wave model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, by having access to various samples of copper, including isotopically enriched material, we were able to study the formation of clusters involving various combinations of copper-63 and copper-65. A binomial distribution was observed for the formation of Cu clusters from natural Cu and clean Cu samples and it indicates the formation of sputter copper cluster is a random multiple sequential aggregation. It’s for the first time to shown isotopes exhibit binomial distribution inside a metal cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explored a potential application of copper clusters, utilizing the energy-and-mass-selected copper cluster to prepare nanoporous graphene for applications such as water desalination. Copper clusters of size (n = 3 and 9) and energy 200 keV were applied to bombard the single-layer graphene with various dosages. Raman spectrum and scanning electron microscopy showed diameter around 2 nm defects were created.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4280</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4830&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4280</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4830</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-19T07:40:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7237721</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4280</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alfredo Galindo-Uribarri</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Anthony Mezzacappa, Thomas Papenbrock</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>