<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The role of the Chilhowee Baptist faith community in healthcare : an association-wide study of member perspectives</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Van Camp</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The United States has documented a strong 30-year history in regards to health promotion and health education. National health leaders recognize that individuals must accept greater responsibility for their own health before improvements in community health can be achieved. The focus on collaboration and partnering between healthcare providers and community organizations is essential for health promotion. Religion has played a role in health promotion by advocating for personal health and accepting responsibility for improving the health of others. Thus, faith-based health organizations provide an excellent venue for offering health programs. As a result of this new awareness, community leaders have initiated grassroots projects to identify local health needs. Blount County, Tennessee provides a strong faith-based organization and a public health infrastructure for community diagnosis. The Blount County Community Diagnosis Status Report of 1999 claims faith-based organizations are a valid option for addressing local health needs.  The purpose of this study was to determine the role of the Chilhowee Baptist faith community in healthcare by analyzing the member&#39;s perceptions of health issues such as: promoting better personal health, managing medical health problems, coping with family/life changes, and addressing mental health. The study was designed to examine if the size of the congregation or the member&#39;s demographic characteristics impact their perceptions regarding the level of involvement or the focus of responsibility in the four health issues.  A closed-form questionnaire was designed to elicit anonymous responses regarding the level of involvement and focus of responsibility for health issues within the Chilhowee Baptist Association. The survey instrument used for this study categorized focus areas from Healthy People 20 IO into four sections: personal health, medical health problems to include acute and chronic illnesses, coping and emotional health, and finally, mental health. The survey was field-tested by members of the Knoxville and Sweetwater Baptist Associations prior to distribution to the Chilhowee Baptist Association. The participants completed a survey designed to elicit perceptions on two healthrelated questions: 1) to what extent should the Baptist faith community be involved in promoting better personal health, managing medical health problems, coping with family/life changes, and addressing mental health, and 2) who should be responsible for addressing these health issues. Participants were selected by a convenience sample as pastors of the Chilhowee Baptist Association volunteered to participate in the study. A total of 500 surveys were distributed among small (&lt;250 members) and large (=&gt; 251 members) churches. Either the pastor or an alternate member of the congregation administered surveys. Only adult members participated in the research and anonymity was maintained throughout the study. The overall response rate was 61. 6% with small churches providing 53. 9% of the returned surveys and 46.1 % of the responses represent large churches. The majority (57.8%) of responses came from regular church members as opposed to pastors, teachers, deacons, or other church staff. Most (73. 7%) respondents have been involved in church for over 20 years. More females (5 8. 8%) participated than did men (38.6% ). All age categories from 18 to over 65 years of age were represented in the study; however, only 33.2% were aged 18 - 44 years while 66.2% of participants were aged 45 years and greater.  Survey responses indicated how the participants perceived the role of the Baptist faith community in healthcare based on church size, participant&#39;s age, and the number of years participant has been involved in church. There was no difference in reported level of involvement for promoting better personal health, managing medical health problems, coping with family/life changes, and addressing mental health based on church size and number of years member has been involved in church. Members of small churches indicated a significantly greater interest in shared responsibility between the individual church and the Baptist Association for managing medical health problems and addressing mental health than members of large churches. Members involved in church 21 or more t years indicated a greater interest in shared responsibility for addressing mental health issues. Participants aged 18 - 44 years perceived a higher level of involvement for coping with family/life changes; yet age did not factor into the focus of responsibility. Further statistical analysis indicated a commonality among all the health issues. Most participants indicated a need to be involved in promoting better personal health, managing medical health problems, coping with family/life changes, and addressing mental health and the majority favored a shared responsibility between the individual church and Baptist association.  Results enable the Chilhowee Baptist Association to address the health issues identified through this study, particularly addressing mental health and coping with family/life changes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5309</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6717&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5309</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6717</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847252</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5309</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paula Carney</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Health Promotion and Health Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>