<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>One Person, One Vote and the Constitutionality of the Winner-Take-All Allocation of Electoral College Votes</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-03T14:35:14-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Duquette</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Schultz</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electoral college</keyword>
<keyword>votes</keyword>
<keyword>voting</keyword>
<keyword>constitutionality</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Constitutional Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Electoral College is an American political and constitutional curiosity. The constitutional framers believed it would produce &quot;extraordinary persons&quot; as presidents because they would be selected by &quot;men most capable of analyzing the qualities adapted to the station&quot; of the presidency.&#39; Its more recent defenders, such as Martin Diamond, have justified it as either a constitutional system meant to protect individual and minority rights or a mechanism to overcome regionalism. In Diamond&#39;s view, along with the principles of separation of powers and checks and balances, it was necessary to thwart the dangers of factionalism that a popular government posed. Some have noted that, with an Electoral College, national recounts are unnecessary, as only the votes cast in disputed jurisdictions would need to be recounted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol2/iss3/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1042&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1042</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-03T14:17:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5257252</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol2/iss3/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Christopher Duquette: Research Staff, Center for Naval Analysis, Alexandria, Virginia.

David Schultz: Professor, Graduate School of Management and Department of
Criminal Justice and Forensic Science, Hamline University, and School of Law, University of Minnesota.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Electoral College Votes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>