<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Histological Examination of &lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt; for Forensic Application</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Trammell</lname>
<fname>Lindsay</fname>
<mname>Hines</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Few researchers have endeavored to approach the issue of bone histology in non-human specimen. In the forensic setting, it is oftentimes the norm to establish the origin of fragmentary remains as human or non-human; if the fragments are non-human then the analysis is usually said to be finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the specimen does prove to be non-human, it is useful and important to learn the identity of the faunal species. The white-tailed deer (&lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) is common to the Eastern United States and is very often found in forensic settings, commingled with or alongside of human remains. This study thoroughly examines the histological character of the white-tailed deer so that it may be identified with confidence in the forensic field or in an archaeological setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assess the white-tailed deer femora and humeri were procured from five deer of varying ages -- the goal being to understand histological changes within bones from the same specimen and between bones of deer at different stages of maturity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the aid of a Buehler Isomet 1000 saw, two 0.08mm sections were cut at three-centimeter intervals on each diaphysis of the femur and humerus for each deer. These thin-sections were examined under a Leica DMRX light microscope at 100x magnification. The presence of all histological structures was noted for each slide and when evidence of bone remodeling was recorded, area measurements were taken on secondary osteons and Haversian canals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The observations and measurement data from each femur and humerus of the deer samples were compared in a statistical analysis to assess inter- and intra-bone variability among the deer. A repeated measures ANOVA examined the differences in osteon and Haversian canal area across the segments of the femoral and humeri shafts and between ages. These results indicate whether or not the histological character of the white-tailed deer differs depending on the age, the bone, or the specific location on a bone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results indicate no significant mean differences within shafts or across ages for osteon area in the femur. No differences exist within the shafts of the humeri. Notable variations in osteon area do exist between ages in the humerus -- the 3-year-old deer diverged from both the 1.5-year-old and the 2.5-year-old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results also indicated no significant mean differences intra-shaft or across ages for Haversian canal areas in the femur. A significance difference was noted between the Haversian canal areas in the nine-month deer and the 2.5-year-old deer humeri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the findings a blind test was performed on four unidentified bones samples to discern deer from other ungulates based on osteon areas. The methodology and results of this research were successfully utilized to distinguish white-tailed deer bone from pig, sheep, and goat at the histological level.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1818</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3173&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1818</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3173</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-11T10:07:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4574753</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1818</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Walter Klippel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lee Meadows Jantz, Murray Marks</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>