<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Estimates of Linear Energy Transfer from Solar Energetic Particles in Earth&#39;s Upper Atmosphere to Human Tissue in Aluminium Aircraft</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mhall40@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hall</lname>
<fname>Michael Ian</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>The Sun and the Solar System</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Radiation from extraterrestrial sources is a concern for the safety of passengers and crew in high altitude aircraft. Cosmic radiation and solar particles constantly bombard the atmosphere with energy. Radiation levels from these sources can vary considerably depending on solar activity cycles and energetic particle events such as solar flares. In order to predict the effects of such events the nature of the radiation spectrum must be characterized, and the individual effects of each radiation type understood. The background radiation spectrum is known to good accuracy and prediction of radiation levels due to specific solar events is currently under investigation. This work begins the task of calculating the expected effects upon human tissue from these radiation sources with intervening air and aluminum. Proton and alpha radiation of 3000 MeV/nucleon and less is simulated using a software package called the High Energy Transport Code – Human Exploration and Development in Space (HETC-HEDS), and linear energy transfer to tissue surrogate is tabulated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/876</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2010&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>876</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2010</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-19T15:24:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1947574</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/876</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence W. Townsend</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lawrence H. Heilbronn, Bethany L. Goldblum</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>