<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Congressional Career of Cordell Hull</title>
<publication-date>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Leland</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Preface: During the summer of 1963, under the direction of Dr. Stanley J. Folmsbee, Professor of History at The University of Tennessee, I prepared a short paper on an early period of Cordell Hull&#39;s congressional career. This study was fascinating. It appeared to me that many students who know a great deal about Hull&#39;s secretaryship under President Roosevelt are unaware of his preparation for this high position. Thus, during the latter part of the summer after a trip to Hull&#39;s hometown, Carthage, Tennessee, it was concluded that a thesis on the congressional career of Cordell Hull would prove a valuable contribution to historical research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of invaluable help in this project was the staff of The University of Tennessee Library. Miss Eleanor Goehring, research librarian at the University of Tennessee, deserves special appreciation. Also of assistance was the staff of Knoxville&#39;s Lawson McGhee Library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also deeply indebted to those of the Department of History, University of Tennessee, who served so ably as members of the committee responsible for the reviewing of this thesis. Of great assistance were Dr. LeRoy P. Graf and Dr. Ralph W. Haskins. A special word of gratitude is given Dr. Folmsbee, head of the committee. An above all, my faithful mother is thanked for her splendid help in typing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4209</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5663&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4209</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5663</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-11-04T11:24:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9346389</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4209</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stanley J. Folmsbee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>LeRoy P. Graf, Ralph W. Haskins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>