<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Conceptualizing Organizational Growth by Biomimicking the Growth of Genetically Modified Trees</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Sindi</lname>
<fname>Magdi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The development of human-based organizations for the purpose of surviving during the transitional crisis periods is always faced with continuous challenges concurrently with the deployment of new technologies, with new competitors entering the market, with changes in customers’ needs, with new regulations enforced, etc. As a result of not successfully passing transitional crisis periods, many businesses go bankrupt every year, and therefore organizational developers need to consider new approaches for development. Biomimicry is one of the rising approaches that has not been studied well for organizational development purposes. Biomimicking trees inspire organizational developers in recent years. However, there is still no much information about biomimicking genetically modified trees since GMOs played a significant role in many industries. This research is trying to mathematically determine whether biomimicking genetically modified trees are a better representation than normal trees for organizational development purposes. The research did mathematically find that GM trees are superior over their normal version on relevant econometrics of human-based organizations. However, the connection between trees and human-based organizations could not be considered in the mathematical model due to the finding of this research that the connection is based on the universal growth pattern of all natures processes “s-curve” that is not quantifiable per up to date findings in this research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5783</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7549&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5783</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7549</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419686</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5783</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James Simonton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Kobza, Yu Andrew, Trevor Moeller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>