<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Jean-Paul Sartre&#39;s Concepts of Praxis and History in his &lt;em&gt; Critique of Dialectical Reason&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chun</lname>
<fname>Kyung</fname>
<mname>Ock</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Political Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary problem of this study is to clarify Sartre&#39;s concept of praxis as a projective action of human consciousness which creates history and makes it intelligible. I focus on Sartre&#39;s attempt to combine an existential humanism with a theory of history as a progressive movement generated by individual actors, their social groups, and their environmental surroundings. Sartre&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Critique&lt;/em&gt; provides the philosophical basis for understanding social institutions and behavior, and describes human action as a complex totality comprising free subjectivity and its unavoidable environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inquiry focuses on the existential root of Sartre&#39;s theory of history and the problematic nature of his position. Although he allocates priority to an actor&#39;s consciousness and actions, his explanation, at times, is vague and unconvincing. While he emphasizes human freedom he inadvertly illustrates the enormous influence of a material world which is beyond our control.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1486</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2927&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1486</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2927</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-16T13:15:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4318945</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1486</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert A. Gorman</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Vernon R. Tyrell, James O. Burnett</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Political Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>