<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SP572 Transplanting Trees</title>
<publication-date>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Trees</keyword>
<keyword>Planting</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Successfully transplanting trees depends on decisions and production practices that take place long before the first shovel of soil is turned. Selecting the right species and high-quality nursery stock based on planting site characteristics, available care after planting, transplant size, root ball characteristics and nursery production practices is essential to successful transplanting. The rewards for attention to these details will be realized as the transplanted tree matures and increases its importance to your property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trees experience tremendous stress in the transplanting process, primarily from adverse changes in their ability to absorb water due to root loss. Water stress is the primary cause of transplant failure. Root loss affects hormone synthesis and distribution that regulate shoot growth. Root loss also reduces carbohydrate storage, affecting energy available for rapid root regeneration, critical for transplant survival. The ability of a tree to maintain sufficient vigor while recovering from the adversities of transplanting will determine its success or failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trees have traditionally been offered for sale in the nursery trade using three methods: bare-root, balled and burlapped (B&amp;B), and containers including pot-in-pot and in-ground fabric containers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfores/89</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1088&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfores&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>89</label>
<document-type>treeplanting</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1088</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-31T11:24:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Forestry, Trees, and Timber</publication-title>
<context-key>1256558</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfores/89</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>SP572-15M-12-00    R12-4910-21-004-01</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>