<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Structure, Function and Regulation of Two Isoforms of Glutamine Synthetase from Soybean Root Nodules</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pmasalka@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Masalkar</lname>
<fname>Pintu</fname>
<mname>Daulatrao</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>glutamine synthetase</keyword>
<keyword>oxidation</keyword>
<keyword>nodulin 26</keyword>
<keyword>ammonia</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Glutamine synthetase (GS) is a major ammonia assimilatory enzyme in soybean nodules. The four isoforms of cytosolic glutamine synthetase (GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;[glutamine synthetase 1]β[beta]1, GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;β2, GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ[gamma]1 and GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ2) present in soybean nodules are 80% identical with respect to amino acid sequence, and share similar kinetic properties. It is shown all major GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; isoforms interact with nodulin 26, a member of the aquaporin family of membrane channels. Nodulin 26 is the major protein component of the symbiosome membrane (SM), where it serves a function as an ammonia and water channel. The site of interaction of GS on nodulin 26 is the cytosolic C-terminus, where it binds with 1:1 stoichiometry. The binding of GS is proposed to dock the enzyme to the cytosolic surface of the SM. This would promote efficient assimilation of fixed nitrogen, as well as prevent potential ammonia toxicity, by futile cycling of ammonia/ammonium across the SM. Quantitative PCR analysis of the transcripts of all the isoforms from soybean tissues shows that GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ are the nodule-specific isoforms, but that the GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;β isoforms are highly expressed and the highest transcripts in nodules is GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;β1. Further investigation of GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; isoforms showed that they are subjected to differential regulation by thiol based disulfide bond formation. Specifically, GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ1 is sensitive to inhibition by reversible oxidation whereas the GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;β1 is not sensitive to oxidizing conditions. Site-directed mutagenesis of the GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ1 isoform showed that the oxidation observed is due to reversible disulfide bond formation through intersubunit cys92 and cys159 across the shared active site. Analytical ultracentrifugation studies showed a difference in the native oligomeric molecular weight of the two isoforms, with GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;β1 forming a decamer and GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ1 forming a dodecamer. It is hypothesized that these differences in quaternary structure is linked to their different sensitivities to thiol based regulation, possibly due to distinct positioning of the intersubunit cysteine sulfhydryls. The reversible oxidation observed for GS&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;γ1 is unique to this isoform and may serve as an additional level of regulation in response to oxygen tension in the infected cell, as well as in response to reactive oxygen production during stress responses.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2842</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4208&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2842</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4208</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-06-18T09:51:25-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4208/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5699529</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2842</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel M. Roberts</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Elizabeth Howell, Gladys Alexandre, Beth Mullin, Feng Chen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>