<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Now is the Winter of Ginsburg&#39;s Dissent: Unifying the Circuit Split As To Preliminary Injunctions and Establishing A Sliding Scale Test</title>
<publication-date>2018-11-07T13:41:12-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>taylor.dale.payne@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Payne</lname>
<fname>Taylor</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil Procedure</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Politics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The preliminary injunction is an equitable remedy that may be granted to prevent harm to a movant before adjudication on the merits can be reached. The United States Supreme Court most recently iterated in &lt;em&gt;Winter v. National Resource Defense Counsel, Inc.&lt;/em&gt; the four factors a court must consider for a preliminary injunction to issue.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; A movant seeking a preliminary injunction must establish that the movant is likely to succeed on the merits; that the movant is likely to suffer irreparable harm in the absence of preliminary relief; that the balance of equities tips in the movant’s favor; and that an injunction is in the public interest.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; Federal circuits have long been split over how to apply these factors and what kind of test these factors create. Following &lt;em&gt;Winter&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;there is still no consensus. The circuits apply three different tests to preliminary injunction questions: the sequential test, the sliding scale test, and the gateway factor test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circuits that apply the sequential test require a movant to prove each of the four factors in turn, and a failure to prove one factor bars injunctive relief. Circuits that apply the sliding scale test balance all four factors, and a higher showing on one factor can make up for a lesser showing on another factor. Circuits that apply the gateway factor test require movants to demonstrate a likelihood of success on the merits and a likelihood of suffering irreparable harm in the absence of preliminary relief before addressing the remaining two elements. Under this approach the first two factors are dispositive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article argues that the sliding scale test is the most appropriate test when determining whether to issue a preliminary injunction. The history of equity in the United States supports this assertion. Further, the Supreme Court has historically endorsed the sliding scale test.   &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; 555 U.S. 7 (2008).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; Winter v. Natural Res. Def. Council, Inc., 555 U.S. 7, 20 (2008) (Ginsburg, J., dissenting) (citing&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Munaf v. Geren, 553 U.S. 674, 689–90 (2008); Amoco Prod. Co. v. Village of Gambell, 480 U.S. 531, 542 (1987); Weinberger v. Romero-Barcelo, 456 U.S. 305, 311–12 (1982)).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol13/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1191&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1191</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-10-31T14:43:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>13215618</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol13/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Now is the Winter of Ginsburg&#39;s Dissent</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>