<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Speaking in Whispers: Developing and Using Subtle Communication Skills to Enhance Interactions During Animal-Assisted Mental Health Applications</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T14:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>animalsystems@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Denver</institution>
<lname>MacNamara</lname>
<fname>Maureen</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaking in whispers: Developing and using subtle communication skills to enhance interactions during animal-assisted mental health applications.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No activity involving animals compares with the intrinsically stressful social interaction that takes place in animal-assisted mental health sessions. No other animal-related event, no sport nor competition requires animals to enter the intimate zones of unfamiliar humans and remain there for several minutes or longer while an unfamiliar person engages in petting, hugging, or directing (training, riding) the animal. The role is new, specific, and profound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This presentation provides a review of recent findings related to canine learning and communication that can be intentionally utilized in order to optimally support participant goals. The session moves beyond the use of obedience training and agility activities and introduces a process for linking participant goals to the development of specific human-canine interactions. Video and live demonstrations will be presented to illustrate interaction techniques and processes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/13</coverpage-url>
<label>13</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1057</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-18T09:13:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3545570</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/13</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Maureen is a doctoral candidate at the University of Denver Graduate School of Social Work. Her dissertation focuses on the influence of dogs during child maltreatment investigations. She designed the Human Service-AAI technician track for Tri-County Community College and is adjunct faculty at Western Carolina University. As a macro-level social worker, Maureen developed a volunteer training and animal screening program which was adopted internationally. Currently, she assists clinicians with the selection and training of animals working in animal interaction applications and is a consultant in the development and implementation of mental health programs incorporating animals.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;41 Haw Creek Circle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asheville, NC 28805&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;612 701 9462&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T15:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>LECONTE</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Workshop: 1-hour workshop</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T14:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T14:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>