<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Differential Expression of Skin Cancer and Hair-Follicle Cycle Regulated Genes in Tumor Susceptible K14-Agouti Mice</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Son</lname>
<fname>Yesim</fname>
<mname>Aydin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The mouse agouti protein is transiently expressed in the skin and signals through the melanocortin 1 receptor to switch pigment production of hair-follicle melanocytes from black to yellow. Ubiquitous over-expression of agouti protein in mice carrying the spontaneous dominant mutations &lt;em&gt;A&lt;em&gt;y &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;A&lt;em&gt;vy &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;causes a pleiotropic syndrome characterized by solid yellow hair color, obesity, diabetes, and increased susceptibility to carcinogenesis in a wide variety of tissues, including the skin. Over-expression of agouti in the skin of keratin 14 (K14)- Agouti transgenic mice promotes skin carcinogenesis, even in the absence of obesity and diabetes. In this study cDNA microarray and qRT-PCR analyses are used to identify molecular changes in the skin of K14-Agouti mice associated with the promotion stage of carcinogenesis. Histological analysis of the skin revealed that there were no differences in gross morphology or in timing of hair- follicle stages between transgenic and control mice. However, cDNA microarray analysis identified 181 genes with significantly altered expression levels in the skin of transgenic mice. Additionally, qRT-PCR analysis demonstrated that the levels and temporal patterns of expression of 10 genes previously associated with skin and/or other epithelial cancers were significantly altered in the skin of K14- Agouti transgenic mice. Agouti-induced over-expression of these proto- oncogenes in the skin of K14-Agouti mice is proposed to be associated with the increased susceptibility to skin carcinogenesis. A hypothetical model is presented to explain the mechanism of action of the agouti protein as a tumor promoter in skin carcinogenesis. Additionally, strategies for future follow-on experiments to further investigate the role of agouti in tumor promotion and to test aspects of the proposed hypothetical model are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1636</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3147&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1636</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3147</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-24T11:38:21-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4343016</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1636</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward J. Michaud</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cymbeline T. Culiat, Mitchel J. Doktycz, Mary Ann Handel, Jay R. Snoddy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>