<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Virulence Characteristics and Genetic Diversity of &lt;i&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/i&gt; Isolates from Cases of Bovine Mastitis in Eastern Tennessee.</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jacmvaug@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Vaughn</lname>
<fname>Jacqueline</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Dairy</keyword>
<keyword>Enterotoxins</keyword>
<keyword>PFGE</keyword>
<keyword>Bovine</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/i&gt; is an important zoonotic mastitis pathogen that has significant effects on animal and human health. &lt;i&gt;S. aureus&lt;/i&gt; is also a foodborne pathogen that causes food poisoning through its diverse enterotoxins. Some studies showed that &lt;i&gt;S. aureus&lt;/i&gt; strains that cause infection in a particular host are genetically distinct and are host specific, although most strains are believed to be infective to a wide range of host species. However, there are no clearly defined clonal patterns of &lt;i&gt;S. aureus&lt;/i&gt; that possess certain virulence factors responsible for causing a disease. The objectives of this study were: 1) evaluate clonal diversity of &lt;i&gt;S. aureus&lt;/i&gt; isolates from cases of bovine mastitis 2) determine staphylococcal enterotoxin production patterns 3) evaluate &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; adhesion and invasion ability of dominant strains on bovine mammary epithelial cell line (MAC-T cells). Milk samples from bovine mastitis were evaluated at Tennessee Quality Milk Laboratory (TQML) for causative agents. Overall, 111 &lt;i&gt;S. aureus&lt;/i&gt; strains were isolated and evaluated for genetic diversity by pulsed field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) and for presence of toxin genes that encode for staphylococcal enterotoxins (&lt;i&gt;sea&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;seb&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;sec&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;see&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;sej&lt;/i&gt;) and toxic shock syndrome toxin 1 (&lt;i&gt;tsst-1&lt;/i&gt;) by PCR. The &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; adhesion and invasion ability of the dominant strains were evaluated on mammary epithelial cell line (MAC-T). We found 16 PFGE types (dominant clones) ranging from A – P. The PFGE type M is the most prevalent of all 16 PFGE types. The PCR results of enterotoxins genes showed that some of these strains were positive for staphylococcal enterotoxin genes including &lt;i&gt;seb&lt;/i&gt; (11.7%), &lt;i&gt;sec&lt;/i&gt; (2.7%), &lt;i&gt;see&lt;/i&gt; (0.9%) and toxic shock syndrome toxin 1 (&lt;i&gt;tsst-1&lt;/i&gt;) (7.2%), whereas most strains (75.7%) were negative for enterotoxin genes. In addition, evaluation of association of PFGE types, enterotoxins and other virulence factors, that were evaluated previously, showed that PFGE types O and M tend to cluster with beta-hemolysin, absence of enterotoxins and susceptibility to antimicrobials. Analysis of &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; adhesion to and invasion into MAC-T cells showed relatively higher number of O strain adhered to and invaded into MAC-T cells followed by M and I strains however were not statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5185</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6592&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5185</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6592</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415175</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5185</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Oudessa Kerro Dego</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jun Lin, Gina M. Pighetti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>