<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Studies of Reaction Processes for Voloxidation Methods</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jjohns87@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Jared</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Other Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Various facets of the voloxidation process and processes that have been derived from the voloxidation process have been investigated since its development over four decades ago. Despite the numerous studies performed, gaps remain in understanding of particular fundamental aspects of the reaction processes. In this work, several of these specific aspects of the oxidation processes for standard voloxidation and NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; [nitrogen dioxide] voloxidation are studied experimentally and modeled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of standard voloxidation, the oxidation rates of simulant UO&lt;sub&gt;­2 &lt;/sub&gt;[uranium dioxide] pressurized water reactor pellets in oxygen-rich environments were studied with an emphasis on the controlling phenomena for the reaction and the influence of cladding on these phenomena. Parametric isolation experiments for the oxidation of UO&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;pellets using thermogravimetric analysis were employed in which oxidant concentration, temperature, gas flow rate, and effect of cladding were studied. To supplement the thermogravimetric experiments, the reaction interface was characterized using neutron diffraction to validate assumptions for model development. From these experiments, a model approach is derived for the oxidation of clad UO&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;pellets during voloxidation. This work provides needed insight into the influence of various parameters on oxidation rate and reveals the potential controlling phenomena and their parameter dependencies to allow for improved process design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced NO&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;voloxidation, unlike standard voloxidation, is a novel process only recently proposed and thus there is much to investigate. The NO&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;voloxidation experiments and reaction models presented focus on the oxidation process of U&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; [triuranium octoxide] to UO&lt;sub&gt;3 &lt;/sub&gt;[uranium trioxide]. A structure for the ε [epsilon]-UO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; polymorph is proposed and employed for &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; X-ray diffraction studies for quantitative analysis to determine reaction rates and reaction mechanism. The data collected were modeled using a phenomena-based approach to propose the controlling mechanism for reaction. From the findings of the research presented, a better understanding of the oxidation process of U&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; to UO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; by NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; was achieved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1744</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2839&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1744</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2839</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-15T13:35:52-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2839/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3714780</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1744</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert M. Counce</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David J. Keffer, Barry B. Spencer, Claudia J. Rawn, Tom T. Meek, Jack S. Watson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>