<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spirituality in the workplace : a predictor of job satisfaction in the nursing profession</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Looney</lname>
<fname>Ruth</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The researcher conducted this study to investigate spirituality in the workplace and its influence on job satisfaction among nurses who belonged to a professional nursing organization. A secondary purpose of the study was to determine whether or not individuals&#39; demographic characteristics presented any effect on spirituality in the workplace and on job satisfaction. The researcher surveyed 500 members of the Tennessee Nursing Association for completion of this study. A total of 300 participants responded, which yielded an overall response rate of 60%. The data assessment for this study consisted of a questionnaire for gathering demographic information, the Finding Meaning and Purpose at Work Scale (FMPW), and the Job Satisfaction Scale (JSS). Parametric statistical analyses, including one-way analysis of variance, was used to determine significant differences among the individuals&#39; scores on the spirituality in the workplace scores, the job satisfaction scores, and the demographic characteristics. The researcher selected the Pearson r correlation coefficient to illustrate a significant relationship between scores on the FMPW and scores on the JSS. Stepwise multiple regression was used to predict the influence of the spirituality in the workplace scores on the job satisfaction scores. Major findings of the study included (a) individuals indicated strong homogeneity in their responses; (b) most demographic data had no impact on spirituality in the workplace or job satisfaction; (c) age determined significant difference in regards to spirituality in the workplace; (d) a strong positive relationship was established between spirituality in the workplace and job satisfaction. In conclusion, findings indicated that spirituality in the workplace was a strong predictor of job satisfaction through all of its subscales in the order of (a) community, (b) community and individual, and (c) community, individual, and unit. Thus, spirituality in the workplace showed influence on job satisfaction within this professional nursing organization.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5953</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7586&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5953</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7586</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467614</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5953</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Connie Hollingsworth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>