<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Encapsulation of Vitamin D3 in Gum Arabic to Improve Application in Beverages and Enhance Bioavailability</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mlamsen@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lamsen</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Ross</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cholecalciferol</keyword>
<keyword>gum acacia</keyword>
<keyword>encapsulation</keyword>
<keyword>physicochemical properties</keyword>
<keyword>absorption</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Delivery of vitamin D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) in foods should exhibit desirable physicochemical characteristics and enhance nutritional significance. To incorporate lipophilic VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in beverages, micro/nanoencapsulation of VD in food biopolymers stable at a wide pH range is a potential strategy. Gum arabic (GA), a highly branched arabinogalactan with a conjugated peptide, was investigated as a potential VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; carrier in this dissertation with objectives to determine (1) optimum conditions of encapsulating VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in GA to maximize loading and characterize physicochemical properties, (2) &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; bioaccessibility of encapsulated VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in optimized formulation, and (3) absorption of VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; after a single high-dose (300 μg) and daily-dose (60 μg d&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, 2-wks) oral supplementation by measuring 25(OH)D levels in Sprague-Dawley rats. To encapsulate VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, GA solution was prepared at 5% (w/v) in deionized water, VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; solutions were prepared separately in 5 mL ethanol corresponding to 0.03-6.0% mass of GA. VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; solution was added dropwise into 50 mL of the GA solution while blending at 8,000 rpm for 3 min and then 10,000 rpm for 2 min and freeze-dried. The optimized formulation had an encapsulation efficiency of 71.3% and a loading capacity of 3.44%. As pH increased from 2.0-7.4, the average hydrodynamic diameter decreased from 238.1 to 81.3 nm; whereas the polydispersity index increased from 0.372-0.478, and zeta-potential increased its magnitude from -3.09 to -30.97 mV. No precipitation was observed for all dispersions during 100-d storage at 3 °C. &lt;i&gt;In vitro&lt;/i&gt; bioaccessibility of encapsulated VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; was 95.76%, compared to 68.98% for non-encapsulated VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (p &lt; 0.05). The &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt; pharmacokinetic study after oral gavage of 300 μg VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; showed that the area-under-curve in 48 h of the encapsulation treatment was 4.32-fold of the non-encapsulated VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and more than twice higher than the physical mixture. For rats given a daily-dose of 60 μg VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; d&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; for 2 weeks, the serum 25(OH)D levels of rats that received capsules versus physical mixture showed an increase by 50% and 65%, respectively, when compared with the non-encapsulated VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; group. The current work demonstrates that the studied encapsulation system may be used to fortify VD&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in beverages with a wide pH range.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5403</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6939&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5403</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6939</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545423</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5403</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Qixin Zhong</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Guoxun Chen, Vermont P. Dia, Doris D&#39;Souza</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>