<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Influence of Quality of Worklife Variables on the Retention and Career Satisfaction of Science and Mathematics Teachers</title>
<publication-date>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Barker</lname>
<fname>Jerry</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Teacher shortages are predicted in all areas of public education.  These shortages are already a reality for science and mathematics.  The overall purpose of this study was to identify major workplace variables that affect job satisfaction within educational organizations.  Once identified these variables were utilized to construct an intervention framework grounded in the principles of the Quality of Work-life (QWL) paradigm.  The investigation was designed as a descriptive study utilizing a survey instrument and interviews developed around the QWL model of workplace satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study sample included 479 secondary classroom teachers representing a diverse range of school district types from four states.  A quality of work-life index was created for purposes of analysis.  Frequencies, correlations and weighted importance and satisfaction values were also calculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All major variables (e.g., work load, recognition, inclusion, working conditions) were perceived at relatively high levels of importance by all groups of participants.  The QWL variables perceived to be of highest importance were the extrinsic factors of resources, support systems and work load.  Those perceived as least important were recognition, inclusion and growth, all intrinsically related to workplace satisfaction.  QWL variables viewed at a relatively high level of satisfaction were sense of achievement, resources, job enrichment and support systems.  Areas of least satisfaction included growth, status and formal rewards.  Workplace factors perceived as having the highest discrepancy between degree of importance and level of satisfaction were formal rewards and status while least discrepant factors included job enrichment and sense of achievement.  Several significant relationships existed between demographic factors representing age, experience, salary, and level of education and the QWL variables of highest concern.  Based upon the above findings, a model was developed to integrate aspects of the QWL approach to workplace satisfaction.  This model would potentially reduce attrition among classroom teachers representing science, mathematics, and other instructional areas.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2980</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4467&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2980</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4467</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-24T11:03:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6282958</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2980</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>A. Paul Wishart</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James Camponetti, John Ray, Schuyler Huck</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>