<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Current and Best Practices for Recruiting Qualified Rehabilitation Counselors</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Walker</lname>
<fname>Kristi</fname>
<mname>Turner</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate the current status of the Comprehensive System of Personnel Development (CSPD) in Rehabilitation Services Administration’s Region IV, along with their current recruitment practices.  Written surveys and follow up phone interviews were used to gather data from the 19 Rehabilitation Counselor Education programs and the 12 Federal/State Vocational Rehabilitation programs in Region IV.  Additionally, suggestions were obtained from key stakeholders regarding future recruitment activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently there are 891 positions not filled with qualified Rehabilitation Counselors.  In addition, a majority of graduates from the Rehabilitation Counselor Education programs are not seeking employment from the Federal/State VR programs (51%).  The anticipated retirement and turnover rate for VR Counselors in the next three years is projected to be three times larger than the number of students graduating from RCE programs.  Consequently there is a need for an aggressive recruitment campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RCE Coordinators and VR Directors agreed that some needed recruitment strategies included:  recruitment and development of recruitment videos and development of a regional spokesperson, and development of a regional spokesperson, and development of a web based marketing program, paid internships for VR agencies, and marketing strategies for high schools and universities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4581</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6302&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4581</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6302</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-25T12:39:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10805857</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4581</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kathy Greenberg, Steve McCallum, Wayne Mulkey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>