<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Analysis of Values Conveyed by Fiction in &lt;em&gt;Boys’ Life&lt;/em&gt; Magazine, 2002-2006</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mendzigall</lname>
<fname>Tina</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Critical and Cultural Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Scholars involved in gender research generally advocate the idea that gender subjectivities are based on active social construction and interaction and as such are amenable to change. Notions and values of masculinity therefore are cultural constructs that are reflected and articulated through symbolic systems such as spoken and written language. Fiction narratives in teens’ magazines are one form of textual media content in which these values can be expressed. The purpose of this study was to explore the textual representations of American values of masculinity in 56 contemporary fiction stories of &lt;em&gt;Boys’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine by conducting a qualitative content analysis. The study used the values of the Scout Law as one definition of masculinity formulated by the Boy Scouts of America, one of the nation’s leading youth organizations and publisher of &lt;em&gt;Boys’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. Through close reading and thematic coding, this study revealed, on the one hand, that the values, with two exceptions, are well-reflected in different meanings and contexts and constructed through the use of different literary devices in the narratives. The study also indicated, on the other hand, that the portrayal of these values may lead to a rather narrow definition of a boy’s life and contribute to the limited construction of traditional masculinity. Further, it appeared that social recognition is represented as an important aspect in terms of performing in accordance with the values of the Scout Law. The study discusses implications of these and other findings as well as suggestions for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/171</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1203&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>171</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1203</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-09T13:51:15-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1138191</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/171</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ronald E. Taylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jinx Watson, Courtney Carpenter Childers</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/MendzigallTina.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>