<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Lakeshore Mental Health Institute - The Chota Building Lobby: A Case Study of Perceived Image</title>
<publication-date>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Milan</lname>
<fname>Patricia</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Interior Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The community Image of mental institutions has long been a negative one. Although many studies have examined the effect of the interior physical environment on patients m mental institutions, very little has been done to explore the effect of the interior environment of mental hospitals on public opinion. This case study was designed to determine if the physical environment plays a significant role m how various people of the community perceive Lakeshore Chota building lobby, and how their opinion may differ from viewing the existing lobby and then a 1&quot; = 1 &#39;0&quot; scale model of the lobby renovated. The opinions of three subject groups, mental health organization members, design professionals, and the layperson were taken through the use of two questionnaires. Fifty-four subjects were asked to view the existing lobby and fill out the first questionnaire. They were then taken to view the scale model of the lobby and fill out the second questionnaire. An analysis of variance with three variables, one between factor (subjects) and two repeated factors (environment &amp; dimension) was used to evaluate any differences between subjects, the two environments and seven dimensions within each environment. The results indicated that all subjects preferred the modeled environment. The mental health volunteers were the least critical, the laypeople were in the middle, and the designers were the most critical. All the dimensions were statistically different between the two environments, but the means indicated that the window treatments and the flooring were most likely the most significant. Ninety-six percent of subjects agreed that the interior space of a facility affected their opinion of the healthcare of a facility. Although the results from this study can not be generalized for all mental health facility, it does contribute to a research base for a better understanding of community members&#39; opinions towards mental health facilities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2687</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4106&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2687</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4106</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-28T08:29:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5626825</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2687</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Josette Rabun</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carl Dyer, Stanley Rabun</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>