<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Utilization of Tofu By-products as an Alternative Source of Bioactive Peptide Lunasin</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-17T12:37:14-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ashaunak@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Shaunak</lname>
<fname>Allison</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Schumacher</lname>
<fname>Niamh</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Veloza</lname>
<fname>Andrea</fname>
<mname>Nieto</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Utilization of tofu by-products as an alternative source of bioactive peptide Lunasin Lunasin is a 5kDa water-soluble bioactive peptide present in soybeans with anti-inflammatory, anti-carcinogenic, and chemotherapeutic properties. Current mechanisms for obtaining Lunasin from soybeans involve complicated and expensive methods that limit its utilization to a laboratory scale. Tofu is a cheese-like product obtained from soybeans. Whey and okara are the major by-products of the process and are mainly destined for animal feeding or as ingredients for food preparations, but their potential application as a sources of lunasin remains unexplored. Therefore, the aim of this study was to stablish if tofu by-products are suitable sources for obtaining lunasin enriched material by applying simple and easily scalable methods. Tofu was prepared from soybeans by a standardized procedure, and calcium was used to induce preferential precipitation of lunasin present in the by-products. Precipitate and supernatant fractions were characterized by measuring protein content, protein profile, lunasin content, and presence of isoflavones via Bradford assay, electrophoresis, western blot and HPLC respectively. Liquid fractions showed a wide distribution of proteins while calcium precipitates only contained low molecular weight proteins (&lt;15kDa). Both fractions contain negligible amounts of isoflavones and a significant concentration of lunasin, indicating that tofu by-products can be used as a source of lunasin enriched material.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/agsciences/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1279&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1279</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-05-17T08:32:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14522935</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/agsciences/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Herbert College of Agriculture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Vermont Dia</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>