<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The dendroarchaeology of the Swaggerty Blockhouse, Cocke County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Mann</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study is the first in the region in which dendrochronological and archaeological principles were combined to establish a site chronology, and attempted to answer two questions. First, does the dendrochronogical dating of the timbers correlate to the archaeological dating of artifacts recovered during excavations? Second, can dendrochronological processes be used to verify and establish more precise dating of artifact assemblages developed at sites in which wood or wooden artifacts have been recovered? I addressed these questions by examining the Swaggerty Blockhouse located northeast of Newport, in Cocke County, Tennessee, believed to have been built by James Swaggerty in 1787. The structure is made up of three levels. The first is a stone springhouse. The second level is 16 feet square and constructed with hewn oak timbers with comer notching. The third level is 21 feet square and constructed with poplar timbers joined by mortise and tenon. Dendrochronological testing at the Swaggerty Blockhouse began in June of 2001. I collected 37 oak samples, then created skeleton plots for each sample and to develop a floating chronology. The Norris Dam white oak chronology, which dates from 1633 and is anchored in 1980, was used as a master reference chronology for this study. In addition, I began archaeological testing in July of 2001. A total of 42 shovel tests were excavated, resulting in the recovery of 167 artifacts. Comparison of skeleton plots resulted in a cutting date of 1860. Rings from each sample were measured and the crossdating accuracy was tested using the COFECHA program. Correlation analyses on segments of ring measurement time series versus the master reference dating chronology gave an overall correlation of .557 (p&lt;.001) to the year 1860. The flat glass and nail portion of the artifact assemblage were analyzed to develop a mean date and an inception date. Glass thickness was analyzed which resulted in the mean glass date of 1864. Examination of nails recovered during shovel testing resulted in a median date of 1860. Based on my analysis, the Swaggerty &quot;Blockhouse,&quot; originally assigned to James Swaggerty in 1787, is instead a cantilever barn built by Jacob Stephens in 1860.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5959</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7592&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5959</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7592</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467621</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5959</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Henri Grissino-Mayer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>