<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fact Book: 1994-1995</title>
<publication-date>1994-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The Office of Institutional Research and Assessment</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the fifth annual Fact Book of the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. This edition commemorates the bicentennial of the founding of the University. Over the past 200 years, the institution has matured into one of the country&#39;s eminent state universities and land grant colleges. This compendium helps describe the &quot;multiversity,&quot; as former University of California President Clark Kerr has described the modem university, into which UTK has evolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all the previous issues, the staff of the Office of Institutional Research is grateful for the assistance we receive from our colleagues who collect and maintain the various university data bases. The amount of effort required to manage the information of the university is not always fully appreciated. Most of the tables and graphs herein identify the source from whom more detailed information may be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is our goal with each new edition of the Fact Book to amend its contents so that the information can be more useful to you, the reader. Toward that end, we appreciate and weicome your comments and advice on how this document may be improved to better serve your needs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_factbook/20</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1016&amp;amp;context=utk_factbook&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>20</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1016</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-21T12:24:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>UTK Fact Book</publication-title>
<context-key>3554870</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_factbook/20</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>