<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Entomological Technique as Referring to the Life History of Insects</title>
<publication-date>1927-05-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wheeler</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
<mname>Jefferson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;According to the statement of Kellogg in American Insects, man&#39;s real competitors are not the larger creatures that inhabit the Earth with us. These are relatively few in number and easily controlled; but the tiny creatures - the insects and insect-like creatures are the ones that present a real problem to us. They conquer us many times because they are so prolific and so numerous and because they are so small they often go unnoticed. Our Nation has realized the problem and has appropriated millions of dollars annually for the control of insects. This expenditure, however, is not sufficient and the general public should have more knowledge of insects as well as the other branches of nature study. To a better understanding of insect life and to carry on a more efficient warfare against our insect pests, more trained instructors are needed in our schools, colleges, and universities. Much research and writing has been done in entomology, but there is need of some works of compilation or condensation of large volumes into workable form so that the teacher and student may grasp it quickly and easily. In the following pages I have collected the best information available upon the subjects treated and put it into readable form. It is, however, a mere beginning, and it is presented with the hope that others will carry this work to completion.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3091</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4491&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3091</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4491</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-16T12:32:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6537787</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3091</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ffe6b2728)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1927-05-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1927-05-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>