<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relationships between Birth Order and Adjustment in Adolescents from Post-Divorce Families</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nash</lname>
<fname>Christi</fname>
<mname>Nichole</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study proposal seeks to examine the relationship between actual birth order, psychological birth order and adjustment in adolescence from post-divorced homes. Both actual birth and psychological orders are included in this particular study to investigate correlations, commonalities, and trends associated with each order and its affect on adjustment. The targeted group consists of freshmen attending the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Participants who identify their parents as currently divorced from each other within the past five years will be eligible to complete the research process. Participants will be administered both the Campbell-White Psychological Birth Inventory and Adult Behavior Checklist online to determine their psychological birth order and level of adjustment following their parents’ divorce. Actual birth order will be ascertained through a demographic questionnaire. This study proposal seeks to investigate relationships between birth order and external and internal adjustment to identify information that will be beneficial to mental health counselors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/54</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1082&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>54</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1082</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-20T06:32:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1115429</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/54</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joel Diambra</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Shawn Spurgeon, Jeannie Studer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Counseling</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>