<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Preparation and Certification of High School Teachers with Special Reference to Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1913-05-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Moser</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statistics relative to the actual preparation that the high school teachers of Tennessee have had are very difficult to obtain.  At the beginning of the study of this subject, the writer sent the accompanying questionnaire, to all the high school teachers-including both country and city schools-of the state, but the number returned was not sufficient to form any scientific conclusion on the subject.  Of the four hundred fifty blanks sent to the various high school teachers of the state only sixty were returned giving the desired information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the sixty returned, twenty-seven hold certificates issued on diplomas which is evidence that they hold a bachelor&#39;s degree from a college or university requiring four years of work to obtain the degree.  Three were graduates of some high school with only a high school diploma,  while thirty hold diplomas from some college but have not had the full four year course necessary to obtain a certificate on diploma.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3238</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4559&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3238</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4559</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-18T08:45:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6681070</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3238</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ffe340378)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1913-05-09T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1913-05-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>