<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Studies on Cytochrome P450 genes in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;: Relationship between over expression and DDT resistance, and xenobiotic induction</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kuruganti</lname>
<fname>Srilalitha</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cytochrome P450 monooxygenases (CYPs), are involved in the metabolism of a diverse group of endogenous and xenobiotic compounds. In insects, CYPs are involved in conferring resistance against insecticides. In &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;, the expression of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2, Cyp6a8, Cyp6g1, Cyp6w1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp12d1&lt;/em&gt; is higher in the resistant compared to susceptible strains. Recent study by Daborn et al (2002, &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, 297, 2253-2256) showed that &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; alone can confer resistance phenotype. The aim of my first objective was to re- examine this claim and second to examine the effect of common xenobiotic compounds on the transcriptome of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In first objective, six strains of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; were examined for DDT resistance and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; expression. Results showed that some of the highly susceptible strains showed high level of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; expression and Accord element in the &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; upstream DNA. When &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; allele of the resistant 91-R strain was substituted with that of the susceptible 91-C strain via recombination, the resulting three recombinant lines retained high level of resistance like the 91-R strain, but showed very low &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; expression. This suggests that there is a correlation between overexpression of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; and the presence of &lt;em&gt;Accord&lt;/em&gt; transposable element but not DDT resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part of the first objective, I directly examined the role of the &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6g1&lt;/em&gt; in DDT resistance. Germ line transformation in susceptible strain showed that there was a two-fold increase in DDT resistance (LD&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;) in transformed flies showing two-fold higher expression of GAL4/UAS driven CYP6A2 or CYP6G1 cDNA. A cumulative increase (4-fold) in DDT resistance was observed when both cDNAs were overexpressed in the same fly. Results suggest that the expression of multiple &lt;em&gt;Cyp&lt;/em&gt; genes may be needed to confer a high level of DDT resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second objective, microarray was used to examine the transcripts induced by caffeine and phenobarbital. Results showed that genes involved in detoxification, carbohydrate metabolism, signal transduction and &lt;em&gt;Cyp&lt;/em&gt; genes are induced by caffeine and phenobarbital. These are the same group of genes overexpressed in the resistant 91-R and recombinant strains. These studies shed light on the molecular basis of induction of &lt;em&gt;Cyp&lt;/em&gt; genes and insecticide resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1976</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3407&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1976</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3407</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-20T12:01:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4609423</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1976</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bruce McKee, John Koontz, Albrecht von Arnim, Sundar Venkatachalam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>