<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Communication Strategies in Direct-to-Consumer Prescription Drug Advertisements</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-18T06:56:03-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>iju@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Ju</lname>
<fname>Ilwoo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Advertising and Promotion Management</discipline>
<discipline>Health Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
<discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Little research has incorporated a theoretical framework for the analysis of message and creative strategies used in DTCA to date. The purpose of the current study is to extend the previous literature by providing a more complete list of DTCA message and/or creativity strategies based on Taylor’s message strategy wheel. The results show that DTCA has been used to promote drugs for such life-threatening conditions as asthma, acid reflux, Alzheimer’s disease, depression, and arthritis. The most common inducement was the offer of consumer support information. In general, magazine DTC ads from 2006 to 2010 were likely to take both informational and transformational approaches. The comprehensive list of message and creative strategies found in this study would indicate what strategies might be available for existing marketers or new entrants into the DTCA category. However, the use of emotional appeals in DTCA suggests a public policy concern. The theoretical, public policy, and managerial implications are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2013/session3/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1068&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1068</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-24T07:55:49-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1068/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>3555727</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2013/session3/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>