<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Quantitative Study of Growth of Some Dairy Psychrophiles</title>
<publication-date>1962-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>El-Farekh</lname>
<fname>Taher</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Dairy Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Summary and Conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samples of pasteurized skim milk were steamed for 25 minutes at approximately 100° C. and inoculated with pure cultures of &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fluorescens&lt;/em&gt;, A and B, at different levels, &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fragi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brevibacterium lipolyticum&lt;/em&gt;. The fifth culture was the normal flora of commercially pasteurized skim milk treated as a pure culture. All samples were stored at 4° C. Bacterial growth was determined using agar plates incubated at 25° C. for 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generation time was calculated for all cultures which ranged from 5.55 hours for &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fragi&lt;/em&gt; to 11.24 hours for &lt;em&gt;Brevibacterium lipolyticum&lt;/em&gt;. The generation time was found the same (7.22 hours) for &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fluorescens&lt;/em&gt; cultures A and B regardless of differences in inoculum size for the two cultures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the pure cultures, bacterial count after 7 days of storage was the highest for &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fragi&lt;/em&gt;, 3.0 x 10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, and the lowest for &lt;em&gt;Brevibacterium lipolyticum&lt;/em&gt;, 1.9 x 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; cells per ml. However, the mixed flora culture obtained a slightly lower count, 1.7 x 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; cells per ml.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lag phases for the pure cultures studied ranged from 1 day for &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas &lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;fragi&lt;/em&gt; to 3 days for both cultures of &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fiuorescens&lt;/em&gt;. The mixed flora culture showed still a longer lag phase of 4.2 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all cultures studied, &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fragi&lt;/em&gt; was found to be the most actively growing culture. It had the shortest generation time, the highest counts after 7 days of storage, and the shortest lag phase.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4856</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6361&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4856</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6361</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-01-08T12:13:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>11336480</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4856</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>W. W. Overcast</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. T. Miles, B. J. Demott, M. R. Johnston</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Major is listed as Dairying.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1962-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1962-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>