<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Systematics and species concepts in the genera Lentinus Fr. and Panus Fr., with emphasis on the Lentinus tigrinus, L. crinitus and Panus lecomtei complexes</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grand</lname>
<fname>Edward</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The monographic work of Pegler (1983) on &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;has established the taxonomic guidelines for most recent studies involving members of the genus (Moncalvo &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;2002, Rolen 2001, Krüger 2002).  Pegler’s taxonomic hierarchy combined both &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. and &lt;em&gt;Panus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. into one large genus, &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;Fr.  The combination of these genera and its validity was one of the reasons for beginning this study.  For generic level comparisons, ribosomal DNA sequence data can be helpful for determining relationships among taxa (Binder and Hibbett 2002, Hibbett and Vilgalys 1991, 1993, Hibbett and Donoghue 2001, Moncalvo &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;2002, Thorn &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;2000).  In this study, ribosomal large subunit (LSU) sequences were used to determine if &lt;em&gt;Lentinus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler should contain both &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. and &lt;em&gt;Panus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. LSU data were also used to explore the relationships of &lt;em&gt;Lentinus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler (1983) to genera affiliated with it in other works (Krüger 2002, Hibbett and Donoghue 2001, Moncalvo &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;2002).  I sought to assess various taxonomic schemes and the delineation of taxa using techniques such as morphology, sexual intercompatibility, and DNA sequence data.  In order to determine if ITS data could be useful in elucidating biogeographical patterns, this study concentrated on three morphological species complexes: &lt;em&gt;Lentinus crinitus &lt;/em&gt;(Linn.: Fr.) Fr., &lt;em&gt;L tigrinus &lt;/em&gt;(Bull.: fr.) Fr., and &lt;em&gt;L. strigosus &lt;/em&gt;(Schwein.) Fr. [&lt;em&gt;Panus lecomtei &lt;/em&gt;(Fr.) Corner in this study].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ribosomal ITS1 – 5.8S – ITS2 (ITS) region evolves faster and mutates more frequently than LSU (Hibbett 1992).  ITS sequence data was used to study species circumscriptions and delineations among &lt;em&gt;Lentinus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler (1983) and its segregates.  In some cases ITS sequence patterns can also be used to determine biogeographical patterns (Hughes &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;1999, Petersen and Bermudes 1992, Petersen 1995a, 1995b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Panus &lt;/em&gt;were found to be separable at the generic level based on LSU sequence data.  Several morphological sections (Pegler 1983) of the genera were polyphyletic in maximum parsimony and neighbor-joining analyses (sects. &lt;em&gt;Rigidi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Velutini&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Panus&lt;/em&gt;).  Group &lt;em&gt;Polyporellus &lt;/em&gt;(Nuñez and Ryvarden 1995) was closely related to &lt;em&gt;Lentinus tigrinus &lt;/em&gt;and sect. &lt;em&gt;Tigrini&lt;/em&gt; (Pegler 1983).  Synonymization of &lt;em&gt;L. lindquistii &lt;/em&gt;Lechner and Albertó (2000) and &lt;em&gt;L. glabratus &lt;/em&gt;under &lt;em&gt;L. tigrinus &lt;/em&gt;is suggested.  Data also suggests that &lt;em&gt;Panus fragilis &lt;/em&gt;O. K. Miller (1965) should be synonymized under &lt;em&gt;P. lecomtei &lt;/em&gt;Fr. &lt;em&gt;Lentius suavissimus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. is not part of either generic clade containing &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;Panus &lt;/em&gt;spp.  The transfer of &lt;em&gt;Lentinus suavissimus &lt;/em&gt;Fr. to another genus is necessary.  A bioegeographical pattern observed in sect. &lt;em&gt;Tigrini &lt;/em&gt;showed a correlation between geography and clades based on ITS data.  Synonymization of &lt;em&gt;L. lindquistii &lt;/em&gt;Lechner and Albertó and &lt;em&gt;L. glabratus &lt;/em&gt;Mont. Under &lt;em&gt;L. tigrinus &lt;/em&gt;(Bull.: fr.) Fr. is suggested based on sexual intercompatibility studies and molecular data.  &lt;em&gt;Polyporus &lt;/em&gt;group &lt;em&gt;Polyporellus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Nuñez and Ryvarden appears to be a monophyletic group related to &lt;em&gt;Lentinus &lt;/em&gt;sect. &lt;em&gt;Tigrini.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study concentrated on the circumglobal species complex &lt;em&gt;Panus lecomtei&lt;/em&gt; Fr. to access biogeographical relationships in that group.  Sexual intercompatibility studies indicated that seven collections of this complex formed a cohesive intersterility group.  Ribosomal ITS sequence data for all collections of &lt;em&gt;P. lecomtei &lt;/em&gt;fr. sampled were nearly 100% identical.  Two collections of &lt;em&gt;Panus fragilis &lt;/em&gt;O. K. Miller (1965) were also included and found to be conspecific with &lt;em&gt;P. lecomtei &lt;/em&gt;Fr. based on ITS and LSU sequence data.  Because of the macromorphological similarity of &lt;em&gt;Panus conchatus &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;P. lecomtei, &lt;/em&gt;data from both species were collected.  Eight collections of &lt;em&gt;P. conchatus &lt;/em&gt;were shown to form an intersterility group.  Other species of subg. &lt;em&gt;Panus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler (1983) were sequenced for ITS data, but not used for intercompatibility studies.  These species include the following: &lt;em&gt;Panus ciliatus &lt;/em&gt;Lév. (=&lt;em&gt; Lentinus ciliatus &lt;/em&gt;Lév. &lt;em&gt;sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler 1983), &lt;em&gt;Panus strigellus &lt;/em&gt;Berk. (= &lt;em&gt;Lentinus similis &lt;/em&gt;Berk.&lt;em&gt; sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler 1983), &lt;em&gt;Panus fulvus &lt;/em&gt;(Berk.) Pegler and Rayner (= &lt;em&gt;Lentinus velutinus sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler 1983), and &lt;em&gt;Panus similis &lt;/em&gt;Berk. and Br. (= &lt;em&gt;Lentinus similis sensu &lt;/em&gt;Pegler 1983).  &lt;em&gt;Lentinus suavissimus &lt;/em&gt;Fr., group &lt;em&gt;Polyporellus &lt;/em&gt;(Nuñez and Ryvarden 1995), &lt;em&gt;Ganoderma &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Neolentinus &lt;/em&gt;Redhead and Ginns (1985) were included to explore possible supra-generic relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4544</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6255&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4544</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6255</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-31T11:53:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10692259</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4544</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ronald H. Petersen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Karen W. Hughes, Randall L. Small, Robert N. Trigiano</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>