<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Separation of Carboxylic Acids by Fractional Distribution</title>
<publication-date>1948-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Orr</lname>
<fname>Clyde</fname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The quantitative separation of substances by fractionally distributing them between two liquids phases has only recently become of interest; previously the method has been used for the identification of substances.  This investigation was undertaken to determine if fractional distribution by a column of adsorbent material on which one of the liquid phases is immobilized and through which the other liquid phase perfuses is a method suitable for large scale development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partial separation of the similar substances succinic acid and fumaric acid was obtained without using what was considered an excessive quantity of solvent or requiring an inordinate length of time; however, the separation was shown to be improved by increasing the time for flow through the column.  Much more complete separation was obtained using columns in series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silica in either of two forms was found to be superior to all other of the seven adsorbents tested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreement between theory and experiment was found adequate to indicate that column action may be calculated from the physical properties of the column.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods of column separation are believed applicable in the field of fine chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3074</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4432&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3074</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4432</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-08T11:47:13-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6512615</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3074</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>A.L. Pollard</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ffe9ac038)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1948-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1948-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>