<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Developing Students’ First Language through a Second Language Writing Intervention:  A Simultaneous Approach</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hannahdostal@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dostal</lname>
<fname>Hannah</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>deaf</keyword>
<keyword>writing</keyword>
<keyword>ASL</keyword>
<keyword>bilingual</keyword>
<keyword>instruction</keyword>
<keyword>intervention</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Deaf and hard of hearing (d/hh) children often acquire an L1 after age 3, thus are arguably more diverse than that of the general bilingual population.  A unique problem therefore exists among d/hh late language learners—they often do not have an L1 to later develop an L2.  This study investigated the impact of an English writing intervention (Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction, SIWI) that incorporates support for the development of American Sign Language in an effort to illustrate the necessity of explicitly addressing the proposed interdependence of language learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research involved providing 23 upper elementary and middle school d/hh students with SIWI.  SIWI has been shown to have a significant impact on student outcomes in language and literacy.  The study was conducted in five classrooms—one fourth, two fifth, and two sixth grade classrooms—over a twelve-week period at a state residential school for the deaf.  This allowed for two weeks of pre-test, mid-test and post-test administration, five weeks of regular instruction, and five weeks of intervention.  The students received SIWI for four forty-five minute sessions and one thirty-minute session each week for a total of five weeks.  The intervention replaced their regular 45 minutes of writing instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to measure expressive language growth in ASL, language samples for each student participant were collected.  These samples were analyzed to chart expressive language growth during the time period with no SIWI intervention and while engaged in SIWI by reviewing them for students’ mean length of utterance (MLU), use of unintelligible utterances, and specific grammatical features of ASL, and individually for patterns of ASL expressive language growth.  Repeated measures ANOVAs (within and between subjects) conducted for students’ MLU and unintelligible utterances revealed statistically significant growth after five weeks of SIWI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study demonstrates the reciprocity of language learning.  The foregrounding of written English supported the development of a more nuanced understanding of the use and features of ASL.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/962</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2167&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>962</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2167</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-20T17:16:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1949317</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/962</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Anne McGill-Franzen, Kimberly Wolbers</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Allington, Jeffrey Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>