<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Best Practices in Suicide Pedagogy: A Quantitative Content Analysis</title>
<publication-date>2021-02-02T11:30:40-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>binkleee@wfu.edu</email>
<institution>Wake Forest University</institution>
<lname>Binkley</lname>
<fname>Erin</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gelliott@ccu.edu</email>
<institution>Colorado Christian University</institution>
<lname>Elliott</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>suicide</keyword>
<keyword>pedagogy</keyword>
<keyword>counselor education</keyword>
<keyword>content analysis</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Counselor Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The authors used a quantitative content analysis methodology to explore the available literature on pedagogical practices for teaching counselors how to work with suicidal clients. From an initial pool of 71 potentially applicable articles found in Counseling, Psychiatry, general mental health, Psychology, and Social Work journals, 26 articles were found to meet inclusion criteria by specifically exploring the impact or efficacy of different pedagogical practices relevant to suicide response in counselor training. These 26 articles were coded using quantitative content analysis procedures. Results indicated that more research is necessary to determine best practices for teaching suicide response to counselors in training. Additionally, these training practices should include attention to the CACREP standards and should be theoretically grounded in pedagogical frameworks. Ideally, future research in this area would focus more heavily on assessment of student competencies and how well students are prepared to respond to suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tsc/vol3/iss1/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1125&amp;amp;context=tsc&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1125</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-03-02T14:31:29-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/tsc/article/1125/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Teaching and Supervision in Counseling</publication-title>
<context-key>16700073</context-key>
<submission-path>tsc/vol3/iss1/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Erin E Binkley   https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1942-3479
Gregory M. Elliott   https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9719-1119
We have no known conflict of interest to disclose.
	Correspondence concerning this article should be addressed to Erin E. Binkley, Department of Counseling, Wake Forest University, PO Box 7406, Winston-Salem, NC 27109.  E-mail: binkleee@wfu.edu</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-03-02T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0x112c5f00)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>