<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid (n-3 PUFA) supplementation to lactating sows on growth and indicators of stress in the post-weaned pig</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmcafee4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McAfee</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>stress</keyword>
<keyword>inflammation</keyword>
<keyword>omega-3</keyword>
<keyword>and weaning</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The first experiment was designed to determine the concentration of protected fish oil product (&lt;strong&gt;PFO&lt;/strong&gt;), as Gromega&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt;, to be added that would sufficiently decrease the polyunsaturated fatty acid (&lt;strong&gt;PUFA&lt;/strong&gt;) ratio in the sows’ milk and colostrum. Of the 3 diets tested (0.25%, 0.5% and 1%) with a control (0% PFO), only the 1% PFO diet had an effect on the PUFA concentrations. The docosahexaenoic acid (&lt;strong&gt;DHA&lt;/strong&gt;) concentration tended (&lt;em&gt;P &lt;/em&gt;= 0.05) to be greater in the 1% PFO diet for both colostrum and milk samples. A second experiment was designed to examine the effects of feeding the 1 versus 0% PFO supplemented diet to sows on growth, markers of acute inflammation and stress in their offspring (16 piglets/treatment group) on d 0 (day of weaning) and d 1 and 3 postweaning. Piglets from sows supplemented the 1% PFO diet had greater gains in weight (&lt;em&gt;P &lt;/em&gt;=0.03) postweaning. These pigs also had a lower (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; ˂ 0.01) n-6:n-3 PUFA in the plasma when compared to piglets on the control diet. There was an overall treatment effect (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.02) on plasm atotal cortisol, observed by lower concentrations in pigs on the 1% PFO diet. Plasma corticosteroid-binding globulin (&lt;strong&gt;CBG&lt;/strong&gt;) concentrations were not different between treatment groups but were lower (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; ˂ 0.001) on d 1 and 3 when compared to d 0. The calculated free cortisol index [&lt;strong&gt;FCI &lt;/strong&gt;(cortisol/CBG)] of pigs on the 1% diet was lower (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.02) on d 1 and 3 when compared to the controls. The cytokines, IL-1β [beta], IL-6, and TNF-α [alpha] were measured following an ex vivo lipopolysaccharide (&lt;strong&gt;LPS&lt;/strong&gt;) stimulation of monocytes and neutrophils in whole blood collected on d 0 and 1. Pigs on the 1% PFO diet tended to have a lower (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.098) mean concentration of TNF-α in response to LPS when compared with that of the controls. These results suggest that providing a PFO supplement as 1% of the diet to sows beginning in late gestation and during lactation can lower the n-6:n-3 PUFA ratio in their offspring, which may reduce the acute physiological stress response in the pigs postweaning.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4297</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5220&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4297</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5220</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-15T15:29:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8737228</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4297</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hank Kattesh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brynn Voy, Hank Kattesh, Cheryl Kojima</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>