<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Endangered Species and U.S. Military Training - What’s the Value?</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to value military training using tradeoffs associated with endangered species. Because of urban sprawl, endangered species are encroaching upon many military training facilities throughout the United States. This encroachment interrupts military training activities and may affect the grounds where training takes place. Laws associated with the Endangered Species Act prevent any activities that may harm or destroy critical habitat necessary to ensure endangered species survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choice modeling, which is a subset of contingent valuation, is a stated preference methodology that allows researchers to question respondents about complex scenarios, and to calculate values based on the responses. Using both mail and the Internet to survey the American public about two different military facilities, this study found that the public is willing to pay the amount required to alleviate conflicts between endangered species and the military. The study also found that the public values continued survival of endangered species as much as military readiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study recommends that the U.S. Government develop a suitable alternative that will facilitate peaceful coexistence between species and soldiers and fund its implementation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2240</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3721&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2240</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3721</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T11:15:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4693200</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2240</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael McKee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert A. Bohm, Henry W. Herzog, Jr., Donald G. Hodges</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>