<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ethical Dilemmas in Safe Haven Programs</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-12T08:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>director@ahimsahouse.org</email>
<institution>Ahimsa House</institution>
<lname>Gupta</lname>
<fname>Maya</fname>
<suffix>Ph.D.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This discussion will address ethical issues that commonly arise for programs providing shelter for animals of domestic violence victims. Beginning with the premise that in the majority of cases, assisting victims with their animals increases safety and well-being for both humans and animals, we will explore unique situations that may test that premise. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Clients who return to the abuser: what happens to the animal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Other situations where we may not feel the animal is returning to ideal conditions: clients who cannot afford proper animal care, clients whose children have demonstrated cruelty, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Clients who refuse spay/neuter or other basic veterinary care&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-When the client has also harmed the animal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Reporting issues: the program’s role or lack thereof&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-What happens when the client’s ownership of the animal is in question?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Should we place limits on repeat use of services? What if she comes back with more animals next time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-How do we write program policies that protect us without disempowering clients?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Are safe haven programs the “final solution” when it comes to providing assistance with animals in domestic violence situations, or is some responsibility shared with the DV service system and/or with the client?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Other situations that service providers (or those interested in providing this service) may bring to the table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, discussion participants will be guided in considering the above questions within the context of ethical obligations to both human and animal clients, and in addressing the fundamental question of “What constituency do I serve: humans, animals, or both?” with respect to both personal allegiances and program/agency identity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april12/10</coverpage-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1043</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-11-01T16:11:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3441156</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april12/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maya Gupta earned her PhD in clinical psychology from UGA, where her research focused on connections between animal cruelty and domestic violence. She is Executive Director of Ahimsa House, a nonprofit dedicated to helping human and animal victims of domestic violence reach safety together. Dr. Gupta also serves on the Board of the Georgia Coalition Against Domestic Violence, as Vice Chair of the Cobb County DV Task Force, on the Steering Committee of the National Link Coalition, on the Animal Cruelty Advisory Council of the Association of Prosecuting Attorneys, and as Past Chair of the Section on Human-Animal Interaction in the American Psychological Association.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Maya Gupta, Ph.D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PO Box 8181&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atlanta, GA 31106&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;404-496-4038&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T08:15:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Table Topic: Facilitated conversation at meal time</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T08:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T08:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>The link between human and animal violence</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>