<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Validation of the Masculine Gender Role Stress Scale in a Diverse Population</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asherma5@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Sherman</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Eliza</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Masculinity</keyword>
<keyword>Diversity</keyword>
<keyword>Gender</keyword>
<keyword>Stress</keyword>
<keyword>Ethnicity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Adherence to traditional masculinity has been associated with negative physical and psychological health outcomes. Specifically, the standards of masculinity imposed on men have been associated with high levels of stress reactivity, interpersonal violence, and substance abuse. However, previous research has been limited to primarily Caucasian samples. In order to better understand masculinity and the stress associated with adherence to masculinity across ethnicity, we examined the validity of the Masculine Gender Role Stress scale in a diverse sample. We hypothesized that the MGRS in a diverse sample would function similarly to the MGRS in a primarily Caucasian sample in that it would be reliable and valid and that a five factor model of MGRS would be the best fit.  Undergraduate students (N = 234) completed the MGRS scale and several questionnaires measuring masculinity, stress, anger and anxiety. A confirmatory factor analysis was conducted in order to assess the validity of the five-factor model of the MGRS scale in a diverse sample. Results confirmed that the MGRS is valid among a diverse sample, a diverse Caucasian excluded sample, and a Hispanic only sample. Additionally, the five factor model was the better fit for all samples evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/830</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1833&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>830</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1833</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-09T18:00:18-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1833/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1433669</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/830</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Todd M. Moore</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Paula Fite, Gregory L. Stuart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>