<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extended high frequency hearing and speech delay of unknown origin</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Stutsy</lname>
<fname>Mandi</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Objective: The purpose of the current study was to examine hearing in the extended high frequency range in children with speech delay of unknown origin. Specifically, the study asked the questions, do children with speech delay of unknown origin have reduced hearing acuity in the extended high frequencies, do children with speech delay of. unknown origin and who have not acquired the high frequency sounds (Is/ and /z/) have reduced hearing acuity in the extended high frequencies, and/or do children with speech delay of unknown origin and a history of otitis media have reduced hearing acuity in the extended high frequencies?  Participants: Four children ages 3;11 to 6;8 participated in the study. The children were selected because they met the following criteria: ( 1) diagnosed as having speech delay of unknown origin; (2) no hearing loss in the conventional audiometric frequency range (250-4000 Hz); (3) receptive vocabulary as measured by the Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test-3 rd Edition (PPVT-m; Dunn &amp; Dunn, 1997) within 1.3 standard deviation of the mean for their age (Standard Score 80+ ).  Method: Data were gathered through a case history form, an audiometer, the Goldman Fristoe Test of Articulation--2 (GFTA-2), a conversational speech sample, and the Speech Production-Perception Task (SP-PT). Hearing ability was assessed using an audiometer. These results were compared to normative values. In addition, each participant&#39;s asymmetry index was determined. To assess speech production, the GFTA-2 was given and a conversational sample was audio recorded. Percent consonants correct on the GFTA-2 and conversational speech sample were compared.  Data Analysis: Because of the small number of participants, data analysis was descriptive rather than statistical in nature. The participants&#39; conventional hearing thresholds were compared with normative data (ANSI, 1996). The participants&#39; extended high frequency thresholds were compared to the normative values given by Margolis (1993) and Reuter (1998). The participant&#39;s errors on the GFf A-2 and the conversational speech sample were compared and described for fricatives and other errors. The participants&#39; performance on the SP-PT was described and compared to production of fricatives.  Results: Only participant 3 had a reduced hearing acuity in the extended high frequency range in his right ear. He also had the most severe articulation delay and a history of chronic otitis media Participant 1 had normal hearing in the extended high frequencies, but had difficulty perceiving the difference between the phonemes /f / and /8/. He also had a diagnosis of ADHD. These finding suggest that for some children speech delay is associated with chronic otitis media and extended high frequency hearing loss.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5301</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6709&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5301</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6709</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847233</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5301</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter Flipsen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Speech Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>