<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Brundibár:  Confronting the Misrepresentation of Resistance in Theresienstadt</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>agreer11@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Greer</lname>
<fname>Anna Catherine</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Krasa</keyword>
<keyword>Holocaust</keyword>
<keyword>Freizeitgestaltung</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Jewish Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Musicology</discipline>
<discipline>Other German Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brundibár&lt;/em&gt;, a children’s opera written by Czech composer Hans Krása (1899-1944), routinely appears in Holocaust musical scholarship as a depiction of “thriving” Jewish cultural activity during the Holocaust. First performed clandestinely in a Prague orphanage in 1942, the work was ultimately co-opted by Nazi authorities in Theresienstadt. Under the jurisdiction of the &lt;em&gt;Freizeitgestaltung&lt;/em&gt; (Leisure Time Activities), the opera came under control of the camp administration and became part of several propaganda schemes, including the 1944 Nazi propaganda film, &lt;em&gt;Der Führer schenkt den Juden eine Stadt (The Führer Gives a City to the Jews).&lt;/em&gt; In preparation for the International Red Cross’s visit in 1944, camp authorities initiated a &lt;em&gt;Stadtverschönerung &lt;/em&gt;(city beautification) campaign in Theresienstadt. Accordingly, &lt;em&gt;Brundib&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;ár&lt;/em&gt; performances moved into a performance hall, stage-managed by the SS. Yet only weeks following the Red Cross visit, most prisoners involved in the &lt;em&gt;Brundib&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;ár &lt;/em&gt;production were sent to their deaths at Auschwitz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conscious resistance underlying the work’s Prague performance evaporated in the Nazi-orchestrated Theresienstadt performances. The first performance of &lt;em&gt;Brundibár&lt;/em&gt; remains largely ignored, in favor of scholarship that focuses overwhelmingly on the concentration camp performances and inscribes them within redemptive narratives. &lt;em&gt;Brundib&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;ár &lt;/em&gt;repeatedly appears in the commodification of memory increasingly subject to retrospective recastings of “spiritual resistance.” Through a contextualized examination of &lt;em&gt;Brundibár&lt;/em&gt;, I argue that the inherent social stratification in Theresienstadt offered cultural activity to a select few and &lt;em&gt;Brundibár’s&lt;/em&gt; function within the &lt;em&gt;Freizeitgestalung&lt;/em&gt; merely furthered Nazi agenda.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2417</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2820&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2417</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2820</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-24T11:53:22-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2820/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4172498</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2417</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel H. Magilow</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Rachel M. Golden, Leslie L. Gay</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>German</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>