<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Organizational structure of telehealth care : an examination of four types of telemedicine systems</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Welsh</lname>
<fname>Teresa</fname>
<mname>Smith</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to make recommendations for a sustainable telemedicine system by examining the structural attributes of telemedicine across and within different types of organizations. A survey instrument with two categories, background questions and evaluation questions, was developed and used as a guide to interview eight key informants from four different types of telehealth systems. The eight transcribed interviews were coded using NUD*IST qualitative software. Research publications, archival documents, and government reports were collected to triangulate, or cross check, interview data. Multi-case study methodology was used as a guide to design the research, analyze date, compare results, and make recommendations. A telehealth typology is proposed as well as a simplified conceptual telehealth model and a diffusion of telemedicine model. While there are some structural differences among the different types of programs, there are many more similarities. All receive funding fiom multiple sources, and all employ a combination of full and part-time employees. Three core staff categories include administrative, medical, and technical support. Additional categories may include evaluation researchers and project coordinators.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6347</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8299&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6347</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8299</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:36:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450596</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6347</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carol Tenopir</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Susan Dimmick, Gretchen Whitney, Herbert Howard, Samiel Burgiss</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>