<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Lessons Learned From the Developmental Flight Testing of the Improved Tactical Air Launched Decoy</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hutson</lname>
<fname>Bradley</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this thesis is to examine the test team responsibilities and decisions made in the planning, execution, and reporting of test results for the Developmental Flight Testing of the Improved Tactical Air Launched Decoy (ITALD).  Information gathered as lead Flight Test Engineer for the series of ITALD flight test events is the primary data source for the opinions formulated in this thesis.  Test team decisions, influenced by training, budget constraints, test schedules, and changes in production contractors were analyzed to determine their effect on the flight test program.  The Development Test guidance obtained from Department of Defense (DoD) Regulation 5000.2-R, the teachings of the United States Naval Test Pilot School, and other DoD acquisition documentation were reviewed to evaluate test team responsibilities and the approach that was taken throughout the flight test program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ITALD Developmental Flight Test program that is examined in this paper consisted of two series of flight tests, the ITALD Baseline Demonstration Flight Test program, which occurred in 1996, and the ITALD DT-IIIE Flight Test Program, which occurred in 1998.  Both series of tests are examined since they are similarly related in test team structure, planning and conduct of test, and test results.  The major difference between the two series of tests was the reporting of the test results.  This will be discussed in detail within this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the ITALD flight test program was successful in determining what deficiencies existed and what improvements needed to be incorporated, there were a number of lessons learned that were generated.  The primary issues that developed were the need to develop a coordinated test philosophy and the necessity to improve communication within the Integrated Program Team.  These, along with other lessons learned are discussed within the body of this paper and in the conclusions and recommendations sections.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2012</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3372&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2012</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3372</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T13:26:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4641388</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2012</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph Kimberlin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George Garrison, Richard Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>