<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Reading Ollantay: The Negotiation of Communication in Colonial Quechua Theater</title>
<publication-date>2010-02-26T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>aray12@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ray</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Colonial Latin American Literature</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Ollantay</keyword>
<keyword>Negotiation</keyword>
<keyword>Communication</keyword>
<keyword>Colonial</keyword>
<keyword>Quechua</keyword>
<keyword>Theater</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Spanish and Portuguese Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Quechua theatrical work Ollantay (discovered in the 18th century) provides a vital opportunity to observe how the colonial Quechua peoples contextualized the importance of communication. My reading of Ollantay focuses on the negotiation of communication between characters as a didactic means of social interaction for indigenous peoples living in colonial Latin America. The act of communication is prioritized over the actual message communicated between characters; it is clear that those that abide by this communicative equation find themselves in positions of either power or accomplishment and those that ignore this rule do not. In order to sustain a hierarchal position it is not necessary to maintain absolute control over communicative expression; rather it is imperative to cede control of the conversation at times to other characters. Reading Ollantay from this perspective–as a social model of negotiated communication–may provide the reader a better understanding of indigenous thought processes during the colonial period in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_modepubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_modepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-04T12:43:33-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_modepubs/article/1000/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Modern Foreign Languages and Literatures Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1250166</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_modepubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-26T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>9th Ohio Latin Americanist Conference at Ohio University</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>