<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Induction and Regulation of Herpetic Stromal Keratitis</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sarangi</lname>
<fname>Pranita</fname>
<mname>Pragnyadipta</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Herpetic stromal keratitis (HSK) is an immunopathological and tissue destructive  corneal lesion caused by herpes simplex virus (HSV) infection, which induces an  intense inflammatory response and finally leads to blindness. Accumulating  evidence using the murine model has shown that Th-1 phenotype CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cells  orchestrating the inflammation mainly contribute to the immunopathological  reaction in HSV-1 infected cornea. However, prior to CD4&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; T cell infiltration into  corneal lesions, various innate immune cells recruit and produce numerous  inflammatory and angiogenic molecules into the corneal stroma those in turn drive  the corneal immunopathology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part (Part I) of this dissertation focuses on the understanding of  HSV-1 induced immunoinflammatory processes in the cornea and trigeminal  ganglia including the secondary lymphoid tissues. The next three parts (Part II-IV)  focus on different inflammatory and anti-inflammatory mechanisms that are  activated following virus infection in the cornea. Results in Part II evaluate the role  of various Toll-like receptors (TLRs) in driving the early inflammatory events that  occur in the HSV infected corneas. Thus, this part demonstrates that mainly TLR2  and to a lesser extent TLR9 ligand activity of HSV is important for driving SK  pathology. Results of the third section show that HSV infection results in the up  regulation of IL-23 that is needed for the survival of pathogenic Th-17 cells. The  data show that mice lacking IL-23 were more susceptible to SK lesions and that the  heightened lesion severity was attributed to higher IL-12 production and Th1  immune response in such animals. The fourth section describes the relative role of IL-10 and natural regulatory T cells (nTregs) as two independent anti-inflammatory  mechanisms that are needed for controlling HSK lesions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, experiments were designed to understand the mechanisms  involved in the induction and regulation of immunopathology in HSK and  modulation of such processes could be useful in designing therapeutic for HSK.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/344</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1402&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>344</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1402</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-15T10:17:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1145711</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/344</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Barry T. Rouse</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert N. Moore, Steven J Kennel, Mark Y. Sangster</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/SarangiPranita.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>