<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Electronic Excitations in Metals and Semiconductors: Ab Initio Studies of Realistic Many-Particle Systems</title>
<publication-date>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ku</lname>
<fname>Wei</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Electronic excitations in metals and semiconductors, measured through inelastic x-ray scattering, electronic energy-loss spectroscopy, and angle-resolved photoemission, provide valuable information about the intrinsic many-body interactions between electrons in the crystal environment. These dynamical interactions are usually analyzed with intuitive simple models. With the problems studied, which correspond to linear response and quasi-particle excitation, it will be shown that &lt;em&gt;ab initio &lt;/em&gt;approaches not only can provide more realistic understanding of microscopic processes and mechanisms, but also result in new theoretical interpretations that resolve a number of remarkable &quot;anomalies.&quot; Specifically, these problems include the dispersion of the plasmon lifetime in potassium, the electron-hole excitations near the &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;-band threshold of zinc, the occupied bandwidth of sodium, and the band gap of silicon and germanium. These analyses are based on newly developed all-electron, full potential implementations of the time-dependent density functional theory and the conserving finite temperature many-body perturbation theory. These studies also illustrate the limitation of current knowledge of many-body approaches, and demonstrate the importance of the interplay between experiment and theory.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2030</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3464&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2030</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3464</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-24T13:15:00-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4618999</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2030</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Adolfo G. Eguiluz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bennett C. Larson, John J. Quinn, Peter T. Cummings</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>