<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Prisoner as Master of His Own Lawsuit: The Interpretation of Prisoners&#39; §1983 Civl Rights Claims After Wilkinson v. Dotson</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-03T14:35:18-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>White</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>§1983 Civl Rights Claims</keyword>
<keyword>Wilkinson v. Dotson</keyword>
<keyword>prisoner</keyword>
<keyword>lawsuit</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In Wilkinson v. Dotson,l the U.S. Supreme Court explored the &quot;jurisdictional periphery of habeas corpus&#39; and re-examined 42 U.S.C. § 1983 as a mechanism to challenge incarceration procedures. The issue before the Court was whether prisoners may seek declaratory and injunctive relief for alleged unconstitutional parole procedures through a § 1983 challenge or &quot;whether they must instead seek relief exclusively under the federal habeas corpus statutes.&quot; In Wilkinson, two Ohio prisoners individually brought § 1983 claims against the Ohio Department of Rehabilitation and Corrections for violating their civil rights during parole considerations. In each case, the district court held that &quot;the prisoner would have to seek relief through a habeas corpus suit.&quot; After the consolidation and reversal of the cases by the Sixth Circuit, the State of Ohio petitioned the Supreme Court for certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol2/iss3/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1045&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>policynotes</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1045</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-03T14:28:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5257319</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol2/iss3/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>J.D. Candidate 2007, University of Tennessee College of Law; M.A. 1996 University of Tennessee; B.A. 1993 University of Tennessee. Author also served as Research Editor of the TENNESSEE JOURNAL OF LAW &amp; POLICY.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>§1983 Civl Rights Claims</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>