<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A General Educational Survey of Alpine Institute and Community</title>
<publication-date>1939-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cantrell</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Benton</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: 1. Purpose. Four years ago the writer, along with two other teachers, was asked by Dr. Warren H. Wilson of the Board of National Mission of the Presbyterian Church in the United States of America to form a committee for the purpose of supervising the school at Alpine, Tennessee. The committee was formed and the writer was chosen as chairman, a position that carried with it the task of acting as principal. Following the second year at Alpine, at the suggestion of Dr. Wilson for further study, the Author purposed attending the University of Tennessee and making a study of the Alpine School and Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motive back of this study is to learn of the resources, both human and material, in the Alpine Community in order that a more efficient piece of work may be done by the school in the community. During the past decade or so many surveys have been made in various parts of the state. There are common elements as to items covered in most of these surveys; still, the information differs. If the data of such surveys are to be used in a particular situation, they must be applicable to that situation. The data collected in this survey are to be used for the purpose of formulating and carrying on a more inclusive and extensive school program for the section in which the school is located.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2518</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3884&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2518</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3884</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-03T13:42:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4871975</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2518</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>B. O. Quaggau</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Josh Daunt, Adair Phillips, W. B. Jones, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;(large file - 41 MB)&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1939-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1939-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>