<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>From Isomorphism Identities to Levy measures of Non-negative Infinitely Divisible Processes</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>vnguye12@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Nguyen</lname>
<fname>Vy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Levy measures</keyword>
<keyword>Non-negative infinitely divisible processes</keyword>
<keyword>Squared Bessel processes</keyword>
<keyword>Isomorphism Identities</keyword>
<keyword>Ray Knight theorems</keyword>
<keyword>Dynkin Isomorphism Theorem</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this dissertation, we examine the L ́evy measures of non-negative infinitely divisible processes. For a non-negative infinitely divisible process with no drift, L ́evy measure is the single most important factor characterizing the process. Understanding the structure of L ́evy measure can give more insight about the behavior of the process. However, it is not always easy to describe the L ́evy measure of an infinitely divisible process. The descriptions of L ́evy measures of squared Bessel processes proposed by Pitman and Yor are examples. It requires deep knowledge from the Ray-Knight theorems and Itoˆ excursion laws to interpret these descriptions. We use isomorphism identities as the main tool to describe the L ́evy measure of a non-negative infinitely divisible process. The isomorphism identities that we are interested in connect every non-negative infinitely divisible process to the family of its random translations. It turns out that the L ́evy measure of a non-negative infinitely divisible process can be written in term of the laws of its random translations. More precisely, we manage to write the L ́evy measure as a series of other L ́evy measures which are written in term of the law of random translations. The special technique that we develop to ensure the condition distribution of a non-negative infinitely divisible process being consistently well defined enables us to find the laws corresponds to the component L ́evy measures in the series. Using this method, we have an alternative way to describe the L ́evy measures of squared Bessel processes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5770</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7536&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5770</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7536</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419663</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5770</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jan Rosinski</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tuoc Phan, Yu-Ting Chen, William Seaver</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>