<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Lake Erie &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt;:  relationship between microcystin production, dynamics of genotypes and environmental parameters in a large lake</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Rinta-Kanto</lname>
<fname>J.M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>DeBruyn</lname>
<fname>J.M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Konopko</lname>
<fname>E.A.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Bourbonniere</lname>
<fname>R.A.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Boyer</lname>
<fname>G.L.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilhelm</lname>
<fname>S.W.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>toxic cyanobacteria</keyword>
<keyword>qPCR</keyword>
<keyword>environmental controls</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cyanobacteria of genus &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; sp. have been commonly found in Lake Erie waters during recent summer seasons. In an effort to elucidate relationships between microcystin production, genotypic composition of &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; community and environmental parameters in a large lake ecosystem, we collected DNA samples and environmental data during a three-year (2003–2005) survey within Lake Erie and used the data to perform a series of correlation analyses. Cyanobacteria and &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; genotypes were quantified using quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR). Our data show that &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; in Lake Erie forms up to 42% of all cyanobacteria, and that &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; exists as a mixed population of potentially toxic and (primarily) non-toxic genotypes. In the entire lake, the total abundance of &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; as well as the abundance of microcystin-producing &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; is strongly correlated with the abundance of cyanobacteria suggesting that &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; is a significant component of the cyanobacterial community in Lake Erie during summer seasons. The proportion of total &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; of all cyanobacteria was strongly linked to the microcystin concentrations, while the percentage of microcystin-producing genotypes within &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; population showed no correlation with microcystin concentrations. Correlation analysis indicated that increasing total phosphorus concentrations correlate strongly with increasing microcystin concentrations as well as with the total abundance of &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; and microcystin-producing &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/8</coverpage-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1012</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-28T11:58:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1584184</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B73D7-4VF56WW-1&amp;_user=422010&amp;_coverDate=06%2F30%2F2009&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_searchStrId=1477456195&amp;_rerunOrigin=google&amp;_acct=C000019958&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=422010&amp;md5=030a4681f758efb8054409671e5e3aa1&amp;searchtype=a</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>