<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of the CF188 Landing Gear Upgrade</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grandmont</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A study was undertaken to assess the effectiveness of the CF188 main landing gear upgrade on reducing Planing Link Mechanism failures. Two main landing gear configurations were studied: the prototype configuration and, for comparison purposes, the current configuration referred to as the baseline. Under this study, the flight test data that was analyzed came from key measurements recorded during maintenance rigging procedures, pilot ground handling quality ratings, and from over 80 landings at different descent rates and aircraft attitudes. Landings consisted of touch and go, full stop, cable overrun and cable engagement. The aircraft that was used through the flight test program had both its main landing gears instrumented. While the prototype configuration had minimal impact on the ground handling characteristics, it demonstrated promising results during maintenance activities as well as loads distribution during landings. The prototype was easier to rig which will allow the use of tighter limits further standardizing the complex maintenance procedure. From both a static and dynamic point of view, the hold down force was significantly increased. Within the scope of this study, it was found that the CF188 main landing gear upgrade will reduce Planing Link Mechanism failures.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/81</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1110&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>81</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1110</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-22T09:26:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1119263</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/81</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter Solies</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank Collins, John Muratore</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>