<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nutrition Field Observations and Experiences in the State of Colorado</title>
<publication-date>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hambright</lname>
<fname>Margaret</fname>
<mname>Susan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report is based upon experiences and observations of the student during a seven weeks&#39; period of field training with the Colorado State Department of Public Health. The Senior Nutrition Consultant of the Maternal and Child Health Section in the Child Health Services Division provided the guidance for the field experiences. Approximately five weeks and two days were devoted to working with the Senior Nutrition Consultant at the state health department. One week was spent in the Denver City-County Health Department with the health educator who planned experiences emphasizing environmental health and nursing services of the local department. Three days were spent visiting the Western Slope of Colorado to observe Hearing and Orthopedic Clinics, and one day was devoted to observing the dietary consultant in her program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the field experience was to supplement the student&#39;s academic training in public health nutrition at The University of Tennessee and to broaden her concept of public health work at the state and local levels. The specific objectives of the student were (1) to study the organization, administration, and functions of an official health agency; (2) to gain an understanding of how a state nutrition program is planned and executed to meet the needs of the people served; (3) to learn how nutrition is integrated with the programs and services of other disciplines in the public health agency; and (4) to recognize the contributions of community agencies and organizations in the development of the overall nutrition program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various activities were arranged to help the student accomplish these objectives. During academic study data were gathered by the student about the state and its health programs by reading the Colorado State Department of Public Health&#39;s Biennial Reports for 1960-1961 and 1962-1963. Other pamphlets and booklets published by the state health department and other stage agencies were read to obtain descriptive information about the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(abbreviated)&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3826</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5307&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3826</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5307</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-08T11:31:30-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8941568</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3826</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Rose Gram, Harold H. Walker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1965-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>