<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of two-centimeter lateral surgical margin for excision of grade 2 cutaneous mast cell tumors in dogs</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Fulcher</lname>
<fname>R</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Ludwig</lname>
<fname>L</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Bergman</lname>
<fname>P</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>excision</keyword>
<keyword>canine</keyword>
<keyword>mast cell tumors</keyword>
<keyword>lateral margin</keyword>
<keyword>surgery</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: To evaluate completeness of excision and clinical outcome in dogs with cutaneous mast cell tumors (MCTs) excised with a lateral margin of 2 cm and a deep margin of 1 fascial plane. DESIGN: Prospective study. ANIMALS: 16 client-owned dogs with 1 or more cutaneous MCTs. PROCEDURE: Excision of MCTs was performed with a 2-cm lateral margin and a deep margin of 1 fascial plane. Histologic tumor grading was performed; surgical margins were categorized as complete or incomplete. Follow-up information was obtained via repeat examination of the dogs by veterinarians or client-completed questionnaires. RESULTS: 4 grade I and 19 grade II cutaneous MCTs were evaluated. Overall, 21 (91%) MCTs were completely excised; 2 grade II tumors had foci of mast cells at the 2-cm margin. Two dogs received adjunctive treatments following surgery. Follow-up information was available for all dogs (median follow-up period, 379 days; range, 51 to 538 days); no local recurrence was detected during this time. De novo MCTs were detected in 3 of 16 dogs at 37, 54, and 154 days after surgery. Via Kaplan-Meier analysis, median survival time and disease-free interval were both &gt; 538 days (medians not yet reached). No prognostic variables were identified. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL RELEVANCE: Excision with a 2-cm lateral margin and a deep margin of 1 fascial plane may result in satisfactory excision of grades I and II MCTs in dogs, with recurrence rates similar to those reported previously. Use of these margins may minimize complications associated with larger local tumor resection.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/35</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1034&amp;amp;context=utk_pathobiopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>35</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1034</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284758</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/35</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>R P. Fulcher, L L. Ludwig, P J. Bergman, Shelley Newman, A M. Simpson, and A K. Patnaik. &quot;Evaluation of two-centimeter lateral surgical margin for excision of grade 2 cutaneous mast cell tumors in dogs&quot; Journal of the American Veterinary Medical ASsociation 228 (2006): 210-215.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>