<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sara Liza: a Pant Suit and a Paint Brush</title>
<publication-date>2017-04-17T05:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sseaman@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Seaman</lname>
<fname>Sara</fname>
<mname>E</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;I am a painter who seeks more for my art business and career than that of a “starving artist.” &lt;em&gt;Trading the Pant Suit for a Paint Brush&lt;/em&gt; is a business plan that serves as my blueprint and foundation for becoming a well-known artist, owning a personal studio and maintaining significant gallery presence across the country. I am to accomplish this through intentional customer targeting and production mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My target market is not specific to a certain demographic but instead a psychographic – original art enthusiasts and collectors. I am specifically targeting those who appreciate the value of original paintings through physical galleries, an online gallery, a monthly newsletter and social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My evolving plan is split by stages – starting with an online gallery to later holding a large physical gallery presence and owning a studio – which encompass both short and long-term goals and milestones. I am to be consistent in continually researching artists in order to mold my product, informing my community and audience of new works and accomplishments, and adapting my business plan as I learn more about the market and where I fit. Each artist fits a niche based on whom they inspire, or emotionally touch, with their work – which is what I have found to be the primary motivator of purchasing original artwork. My goal is to become a successful, full-time painter through creating original, inspiring pieces that speak to others in a unique way.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/business/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1130&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1130</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T20:51:21-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1130/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10008933</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/business/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Management and Entrepreneurship</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Lynn Youngs</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-04-17T05:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>