<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Electrical Analogue Computer for the Heat Pump</title>
<publication-date>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Goff</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Taken from the Summary&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Because of the complex behavior of a cylindrical heat source-sink under intermittent operating conditions, analysis by analytical means is very difficult. Therefore an electrical analogy computer consisting of a distributed resistance capacitance model was designed and built. It was shown analytically that the behavior of this computer model was the same as that of the heat system. That the model was a true analogy is verified by the fact that data obtained from this model could be used to check certain heat flow problems previously solved by analytical means. Data were obtained for a cylindrical heat source in an infinite medium. These data were used to check the analytical solution presented by A. Gemant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generator was designed and built which could be used to solve two dimensional heat flow problems involving intermittent operation. Its theory of operation was set forth and the circuit diagram presented. With such equipment one may obtain numerical answers to many two dimensional problems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2972</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4342&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2972</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4342</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-11-25T10:20:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6393253</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2972</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paul C. Cromwell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edgar D. Ecawls, C. H. Weaver, A. V. Schultz, C. T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>