<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Technical Bulletins: Qualifications of Companies Providing Deferred Compensation Plan for Employees of Municipality Must Be Determined by Specified State Officials</title>
<publication-date>1980-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>MTAS</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>personnel</keyword>
<keyword>deferred compensation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;MTAS issued this Technical Bulletin to inform municipalities of an opinion of the Attorney General of Tennessee that under T.C.A. section 8-4303, the Commissioner of Finance and Administration, the Chairman of the Finance, Ways and Means Committee of the Senate, and the Chairman of the Finance, Ways and Means Committee of the House are required to determine the qualifications of each company providing a deferred compensation plan established pursuant to the Government Employees Deferred Compensation Act (T.C.A. sections 8-4301, et seq.), and that this includes deferred compensation plans for municipal employees.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtastech/301</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1295&amp;amp;context=utk_mtastech&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>301</label>
<document-type>bulletin</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1295</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-01T07:56:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Technical Bulletins</publication-title>
<context-key>3977836</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtastech/301</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1980-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>