<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Disordered Eating Behavior Frequency and Body Mass Index Comparison among Racially Diverse Sorority Women: The Strong Bodies and Strong Minds Unite Sisters! Study</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kittle</lname>
<fname>Leah</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Objective: The purpose of this study was to describe and compare the frequency of disordered eating behaviors (DEB) among primarily Caucasian and primarily Minority sorority women. A secondary purpose was to describe weight status of sorority women by comparing Body Mass Index (BMI) categories, using guidelines from the Centers of Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), among the two sorority groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Method: Sorority women (primarily Caucasian, n=291; primarily Minority, n=44) completed an online survey designed to assess lifestyle habits, body image, and eating attitudes. We focused upon differences in Eating Disorder Examination-Questionnaire (EDE-Q) global and subscale scores and BMI scores, calculated from self-reported height and weight, between primarily Caucasian and primarily Minority sorority women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: The mean global scores for primarily Caucasian sororities was 1.98 ± 1.30; for primarily Minority sororities, 1.72 ± 1.40 (p≤0.23). The reported mean BMI of the primarily Caucasian sororities was 22.34 ± 2.66 compared to the reported mean BMI of the primarily Minority sororities at 26.99 ± 5.96 (p≤ 0.001). The prevalence of overweight, based upon self-report height and weight, among primarily Caucasian sorority women was 12.71% compared to the prevalence of overweight among primarily Minority sorority women at 31.82% (p≤ 0.001). The prevalence of obesity among primarily Caucasian sorority women was 1.37%, compared to primarily Minority sorority women at 22.73% (p≤ 0.001).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3662</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4995&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3662</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4995</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-10T09:27:23-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8124091</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3662</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisa Jahns</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Leslee Fisher, Jay Whelan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>