<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effectiveness of victim-offender mediation and family group conferencing : a meta-analysis</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Williams-Hayes</lname>
<fname>Mona</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The costs associated with crime are staggering. Victims, offenders, and communit ies are all affected by criminal offenses, and the current approach to justice seems both ineffective and inefficient. Restorative justice proponents have posited that their approach to justice through dialogue and negotiation may be more effective than traditional retributive justice. The purpose of this study was to conduct a meta-analysis to determine if such a conjecture was supported or rejected. Inclusion criteria were developed to find appropriate studies. A thorough review of the literature found a total of 40 studies that were suitable for analysis. After the findings were systematically organized, the dissertation addressed questions about whether or not variation across studies in outcomes was systematic. If the variation across studies in outcomes was systematic rather than random, then the types of factors that might have explained the variation were analyzed. Results were analyzed using Hierarchical Generalized Linear Models (HGLM) with a legit link function. The program HGLM version 4 was used&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6335</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8287&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6335</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8287</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450446</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6335</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William R. Nugent</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Karen M. Sowers, Catherine N. Dulmus, Jo Lynn Cunningham</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>