<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Prostaglandin E2 Secretion and Effect on Adipocyte Lipogenesis</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wortman</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the current focus on the role of n-3 PUFAs as beneficial dietary interventions in the fields of cardiovascular disease and cancer, there has been a vastly increased awareness and focus on the mechanism of action for these essential fatty acids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the effects of PUFAs are mediated via changes in prostaglandin (PG) levels.  One primary substrate for PGs is arachidonic acid (AA) (20:4 n-6), which results in the production of 2-series PGs.  Increased concentrations of AA have been shown to increase levels of PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in vitro and in vivo.  The omega-3 fatty acid EPA (20:5 n-3) is of particular interest due to its incorporation into cell membrane phospholipids in competition with AA.  EPA can also serve as a substrate for prostaglandin production when present in tissue and results in the production of 3-series PGs, which do not appear to produce the same effects as 2-series PGs, although data is extremely limited.  The secretion of prostaglandins (PGs), and specifically PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; has been demonstrated in human and rodent adipocytes, and the presence of PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; receptors in these tissues has also been demonstrated.  PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; can act in an autocrine/paracrine fashion in adipocytes to decrease lipolysis via G-protein coupled receptors.  Preliminary data from our lab on &lt;em&gt;Apc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Min/+&lt;/sup&gt; mice showed that cyclooxygenase (COX) inhibition significantly reduced the activity of fatty acid synthase (FAS) in adipose tissue, and PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; receptor agonists partially but significantly reversed this effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our overall objective was to determine whether treatment with EPA or selective COX-2 inhibitors would lead to a reduction in measured PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; that would in turn regulate markers of lipogenesis.  We hypothesized that increased levels of EPA would competitively reduce tissue AA levels, and consequently PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; production, leading to decreased activity of markers specific to adipogenesis, specifically the FAS enzyme.  Selective COX-2 inhibition was expected to produce similar effects via inhibition of COX metabolism of AA to PGs.  Studies were conducted on 3T3-L1 adipocytes.  Dose-response studies demonstrated a clear relationship between increasing doses of EPA or AA and measured PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/PGE&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; levels.  Manipulation of PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels via addition of EPA to culture media led to significant changes in measured PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels versus AA, but did not result in a significant decrease in FAS enzyme activity.  Addition of celecoxib, a selective COX-2 inhibitor (CI), to culture media resulted in a significant decrease in PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;levels and FAS activity.  Addition of exogenous PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; to CI treatment did not reverse the decreased FAS enzyme activity.  These results indicate that addition of EPA can displace AA in cell membrane phospholipids and reduce PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; production, but does not impact FAS activity.  Suppression of PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by selective COX-2 inhibition does lead to decreased FAS activity, which is not reversed by exogenous PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; addition.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4825</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6330&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4825</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6330</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-28T12:50:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10670407</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4825</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Naima Moustaid-Moussa</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, Betsy Haughton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>