<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Epidemiological Study Of &lt;i&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/i&gt; Populations Reveals A Selective Pressure By Roxarsone</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>spendlet@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pendleton</lname>
<fname>Sean</fname>
<mname>Jeffery</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Campylobacter</keyword>
<keyword>arsenic</keyword>
<keyword>resistance</keyword>
<keyword>typing</keyword>
<keyword>whole genome sequencing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Whole genome sequencing (WGS) is the most discriminatory of typing methods and can provide additional information including virulence, antigen targets for vaccine development, and antimicrobial resistance profiles. The first part of this study aimed to determine the application of WGS as a genotyping method for &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter &lt;/em&gt;by comparing WGS to two commonly used genotyping methods, Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) and &lt;em&gt;flaA&lt;/em&gt; typing. Five &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt; strains isolated from conventional and organic poultry, and five additional isolates with published genomes were compared using the three methods. A total of 8 PFGE patterns and 8 &lt;em&gt;flaA&lt;/em&gt; alleles were identified from the 10 strains. Not surprisingly, WGS was more discriminatory than the other two methods and identified distinct differences among all ten isolates including genome size, G-C% content, and distribution of genes. Additionally, WGS revealed a number of virulence factors, including antibiotic and heavy metal resistance. Interestingly, genes coding for resistance to antibiotics were present in both conventional and organic isolates, but only conventional isolates possessed resistance to arsenic. The second part of this study aimed to understand the differences in resistance in organic and conventional isolates and determine if roxarsone, an organoarsenical coccidiostat used in poultry production, selected for arsenic resistance in&lt;em&gt; Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt;. Eighty-two isolates of &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt; were collected from 246 retail organic and conventional chickens from 2009 to 2010 prior to the roxarsone withdrawal. In 2013 and 2014, an additional 65 isolates were collected from 120 retail organic and conventional chickens, after the roxarsone withdrawal. PCR determined the presence of arsenic resistance (&lt;em&gt;ars&lt;/em&gt;) genes &lt;em&gt;arsC&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;acr3&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;arsB&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;arsP&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;arsR&lt;/em&gt; and agar dilution MICs were conducted to determine levels of resistance. Presence of &lt;em&gt;arsP&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;arsC&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;acr3&lt;/em&gt; were significantly correlated to isolates from conventional chickens pre-roxarsone withdrawal (Pre-RW) and these isolates had higher resistance to all arsenic compounds tested, compared to those from organic. Post-RW isolates retained arsenic resistance genes, but an overall reduction in arsenate and roxarsone MICs was observed. It appears that despite the removal of the selective pressure of roxarsone, &lt;em&gt;Campylobacter&lt;/em&gt; retains genes that confer arsenic resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3160</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4409&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3160</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4409</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-10T13:56:39-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4409/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6228048</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3160</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Irene B. Hanning</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jun Lin, David Golden, P. Michael Davidson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>