<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Student utilization of a College Counseling Center: a comparision of African Americans and Whites</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Stone</lname>
<fname>Rhoda</fname>
<mname>Gayle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the use of counseling services by African Americans on a predominantly White campus. It was hypothesized that minority students are more likely to present with academic issues as a &quot;foot in the door approach&quot; to dealing with interpersonal issues; in contrast students in the white majority are more likely to acknowledge interpersonal issues in their presenting complaints. The sample consisted of 1624 students who sought services at the University Counseling Center. Results indicate that African Americans and White students look somewhat similar when they initially seek help. Early findings indicate both groups are likely to address academic issues as a major point of concern. However, White students are more likely to be revealing of emotional and interpersonal concerns than African Americans students are when they initially present for services. The study also discusses the importance of outreach and ways to improve services for minority students who may find it difficult to address problems related to interpersonal issues.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6441</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8415&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6441</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8415</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075116</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6441</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert G. Wahler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Leonard Handler, Mike Nash, Wes Morgan, Gary Klukkin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>