<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A profile from a secondary analysis of alcohol consumption among undergraduate college students</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Tallant</lname>
<fname>April</fname>
<mname>Conley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Health and human sciences</keyword>
<keyword>College students</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to create a profile of four types of undergraduate alcohol drinkers enrolled in post-secondary institutions in the Southern United States. The study focused on non-frequent, frequent, non-binge and binge drinkers. The study also identified alcohol-related personal protective behaviors and analyzed the difference in alcohol-related health consequences reported by non-frequent, frequent, non-binge and binge drinkers who were undergraduate college students enrolled in higher education institutions in the Southern United States. The research study was a secondary analysis of data using responses to the Spring 2006 National College Health Assessment. Select data were analyzed using chi-square tests and multivariate analysis of variance. Frequent drinkers were more likely to be male, White, and in his third or fourth years of undergraduate study. A non-frequent drinker was more likely to be female, non-White, and in her first or second undergraduate year.Binge drinkers were more likely to be male, White and in his fourth undergraduate year. Non-binge drinkers were more likely to be female, non-White and in her first year of undergraduate study. Frequent drinkers reported using some alcohol-related personal protective behaviors than less often than non-frequent drinkers. Binge drinkers self-reported using some alcohol-related personal protective behaviors less often than non-binge drinkers. More frequent drinkers reported experiencing alcohol-related health consequences than non-frequent drinkers. Binge drinkers were more likely to report experiencing alcohol-related health consequences than non-binge drinkers. Future research should continue to identify characteristics of frequent drinkers and binge drinkers. Programs to reduce frequent drinking and binge drinking should target male and White upper classmen.In addition, future research should examine different types of consequences and whether personal protective behaviors are effective in reducing the risk of such consequences. Further research should examine actual alcohol consumption, alcohol-related personal protective behaviors and health consequences rather than rely on recall.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6013</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7946&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6013</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7946</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467717</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6013</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Susan M. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Health and Human Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>