<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Prehistoric Use of Hubbards Cave, Warren County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pritchard</lname>
<fname>Erin</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Hubbards Cave, in Warren County, Tennessee, contains evidence of a prehistoric gypsum mine. Such evidence is rare in the southeastern United States and few caves have been identified as prehistoric mineral extraction locations. Evidence of mining at Hubbards was documented using a total station laser transit and ArcView ã GIS program in order to identify and evaluate prehistoric activities throughout the cave. While much of the archaeological evidence pertaining to the prehistoric occupation of the cave has been removed as a result of later saltpeter (KNO 3) mining, traces of prehistoric evidence are documented in an attempt to interpret prehistoric use of the cave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results indicate that prehistoric people likely utilized the cave throughout the Woodland period for a number of different purposes. Evidence of a prehistoric occupation is present within the vast entrance shelter and extensive prehistoric activity is present throughout the lengthy passages of the associated cave. Spatial patterning of artifacts is examined to identify specific locations within the cave where prehistoric activity are concentrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hubbards is compared to four other mineral mining caves in the Southeast in terms of chronological and geographical relationships. Statistical analysis suggests Hubbards was mined later than other mineral mining caves in the Southeast. Geographically, it appears that gypsum mining began further north at Mammoth and Salts caves. Hypotheses are presented in an attempt to explain this phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1989</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3347&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1989</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3347</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T09:16:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4639295</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1989</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Jan F. Simek</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Charles H. Faulkner, Dr. J. Michael Elam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>