<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Methodological Basis of Dewey&#39;s Philosophy of Education</title>
<publication-date>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parker</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>LeRoy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this investigation was to show the methodological basis of John Dewey&#39;s Philosophy of Education, to state his explanation of  the method best suited to education, and to establish a relationship, if any, between his philosophy and attitudes in contemporary education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A search was made covering most of Dewey&#39;s written work, including a bound edition of his lecture notes. A thorough study of Joseph Ratner&#39;s commentary on Dewey&#39;s Philosophy of Education and of Dewey&#39;s exposition on logic, or inquiry, was undertaken. It was mainly from these sources that Dewey&#39;s Philosophy of Education was determined. The experiences and comments of a few contemporary educators were cited to indicate the relevancy of what Dewey advocated for what is taking place in education today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dewey&#39;s method of teaching was based essentially on the scientific method, which he expanded or modified to fit the individual&#39;s educational needs in his total environment. Dewey emphasized the importance of a student having experiences immediately beneficial to him. He also advocated that educators be on the alert for signs of creativity and to encourage its development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimentation is, according to Dewey, the mode of acquiring knowledge in science and, therefore, in education. He insisted that a necessary condition for knowledge is that it be useful or enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study concludes with some observations concerning Dewey&#39;s influence on education:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.  Educators today are making considerable effort to develop the &quot;whole&quot; person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.  Individual differences in students are considered in teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.  The importance of vocational development is recognized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4.  Many educators are interested in applying the scientific method of inquiry to teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5.  Many teachers consider education as growth, the one word that perhaps identifies John Dewey&#39;s philosophy of education.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3201</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4526&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3201</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4526</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-30T09:19:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6585887</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3201</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John W. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dwight Van de Vate Jr., Orin B. Graff</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>