<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Creating and Validating an Instrument to Measure Middle School Mathematics Teachers’ Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge (TPACK)</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>glandry@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Landry</lname>
<fname>Geri</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Middle School</keyword>
<keyword>Mathematics</keyword>
<keyword>Technology</keyword>
<keyword>TPACK</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Due to the pervasiveness of technology, the role and preparation of teachers as they strategically use technology for teaching mathematics needs to be examined. Technological pedagogical content knowledge (TPACK) is a framework for knowledge as teachers develop meaningful learning experiences for their students while integrating strategic use of technology (Mishra &amp; Koehler, 2006). The purpose of this study was to develop a survey for measuring mathematics teachers’ Mathematical Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge (M-TPACK). The survey measures the domains of mathematics content, pedagogy and technology. This mixed methods study first examined middle school mathematics teachers’ TPACK through the use of an existing survey (Schmidt et al., 2009). Interviews were conducted to determine the availability and use of technology in middle school mathematics classrooms, and teachers’ strategic use of available technology for mathematics instruction. Finally, a survey measuring M-TPACK was developed to specifically measure teachers’ mathematical TPACK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grandegenett (2008) asks for more concentration on helping teachers to imagine “possibilities” for using various approaches and strategies for integrating technology in mathematics instruction. This study presents important findings and supports the need for mathematics teachers’ professional development to reconceptualize the role of technology in mathematics instruction. By using the developed M-TPACK Survey, teacher educators and administers can use information about teachers’ knowledge and beliefs concerning technology to enhance teacher education programs and plan professional development.  The survey developed from this study can be used for stakeholders as they determine the needs of mathematics teachers, move the concept of TPACK beyond theory and toward practice, and move toward offering appropriate technology experiences to enhance strategic mathematics instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/720</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1727&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>720</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1727</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-22T08:47:19-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1727/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1238021</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/720</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vena M. Long</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>P. Mark Taylor, Blanche W. O&#39;Bannon, Charles R. Collins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>