<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Developing, Refining, and Validating a Survey to Measure Adolescent Food Safety Self-Efficacy</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>m.k.brandon@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Brandon</lname>
<fname>Monica K</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Assessment, Evaluation, and Research</discipline>
<discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Food Science</discipline>
<discipline>Other Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Self-efficacy is a proven indicator of predicting risky behaviors, but without a baseline level of adolescent food safety self-efficacy to develop targeted interventions it is difficult to produce meaningful behavior change. The research question around which this study was designed is:  To what extent can a validated instrument accurately capture adolescent beliefs of food safety self-efficacy. Through rigorous field testing and statistical analysis we hypothesize a valid and reliable instrument can be created for measuring adolescents’ food safety self-efficacy. The purposes of this study included: (a) development of a high quality, food safety self-efficacy instrument, (b) validation of the instrument through expert review, and (c) field testing of the instrument to measure adolescent food safety self-efficacy. A field test of the instrument was conducted with adolescent students (n=91) using expert review and the following analyses: a) the normality, (b) the validity, and (c) the reliability. The final instrument yielded 16 items that were within the boundaries of normality, passed expert review, and/or had strong validity and reliability results. The results of this study indicate that an instrument accurately measuring and capturing adolescent food safety self-efficacy is possible to create by using proven valid and reliable methods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/774</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1784&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>774</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1784</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-24T06:03:46-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1784/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1408055</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/774</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>P. Michael Davidson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Richards, Gary Skolits</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>