<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Students’ Perceptions of Teaching Styles and Use of Learning Strategies</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ychang5@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Chang</lname>
<fname>Ya-Ching</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The study was conducted to investigate Taiwanese junior high school students’ perceptions of their teachers’ teaching styles and the students’ own use of learning strategies and to determine if there was a significant relationship between perceived teaching style and learning strategy use. The data for this study were gathered from a sample of 95 junior high school students enrolled in four Chinese language classes at Yuanlin Junior high school. The students completed the Junior High School Teacher’s Teaching Style Questionnaire and the Taiwanese version of the Motivated Strategies for Learning Questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings from this study led to the following conclusions: (1) the students preferred to use learning strategies that enabled them to use time well and choose environments conducive to learning. Moreover, they preferred to seek assistance from their teachers or classmates when encountering learning difficulties; (2) gender differences in learning strategy use were not significant. Among nine learning strategies, male and female students both exhibited more use of strategies for Effort Management, Help-seeking, and Time and Study Management; (3) the dominant teaching style, as perceived by the students, was indifference; (4) the results revealed that there were no significant relationships between students’ perceptions of teaching styles and learning strategy use.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/782</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1835&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>782</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1835</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-10T06:15:26-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1835/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1434377</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/782</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Schuyler Huck</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Katherine H. Greenberg, Sherry Bain</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>