<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Use of the AnnAGNPS Pollutant Loading Model for Prediction of Sediment Yields in a Mountainous Cumberland Plateau Region: Correlations with the Stream Bed Sediment Characteristics</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Massey</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Patrick</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study attempts to develop a relationship with the hillslope sediment yield (estimated from a computer model) and the deposited sediment particle size characteristics within stream channels. By using specific hydrological parameters within a watershed, a calibrated Annualized Agricultural Non-Point Source (AnnAGNPS) pollutant loading model was created for four different sub-watersheds in the mountainous New River Basin of eastern Tennessee. The AnnAGNPS pollutant loading model predicted daily runoff and sediment yield reasonably well, but it poorly predicted daily peak flow rate for most sub-watersheds analyzed in the New River Basin. Overall, the AnnAGNPS pollutant loading model provided satisfactory results in a mountainous, nonagricultural landscape with a limited amount of climatic data available. The average annual hillslope sediment yield, in terms of clays, silts, and sands, was calculated with the AnnAGNPS model for years 2006 and 2007, to compare with sediment deposition characteristics in the streams. The fine particle size characteristics collected at specific bed deposition points were suspected to have a strong correlation with predicted sediment yield output from a calibrated AnnAGNPS pollutant loading model. The sites of the captured sediment were at locations just downstream of specific land use disturbances such as dirt roads, surface mining, and forest logging, all of which can be detrimental to the health of a stream environment and habitat if disturbances are not properly managed. In this study, the sediment collected at the channel bed deposition points represented the distribution of different material sizes that have recently moved within the stream during large discharge events. This investigation concluded that the certain measurements of the clays, silts, sands, and gravel material found in downstream sediment depositional points had a variety of significant relationships (p-value &lt; 0.05) with the clays, silts, sands, and total sediment yield occurring on the watershed hillslopes. Overall, there are a limited amount of studies that analyze these collections of fine sediment deposited in areas of the stream that have interrupted velocity forces due to channel shape, objects, or formations. This study showed that the use of the AnnAGNPS pollutant loading model and the analyzation of specific fine sediment at depositional points in the stream, proper watershed management of a rural mountainous region can be better established.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/404</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1437&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>404</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1437</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T11:12:55-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1147990</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/404</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John S. Schwartz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Eric C. Drumm, Raymond Albright</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/MasseyPatrick.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>