<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Organizational Citizenship Behavior As A Predictor of Work Team Performance</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nielsen</lname>
<fname>Tjai</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study assesses the relationships among organizational citizenship behavior (OCB), task interdependence, and performance at the team level. A longitudinal, correlational field study was conducted with 52 work teams from 6 organizations located in the Eastern United States. At the individual level of analysis it was hypothesized that OCB is positively related to individual performance. At the team level of analysis it was hypothesized that OCB is positively related to concurrent team performance, subsequent team performance, and customer-rated performance. It was also predicted that customer-rated OCB is related to concurrent and subsequent team performance. Task interdependence was expected to moderate the relationships between OCB and team performance at times 1 and 2, such that the relationships are stronger as task interdependence increases. Assessing team norms was hypothesized to be a more complete and accurate method for assessing team level variables and it was predicted that team norms of OCB is a better predictor of team performance compared with individual OCB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surveys were administered to 52 work teams. Team leaders (&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 52) provided ratings on team OCB, individual performance, and team performance at times 1 and 2. Team members (&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 209) provided ratings on individual OCB, team OCB, and task interdependence. Team customers (&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 83) provided ratings on team OCB and team performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results indicated that individual OCB is not related to individual performance. Team OCB positively correlates with concurrent team performance, subsequent team performance, and customer-rated team performance. Customer-rated team OCB is related to concurrent and subsequent team performance. Task interdependence moderates the relationship between team OCB and subsequent team performance, but not concurrent team performance. Team norms of OCB is positively related to team performance and predicts team performance better than individual level OCB. Eight of nine hypotheses were supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study extends the current literature on OCB and performance at the team level by demonstrating that team OCB is a robust predictor of team performance. It also indicates that team OCB is related to concurrent &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; subsequent team performance and provides support for the validity of assessing team norms of OCB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings from this study provide valuable information for individuals involved in the development and measurement of work teams. That is, the consistent and strong relationship between OCB and performance at the team level indicates that increasing citizenship behaviors within teams may be related to increased performance. In addition, results demonstrating the value of measuring team level process variables by assessing the degree to which they are team norms, indicates a potentially more accurate method for assessing team level variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A summary of findings is presented and an agenda for future research is suggested.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4193</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5754&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4193</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5754</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-13T12:35:00-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9678520</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4193</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eric Sundstrom</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Lounsbury, Michael Johnson, Craig Wrisberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>