<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>New Optical and Electrochemical Probes for Trace Chemicals with Health and Environmental Impacts</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tcarpen7@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carpenter</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Stewart</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Analytical Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The work in this dissertation focuses on the development of probes for the analysis of trace chemicals in samples with health and environmental impacts. A paper, Cu(copper)-based colorimetric probe was developed for the detection of toxic hydrogen sulfide (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S) gas. A modified Kipp’s apparatus was used to generate desired concentrations of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S in a total volume of 1.35 L (liters). The probe shows a qualitative response down to 60 ppb (parts per billion), indicating its ability to be used in industrial settings as a replacement for the commonly used lead acetate strips. When used in conjunction with a handheld colorimeter and smartphone, the probe can quantitatively detect the gas to a concentration of 16 ppb, which is below concentrations responsible for bad human breath. A method for the electrochemical detection and speciation of inorganic arsenic in pharmaceutical components has also been optimized. A gold electrode modified with a pyridine-functionalized layer has been developed to preconcentrate hexavalent chromium [Cr(VI)] anions for analysis by cathodic stripping voltammetry (CSV). The gold electrodes were modified through chemical deposition of a thiol sol-gel layer on the electrode surface, followed by the incorporation of gold nanoparticles (AuNPs) and a 2-pyridine functional group. The utilization of AuNPs has increased the sensitivity for detection of Cr(VI) anions in aqueous media, with a limit of detection of 93 ng L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;[L^-1].&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4611</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5812&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4611</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5812</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-23T14:21:04-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5812/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9740943</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4611</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Zi-Ling Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael J. Sepaniak, Brian J. Long, Brandon J. Horvath</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>