<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;An Irretrievable Loss&quot;: The Impact of Animal Loss on Older Lesbian Adults</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T16:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>putney@simmons.edu</email>
<institution>Simmons College</institution>
<lname>Putney</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<suffix>PhD</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Social Work</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research was to investigate the perceived impact of companion animals on the psychological well-being of older lesbian adults. This population is important because it is highly under-represented in empirical research; 44 percent of older LGBT adults have one or more companion animal (Fredriksen-Goldsen, et al., 2011); and older lesbian adults tend to be more isolated than their heterosexual counterparts and tend to feel deeply connected to ‘chosen family’, which can include animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psychological well-being of this population was examined within the context of the human-animal bond because animals bolster well-being, particularly among older adults, and human-animal interaction is often overlooked in social work scholarship. Although the primary purpose of the study was not to investigate grief per se, a prominent thematic finding related to the respondents’ experiences of grief and loss, which connected in complex ways with their own experiences of illness and preparation for end of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a non-probability sample gathered through purposive and snowball sampling techniques. The sample consisted of 12 women who ranged in age from 65-80, with a mean age of 71. In-depth, semi-structured interviews included questions about the rewards and challenges of having an animal, the ways in which animals have been important over the life course, and the rewards and challenges of aging. The interviews were audio-recorded and transcribed verbatim. Constant comparison data analysis was used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This presentation focuses on study results related to grief; specifically, the following four themes: (1) anticipation of losing an animal; (2) decisions related to euthanasia; (3) disruption and disequilibrium following the death of an animal; and (4) mourning. A major finding is that human-animal relationships took on pronounced significance while participants navigated life transitions and losses (such as terminal illness). Conversely, death of an animal precipitated substantial disorganization to respondents’ identity, sense of purpose, connectedness, and routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social workers are well positioned to validate the grief associated with death of an animal and provide supportive resources. Social workers who understand the complexities of human-animal interaction can provide older lesbian adults with comprehensive psychosocial care as they navigate end of life for themselves and their animals. Clinicians who include questions about animals during assessments are likely to discover sources of both strength and stress in a client’s life. Continued investigations into grief reactions related to the death or illness of an animal are indicated.&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredriksen-Goldsen, K. I., Kim, H. J., Emlet, C. A., Muraco, A., Erosheva, E. A., Hoy-Ellis, C. P., Goldsen, J., &amp; Petry, H. (2011). &lt;em&gt;The aging and health report: Disparities and resilience among lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender older adults. &lt;/em&gt;Seattle: Institute for Multigenerational Health.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/22</coverpage-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1033</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-10-25T12:48:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3426103</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Jennifer M. Putney, LICSW, PhD is an Associate Professor of Practice at Simmons College School of Social Work in Boston, MA, where she teaches clinical practice and research methods. Her primary research interests are the human-animal bond and LGBT aging.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Jennifer M. Putney, PhD, LICSW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simmons College School of Social Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;300 The Fenway&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boston, MA 02115&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;phone: 617.521.3971&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>LECONTE</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Grief and bereavement</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>