<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Habitat Selection by Northern Bobwhite Broods in Pine Savanna Ecosystems</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:50:43-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Stations and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Wellendorf</lname>
<fname>Shane</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Bostick</lname>
<fname>Allan</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Terhune</lname>
<fname>Theron</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University</institution>
<lname>Crouch</lname>
<fname>Tyson</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>broods</keyword>
<keyword>chicks</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>fields</keyword>
<keyword>fire</keyword>
<keyword>habitat use</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>pine</keyword>
<keyword>savanna</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Habitat for northern bobwhite (Colinus virginianus) broods is a critical component of bobwhite management. Research within pine (Pinus spp.) savannas has provided contradictory results regarding the value of macro-habitats with studies demonstrating selection for annually-disked fallow fields and others showing avoidance of fields and selection for burned pine savannas. Field establishment (up to 30% of a property) is a published management recommendation for bobwhites in pine savannas but there are significant annual costs with fallow-field management; information on factors that influence habitat selection by broods can improve management recommendations and facilitate weighing costs/benefits. We examined 2nd and 3rd order habitat selection by 466 broods on 3 sites during 1999–2009. All sites had similar macro-habitats (e.g., pine savanna, fallow fields, hardwood drains) but differed in soil characteristics and species composition of ground vegetation. Annually-disked fields were preferred by broods in most years on sites with predominantly grass and hardwood scrub ground vegetation. Rainfall mediated use of hardwood drains and burned upland pine savannas; hardwood drains were used more during droughts whereas burned pine savannas were used more with increased rainfall. Burned upland pine savanna was preferred on higher fertility sites in 9 of 10 years at the 3rd order level, fields were avoided or used according to availability in 8 of 10 years, and drains were avoided. Managers should consider how soil, weather, and vegetation community in pine savannas influences habitat use by bobwhite broods when identifying the value of different macro-habitats. Field establishment may or may not provide brood habitat depending on site.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/70</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1397&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>70</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_brood_ecology</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1397</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:44:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472207</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/70</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>