<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Search for Systematic Variability in Inter-Finger Ridge Count Variation Among European Groups</title>
<publication-date>1985-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Binkley</lname>
<fname>Kenneth</fname>
<mname>Melvin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Inter-finger ridge count variability has been shown to discriminate among major racial groups. However, little has been accomplished in the way of demonstrating patterned dispersion of inter-finger ridge count variability among groups of a major population. Here, multivariate techniques are used in a series of discovery procedures to search for systematic variability of finger ridge count contrasts among 48 male and 47 female European groups. Among-group biological variability of each sex is defined by principal components analysis, using the finger ridge count means of each group and a pooled within-group, within-sex covariance matrix having 5,474 degrees of freedom. Multiple regression analysis and spatial autocorrelation are used to compare biological group dispersion to geographic and linguistic dispersion. Among-group geographic variability is defined by the variation among group locations on a regression plane, and by specific inter-group direction and distance classes. The discovery of patterned among-group biological variability in a northwest direction is concordant with studies which used serological variables to define among-group biological variability. The findings are interpreted as evidence in support of a Neolithic demic expansion of Near Eastern agriculturalists.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4030</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5647&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4030</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5647</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-27T09:29:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9314888</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4030</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard L. Jantz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>P.S. Willey, William M. Bass, Gary F. McCracken</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1985-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>