<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The generation of influenza-specific humoral responses is impaired in ST6Gal I-deficient mice.</title>
<publication-date>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tonami@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Onami</lname>
<fname>Thandi</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Zeng</lname>
<fname>J</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Joo</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Rajini</lname>
<fname>B.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Wrammert</lname>
<fname>J.</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Sangster</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
<mname>Y.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Immune System Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Immunity</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology and Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology of Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunopathology</discipline>
<discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Virus Diseases</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Posttranslational modification of proteins, such as glycosylation, can impact cell signaling and function. ST6Gal I, a glycosyltransferase expressed by B cells, catalyzes the addition of alpha-2,6 sialic acid to galactose, a modification found on N-linked glycoproteins such as CD22, a negative regulator of B cell activation. We show that SNA lectin, which binds alpha-2,6 sialic acid linked to galactose, shows high binding on plasma blasts and germinal center B cells following viral infection, suggesting ST6Gal I expression remains high on activated B cells in vivo. To understand the relevance of this modification on the antiviral B cell immune response, we infected ST6Gal I(-/-) mice with influenza A/HKx31. We demonstrate that the loss of ST6Gal I expression results in similar influenza infectivity in the lung, but significantly reduced early influenza-specific IgM and IgG levels in the serum, as well as significantly reduced numbers of early viral-specific Ab-secreting cells. At later memory time points, ST6Gal I(-/-) mice show comparable numbers of IgG influenza-specific memory B cells and long-lived plasma cells, with similarly high antiviral IgG titers, with the exception of IgG2c. Finally, we adoptively transfer purified B cells from wild-type or ST6Gal I(-/-) mice into B cell-deficient (microMT(-/-)) mice. Recipient mice that received ST6Gal I(-/-) B cells demonstrated reduced influenza-specific IgM levels, but similar levels of influenza-specific IgG, compared with mice that received wild-type B cells. These data suggest that a B cell intrinsic defect partially contributes to the impaired antiviral humoral response.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>4721</fpage>
<lpage>4727</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/32</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1032&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>32</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1032</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-02-04T12:57:00-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3764021</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/32</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Immunology</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>