<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mom Made Me: Students Respond to the Flu Shot</title>
<publication-date>2013-03-18T17:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lgregg@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gregg</lname>
<fname>Lauren Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kcarver6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carver</lname>
<fname>Kristin</fname>
<mname>Kelly</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ccopela7@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Copelan</lname>
<fname>Christine</fname>
<mname>Cordelia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The University of Tennessee Knoxville’s on-campus Student Health Center publicizes the opportunity for students to receive the influenza immunization for $25 during the flu season. Despite on-campus convenience, many students are still deterred from receiving the shot. Advertising and Public Relations research students used survey research to sample more than 200 students in six major colleges across the University of Tennessee’s campus. The research team gathered relevant information about student perceptions of a healthy lifestyle, flu experience (diagnosis and shot), motivations and deterrence from the flu shot, and general knowledge of the Student Health Center. Results show that 27.5% of student respondents received a flu shot in the past year; key deterrents from receiving the immunization for both genders are inconvenience and lack of experience with the virus. The survey results indicate relationships among class year in school and the influences on individual health. Through these findings, the research team developed recommendations for the Student Health Center in regards to advertising campaigns, media relations, and specific targeting associated with year in school.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2013/communicationinformation/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1013&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1013</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-21T18:54:58-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1013/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>3941527</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2013/communicationinformation/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Advertising/Public Relations</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-03-18T17:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2013-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>