<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Developing Kenya’s Educational Capacity in Nuclear Security Through Nuclear Forensics Research</title>
<publication-date>2018-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hkalambuka@uonbi.ac.ke</email>
<institution>Department of Physics, University of Nairobi, Kenya</institution>
<lname>Angeyo</lname>
<fname>Hudson</fname>
<mname>Kalambuka</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Education Capacity; Nuclear Security; Nuclear Forensics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Defense and Security Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Engineering Education</discipline>
<discipline>International Relations</discipline>
<discipline>National Security Law</discipline>
<discipline>Nuclear</discipline>
<discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Radiochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Training and Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nuclear energy’s distinctive characteristics give rise to special educational requirements. These requirements are necessary to not only address the danger of nuclear proliferation, but also to build capacity for a secure nuclear fuel circle. In this paper, I assess the status of educational capacity in nuclear security both in response to, and in support of, Kenya’s nuclear power program. I highlight the nuclear security educational infrastructure’s key features in the context of nuclear power, noting the low capacity at Kenyan universities. I identify the steps required to ensure that the country’s dynamic nuclear regulatory infrastructural framework is used effectively to build capacity in nuclear security. I then examine the link between nuclear security and nuclear forensics and discuss efforts toward developing educational capacity in nuclear security through forensics research at the University of Nairobi, emphasizing in-field nuclear forensics and management of nuclear and radioactive materials out of statutory control. Finally, I consider the research challenges and solutions, which include developing a National Nuclear Forensic Library as a database for illicit trafficking or incidents that involve nuclear and radioactive material. I conclude that, despite the challenges, progress is underway but can be accelerated by promoting broader stakeholder involvement and government buy-in for more comprehensive educational capacity building in nuclear security.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/ijns/vol4/iss1/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1050&amp;amp;context=ijns&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1050</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-21T10:09:06-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ijns/article/1050/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>International Journal of Nuclear Security</publication-title>
<context-key>9295542</context-key>
<submission-path>ijns/vol4/iss1/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>The author wishes to acknowledge grant support from International Science Program, Sweden and World Academy of Sciences for the Advancement of Science in Developing Countries (TWAS) that helped establish the nuclear forensics research line in his laboratory. He further wishes to acknowledge the great support received in this effort from the International Nuclear Security Network (INSEN) community.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.7290/ijns040102</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xc4e7288)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Security Education via Forensics Research</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>