<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The synthesis and spectroscopic studies of titanium-amido complexes as potential catalysts for small molecule activation and polymerization reactions</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Colvin</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
<mname>James</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Chemistry</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The last decade has seen what some have termed a &#39;renaissance&#39; in amido--transition metal chemistry. In part, this has been due to a better appreciation of the amido moiety (R₂N) as a ligand. Moreover, it has been due to the dramatic reactivity that amido complexes have been shown to display, especially when the complex is low coordinate and high valent. This dissertation describes the utilization of dihydrodibenzoazepinyl and carbazolyl ligands to effectively stabilize titanium complexes. These two ligand sets vary in their electron contribution to the metal center due to reduced [pi]-donation from the carbazolyl ligand, this in turn effects the structural properties of the system. These novel titanium--amido systems are potential catalysts for small molecule activation and polymerization reactions. Their synthesis and extensive characterization through X-ray and NMR spectroscopy techniques is described herein. The synthesis of chelating amine ligands for the stabilization of metal centers can afford fascinating molecules. These compounds are fundamentally interesting due to the orientation of the four nitrogen lone pairs that are within close proximity to one another. The synthesis, reactivity and analysis of 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8--octahydro-2a,4a,6a,8a-tetraazacyclopenta[f,g]acenaphthylene is reported.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5973</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7906&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5973</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7906</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467582</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5973</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Baker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>