<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of DDT on Steroid Metabolism and Energetics in Bobwhite Quail (Colinus Virginianus)</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-24T14:23:13-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Ohio State University</institution>
<lname>Lustick</lname>
<fname>Sheldon</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Ohio State University</institution>
<lname>Voss</lname>
<fname>Terry</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Ohio State University</institution>
<lname>Peterle</lname>
<fname>Tony</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Female bobwhite quail (Colinus virginianus) fed low levels (5 ppm) of DDT in their diets showed increased enzyme induction in the liver and consequently a significant increase in steroid (progesterone) metabolism (a mean of 54% conversion of progesterone to its more polar metabolite in experimentals compared to a mean of 24.1% conversion in controls). The mean conversion of testosterone to its polar metabolite (25.1%) in experimental males was greater than in the controls (mean 18.1%) but was only significantly greater in certain males. There was a correlation (r = 0.7 P&lt;0.01) between percent body weight of testes and percent conversion of testosterone to its metabolites (the smaller the testes the greater the conversion). A correlation (r = 0.66 P&lt;0.02) was also found between circulating levels of DDE, DDT, and testes size (the higher the pesticide level the smaller the testes).&lt;br /&gt; Dietary levels of DDT (10,50,100,150 ppm) affected the energetics (oxygen consumption) of bobwhite quail. All DDT-treated birds had a higher metabolic rate than the controls at all ambient temperatures tested except 30 C. After acclimation to an ambient temperature of 5 C for 10-13 weeks, birds on 100-ppm DDT diets had a significantly (P&lt;0.01) higher metabolic rate than controls. After one week of exposure to -18 C there was a significant (P&lt;0.02) increase in thyroid weight in the birds on 100-ppm diets. Birds on 100-ppm diet exposed to extreme cold for 1 week died of DDT toxicity. &lt;br /&gt; Data on tissue residue levels, weight changes, I uptake by the thyroid, and adrenal changes are also presented. The ecological significance of the synergistic effect of DDT and cold stress on the bobwhite quail is discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/27</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1026&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>27</label>
<document-type>technical_session2</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1026</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-24T12:06:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10468828</context-key>
<withdrawn>2017-07-24</withdrawn>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/27</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>