<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Reproductive timing of the Scarlet Shiner (Lythrurus fasciolaris) in Northern Alabama</title>
<publication-date>2018-09-19T17:21:22-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>stallsb@uah.edu</email>
<institution>University of Alabama - Huntsville</institution>
<lname>Stallsmith</lname>
<fname>Bruce</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Alabama in Huntsville</institution>
<lname>Taylor</lname>
<fname>Toacca</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Alabama in Huntsville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Chelsie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cyprinid</keyword>
<keyword>stream fish</keyword>
<keyword>oocyte</keyword>
<keyword>GSI</keyword>
<keyword>clutch size</keyword>
<keyword>spawning</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Physiology</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Scarlet Shiner (&lt;em&gt;Lythrurus fasciolaris)&lt;/em&gt; is a cyprinid species widely distributed in parts of the Ohio, Cumberland and Tennessee river drainages of the United States. The objective of this study was to determine the Scarlet Shiner’s reproductive schedule. Maturation of ovaries and oocytes was determined through the categorization of developmental stages from early maturing to ripe, along with the calculation of monthly gonadosomatic index (GSI) measurements over two reproductive seasons in 2012 and 2015. In both years reproductive competence began in April. Average monthly GSI for females peaked in May, followed by a slow decline through August. Average clutch size was largest both years in April and May, although individual females were found with late developmental stage oocytes as late as August. Compared to other studied sympatric cyprinid species, the Scarlet Shiner was found to be a relatively late spawner with an extended spawning tail well into the summer.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1286&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1286</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-22T09:21:00-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1286/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10337787</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>J. Mann, K. Hodgskins, and S. Greenleaf helped with the fieldwork on this project. K. McDerby helped with much of the oocyte imaging and counting. K. Hodgskins created the maps in Figure 1. The comments of two reviewers improved the manuscript. Co-author T. Taylor was supported on this project in partial fulfillment of the requirements for a Master of Science degree by a stipend from the Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Progress at the University of Alabama in Huntsville. Material support for this project came from in part from a USDA grant, 1890 Institution Capacity Building Grants Teaching Program, #2012-02422, to B. Stallsmith.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xe78a778)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Reproductive timing of the Scarlet Shiner</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>