<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Numerical simulation of freezing shear driven rivulets using an enthalpy method formulation</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wiberg</lname>
<fname>Clark</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A numerical simulation of freezing shear driven rivulets is presented herein. The physics of the freezing process is captured in the simulation through application of the “enthalpy method”; a formulation well suited for the Stefan class of problems. The associated system of fully implicit finite difference equations was solved using the Gauss-Seidel iterative technique. The enthalpy method formulation is first applied to the case of a “stationary” freezing rivulet, but with a convective boundary at the free surface. The “stationary” simulation is utilized as a subset of the more complex “traveling”, or shear driven, simulation. The freezing process of shear driven rivulets was divided into three distinct modes based upon macro-scale observations of freezing rivulet flow on a NACA 0012 airfoil. From such observations, a non-dimensional empirical parameter was developed which establishes the bulk rivulet halt criterion for a freezing rivulet during runback.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6331</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8283&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6331</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8283</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450441</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6331</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Roy J. Schulz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>