<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Annotated Atlas of the Freshwater Fishes of North Carolina</title>
<publication-date>2020-10-19T10:14:20-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>fieryblackshiner@gmail.com</email>
<institution>North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences</institution>
<lname>Tracy</lname>
<fname>Bryn</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>fritz.rohde@noaa.gov</email>
<institution>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</institution>
<lname>Rohde</lname>
<fname>Fred</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gabriela.hogue@naturalsciences.org</email>
<institution>North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences</institution>
<lname>Hogue</lname>
<fname>Gabriela</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>North Carolina</keyword>
<keyword>Freshwater Fishes</keyword>
<keyword>Atlas</keyword>
<keyword>Distribution</keyword>
<keyword>Indigenous</keyword>
<keyword>Nonindigenous</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biodiversity</discipline>
<discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;North Carolina’s first state-specific checklist of freshwater fish species was published in 1709 by John Lawson. Subsequent species lists with descriptions included: Brickell (1737), Cope (1870a), Jordan (1889a), Jordan and Evermann (1896-1900), Smith (1907), Jordan et al&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; (1930), Fowler (1945), Louder (1962), Ratledge et al&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; (1966), Menhinick et al&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; (1974). In 1991, Menhinick published “&lt;em&gt;The Freshwater Fishes of North Carolina&lt;/em&gt;”, which is still widely in use because a comprehensive update has not been produced since its publication. The increase in the availability of historical records in globally accessible databases and the surge of collections post-1991 made by federal and state resource agencies, and academic and museum researchers, allowed for the creation of an update of North Carolina’s freshwater fish species in an annotated atlas. Herein we discuss the distribution of the 257 currently described and undescribed freshwater fish species within North Carolina. Annotations for each species include a distributional map with type locality noted where appropriate, remarks concerning questionable records and misidentifications, extirpations, introductions and interbasin transfers, and imperilment status.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss60/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1300&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1300</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-26T09:48:35-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1300/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>16660715</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss60/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>The authors are greatly indebted to all of the fish enthusiasts around the globe, including state and federal agency personnel, museum curators, collection managers, technicians, interns, and volunteers, that have collected, databased, geo-referenced, curated, and photographed North Carolina freshwater fishes and kindly shared their data. Without this tremendous amount of data, we would not have been able to put this publication together. The authors are also greatly indebted to Zion Creech (formally NCSM) and Scott A. Smith (NCDMF) for guidance and assistance with ArcGIS. Lastly, we would like to thank Dr. Steven Powers (Roanoke College), Editor, and two anonymous reviewers for their constructive criticisms, comments, and suggestions that greatly improved our manuscript.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-02-26T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xeb6da48)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Annotated Atlas of the Freshwater Fishes of NC</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>