<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Diversity in root‐associated fungal communities isolated from &lt;em&gt;Rhododendron maximum&lt;/em&gt; in the southern Appalachian mountains</title>
<publication-date>2012-04-14T09:20:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Appalachian State University</institution>
<lname>Price</lname>
<fname>Emily</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Appalachian State University</institution>
<lname>Walker</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, &lt;em&gt;Rhododendron maximum&lt;/em&gt; has become a dominant understory shrub in the southern Appalachian mountain range. This has profound implications for the future structure of the forest canopy, because &lt;em&gt;R. maximum&lt;/em&gt; reduces understory diversity and tree seedling recruitment by creating dense shade. The chemistry of the soil beneath &lt;em&gt;R. maximum&lt;/em&gt; is altered by the deposition of litter containing phenolic compounds, some of which are broken down and returned to the shrubs by the ericoid mycorrhizal communities associated with their roots. This community of fungi is essential to the success of &lt;em&gt;R. maximum&lt;/em&gt;, as the fungi allow the plants to thrive in nutrient-poor soils by acquiring nitrogen from organic sources. We expect that there are differences in the edaphic conditions across the growing season that may affect diversity and community composition of the associated fungi. In this study, I attempt to identify the 2 fungi that make up these communities and to reveal whether there is a seasonal shift in community structure over the course of a year. I sampled roots during the spring, summer, and fall of 2011 from two transects of ten &lt;em&gt;R. maximum&lt;/em&gt; plants each located at the Gilley Research Station in North Carolina. I extracted genomic DNA from the fungi isolated from root sections and amplified the ITS region of the samples from the spring and summer. I will analyze and present an initial comparison of the diversity and composition of the fungal communities associated with &lt;em&gt;R. maximum&lt;/em&gt; across the first two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/masmc2012/2012/April14/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=masmc2012&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-07-05T11:05:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Middle Atlantic States Mycological Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3057546</context-key>
<submission-path>masmc2012/2012/April14/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:40:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Toyota Auditorium, Howard H. Baker Jr. Center for Public Policy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:20:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:20:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>