<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Correlation of Theory and Experiment for the Dynamics of a Pressurized Water Reactor</title>
<publication-date>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thakkar</lname>
<fname>J.</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Dynamic tests were performed on the Carolina Power and Light Company&#39;s H. B. Robinson Unit 2 to determine the frequency response of the PWR steam supply system. Step inputs and multi-frequency binary signals of various sequence lengths and bit durations were used. The signals were introduced manually by the operator both for reactivity perturbation and steam flow perturbation tests. The experimental results were analyzed on and IBM 360/65 computer. The test results were compared with theoretical results predicted by a mathematical model of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mathematical model for the H. B. Robinson system was formulated. In most cases, the experimental results were in good agreement with the results. An unexplained time delay of about nine to fourteen seconds was observed between the opening of the main steam valve and reactor coolant cold leg temperature. The time delay is much longer than the transport time.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2696</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4170&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2696</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4170</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-25T11:18:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5829352</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2696</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>T. W. Kerlin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Julian E. Roth, P. F. Pasqua, J. C. Robinson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>