<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Motherhood as salvation: The experience of young Appalachian mothers</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T12:06:13-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>eddalton@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dalton</lname>
<fname>Betsy</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Health Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study explored the meaning of teenage motherhood to young Appalachian mothers using a phenomenological approach. In-depth interviews with 14 mothers between the ages of 18-22 from the southern central Appalachian region were conducted. Findings indicate that the experience of teenage motherhood can be described in terms of filling a void and the pervasive drug culture. Analysis of these findings indicates that the experience of motherhood is characterized by salvation. The salvation of motherhood is shaped by the emotional chasm it fills, as well as the protective barrier it provides between the mother and the drug culture surrounding her. Implications of these findings might include a need to examine the protective effects of motherhood from negative sociocultural forces among other subcultures. Also, the ubiquitous drug culture that surrounds young people in Appalachia should be taken into consideration when shaping policy and interventions for teenage pregnancy prevention.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/session2/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1042&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1042</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-12T10:04:12-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1042/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2398285</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/session2/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>