<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Role of Intracellular Free Calcium in the Obesity and Insulin Resistance Associated with Dominant Agouti Mutations</title>
<publication-date>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>Jung</fname>
<mname>Han</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Several dominant mutations at the agouti locus in the mouse cause a syndrome of adult-onset obesity, hyperinsulinemia, and insulin resistance. Although ectopic overexpression of the agouti gene is directly responsible for the disease in these mutations, the precise mechanism is unclear. Intracellular Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+ &lt;/sup&gt;([Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i) appears to have a role in mediating insulin signal transduction, and altered handling of [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i homeostasis and flux is observed in obese and insulin resistant animals and humans. Data reported here demonstrate that mice carrying the dominant agouti mutation, viable yellow (A&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;vy&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;), exhibit an elevation of [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i and Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+ &lt;/sup&gt;influx rate in insulin-sensitive type I skeletal muscle. The degree of elevation in [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i is highly correlated with the degree of expression of agouti gene and the elevation of body weight. Moreover, recombinant agouti protein directly induced a sustained increase in [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i in cultured myocytes and adipocytes; this effect is substantially inhibited by Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;  channel blockade. Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;channel blockade was also effective in reducing fat pad mass and fatty acid synthase (FAS) mRNA levels and activity in adipocytes of transgenic mice expressing the agouti gene in a ubiquitous manner. These results are consistent with previous reports in which recombinant agouti protein directly stimulates FAS mRNA levels and activity and triglyceride content in cultured adipocytes in a Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+ &lt;/sup&gt; dependent manner. Accordingly, altered [Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;]i metabolism appears to be involved in development of obesity syndrome in A&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;vy &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mice, and this defect in Ca&lt;sup&gt;2+ &lt;/sup&gt;signaling may cause activation of FAS either directly or indirectly and subsequent &lt;em&gt;de novo &lt;/em&gt;lipogenesis, contributing accumulation of fat depot in these mice.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3796</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5456&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3796</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5456</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-18T12:28:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8999197</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3796</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael B. Zemel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, Naima Moustaid, Richard P. Woychik</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>