<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular mechanism of caffeine-induced expression of two cytochrome P450 genes, &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt;, in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bhaskara</lname>
<fname>Srividya</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cytochrome P450 monooxygenases or CYPs comprise a large family of enzymes that are found in all classes of living organisms, from bacteria to man. These enzymes are involved in the metabolism of many endogenous and xenobiotic (foreign) compounds. In insects, CYPs confer resistance to various insecticides, and resistance-associated overexpression of multiple &lt;em&gt;CYP&lt;/em&gt; genes in resistant insects is a common phenomenon. In &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;, multiple &lt;em&gt;Cyp&lt;/em&gt; genes including &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; show higher level of expression in resistant strains than in the susceptible ones. To date, molecular basis of &lt;em&gt;CYP&lt;/em&gt; gene overexpression has not been examined in detail. Barbiturate compounds such as phenobarbital and barbital induce both these genes.  An unpublished observation from our laboratory showed that &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; as well as &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; are induced by over-the-counter caffeine tablet, Vivarin. In the present study, I used pure caffeine as a tool to better understand the mechanism of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; gene regulation in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific objectives of this project has been to (1) map the upstream DNA of both genes for the sequences responsible for caffeine-induction; (2) examine whether adenosine receptors and/or cAMP-specific phosphodiesterase (cPDE) are involved in transduction of caffeine signal to induce the two &lt;em&gt;Cyp6&lt;/em&gt; genes; and (3) investigate whether &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; AP-l transcription factors (D-JUN and D-FOS) playa role in caffeine induction of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; gene. For these objectives, several &lt;em&gt;Cyp-luc&lt;/em&gt; reporter plasmids carrying firefly &lt;em&gt;lueiferase (luc)&lt;/em&gt;  reporter gene under the control of different regions of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; upstream DNAs were constructed to transfect &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; embryonic cells, Schneider line 2 (SL-2). Two transgenic reporter strains carrying firefly &lt;em&gt;lueiferase (luc)&lt;/em&gt; reporter gene under the control of O.8-kb or 0.2-kb upstream DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; gene were also used to study the mechanism of caffeine induction &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of Northern blot analysis showed that caffeine induces endogenous &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; genes at the steady-state mRNA levels both in reporter transgenic and wild-type flies. Transfection experiments with SL-2 cells showed that -983/-1 and 7611-11 upstream DNAs of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt;, respectively, have sequences for caffeine-induced expression. Further transfection experiments with reporter plasmids carrying &lt;em&gt;luc&lt;/em&gt; reporter gene attached to truncated upstream DNAs of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; genes showed that the regions between -265/-129 of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and -199/-109 of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; have sequences that confer caffeine-induced expression. However, the level of both constitutive and induced expression was highest with -981/-1 DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt;and -761111 DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt;genes. Sequence analysis identified several putative binding sites for Activator Protein -1 (AP-l) and cyclic AMP response element CRE binding protein. (CREB) motifs in the upstream DNA of both genes. Moreover, when the four core bases of the single AP-l site present in the -109/-11 DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; were mutated, constitutive expression decreased by 8-fold, suggesting the positive role of AP-l in &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To examine whether caffeine signaling is mediated &lt;em&gt;via&lt;/em&gt; adenosine receptor (AdoR) and/or &lt;em&gt;via&lt;/em&gt; cPDE inhibition, SL-2 cells transfected with &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; reporter constructs were treated with AdoR agonists or with antagonists or with cPDE inhibitors. The  &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8-luc&lt;/em&gt; reporter transgenic lines were also treated with these chemicals. The results showed that caffeine signaling is mediated by PDE inhibition and &lt;em&gt;via&lt;/em&gt; increase in the intracellular cAMP level. Indeed, treatment with dibutyryl cAMP induces &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; as well as &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; promoters. Since induction of cAMP pathway is known to upregulate AP-I transcription factors, effect of overexpression of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; D-FOS and (or) DJUN (components of AP-I) on &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; promoter activity in SL-2 cells was examined. Surprisingly, activity of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8-1uc&lt;/em&gt; reporter construct was inhibited when D-FOS or DJUN proteins were overexpressed, suggesting that AP-I proteins are inhibitory for &lt;em&gt;Cyp6&lt;/em&gt; gene expression. In contrast, the &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; promoter activity was upregulated, when cells were transfected with anti-D-JUN plasmid or when cells transfected with D-JUN or DFOS sense construct were treated with caffeine. When relation between caffeine and the two AP-I proteins was examined, it was found that caffeine treatment significantly lowers the D-JUN protein level both in SL-2 cells as well as in adult flies. Reporter gene assays and Northern blot analysis showed that caffeine treatment has no effect on the transcriptional activity of the &lt;em&gt;D-jun&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;D-fos&lt;/em&gt; genes. Taken together, it might be concluded that caffeine induction of  &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; genes is mediated via degradation of D-JUN that acts as a repressor for the promoter of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt;.  Induction of the cAMP pathway and subsequent phosphorylation of the AP-l proteins may relieve the AP-l mediated-repression by promoting the degradation of these proteins. Further investigation is required to resolve these possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/673</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1859&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>673</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1859</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-21T08:39:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1365305</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/673</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bruce McKee, Albrecht von Arnim, Jae Park, Sundar Venkatachalam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>