<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Beta decay of neutron-rich isotopes of zinc and gallium</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>malshudi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Al-Shudifat</lname>
<fname>Mohammad</fname>
<mname>Faleh M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Beta-decay</keyword>
<keyword>Zinc</keyword>
<keyword>Gallium</keyword>
<keyword>NuShellX</keyword>
<keyword>Gamow-Teller</keyword>
<keyword>PSPMT</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear</discipline>
<discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Beta-decays of neutron-rich nuclei near the doubly magic &lt;sup&gt;78&lt;/sup&gt;Ni [78Ni] were studied at the Holifield Radioactive Ion Beam Facility. The half-life and the gamma-gamma coincidence spectra were used to study the nuclear structure. A new &lt;sup&gt;82,83&lt;/sup&gt;Zn [82Zn, 83Zn] decay-scheme was built, where a 71±7% beta-delayed neutron branching ratio was assigned in &lt;sup&gt;82&lt;/sup&gt;Zn [82Zn] decay. New gamma-ray lines and energy levels observed in &lt;sup&gt;82,83&lt;/sup&gt;Ga [82Ga, 83Ga] beta-decay were used to update previously reported decay-schemes. The experimental results were compared to shell model calculations, which postulate the existence of Gamow-Teller transitions in these decays. The half-lives of 155±17 and 122±28~ms were determined for &lt;sup&gt;82,83&lt;/sup&gt;Zn, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to enable future studies of very neutron rich isotopes a new detector was developed as a second project. This detector is intended for use in fragmentation type experiments, which require segmentation in order to enable implantation-decay correlations. In addition, the detector requires good timing resolution for neutron time-of-flight experiments. A Position Sensitive Photo-Multiplier Tube (PSPMT) from Hamamatsu coupled with a 16x16 fast pixelated plastic scintillator was used. The PSPMT&#39;s anodes form 8x8 segment panel used for position reconstruction. Position localization has been achieved for energies range of 0.5-5 MeV. A single signal dynode (DY12) shows a sufficient time resolution between this signal and the anode&#39;s signals, which enable us to used DY12 signal alone as a trigger for timing purposes. The detector&#39;s DY12 signals was tested with reference detectors and it provided a sub-nanosecond time resolution through the use of a pulse-shape analysis algorithm, which is sufficient for use in experiments with the requirement for the fast timing. The detector ability to survive after implanting high-energy ions was tested using a laser that simulated energy of 1 GeV. The recovery time of the detector in this situation was 200 nanosecond.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3288</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4802&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3288</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4802</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-16T13:27:21-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6996206</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3288</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Grzywacz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Soren Sorensen, Thomas Papenbrock, Jason P. Hayward</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>