<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Performance of HAGRID array in beta delayed neutron emission measurements</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>King</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Tobias</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;One of the most prevalent decay modes of unstable nuclei is β[beta] decay. For nuclei far from stability these decays can be followed by the emission of a neutron. The Versatile Array of Neutron Detectors at Low Energy (VANDLE) is a proven detection system for measuring the energies of delayed neutrons. VANDLE has been upgraded to include high-efficiency scintillators for gamma-ray detection. This increases the sensitivity for the γ[gamma]-rays that can follow the neutron emission. These scintillator components form an array of large volume NaI detectors and the Hybrid Array of Gamma-Ray Detectors (HAGRiD), which is an array of LaBr&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;[LaBr3] scintillators (BrilLanCe 380™). An experimental campaign at the Holifield Radioactive Ion Beam Facility at Oak Ridge National Laboratory was completed in the Spring of 2016. Beams of several &lt;sup&gt;238&lt;/sup&gt;U[238U] fission fragments were delivered to VANDLE. Some of the advantages and drawbacks of the new γ[gamma]-ray systems, in particular HAGRiD, will be presented in this work through the results for the decays of two neutron rich Rubidium isotopes (&lt;sup&gt;94&lt;/sup&gt;Rb [94Rb] and &lt;sup&gt;97&lt;/sup&gt;Rb [97Rb]).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5354</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6764&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5354</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6764</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T09:29:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>14343076</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5354</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Grzywacz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Katherine Grzywacz-Jones, Miguel Madurga Flores</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>