<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Balance Training On Falls Efficacy for Older Adults Residing In Assisted- Living Facilities</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Hurtubise</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Norman</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study investigated the impact of a four-week foam-support balance training program on falls self-efficacy in assisted-living older adults.  A Falls Self-Efficacy Scale (FES) and four balance performance measures (single-leg stand, tandem stand, functional reach, and eight-foot up-and-go) were completed to measure functional status and fear of falling.   The sample consisted of fifteen older adults from two separate assisted-living facilities.   Participants (N = 8) from one facility served as the control group, while those (N = 7) from the other facility represented the intervention group.  There were 6 females and 2 males in the control group ranging in age from 79 to 86 years (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 83, &lt;em&gt;SD&lt;/em&gt; = 3.52).  The 3 females and 4 males in the intervention group, ranged in age from 86 to 93 years (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 89, &lt;em&gt;SD&lt;/em&gt; = 2.73).  FES scales and balance measures were completed on the same day.  The pre-test-adjusted post-test mean for falls efficacy level in the intervention group (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 13.82) was less than in the control group (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 16.73).  Pre-test‑adjusted post-test means for single-leg stand, tandem stand, and functional reach scores for the intervention group were higher than those for the control group, (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 5.50 vs. &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 3.35; &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 308.55 vs. &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 171.73; &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 11.40 vs. &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 10.34, respectively).  For the eight-foot up-and-go test, the pre-test‑adjusted post-test mean score for the intervention group (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 11.81) was lower than for the control group (&lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; = 12.3).  Results suggest that the older adults who participated in the four-week balance training program may have reduced their fear of falling and improved their balance; however, there were no statistically significant differences between the groups, except for the single-leg stand.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1688</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3214&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1688</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3214</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-09T12:55:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4414591</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1688</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Diane Klein</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jim Neutens, June Gorski, John Orme, Buck Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>