<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessment of spatial and temporal patterns of log structures in East Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Reding</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research is to investigate hypotheses of settlement in the Ridge and Valley region of east Tennessee. The primary hypothesis of the study is that settlement patterns can be explained through the analysis of log structures in the region. I also hypothesize that survivability of log structures is associated with construction methods and wood used in the assembly and that dendrochronology can be used to determine construction dates. Through established research methods, dates of construction for log structures were obtained and locations were mapped temporally. This type of study has not been done in the region before and the results will help future research into the settlement of this area of east Tennessee. Log structures with estimated construction dates between 1800-1860 are analyzed in four counties. The initial phase of research establishes the locations and estimated construction dates of structures using information collected for the Historical Building Survey by the Tennessee Historical Commission. Utilizing field techniques, locations were confirmed and core samples from logs were collected for dendrochronological analysis to determine the precise construction dates of four structures. Dendrochronology confirms the accuracy of the methods of dating structures employed by the Historical Commission survey teams. The research validates the hypotheses and mcreases the understanding of settlement history in the Ridge and Valley region. The study also discovered a serious reduction in the numbers of log structures in the region. Preservation of log buildings needs to be addressed. The continued decline of log structures will adversely impact future research of settlement employing dendrochronology.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5979</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7612&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5979</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7612</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467641</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5979</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles S. Aiken</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>