<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Constructed Sites ad Collective Memory: A Proposal for Lower Manhattan&#39;s African Burial Ground</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Jessica</fname>
<mname>Lauren</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Architecture should be a derivative of site. As constructed sites, Archaeological sites pose an interesting dilemma with architecture: How does one approach an archaeological site with architecture? What operation best suits the site? The African Burial Ground is an exceptional example of a constructed site as well as the expression of the public’s desire to remember and signify this sacred site. Public request for these associations should result in site-derived architecture. Facilitating architecture as a derivative of site produces an expressive built form of culture, history and temporality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To derive architectural form from the African Burial Ground I will use a process of uncovery, discovery, and recovery. Through researching the history of the site and of the city, I will uncover the site. To discover the site I will use Anthropological and Archaeological analyses. These analyses will aide cultural, historical and temporal knowledge. I will recover the site to the collective memory of Lower Manhattan by re-representing the artifacts and the site itself.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4504</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6019&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4504</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6019</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-13T05:52:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10015102</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4504</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George Dodds</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles Debelius, Barbara Klinkhammer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>