<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Extreme Heat on Aviation</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:56:18-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bcarpen5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carpenter</lname>
<fname>Brandon</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business</discipline>
<discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Analytics</discipline>
<discipline>Operations and Supply Chain Management</discipline>
<discipline>Tourism and Travel</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Weather is a common cause of flight delays and cancellations. However, the vast majority of the time we think about weather and its effect on aviation, winter conditions, such as snow, come to mind. Heat is usually one of the last types of weather we associate with airline challenges. Recently, the Bomb Cyclone has made headlines for the headaches it caused with travel, especially at The John F. Kennedy International Airport. Interestingly, the exact opposite of winter weather conditions can cause just as many challenges. Over this past summer, a number of flights at various airports such as Phoenix Sky Harbor International and McCarran International were cancelled because the temperature on the runways was physically too hot for the planes to take off. The cancellations themselves only affected smaller, regional aircraft, but high temperatures still significantly affect larger Boeing and Airbus aircraft in the form of weight restrictions (meaning less passengers, less cargo, and potential delays in departure). This project overviews and analyzes the incident that occurred in Phoenix, details how heat significantly affects both small and large aircraft, and poses a few potential solutions (increasing runway lengths, adjusting airport routing, swapping aircraft, adjusting departure times, improving aircraft design, and decreasing on-board weight) that can help mitigate the effects of extreme heat on the aviation industry.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/business/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1163&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1163</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-12T18:37:15-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1163/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11955254</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/business/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Supply Chain Management</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Mary C. Holcomb</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>