<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>THE BAD, THE UGLY, AND THE UGLIER: HOW FEAR AND MISCONCEPTIONS ARE FLUSHING AWAY EQUAL RIGHTS AND TREATMENT FOR TRANSGENDER PEOPLE</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-28T08:06:38-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>falcol@tamu.edu</email>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University School of Law</institution>
<lname>Falco</lname>
<fname>Laura</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Transgender</keyword>
<keyword>Transgender Rights</keyword>
<keyword>Transgender Equal Rights</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil Rights and Discrimination</discipline>
<discipline>Constitutional Law</discipline>
<discipline>Fourteenth Amendment</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Our country has gone through multiple social changes over the years, and now we find ourselves in the middle of another change—one involving the transgender community. This community is and has been continuously fighting for equal rights and treatment. It is 2016 and the fight for equal rights in our country is at a tipping point. A tip in one direction would constitute a huge step in the fight for equal rights, but a tip in the other direction could result in unprecedented effects on transgender individuals and the rest of the LGBTQ community. The LGBTQ community just wants the same protection as everyone else, but opponents use fear and religion to excuse discrimination against an entire community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who consider themselves straight and identify with the gender assigned to them at birth may take the everyday equal protections they enjoy for granted. For transgender individuals, however, these basic human rights are not so easily enjoyed. Equal protection ordinances and bills give transgender people the opportunity to receive protection under the law and to exercise the same rights as everyone else. This paper takes a look at equal rights ordinances across the country and analyzes the arguments opponents have use to defeat those ordinances. This paper will further discuss what we as allies can do to overcome those arguments and obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/rgsj/vol5/iss2/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1085&amp;amp;context=rgsj&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1085</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-24T17:59:19-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Race, Gender, &amp; Social Justice</publication-title>
<context-key>9500914</context-key>
<submission-path>rgsj/vol5/iss2/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-24T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>THE BAD, THE UGLY, AND THE UGLIER</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>