<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Electrophysiological and Electrolyte Changes in Frog Striated Muscle After Irradiation</title>
<publication-date>1957-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Darden</lname>
<fname>Edgar</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Abbreviated&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present work, evidence is presented that radiation injury in excised frog muscle may be very early reflected in a loss of membrane potential which occurs at loci more or less randomly distributed over the fibers available for impalement; i.e., the superficially located fibers. The number and severity of these electrical lesions increase with time and with dose and appear to be strongly influenced also by the temperature of the surroundings. Concurrently, potassium leakage is presumably occurring at these lesions, for in time a net loss of K can be demonstrated by gross analysis of the muscle bath and/or ash. At this time, or shortly thereafter, visible changes are initiated at sites which, according to the evidence presented, correspond largely with the loci of the original electrical lesions. This visible fiber alteration leads to a histological condition similar to that commonly seen in many kinds of muscle injuries and diseases and known as Zenker&#39;s waxy or hyaline degeneration, just as described by previous workers for mammalian muscle heavily irradiated in the intact animal. This pattern of events is not uniquely confined to radiation effects but appears to be of some general significance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3223</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4638&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3223</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4638</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-13T11:42:27-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6653311</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3223</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Samuel R. Tipton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>C.W. Sheppard, R.F. Kimball, J.G. Carlson, R.D. Present</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Veterinary Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1957-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1957-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>