<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Job satisfaction and employee perception of the learning environment in the health care industry</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Cross</lname>
<fname>Marcia</fname>
<mname>E</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The researcher&#39;s purpose in conducting this study was to examine the relationship between job satisfaction and perception of the learning environment of administrative employees. Another objective was to distinguish whether or not relationships exist between job satisfaction and perceptions of the learning environment and between facets of job satisfaction and facets of the learning environment. Administrative employee attitudes were examined to discover whether or not demographic variables such as age, education, ethnicity, gender, location, marital status, position classification, and years of service were related to job satisfaction. The population of this study consisted of 480 administrative employees of a national health care management organization. A total of 261 participants (55%) responded to a demographics questionnaire, the Job Satisfaction Survey (JSS) for measuring job satisfaction, and to the Learning Environment Survey (LES) for measuring the learning environment Data analysis included frequencies, analysis of variance on each hypothesis, and multivariate analysis of variance on subscales when differences occurred. Tukey&#39;s HSD post hoc tests were run for significance. Pearson r tests were run to test relationships between total JSS and total LES and total JSS and subscales of the LES. Significant relationships were found for five out of six hypotheses. Major :findings of this study revealed that minority and billing center location participants were dissatisfied with overall job satisfaction; non-exempt participants were dissatisfied with pay and contingent rewards; and older participants perceived the organization was less tolerant of errors and perceived that the organization provided opportunities to utilize newly acquired skills than ymmger participants. Billing center participants had lower perception with opportunities to learn than participants in other locations. Billing center participants had lower perception that the organization was open to new ideas and change than participants in other locations. Higher levels of job satisfaction correlated with higher levels of the perceived learning environment. Strong correlations existed between total job satisfaction and facets of the learning environment. The conclusions, implications, and recommendations for further research are discussed based on these findings.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5208</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6616&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5208</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6616</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847044</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5208</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>