<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;You know your voice is kind of nice when your mouth isn&#39;t screwing it up.”</title>
<publication-date>2013-03-18T17:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jgrant24@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grant</lname>
<fname>Jennifer Anne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Fine Arts</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We watch movies, mostly for the mind-blowing special effects, extraordinary actors and actresses, and/or the unforgettable stories, but when do we ever remove the visual and just listen to the scripts or embrace the noise? In my work, I stray from the visual studies and draw that which I hear. I am interested in capturing the visual formation of words that become noise as they build up in my memory. As the mouths group together, so then does all of the character dialogue, ultimately resulting in incoherent noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through growing up around parents who started an audio visual business, I have been exposed to not only hundreds of movies, but I have watched these hundreds of movies over and over and over again, to the point of being able to recite words and phrases. I can quote just about every movie character from every movie I have ever seen. At times, it even becomes a useless talent that serves no purpose other than taking up space in my memory storage, ultimately causing me to constantly forget more important facts and details. As useless as it is in a practical sense, however, I will say that movie quotes have become a sort of code when communicating with my family; a life-long inside joke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this series, I then allow my audience to partake in this code and see movies and characters as I hear them.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2013/artsandsciences/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-19T18:23:50-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1001/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>3930159</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2013/artsandsciences/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Arts and Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Art</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-03-18T17:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2013-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>