<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Weaning and Syndyphalin-33 on Appetite Regulators in Swine</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cooper</lname>
<fname>Tabatha</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The synthetic met-enkephalin syndyphalin-33 (SD-33) increases feed intak in sheep and recently-weaned pigs. An experiment focused on changes in hypothalamic levels of mRNA transcripts from the following genes: μ-opioid receptor (&lt;em&gt;MOR&lt;/em&gt;), neuropeptide Y (&lt;em&gt;NPY&lt;/em&gt;), orexin (hypocretin; &lt;em&gt;HCRT&lt;/em&gt;), melanocortin 4 receptor (&lt;em&gt;MC4R&lt;/em&gt;), and agouti-related protein (AGRP). There was no effect of treatment on BW or FI at any point in the study. There is a strong positive correlation (p &lt;0.001) between MOR and MC4 that remains regardless of treatment or time. Weaning resulted in a numerical increase in hypothalamic &lt;em&gt;MOR&lt;/em&gt; mRNA expression. There was a treatment effect of &lt;em&gt;MOR&lt;/em&gt; expression levels 4 days postweaning. Hypothalamic NPY expression was unchanged through time or treatment. In VEH pigs, weaning resulted in increased hypothalamic expression of the &lt;em&gt;HCRT&lt;/em&gt; gene at d 1 and d 7 postweaning (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(time)&lt;/sub&gt; &lt; 0.01). In SD pigs, an increase in &lt;em&gt;HCRT&lt;/em&gt;expression (relative to d 0) was observed at d 4 postweaning. Expression of &lt;em&gt;HCRT&lt;/em&gt; did not significantly differ between treatment groups at d 1 and d 4, but &lt;em&gt;HCRT&lt;/em&gt; expression was greater in VEH pigs than in SD pigs at d 7 (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(time x treatment)&lt;/sub&gt; &lt; 0.05). Expression of hypothalamic MC4R did not change through time, but a trend (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(treatment)&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.07) was observed such that expression was less in SD pigs than in VEH pigs on d 1 and d 4 postweaning, possibly due to a numerical increase in expression in VEH pigs on d 1 relative to d 0.  Expression of &lt;em&gt;AGRP&lt;/em&gt; was decreased 1 d postweaning in VEH pigs but not in SD pigs,. On d 4, levels of &lt;em&gt;AGRP&lt;/em&gt; expression were lower in SD pigs than in VEH pigs, and lower than d 0 levels as well. On d7, &lt;em&gt;AGRP&lt;/em&gt; expression was less in VEH pigs than in SD pigs (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(time x treatment)&lt;/sub&gt; &lt; 0.01). Syndyphalin-33 has the potential to alleviate the negative effects of stress during weaning, and has the potential to increase feed intake through the melanocortinergic pathway. Further investigation is needed to more fully elucidate the complex mechanisms by which syndyphalin-33 may act to abrogate the post-weaning growth lag in pigs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/34</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1062&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>34</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1062</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-15T09:19:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1112078</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/34</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cheryl J. Kojima</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Arnold M. Saxton, Brynn H. Voy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>