<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Physical Activity and Weather: The Association of Physical Activity with Weather-Related Factors Measured on the Knoxville Third-Creek Greenway</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Burchfield</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to examine the association of outdoor physical activity (PA) with weather-related factors (temperature, humidity, heat index, and precipitation) when data was measured onsite (Knoxville Third-Creek Greenway). Secondary to this research question, this study explored whether the source of weather-related data (site-specific vs. public domain) influenced the strength of association with outdoor PA. PA, the dependent variable, was measured as trail counts by an infrared trail counter. Weather-related factors were obtained by an on-site weather station and through the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), a public domain weather source. Hourly PA (trail counts) and weather-related factors were matched and analyzed using correlations, dependent correlation comparisons, and linear regression modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical analysis showed that weather-related measures from both onsite and public domain weather sources were moderately correlated with PA. Weather-related factors explained approximately 13% and 20% of the variance in PA on weekdays and weekends, respectively, regardless of the source of weather related data. The amount of variance explained by weather-related factors in this study was 2-3 times more variance reported than any other study to date. The analysis of PA and weather-related data at the hourly level, as opposed to aggregated daily averages, may have increased the precision to detect differences in PA levels due to weather-related measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weather-related factors have a moderate association with outdoor PA. The association of PA with weather-related measures was different on weekdays compared to weekend days. No practical differences were found between weather-related measures collected from site-specific and public domain weather sources and their associations with PA. Future research is needed to better understand the effects of weather-related factors on total PA (indoor and outdoor) and to help explain the different effects of weather-related factors on weekdays compared to weekend days.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4473</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5987&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4473</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5987</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T09:51:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10004318</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4473</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dixie Thompson, Mary Evans, David R. Bassett, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>