<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Surface Symmetry Energy of Nuclear Energy Density Functionals</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nnikolov@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Nikolov</lname>
<fname>Nikola Iliev</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Surfae symmetry energy</keyword>
<keyword>fission</keyword>
<keyword>neutron rich nuclei</keyword>
<keyword>shell coorection</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thesis studies the bulk deformation properties of the Skyrme nuclear energy density&lt;br /&gt;functionals. Following simple arguments based on the leptodermous expansion and&lt;br /&gt;liquid drop model, the current research applies the nuclear density functional theory to&lt;br /&gt;assess the role of the surface symmetry energy in nuclei. To this end, one can validate&lt;br /&gt;the commonly used functional parametrizations against the data on excitation energies of&lt;br /&gt;superdeformed band-heads in Hg and Pb isotopes, and fission isomers in actinide nuclei.&lt;br /&gt;After subtracting shell effects, the results of our self-consistent calculations are consistent&lt;br /&gt;with macroscopic arguments and indicate that experimental data on strongly deformed&lt;br /&gt;congurations in neutron-rich nuclei are essential for optimizing future nuclear energy density&lt;br /&gt;functionals. The resulting survey provides a useful benchmark for further theoretical&lt;br /&gt;improvements. Unlike in nuclei close to the stability valley, whose macroscopic deformability&lt;br /&gt;hangs on the balance of surface and Coulomb terms, the deformability of neutron-rich&lt;br /&gt;nuclei strongly depends on the surface-symmetry energy; hence, its proper determination&lt;br /&gt;is crucial for the stability of deformed phases of the neutron-rich matter and description&lt;br /&gt;of fission rates for r-process nucleosynthesis. The results and consequent discussions from&lt;br /&gt;the thesis were published in Ref. [134].&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1107</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2203&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1107</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2203</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T11:46:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2035455</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1107</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Witold Nazarewicz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lawrence W. Townsend, Thomas Papenbrock, Robert Grzywacz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>