<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Impact of supplementing rumen-protected arginine on blood flow parameters and luteinizing hormone concentration in cyclic beef cows consuming endophyte-infected tall fescue seed</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>medwar23@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>arginine supplementation</keyword>
<keyword>beef cows</keyword>
<keyword>caudal blood flow</keyword>
<keyword>endophyte-infected fescue seed</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Livestock grazing endophyte-infected tall fescue can have decreased performance due to vasoconstriction and reduced reproductive performance. Therefore, the objective of this study was to determine the effect of supplementing rumen-protected arginine to cows consuming endophyte-infected tall fescue seed on caudal blood flow and LH dynamics. Four ruminally cannulated, open beef cows (539 ± 30 kg) were used in a 2 x 2 factorial arrangement of treatments utilizing a Latin Square design with 4 periods of 31 d each. Each cow was assigned to individual pens and fed orchardgrass hay (10.3% CP and 85% NDF; OM basis) during a 10-d adaptation period, followed by a 21-d collection period in which each cow was assigned one of 4 treatments: (1) rumen-protected ARG (180 mg/kg of BW) and 1.0 kg/d of endophyte-infected fescue seed (&lt;strong&gt;AE+&lt;/strong&gt;); (2) rumen-protected ARG (180 mg/kg of BW) and 1.0 kg/d of non-infected fescue seed (&lt;strong&gt;AE-&lt;/strong&gt;); (3) 1.0 kg/d of endophyte-infected fescue seed (&lt;strong&gt;E+&lt;/strong&gt;) alone; or (4) 1.0 kg/d of non-infected fescue seed (&lt;strong&gt;E-&lt;/strong&gt;) alone. In each period, doppler ultrasound measurements for blood flow parameters were quantified on d 1, 5, 10, 15, and 19. On d 20 of each period, blood samples were collected every 10 min for 6 h and then once every hour for 12 h. Caudal blood flow exhibited an interaction (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.05) of ARG × fescue seed type, resulting from an increase in blood flow in cows fed rumen-protected ARG. In addition, mean velocity was greater (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.01) with the inclusion of rumen-protected ARG in the diet. Caudal artery area (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.03) and diameter (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.01) were decreased in cows consuming E+ compared to E- with no effect (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; ≥ 0.38) by ARG supplementation. Mean serum LH concentration exhibited (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.02) an ARG × fescue seed type interaction. Cows consuming E+ had decreased LH concentrations compared to all other treatments. However, cows consuming AE+ had similar LH concentrations compared to cows consuming AE- or E-. Thus, supplementing rumen-protected ARG to cows grazing endophyte-infected fescue seed has the potential to increase reproductive performance and peripheral blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2869</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4120&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2869</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4120</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-06-18T08:00:55-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4120/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5698636</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2869</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John T. Mulliniks</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Janice L. Edwards, Brian Whitlock, Justin Rhinehart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>