<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Stretching with whole body vibration versus traditional static stretches to increase acute hamstring range of motion</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>abourne@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Bourne</lname>
<fname>Anastasia</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>hamstring stretching</keyword>
<keyword>static stretching</keyword>
<keyword>vibration</keyword>
<keyword>passive range of motion</keyword>
<keyword>active range of motion</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Musculoskeletal System</discipline>
<discipline>Other Rehabilitation and Therapy</discipline>
<discipline>Physical Therapy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPOSE &lt;/strong&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine if performing static active knee extension hamstring stretching using the Pneumex Pro-Vibe vibrating platform increased acute hamstring range of motion (ROM) greater than traditional static active knee extension hamstring stretching. &lt;strong&gt;METHODS:&lt;/strong&gt; A within subject design was utilized with subjects undergoing static stretching with vibration and without vibration (conditions counterbalanced). Pre- and post-test active and passive ROM was measured for the right leg, with subjects first undergoing a 5-minute warm-up on a stationary bicycle. Supine active knee extension was performed on the Pro-Vibe platform with and without vibration. The stretch was held 3 times each for 30 seconds, with a 20-second rest period between each stretch. Vibration was set at 30 Hz at the “high” amplitude setting. Active hamstring ROM was measured via active knee extension using a goniometer with the leg in 90° of hip flexion. Passive ROM was measured via clinician-assisted knee extension with the leg in 90° of hip flexion. &lt;strong&gt;RESULTS:&lt;/strong&gt; A 2-way repeated measures ANOVA was performed for passive ROM, and revealed a significant main effect for condition, F (1, 23) = 0.5875, p &lt; 0.05, and time, F (1, 23) = 5.029, p &lt; 0.05. Another repeated measures ANOVA was performed for active ROM with the same factors, and revealed a significant time by condition interaction, F (1, 23) = 4.730, p &lt; 0.05, and a significant main effect for time, F (1, 23) = 18.612, p &lt; 0.001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-hoc paired samples t-tests determined the difference between the pre-test and post-test measurements for each condition. Active ROM showed a significant difference pre-test to post-test for the vibration condition, t (23) = -5.41, p &lt; 0.001. The vibration condition also resulted in significantly different pre-test vs. post-test measurements on passive ROM, t (23) = -2.55, p &lt; 0.05. In both cases the average ROM was higher for the post-test. &lt;strong&gt;DISCUSSION:&lt;/strong&gt; Three 30-second active knee extension hamstring stretches using a vibrating platform are sufficient to cause significant acute increases in hamstring ROM. These findings suggest this device may be useful when desiring increased hamstring ROM.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/950</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1978&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>950</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1978</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-31T14:44:13-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/1978/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1913269</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/950</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Eugene C. Fitzhugh, Clare C. Milner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>