<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Undergraduate Experience and Giving: What Makes a Donor?</title>
<publication-date>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Simic</lname>
<fname>Laura</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Private support of public higher education has become increasingly important for institutions to remain competitive in times of decreasing tax support. Among scholars, there is general agreement that private support has become the vital ingredient which provides the difference between adequate and great institutions. There is little agreement, however, about the primary factors that motivate donors to give to colleges and universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help answer the question, &quot;Why do people give?&quot; a study was conducted of University of Tennessee, Knoxville College of Communications alumni with regard to aspects of their undergraduate experience. The alumni were divided into non-donor and donor groups and were surveyed about their satisfaction with their undergraduate experience, their involvement in extracurricular activities, relationships formed with faculty members, scholarship assistance received, and their perceived quality of career preparation. A chi square analysis of the survey responses was done to determine whether there is a significant relationship between each of the five factors mentioned above and giving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data indicate that there is a relationship between satisfaction with the overall undergraduate and general academic experience, and giving. The more specific experiences--involvement in extracurricular activities, relationships formed with faculty members, scholarship assistance received, and quality of career preparation skills--have no significant relationship to donor behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the study point to some aspects of the undergraduate experience which should be nurtured among students, while they are in school, to increase the likelihood of giving to their alma mater.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2531</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3897&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2531</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3897</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-13T11:57:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4923771</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2531</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>E. Grady Bogue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f7000615628)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>