<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Use of Audio Interaction in a Telecourse Offered by Satellite: Foundation of Adult Basic Education</title>
<publication-date>1990-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jahenschke@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Lindenwood University</institution>
<lname>Henschke</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
<suffix>EdD</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Community College Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
<discipline>Online and Distance Education</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The information explosion in our technologically oriented society has brought with it a shortened time span of cultural and factual knowledge change in each succeeding decade. Thus, professionals being educated in graduate Adult Education/Human Resources Development programs as teachers and for other roles need a lifelong learning perspective to prevent their becoming obsolete. These graduate programs have increased in North America from approximately thirty in 1960 to more than three hundred in 1990. However, a question remains for those who seek to serve these needs. How will the long-term impact of these graduate programs be measured, determined and evaluated? One program has sought to answer that major question. The University of Missouri-St. Louis has had competency-based adult education graduate offerings with nearly two hundred participants in less than a decade the graduate program has been actively in operation. A two-page &quot;Impact Survey Report Form&quot; was adapted and developed to include Kirkpatrick&#39;s evaluation paradigm of reaction, learning, behavior, and results. One hundred eighty-six different participants were sent forms with seventy-five responding. Questions included: what they gained, applied, the value to them and others, skill practice adequacy, cost/&#39;benefit ratio, benefits resulting, how the course could be improved, people served weekly, space to describe something they used and the results, how the use of self-directed learning affected other courses or their career, if they used learning contracts in other courses and in other education situations with people with whom they worked, and how self-directed learning was accepted in those situation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_IACE-browseall/450</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1455&amp;amp;context=utk_IACE-browseall&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>450</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1455</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-07-16T13:19:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>IACE Hall of Fame Repository</publication-title>
<context-key>7336707</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_IACE-browseall/450</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="class_year" type="date">
<value>1998-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1990-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>