<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Investigation of the Relationships among Work Values, Personality Traits, Job Satisfaction, and Career Satisfaction</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Salyer</lname>
<fname>Shannon</fname>
<mname>Danielle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, the relationships among work values, personality variables, job satisfaction and career satisfaction were investigated. The specific work values assessed in this research included: achievement, autonomy, challenge, creativity, ecology, family, informality, income, leadership, leisure, geographic locale, excitement, work space aesthetics, social responsibility, security, expertise, integrity, power and teamwork. Personality was assessed broadly by using the Big Five personality variables and narrowly, using more specific constructs of personality. An archival data source was used consisting of a sample of 457 employees from various industries. Several research questions were addressed answered including: How are work values related to broad and narrow personality traits? How are the work values related to job satisfaction and career satisfaction? And how are the Big Five and Narrow personality traits related to job and career satisfaction? Results of the study indicate several relationships between work values and the personality traits (both broad and narrow) in relation to each other and career and job satisfaction. Specifically, correlations showed a negative relationship between Emotional Stability and creativity (r = -0.27, p &lt;.001), and intrinsic motivation and income (r = -0.38, p &lt;.001). Work values were also related to both job and career satisfaction. However, more correlations were identified among the work values and career satisfaction. The results of a series of multiple regressions identified openness, conscientiousness, agreeableness, and emotional stability as significant predictors of job satisfaction. The narrow personality traits identified in the multiple regression as significant predictors of career success were: tough mindedness, optimism, assertiveness, customer service, and intrinsic motivation. Implications of the current study as well as future directions are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/296</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1349&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>296</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1349</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-05T11:48:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1133966</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/296</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Debora R. Baldwin, Eric D. Sundstrom, Tricia McClam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/SalyerShannon.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>