<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Age-related Effects of Reproduction on Bone Mineral Density in Saddle-back Tamarins (&lt;em&gt;Saguinus fuscicollis, Callitrichidae, Primates&lt;/em&gt;)</title>
<publication-date>1991-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Power</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research examines the age-related effects of reproduction on bone mineral density in saddle-back tamarins (&lt;em&gt;Sanguinus fuscicollis&lt;/em&gt;). Analyses of variance and bootstrapping statistical techniques were performed on a sample of 69 tamarins (31 males and 38 females) in order to determine the relationship between bone mineral density, age, gender, and reproductive status. The total sample of tamarins exhibits a significant decrease in bone mineral density with age, paralleling the condition observable in humans and Old World monkeys. Of particular interest are the results observable in the female sample relative to reproductive status. A significant increase in bone mineral density with age is exhibited by the non-reproducing females, while a significant decrease with age is observable in the reproducing females. It should be noted, however, that there was no sample representation for non-reproducing females within the older age range (&gt;150 months). Thus, it is questionable as to whether the decrease observed in the reproducing females is the direct result of reproduction and lactation, or primarily an artifact of age.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4231</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5699&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4231</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5699</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-12-19T09:51:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9487430</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4231</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Suzette D. Tardif</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allison Galloway, Lyle W. Konigsberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1991-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1991-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>