<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Low Power Integrated Circuit for Implantable Biosensor Incorporating an On-Chip FSK Modulator</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Oh</lname>
<fname>Taeho</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Medical care has been significantly improved in recent years due to tremendous technological advancement in the field of CMOS technology. Among those improvements, integrated circuit design and sensing techniques have brought to the doctors more flexibility and accuracy of examinations of their patients. For example, a diabetic patient needs to visit a hospital on a regular basis for the examination and proper treatment. However, with the tremendous advancement in electronic technology, a patient can soon monitor his or her own blood glucose level at home or at office with an implantable sensor which can also trigger insulin pump attached to the body. The insulin delivery system can be precisely controlled by the electronics embedded in the implantable device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, a low power integrated circuit for the implantable biosensor incorporating an on-chip FSK modulator is presented. This design has been fabricated using AMI 0.5-μm CMOS process available through MOSIS. The simulation and test results are also presented to verify its operation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/422</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1455&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>422</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1455</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T13:49:26-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1148685</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/422</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Syed Kamrul Islam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Donald W. Bouldin, Jayne Wu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/OhTaeho.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>