<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dynamics of Individual Molecules of Linear Polyethylene Liquids under Shear: Atomistic Simulation and Comparison with a Free-draining Bead-rod Chain</title>
<publication-date>2010-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>J.</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>B.</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Keffer</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Khomami</lname>
<fname>B.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Brownian motion</keyword>
<keyword>Gaussian distribution</keyword>
<keyword>molecular dynamics method</keyword>
<keyword>non-Newtonian flow</keyword>
<keyword>polymer solutions</keyword>
<keyword>rheology</keyword>
<keyword>shear flow</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nonequilibrium molecular dynamics (NEMD) simulations of a dense liquid composed of linear polyethylene chains were performed to investigate the chain dynamics under shear. Brownian dynamics (BD) simulations of a freely jointed chain with equivalent contour length were also performed in the case of a dilute solution. This allowed for a close comparison of the chain dynamics of similar molecules for two very different types of liquids. Both simulations exhibited a distribution of the end-to-end vector, |R&lt;sub&gt;ete&lt;/sub&gt;|, with Gaussian behavior at low Weissenberg number (&lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;). At high &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;, the NEMD distribution was bimodal, with two peaks associated with rotation and stretching of the individual molecules. BD simulations of a dilute solution did not display a bimodal character; distributions of |R&lt;sub&gt;ete&lt;/sub&gt;| ranged from tightly coiled to fully stretched configurations. The simulations revealed a tumbling behavior of the chains and correlations between the components of R&lt;sub&gt;ete&lt;/sub&gt; exhibited characteristic frequencies of tumbling, which scaled as &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−0.75&lt;/sup&gt;. Furthermore, after a critical &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt; of approximately 2, another characteristic time scale appeared which scaled as &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−0.63&lt;/sup&gt;. Although the free-draining solution is very different than the dense liquid, the BD simulations revealed a similar behavior, with the characteristic time scales mentioned above scaling as &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−0.68&lt;/sup&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−0.66&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_chembiopubs/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;amp;context=utk_chembiopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1007</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-19T07:16:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>1319070</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_chembiopubs/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Copyright (2010) American Institute of Physics. This article may be downloaded for personal use only. Any other use requires prior permission of the author and the American Institute of Physics.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>J. M. Kim, B. J. Edwards, D. J. Keffer, and B. Khomami, J. Rheol. (2010). Dynamics of individual molecules of linear polyethylene liquids under shear: Atomistic simulation and comparison with a free-draining bead-rod chain. 54, 283 DOI:10.1122/1.3314298</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>