<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Structural characterizations of photo-catalytic titanium oxide nanoparticles made from amorphous building blocks</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mtian1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tian</lname>
<fname>Mengkun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>TiO2</keyword>
<keyword>band gap narrowing</keyword>
<keyword>amorphous precursors</keyword>
<keyword>TEM techniques</keyword>
<keyword>monochromated EELS.</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; [titanium dioxide] nanoparticles (NPs) exhibit a variety of properties substantially departed from the optical and catalytic properties of the known bulk phases. A special interest in the engineering of functionality is how structures and bandgaps interact to enhance the photo-activity of TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. However, fundamental understanding of bandgap-related changes is difficult at these length scales because of scarcity of methods capable of probing the bandgap and the structure of isolated small particles. In this research, we adopt a series of highly spatially resolved transmission electron microscopy (TEM) techniques to characterize the structures of amorphous TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanoparticles (NPs) used as precursors and the TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; NPs with narrowed band gap derived from these amorphous precursors. The results show: (1) The amorphous TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; precursors consist of TiO&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; [titanium atom surrounded by six oxygen atoms] octahedra randomly connected with each other; (2) An unconventional phase transformation occur wherein anatase and TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(B) coexist when annealing the amorphous TiO&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;NPs in a temperature range from 400°C to 900°C in oxygengas; (3) Chromium and nitrogen co-doped TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; NPs have significantly narrowed band gaps originating from extra states on the top of valence band; (4) Black rutile NPs are produced by annealing amorphous TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; NPs at 700 °C in argon gas, which have a (crystalline TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) core-(amorphous Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3 &lt;/sub&gt;[titanium sesquioxide]) shell structure. Formation of Ti&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; originates from diffusion of oxygen vacancies towards vacuum in the amorphous precursors; (5) The black anatase NPs are produced by annealing amorphous TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; NPs at 400 °C in argon gas, whose structures are (i) core-shell, or (ii) randomly distributed phases. These two structures originate from different degrees of crystallization and diffusion rate of oxygen vacancies; (6) Cubic-TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is induced by the electron beam, which originates from the migration of interstitial Ti atoms grown on a rutile template; (7) We also discuss the origins of deviations from known phases’ EELS spectra which is the most important tool of electronic structure characterizations in this research; (8) Finally, we found a group of intense peaks in the interface between silicon and TiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. These peaks may originate from interface plasmon excitations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3522</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4899&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3522</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4899</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-16T09:07:11-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4899/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7221911</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3522</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gerd Duscher</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kurt Sickafus, Kalyanaraman Ramakrishnan, Gong Gu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>