<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Salk Institute</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:52:49-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sbitting@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bittinger</lname>
<fname>Sydney</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>egowder@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gowder</lname>
<fname>Emily</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architectural Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;After numerous iterations and red lines we&#39;ve come to create pages that accurately describe the visual and physical properties of the world renowned institute. Not only did we form an understanding of a space that we were once unfamiliar but we were able to share our knowledge with our classmates and the visiting professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conditions within the separate mechanical floors and the minimally connected towers for the offices create such unique spaces that were a vital part of the design of Louis Kahn. The custom rafters and capability to consistently update technological systems creates an ideal setting for scientific research. The offices accented with teak paneling fit in the facade like drawers in a shelf creating a clear distinction between the comfort of the offices and the purely brutalist polozan concrete. Laboratories of the offices help note the location and difference in comfort between the offices and the all polozan concrete laboratories. The organization of separated mechanical floors and minimally connected towers containing offices create unique spaces that become a vital part of Louis Kahn&#39;s design.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/architecturedesign/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1122&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1122</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-03T09:44:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>9966143</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/architecturedesign/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Architecture and Design</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Hansjörg Göritz</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>