<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Influence of Beauty-Related YouTube content on Consumers&#39; Purchase Intention</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>klee80@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Kyungji</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Electronic word of mouth (eWOM)</keyword>
<keyword>YouTube</keyword>
<keyword>Information Adoption Model (IAM)</keyword>
<keyword>information quality</keyword>
<keyword>source credibility</keyword>
<keyword>purchase intention</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the development of the internet, electronic word of mouth (eWOM) has been considered a significantly effective tool to appeal to consumers. Many previous studies have investigated eWOM, but most of them focused on textual eWOM. Thus, this study examines eWOM in the context of beauty-related videos on YouTube. The Information Adoption Model is used to test whether those videos influence cosmetics purchase intention of consumers. This study conducted an online survey of 427 female millennials. The collected data was analyzed by Partial Least Square (PLS) regression. The results confirmed that information quality and source credibility were the important determinants of perceived information usefulness which significantly and positively influenced information adoption and purchase intention. Moreover, this study also supported the extended vision about the relationship between information quality and source credibility in the context of the elaboration likelihood model (ELM). Based on the results, theoretical and practical implications are highlighted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5151</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6558&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5151</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6558</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415096</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5151</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sally J. McMillan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Courtney C. Childers, Ronald E. Taylor</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>