<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Exploring the Mechanism of Meiosis in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;: Meiotic Functions of a Novel Cohesion Protein SOLO and a Translation Initiation Factor VASA</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yan</lname>
<fname>Rihui</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Sister chromatid cohesion is essential for proper chromosome segregation during meiosis. However, the mechanism of meiotic cohesion in Drosophila is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We describe a novel protein, SOLO (Sisters On the LOose) that is essential for meiotic cohesion in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster. solo&lt;/em&gt; mutations cause high nondisjunction of sister and homologous chromatids of sex chromosomes and autosomes in both sexes. In &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; males, sister chromatids separate prematurely and segregate randomly during meiosis II. Although bivalents appear intact throughout meiosis I, sister centromeres lose cohesion prior to prometaphase I and orient nearly randomly on the meiosis I spindle. Centromeric foci of SMC1 are absent in &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; males at all meiotic stages. SOLO and the cohesin protein SMC1 co-localize to meiotic centromeres from early prophase I until anaphase II in wild-type males but both proteins are removed prematurely from centromeres at anaphase I in &lt;em&gt;mei-S332&lt;/em&gt; mutants, coincident with premature loss of cohesion in those mutants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; mutations in females cause reduced frequency of homologous recombination between X chromosomes and autosomes, partially due to the loss of inhibition of sister chromatid exchange. Synaptonemal complex assembly is severely disrupted in early meiotic stage in &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; females. SOLO colocalizes with SMC1 and C(3)G in meiosis. Additionally, SOLO is required for stabilizing chiasmata generated from residual recombination events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data about the phenotypes of &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; males and females and colocalization patterns of SOLO strongly suggest SOLO is a component of potential cohesin in Drosophila meiosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drosophila males undergo meiosis without recombination. However, the underlying mechanism is not known. Mutations of vasa cause high frequency of X-Y exchange in meiosis. Chromatin bridges at anaphase I and II, due to dicentric recombination events, were observed in vasa males. &lt;em&gt;vas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; double mutant showed precocious segregation of homologs at metaphase I besides chromatin bridge at anaphase I and II. Our data thus for the first time demonstrate that inhibition of meiotic recombination during male meiosis requires vas function and interactions between &lt;em&gt;vas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt; regulate chromosome dynamics in male meiosis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/280</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1333&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>280</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1333</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-05T09:21:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1133423</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/280</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bruce D. McKee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly, Jae Park, Mariano Labrador, Yisong Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/YanRihui.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>