<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unmasking Wagner&#39;s Grail: Homoeroticism, Androgyny, and Anxiety in &lt;i&gt;Parsifal&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tmitch22@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mitchell</lname>
<fname>Tyler</fname>
<mname>Cole</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Wagner</keyword>
<keyword>Gender</keyword>
<keyword>Sexuality</keyword>
<keyword>Opera</keyword>
<keyword>Anti-Semitism</keyword>
<keyword>Parsifal</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>German Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Musicology</discipline>
<discipline>Other Feminist, Gender, and Sexuality Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Most readings of Wagner’s final music drama &lt;em&gt;Parsifal &lt;/em&gt;seek to illumine a clandestine presentation of Wagner’s racist doctrine or make sense of a less-shrouded but still ambiguous panegyric to Christianity. However, little scholarly material addresses Wagner’s provocative account of sensuality and homoeroticism in this &lt;em&gt;Bühnenweihfestspiel &lt;/em&gt;[Stage Consecration Festival Play]. This thesis explores desire and homosexuality within the drama and considers how and why Wagner masks these themes through the opaque mythos of religion, race, and community. &lt;em&gt;Parsifal&lt;/em&gt; was partly informed by Wagner’s own complex neuroses: his sexual anxieties and scandals, amalgam of German philosophies, and confusion concerning Germanness. As filtered through his own belief system, Wagner’s &lt;em&gt;Parsifal&lt;/em&gt; ambivalently presents homoeroticism, wavering between an idealized pure love and a destructive, even unnatural, force of desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was initially inspired by Laurence Dreyfus’s work &lt;em&gt;Wagner and the Erotic Impulse&lt;/em&gt;, which struck me as a fresh exegesis of Wagner’s oeuvre, embracing the overt sexual nature of his dramatic text, music, and philosophical writings. Carolyn Abbate’s &lt;em&gt;Unsung Voices&lt;/em&gt; and Jean-Jacques Nattiez’s &lt;em&gt;Wagner Androgyne&lt;/em&gt; provide methodologies for narration and androgyny from which I draw. Wagner demonstrates homoerotic sensibilities through both heroic and villainous characters, within an exotic medieval Spain (and a &lt;em&gt;Zauberschloß), &lt;/em&gt;and through opposing sonic worlds of communal diatonicism and chromatic sensuality. Exploring this work from a perspective energized by recent musicological gender studies and musico-textual semiotics and relations, my reading of &lt;em&gt;Parsifal&lt;/em&gt; is thus primarily corrective. Wagner’s final music drama offers a manifestation of love and sensuality with all the contradictions and fears of Wagner’s experiences and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2834</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4064&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2834</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4064</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-21T06:48:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5501732</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2834</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rachel M. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Leslie C. Gay Jr., Jacqueline Avila</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Music</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Music</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>