<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Innovation Outside Firm Boundaries: A Real Options Perspective on Appropriability, Commercialization Strategies and Firm Performance</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mroussea@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Rousseau</lname>
<fname>Mary Beth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Innovation Management</keyword>
<keyword>Technology Commercialization</keyword>
<keyword>Real Options Theory</keyword>
<keyword>Firm Performance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Technology and Innovation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation focuses on the conditions under which innovating firms may employ external commercialization strategies to appropriate value from their innovations and enhance firm performance. Specifically I examine the relationship between appropriability conditions of intellectual property protection, complementary assets and uncertainty, and the firm’s decision to commercialize innovations externally. Applying real options theory to a firm’s innovation strategy, I hypothesize that external commercialization strategies mediate the effect of appropriability conditions on firm performance. Hypotheses tests are conducted on a sample of more than 1600 firms and 300 external commercialization agreements in the manufacturing sector. Notwithstanding the overall lack of support for these hypotheses, there remains potential for making a contribution to the innovation literature. First, the integration of real options theory and the appropriability framework offers a theoretical extension of both literatures. Second, results of post-hoc tests indicate that some relationships do exist and further investigation is warranted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1775</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2886&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1775</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2886</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-27T18:22:54-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2886/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3803349</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1775</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Franz W. Kellermanns</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Annette L. Ranft, David W. Williams, Stephanie A. Bohon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>