<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Comparison of avian biochemical test results with Abaxis VetScan and Hitachi 911 analyzers</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Greenacre</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Flatland</lname>
<fname>B</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Souza</lname>
<fname>Marcy</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fry</lname>
<fname>M</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;To compare results of clinical biochemical analysis using an Abaxis VetScan bench-top analyzer with reagents specifically marketed for avian use and a Hitachi 911 analyzer, plasma (both methods) and whole blood (VetScan method) samples from 20 clinically healthy Hispaniolan Amazon parrots (Amazona ventralis) were analyzed. Correlation between methods was very high (r = 0.9-1.0) for aspartate aminotransferase (AST), calcium, glucose, and uric acid; high (r = 0.7-0.89) for creatine kinase (CK), phosphorus, potassium, and total protein; moderate (r = 0.5-0.69) for globulin; and low (r = 0.3-0.49) for albumin and sodium. VetScan analyzer results for globulin, sodium, and uric acid had a constant negative bias (values below those from the Hitachi method). Based on difference plot analysis, results for AST, calcium, CK, and glucose are comparable. Because 16 of 20 values fell below the lower detection limit of the VetScan analyzer, bile acid data were excluded from analysis. By using a relatively small sample size (0.1 ml whole blood or plasma), the VetScan analyzer offers rapid in-house results, compact size, and ease of operation. For 4 of the most clinically relevant biochemical analytes used in avian medicine (AST, calcium, CK, glucose), it offers reliable values. For an additional 4 analytes (phosphorous, potassium, total protein, uric acid), establishing analyzer-specific reference intervals is recommended. Neither the VetScan nor the Hitachi method is recommended to assess albumin and globulin concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/10</coverpage-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1009</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-27T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1288702</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>C B. Greenacre, B Flatland, Marcy J. Souza, and M M. Fry. &quot;Comparison of avian biochemical test results with Abaxis VetScan and Hitachi 911 analyzers&quot; Journal of avian medicine and surgery 22.4 (2008): 291-299.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.bioone.org/doi/abs/10.1647/2007-034.1</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Avian Medicine and Surgery</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>