<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessing the Impact of Movement Consequences on the Development of Early Reaching in Infancy</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>joshua.williams@armstrong.edu</email>
<institution>Armstrong State University, Savannah, GA</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Corbetta</lname>
<fname>Daniela</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>motor development</keyword>
<keyword>infants</keyword>
<keyword>reaching</keyword>
<keyword>reinforcement learning</keyword>
<keyword>contingent reinforcement</keyword>
<keyword>developmental trajectories</keyword>
<keyword>sensorimotor experience</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;x-x-x-__p4&quot;&gt;Prior research on infant reaching has shown that providing infants with repeated opportunities to reach for objects aids the emergence and progression of reaching behavior. This study investigated the effect of movement consequences on the process of learning to reach in pre-reaching infants. Thirty-five infants aged 2.9 months at the onset of the study were randomly assigned to 1 of 3 groups. Two groups received a 14-day intervention to distinct reaching tasks: (1) in a contingent group, a toy target moved and sounded upon contact only, and (2) in a continuous group, the toy moved and sounded continuously, independent of hand-toy contact. A third control group did not receive any intervention; this group’s performance was assessed only on 2 days at a 15-day interval. Results revealed that infants in the contingent group made the most progress over time compared to the two other groups. Infants in this group made significantly more overall contacts with the sounding/moving toy, and they increased their rate of visually attended target contacts relative to non-visually attended target contacts compared to the continuous and control groups. Infants in the continuous group did not differ from the control group on the number of hand-toy contacts nor did they show a change in visually attended target versus non-visually attended target contacts ratio over time. However, they did show an increase in movement speed, presumably in an attempt to attain the moving toy. These findings highlight the importance of contingent movement consequences as a critical reinforcer for the selection of action and motor learning in early development. Through repeated opportunities to explore movement consequences, infants discover and select movements that are most successful to the task-at-hand. This study further demonstrates that distinct sensory-motor experiences can have a significant impact on developmental trajectories and can influence the skills young infants will discover through their interactions with their surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_psycpubs/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1021&amp;amp;context=utk_psycpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1021</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-13T11:08:12-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Psychology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>9263474</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_psycpubs/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Williams JL and Corbetta D (2016) Assessing the Impact of Movement Consequences on the Development of Early Reaching in Infancy. Frontiers in Psychology 7:587. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2016.00587</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.3389/fpsyg.2016.00587</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Frontiers in Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>