<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>“Participation and Life Skill Development of the Tennessee Junior Livestock Skillathon Programs</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Powell</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
<mname>Margaret</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Education</discipline>
<discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined the Tennessee Junior Livestock Skillathon Program and its objectives.  Research was conducted to determine what motivates or deters youth participation, how youth prepare for the skillathon and life skill development in the areas of communication, critical thinking and self-confidence.  A self-developed, eleven question, likert scale survey was mailed to 200 randomly selected youth that exhibited livestock in the 2003 Tennessee Junior Livestock beef, sheep or market hog shows.  Fifty-two percent (112) participants responded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youth that participate in the skillathon do so because they want to see how much they know about their project and they felt the skillathon was an enjoyable experience that allowed them the opportunity to gain recognition.  Those that did not participate in the skillathon indicated that they did not want to participate and they were not prepared.  Nine preparation methods were identified for youth to determine how they study for the skillathon.  The most popular method was studying with a friend or parent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life skill development was the last component of the survey.  Ninety percent of youth indicated that they did gain communication and critical thinking skills.  Eighty percent of respondents indicated a gain in self-confidence as a result of participating the skillathon.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2321</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3727&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2321</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3727</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-16T12:10:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4729117</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2321</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>H. Dwight Loveday, James B. Neel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communications</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>