<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The revealing cut : horizontal and vertical orthogonal section in the architectural design process</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Laurent</lname>
<fname>Barbara</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis explored the role of orthogonal section in the architectural design process, contending that, in particular, multiple orthogonal sections, both horizontal and vertical, are the primary tools in the design process. It examined spatial layering as the primary architectural language of section, and developed a taxonomy of section as a means for both exploration and design. The thesis examined the historical origins of orthogonal section drawings, how architects used sectional drawings over the centuries, and the role of section in twentieth century architectural production. It also examined several case studies of significant buildings, the analysis of which were pertinent to the thesis exploration. The vehicle for this thesis exploration was the Villa Giulia, a sixteenth century country retreat built for Pope Julius III just outside the north gate of Rome, Italy. Early in the twentieth century, the Italian government converted the Villa into the National Etruscan Museum, and added museum buildings to the complex. With its own intricate longitudinal section, the Villa and its museum buildings provided an ideal site at which to explore the role of section in the architectural design process. The architectural proposal for this thesis provided expansion and additional functions for the museum. The proposal added new gallery space, both an indoor and an outdoor auditorium, access to the grottos, a library, and facilities for visiting scholars as well as expanded the bookstore and cafe. While &quot;proof” of an architectural proposal&#39;s success can only come with the actual construction of the building, this proposal, none-the-less, used section and layering as the vehicle for the new museum design. Program was layered in vertical section, as well as distributed via the traditional plan. The new proposal gave emphasis to the transverse section as well as the traditional longitudinal section of the Villa, and paid particular attention to the different ideas of section developed in the sectional taxonomy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5251</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6659&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5251</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6659</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847115</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5251</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Adam M. Drisin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>