<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Angiotensin II Increases Leptin Secretion in Adipocytes via a Prostaglandin-Independent Mechanism</title>
<publication-date>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>Suyeon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Adipose tissue functions as a secretory organ. Adipocyte-derived All and prostaglandins are involved in promotion of adipocyte hyperplasia through enhancement of preadipocyte differentiation as well as adipocyte hypertrophy. All was proposed to regulate adipocyte differentiation in part via prostacyclin. The peptide hormone leptin encoded by the &lt;em&gt;ob &lt;/em&gt;gene is produced primarily by adipocytes and is believed to be the signal indicating the level of adiposity. We have previously demonstrated that All increases &lt;em&gt;ob &lt;/em&gt;gene transcription in adipocytes. In this study, we have examined mechanisms of All effect on leptin secretion in adipocytes. All at physiological concentrations significantly increased leptin secretion in human adipose tissue and 3T3-Ll adipocytes in a dose and time response manner. Consistently, 6-keto PGF&lt;sub&gt;1a&lt;/sub&gt; (a stable degradation product of PGI&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)  and PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  secretions were also significantly stimulated by physiological doses of AII. Inhibitors of prostaglandin biosynthesis, namely indomethacin and aspirin significantly blocked basal as well as All-induced prostaglandin synthesis. However, inhibition of prostaglandin synthesis by these inhibitors did not modify All-induced leptin secretion. Consequently, these findings demonstrate that All regulation of leptin secretion from adipocytes is independent of prostaglandin.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3991</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5467&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3991</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5467</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-16T08:44:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9129307</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3991</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Naima Moustaid Moussa</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, James Bailey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>