<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Impact of nutritional management strategies on semen quality of developing bulls</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jprocto7@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Proctor</lname>
<fname>Jarret</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>beef cattle</keyword>
<keyword>bull</keyword>
<keyword>hoof conformation</keyword>
<keyword>pH</keyword>
<keyword>rumen</keyword>
<keyword>semen</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nutritional management and semen collection method are thought to influence semen quality parameters evaluated during a breeding soundness examination. Therefore, the objective of this experiment was to evaluate the effects of two feeding strategies on growth performance and semen quality of developing bulls. A secondary objective was to quantify the effects of two semen collection methods on semen quality. Angus bulls (n = 48; 332 ± 47 d of age) were stratified into one of sixteen drylot pens before random assignment to one of two iso-caloric diets: a total mixed ration (TMR; n = 8 pens) or a component-based ration (COMP; n = 8 pens). Bulls were assigned to either electroejaculation (EE; n = 24) or trans-rectal massage (RM; n = 24) and each collection method occurred twice throughout an 84-d feeding period. Rumen pH was continuously monitored via rumen boluses and dry matter intake (DMI) was measured daily. Backfat thickness and hoof conformation were measured on d 0 and 84, with body weight measured and semen collected at 21-d intervals. Semen was assessed for progressive motility, total sperm per ejaculate, and sperm cell morphology. Bulls fed the COMP ration had a greater DMI (P &lt; 0.01) and ADG (P &lt; 0.01), but similar feed efficiency (P = 0.19) when compared to TMR-fed bulls. Bulls fed COMP had a lower mean rumen pH (P &lt; 0.01). Additionally, COMP-fed bulls had greater backfat thickness (P &lt; 0.01) but similar hoof conformation scores (P ≥ 0.55) when compared to TMR-fed bulls on d 84. Bulls fed the COMP had greater semen volume (P &lt; 0.05) but feeding management did not affect progressive motility (P = 0.42), total sperm per ejaculate (P = 0.86), or percent morphologically-normal sperm (P = 0.59). However, bulls collected via RM had greater total sperm per ejaculate (P &lt; 0.05), and semen volume (P &lt; 0.01), but lower percent morphologically-normal sperm (P &lt; 0.05) and progressive motility (P &lt; 0.01). Neither diet nor semen collection method affected BSE passage rate (P ≥ 0.34), suggesting minimal influence on BSE outcomes in developing bulls.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5538</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7011&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5538</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7011</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914348</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5538</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jason Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Justin Rhinehart, Lew Strickland</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5463-6248</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>