<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Anesthesia Clinical Core Competencies and High Fidelity Human Simulation</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jjames6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>James</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>Colby</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Anesthesia</keyword>
<keyword>Competency</keyword>
<keyword>Simulation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the study was to identify anesthesia clinical core competencies that are appropriate for evaluating proficiency utilizing High Fidelity Human Simulation (HFHS). This purpose was achieved by identifying the perceptions of nurse anesthesia educational program administrators and faculty regarding the anesthesia clinical core competencies that are appropriate for evaluating proficiency utilizing HFHS. Participants completed a 50-item web-based survey instrument and demographic questionnaire (Anesthesia Core Competency and Simulation Survey). High fidelity human simulation (HFHS) based evaluation of anesthesia clinical core competency proficiency can be a valuable tool for assessing anesthesia trainees, certifying nurse anesthetists, and recertifying nurse anesthetists. Evidence from this study suggests there is a consensus among anesthesia educational program administrators and faculty regarding anesthesia clinical core competencies that are appropriate for proficiency evaluation utilizing HFHS. Anesthesia educational program administrators and faculty in the United States agree that with the exception of Prone Position (appropriateness score = 2.99, with 3 being neutral), the required experiences put forth by the Council on Accreditation of Nurse Anesthesia Educational Programs and the National Board for Certification and Recertification of Nurse Anesthetists are suitable for evaluating proficiency utilizing HFHS. Thus, the agreement among administrators and educators that emerged from this study provides a foundation on which faculty can begin to incorporate HFHS into their curricula.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3139</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4305&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3139</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4305</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-08-17T19:33:38-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4305/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5987742</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3139</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer A. Morrow, Jean A. Derco, Gary J. Skolits</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>