<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fine mapping in tomato using microsynteny with the Arabidopsis genome: the Diageotropica (Dgt) locus</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Oh</lname>
<fname>KwangChul</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Hardeman</lname>
<fname>Kristine</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Ivanchenko</lname>
<fname>Maria</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Ellard-Ivey</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Nebenfüh</lname>
<fname>Andreas</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>White</lname>
<fname>TJ</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oregon State University</institution>
<lname>Lomax</lname>
<fname>Terri</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Genomics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; genome sequence provides a catalog of reference genes applicable to comparative microsynteny analysis of other species, facilitating map-based cloning in economically important crops. We have applied such an analysis to the tomato expressed sequence tag (EST) database to expedite high-resolution mapping of the &lt;em&gt;Diageotropica&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Dgt&lt;/em&gt;) gene within the distal end of chromosome 1 in tomato (&lt;em&gt;Lycopersicon esculentum&lt;/em&gt;).  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A BLAST search of the &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; database with nucleotide sequences of markers that flank the tomato &lt;em&gt;dgt&lt;/em&gt; locus revealed regions of microsynteny between the distal end of chromosome 1 in tomato, two regions of &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; chromosome 4, and one on chromosome 2. Tomato ESTs homeologous to &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; gene sequences within those regions were converted into co-dominant molecular markers via cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence (CAPS) analysis and scored against an informative backcross mapping population. Six new microsyntenic EST (MEST) markers were rapidly identified in the &lt;em&gt;dgt&lt;/em&gt; region, two of which further defined the placement of the &lt;em&gt;Dgt&lt;/em&gt; gene and permitted the selection of a candidate tomato bacterial artificial chromosome clone for sequence analysis.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsynteny-based comparative mapping combined with CAPS analysis of recombinant plants rapidly and economically narrowed the &lt;em&gt;dgt&lt;/em&gt; mapping region from 0.8 to 0.15 cM. This approach should contribute to developing high-density maps of molecular markers to target-specific regions for positional cloning and marker-assisted selection in a variety of plants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biolpubs/24</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1023&amp;amp;context=utk_biolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-12T11:54:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- General Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4310345</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biolpubs/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Genome Biology 2002, 3:research0049-research0049.11 doi:10.1186/gb-2002-3-9-research0049</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>