<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Essays in Behavioral Economics</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jli54@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Jing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>axiomatic bargaining</keyword>
<keyword>social preferences</keyword>
<keyword>bargaining norms</keyword>
<keyword>gender pay gap</keyword>
<keyword>task allocation</keyword>
<keyword>experiment</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavioral Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Economic Theory</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In chapter one, I propose a model consolidating the norm- and preferences-based approaches to explain laboratory bargaining outcomes. Social norms are identified by the axioms of cooperative bargaining theory, and other-regarding preferences are captured using Fehr and Schmidt&#39;s inequity aversion utility function. The model applies to bargaining situations where other-regarding agents abide by social norms in their decision-making. Preferences and norms interact to determine bargaining outcomes, and their interaction undermines the recoverability of the other-regarding preference parameters based on observations from the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter two, I employ a lab experiment to study whether men receive lucrative tasks more often than equally capable women so that a gender pay gap arises due to the difference in the earnings potential. Subjects allocate a standard task and a lucrative task between two workers, knowing their past performance, task preference, and sex. I find that men receive the lucrative task more often than women, but past performance and a gender difference in task preference account for the difference. Many workers shy away from the challenging yet lucrative task, suggesting that a psychic cost may arise when the tasks are challenging. Managers choose the efficient task allocation less often when the workers&#39; preferences go against rather than with their money-incentive. The result suggests that managers show concern for the subjective utilities of the workers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4747</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6174&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4747</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6174</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-15T12:36:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10310291</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4747</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William S. Neilson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Scott Gilpatric, Matthew C. Harris, Bogdan Bichescu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>