<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Contemporary practices in sustainable design: appraisal and articulation of emerging trend</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asharma8@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sharma</lname>
<fname>Archana</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>sustainable</keyword>
<keyword>design</keyword>
<keyword>development</keyword>
<keyword>eco-architecture</keyword>
<keyword>urban design</keyword>
<keyword>landscape</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Design</discipline>
<discipline>Landscape Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Sustainable design is a phrase commonly used in the realms of design practice and yet the definition of the same remains quite fuzzy, thus providing the motivation for this research. The paper looks at contemporary sustainable design practices in the area of architecture design, building construction and landscape architecture. The objective is to understand what the term “sustainable design” really means as used in practice and what strategies are being employed towards the goal of sustainable development. The practices are assessed for their empathies as per the currently defined social, ecological, economical well-being goals of sustainable development. The paper concludes that out of the conventional triad of social, economic and ecological well-being, the socio-ecological well-being is emerging as the prevalent trend among the contemporary sustainable design practice. The trend needs to be continuously refined in this direction through intelligent employment of social and economic capital.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_architecpubs/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;amp;context=utk_architecpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>conference</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1005</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-12-15T18:22:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Architecture Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1699365</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_architecpubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Sharma, A. 2010. Contemporary practices in sustainable design: appraisal and articulation of emerging trend. Hernandez, S, Brebbia, C. et al (ed). Eco-architecture, Southampton, Boston: WIT Press pp 119-132</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://library.witpress.com/pages/PaperInfo.asp?PaperID=20776</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>