<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modernism within a regional context</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Zukerman</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Barak</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Israel was established as a country of immigrants, most who have arrived only in the last 100 years. When these new immigrants came, they brought with them social and cultural backgrounds different from the local ones. A new identity was created that partially merged the two. The last ten years has brought an influx of over a million immigrants to Israel, mainly from the former Soviet Union. The continued migration has caused a rift in the cultural fabric of the country. The solution for this rift is to understand both the resident culture as well as immigrant culture, and to promote a tolerance and equality in the midst of diversity. This should be done through educational and academic means. Historically, the major population growth&#39;s occured in the 1920&#39;s and just after 1948 when the country was established. The main architectural changes however occurred in the first period of growth. During that period, architectural ideas, mainly Bauhaus, influenced the indigenous architecture and created a hybrid of the two. Today, a new hybrid can emerge that is based on architectural ideas and technologies that have changed over the last century. This hybrid is based on the now indigenous architecture of Israel and Tel-Aviv in particular.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6028</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7661&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6028</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7661</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467690</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6028</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Adam Drisin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tom K. Davis, Peter Lizon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>