<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of Fabrication of Ultra-high Resolution Nano Devices through Electron Beam Lithography Process and Its Application to Electron – Optical Systems</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>Jihoon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Today’s semiconductor industry has been significantly changing in its techniques and processes for the fabrication of devices and accordingly, there has been dramatic increase in performance and a reduction in cost. To obtain still higher device performances and still further cost reduction, the dimensions of patterns in integrated circuits should be as small as possible and the 3-dimensional accuracy of multidimensional semiconductor structures should be also achieved as well. The manufacturing of smaller feature dimensions and 3-dimensional devices has been enabled by developments in lithography – the technology which transfers designed patterns onto the silicon wafer. Especially, electron beam lithography is widely adapted in the nano fabrication technology due to its ability to achieve nanometer-scale resolution. The aim of this work is to fabricate test devices by the electron beam lithography possesses and apply them to the test of electron optical systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, we first develop methods to fabricate a high resolution nano scale Fresnel zone plate and 3-dimenstional stair case structure by E-beam lithography. To optimize the fabrication we optimized the lithographic process and the subsequent process steps accounted for proximity effects via a correction program and controlled pattern transfer through reactive ion etching (RIE). The completed devices were tested in a Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) and the accuracy of feature parameters were examined by Fast Fourier Transformation methods (FFT). Finally, the application of these structures to the calibration and testing of e-beam systems was explored.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/215</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1261&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>215</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1261</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-02T09:26:00-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1129253</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/215</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Joy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Philip D. Rack, Joseph E. Spruiell, Anthony J. Pedraza</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/KimJihoon.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>