<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Demographic shifts and green values in rural America : a southern Appalachian case</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Talley</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Robert</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation examines changing environmental values in rural America, specifically as it applies to differences in support for environmentalism between inmigrants and non-migrants who live in rural places. As a means to this end, we closely examine hypothesized differences across several measures of environmentalism between rural in-migrant and non-migrant residents of the Norris Lake watershed area, in East Tennessee. We also explore the suggestion that the social bases of environmental concern may have changed over time due to a general greening trend that seems to be cutting across all social groups. Stem et al&#39;s (1995) working model of environmentalism is used as a guide to map several conceptual levels of environmentalism and link them to public support for the environment and to examine differences in environmentalism between rural in-migrants and non-migrants. These conceptual levels, or facets, of environmentalism include modified forms of Dunlap et al&#39;s (2000) New Ecological Paradigm Scale and Schwartz&#39;s (1992) theory of integrated value systems. We noted support for the proposition of a broadening of the social bases of environmental concern.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6449</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8423&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6449</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8423</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075127</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6449</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Emmet Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry Cable, J. Mark Fly, Thomas C. Hood</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>