<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Wo liegt die Grenze? Aspekt, Aktionsart und verwandte Phanomene in der Erforschung der deutschen Sprache</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gallmeier</lname>
<fname>Maria</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Modern Languages</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In 1824, Jacob Grimm first used the terms &lt;em&gt;perfective&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;imperfective &lt;/em&gt;to describe the German verbal system and initiated the discussion of the aspecto-actional meaning in such pairs as &lt;strong&gt;jagen&lt;/strong&gt; : &lt;strong&gt;erjagen&lt;/strong&gt;. Since then, German research has frequently failed to define aspectological terms and categories unambiguously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study examines the status of German aspectological research, with special reference to the boundary between the categories &lt;em&gt;Aspekt&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aktionsart&lt;/em&gt;. For background, this dissertation successively examines early German aspectological research (1824 to 1930), landmark German grammars, German aspectological research since 1970, cross-linguistic aspectological research in the Slavic and Anglo-American traditions with regard to these terms and categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This permits clear identification of the most frequent definitional problems in German aspectology: (a) confusing application of the category pairs &lt;em&gt;perfectivity &lt;/em&gt;vs &lt;em&gt;imperfectivity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;terminativity&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;aterminativity&lt;/em&gt;; (b) restriction of the term &lt;em&gt;grammatischer Aspekt&lt;/em&gt; to Slavic aspect; (c) differentiation of &lt;em&gt;Aspekt&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aktionsart &lt;/em&gt;only by the degree of grammaticalization vs. lexicalization; (d) failure to restrict &lt;em&gt;Aktionsart&lt;/em&gt; to a specific level of representation, e.g. morphology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some resulting terminological problems are: (1) the use of term &lt;em&gt;Aspekt&lt;/em&gt; indiscriminately to denote three grammatical categories, &lt;em&gt;aspect&lt;/em&gt;, the semantic category, &lt;em&gt;perfectivity&lt;/em&gt;, and the semantic category, &lt;em&gt;aspectuality&lt;/em&gt;; (2) the use of the term &lt;em&gt;Aktionsart&lt;/em&gt; to denote: (a) semantic groups of verbs, (b) the lexico-grammatical verbal classes, (c) the semantic category, &lt;em&gt;terminativity&lt;/em&gt;, and (d) the semantic category, &lt;em&gt;aspectuality&lt;/em&gt;; (3) the use of the term &lt;em&gt;Aktionsart&lt;/em&gt; to denote simultaneously the actional classes of verbs and morphologically marked and unmarked semantic groups of verbs, such as&lt;em&gt; ingressive&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;inchoative&lt;/em&gt; etc.; (4) plethora of terms for the opposition &lt;em&gt;terminative&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;aterminative&lt;/em&gt;; (5) unjustified use of the terms &lt;em&gt;perfective&lt;/em&gt; vs. &lt;em&gt;imperfective&lt;/em&gt; in the description of the German verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the results of this analysis, unambiguous definitions and internationally acceptable terminology for the major aspectological categories are suggested. Four factors are essential for this: (1) distinguishing aspectual, actional and temporal categories within the functional-semantic domain of aspectotemporality; (II) distinguishing between aspectual and actional meanings; (III) distinguishing aspectual and actional meanings from their &lt;strong&gt;means of expression&lt;/strong&gt;; (IV) distinguishing between &lt;em&gt;Aspekt&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aktionalklassen&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aktionsarten&lt;/em&gt; on the level of expression.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4318</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6027&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4318</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6027</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-05-01T06:52:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10098369</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4318</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Chauncey J. Mellor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Lee, Stefanie Ohnesorg, Robert Sklenar</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Modern Foreign Languages</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>