<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Lithostratigraphy of Conasauga Group Between Rogersville and Kingsport, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Helton</lname>
<fname>Walter</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: The following conclusions are presented from the study of the lithostratigraphy of the Conasauga Group in Carter and Stanley valleys:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. The Conasauga Group presents classic examples of isopic and heteropic facies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. The lithology of the individual formations of the Conasauga Group is remarkably similar in both thrust belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. The carbonate units of the Conasauga Group thicken eastward and southeastward and the claystone units thicken westward and northwestward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. The Pumpkin Valley Shale is a transitional unit which has a Rome lithology in the lower half of the formation and Conasauga-type lithologies in the upper one-half of the unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5. The Rogersville Shale thins to less than four feet in the northeastern part of the study and the Rutledge and Maryville formations merge to form Honaker Dolomite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. The Bradley Creek Limestone Member of the Nolichucky Formation thickens to the southeast of the Carter Valley strike belt. The Bradley Creek Member may be a northward extending tongue (lithostrome) of the Maryville Limestone which occurs south of the Pulaski fault.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1601</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2985&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1601</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2985</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-08T13:17:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4118088</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1601</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George D. Swingle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Russell J. Lewis, Lawrence T. Larson, Harry J. Klepser</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>