<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Corelation between process parameters and Demique® nonwoven web properties</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Dahiya</lname>
<fname>Atul</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Polyetherester, a thermoplastic elastomer, characterized by high elongation and good mechanical properties, has been made into melt blown multi-layer nonwovens using a patented technology developed at Kimberly-Clark. The resulting fabric, Demique®, was targeted for end-uses in the medical and athletic fields. Properties include high impact strength and minimum loss of flexibility at low temperatures, as well as the ability to perform well at elevated temperatures. The objective of this research is to investigate the effects of melt blowing process parameters on properties of single layer nonwoven webs, with the purpose of determining applications as bandaging materials. The polyether ester Amitel® EM400 was processed on a 20-inch melt blowing line into a nonwoven web. Processing conditions included: two die temperatures (249 and 260°C), two die-to-collector distances (DCD) (8 and 16 inches), two throughputs (0.4 and 0.6 grams/hole/minute), and two collector speeds (5 and 10 fpm). These parameters were selected based upon preliminary rheological experiments and processing trials, and represent the range of feasible parameters based on the polymer and the equipment available. Also, these parameters are the important processing variables controlling the end use properties of the nonwoven products made by melt blowing processes. Air permeability was observed highest for high DCD, high collector speeds, low throughput and low die temperature. Tear strength along machine direction was observed highest for high DCD, low throughput and low die temperature, whereas along cross direction it was highest for high DCD and low collector speed. Peak elongation along machine direction was highest for high die temperature and low DCD, whereas along cross direction it was highest for high die temperature, high DCD and low throughput. Peak force along machine direction was highest for high throughput and low DCD, whereas along cross direction it was highest for high die temperature, low DCD and low collector speed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5210</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6618&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5210</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6618</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847049</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5210</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Billie J. Collier</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Textiles, Retail, and Consumer Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>