<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Helping Cities for Half a Century: A History of the Municipal Technical Advisory Service, 1949-1999</title>
<publication-date>1999-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</institution>
<lname>Parkinson</lname>
<fname>Rob</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>municipal technical advisory service</keyword>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>history</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This history of the Municipal Technical Advisory Service looks to examine several aspects of the organization’s first 50 years; more specifically in several areas: the historical context out of which MTAS operated, the bureaucratic or structural changes that have come over 50 years, the people who shaped and breathed life into the organization, and the specific issues and problems MTAS consultants were called on to help Tennessee cities with. These topics fit together to give the reader a larger view of what the Municipal Technical Advisory Service has accomplished since 1949 and what the future holds for the next 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtashist/18</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;amp;context=utk_mtashist&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1017</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-01T07:24:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS History</publication-title>
<context-key>4091799</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtashist/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1999-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>