<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Exploratory Study of Varying Phenotypes of Posttraumatic Stress  Among a Comorbid Substance Misuse Population</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ddonahu7@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Donahue</lname>
<fname>Dennis</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cognitive</keyword>
<keyword>adrenergic</keyword>
<keyword>posttraumatic distress</keyword>
<keyword>drug-of-choice</keyword>
<keyword>substance misuse</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective: &lt;/strong&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore differences in presentation of posttraumatic distress (PTD) that may represent different phenotypes, such as a possible cognitively-driven variant, in addition to those rooted in the prevailing conditioned-fear model. In conjunction, links to substance misuse and a purposeful selection bias for specific drugs-of-choice (DoC) based on phenotype variation were examined. &lt;strong&gt;Method: &lt;/strong&gt;A convenience sample of inpatients in residential treatment for substance misuse who also endorsed posttraumatic distress following at least one previous traumatic experience (&lt;em&gt;N &lt;/em&gt;= 177) completed self-report assessments and an in-person direct inquiry. &lt;strong&gt;Results: &lt;/strong&gt;Hierarchical cluster analysis and ANOVA results partially supported our hypotheses and provided some evidence of a cognitive-focused phenotype, as well as a possible image/adrenergic-based phenotype. Subsequently, multinomial logistic regression determined that the hypothesized phenotypes were significantly linked to DoC selection, specifically (a) cognitive-focused phenotype predicted primary alcohol/benzodiazepine use (b) image/adrenergic-based phenotype predicted cannabinoid/opiate use, and (c) a traditional “mixed” PTD presentation predicted polysubstance use. &lt;strong&gt;Conclusions: &lt;/strong&gt;Findings from this exploratory study offer additional validation to calls for continued examination of varying phenotypes, as well as a cognitively-driven model, of PTD additional to those based in conditioned-fear. Additionally, evidence was shown for a purpose-driven theory of substance misuse, hallmarked by an underlying maladaptive drive to select a DoC with the capacity to alleviate specific symptomatology (e.g., heavy alcohol use to alleviate excessive rumination and sleep disturbance).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6068</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7120&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6068</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7120</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T08:12:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>18901376</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6068</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gina P. Owens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Erin E. Hardin, Jennifer A. Morrow, Dawn M. Szymanski</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>