<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluating the Relationship between Ultrasound-derived  Carcass Characteristics and Production Traits in Angus Cattle</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mayfield@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Mayfield</lname>
<fname>William Michael</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>carcass</keyword>
<keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
<keyword>ribeye area</keyword>
<keyword>intramuscular fat</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Profitability in the beef industry is a crucial aspect of management schemes.  The overall aim of this study was to determine if carcass ultrasonography in replacement heifers could explain variation in traits such as reproduction, a major factor in beef cattle efficiency and profitability.  During a 10-year period, data were obtained from 906 yearling heifers through the use of carcass ultrasonography.  The measurements collected included adjusted values for ribeye area (REA), percent intramuscular fat (%IMF), rib fat (RF), and rump fat.  A retrospective analysis was performed on data collected and variables were separated into the extreme high and low 25% and the median 50%.  Analysis examined whether a relationship existed between reproductive traits (percentage calving at two years of age, age at first calving, first calving interval, lifetime calving interval) and carcass measurements determined by ultrasonography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Age at first calving increased as ribeye area increased (Low REA 731.7±3.1 d; High REA 743.5±3.3 d; P=0.002).  Rib fat was also related to age at first calving as heifers in the high grouping were approximately 9 days older at calving (Low RF, 734.5±3.1 d; High RF, 743.7±3.2 d; P=0.008).  Expected progeny differences (EPD) for carcass traits such as REA also indicated differences between all three groups for age at first calving (Low REA EPD, 727.4±3.1 d; Med, 736.3±3.2 d; High, 746.2±3.2 d; P&lt;0.0001).  Observation of marbling EPD’s resulted in a difference of 10 days for age at first calving between the high and low groups (Low MARB EPD, 734.4±3.1 d; High, 744.0±3.2 d; P=0.002).  Interval from first to second calving (Low RF, 374.3±3.2 d; High RF, 361.7±3.5 d; P=0.014) and average lifetime calving interval (Low RF, 369.9±1.8 d; High RF, 362.8±2.1d; P=0.048) were both correlated with adjusted rib fat.  Evaluation of longevity (birth date to date of last calving) established that heifers with a higher carcass EPD for REA remained in the herd for an additional 7.2 months (Low REA EPD, 39.8±4.2 mo.; High REA EPD, 47.0±4.2 mo.; P=0.023).  Ultrasonography-derived carcass measurements and calculated carcass EPDs may be used as potential tools to predict reproductive soundness of a replacement heifer before being retained in the herd.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1300</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2412&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1300</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2412</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-05-31T06:13:27-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2412/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2924456</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1300</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Neal Schrick</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Fred Hopkins, Dr. Justin Rhinehart</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;William M. Mayfield&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulaski, TN&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>