<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Protective Coating of Titanium Diboride Reinforcement Particulates for Improvement of Titanium Metal Matrix Composite Armor Systems</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rpack2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pack</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Cody</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>functionally graded armor composite</keyword>
<keyword>titanium metal matrix composite</keyword>
<keyword>composite armor</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Titanium and titanium diboride (TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) are two materials that have attracted interest for application in armor systems. Titanium exhibits a high strength-to-weight ratio and good corrosion resistance while TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; exhibits high hardness and stiffness. Combining these into a titanium metal matrix composite would allow the superior ballistic properties to be taken advantage of in one composite material and lead to an improved armor system. The main obstacle behind doing so is the detrimental in situ reaction during processing between the Ti matrix and the TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reinforcing particles that converts TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into TiB. It was hypothesized that a protective coating on the TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; particulates would protect and prevent the in situ reaction. Two protective designs were investigated: depositing a carbon layer on the particle surface and also nitrogenizing the particle surface to create a boron nitride (BN) coating. TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; particulates were coated using fluidized bed chemical vapor deposition. Powders were blended and then produced either by pressing and firing or by hot pressing. Three separate experiments were performed: variable time, variable temperature, and hot pressing experiments. Samples were characterized using X-ray diffraction and microscopy focusing on phase identification and the coating’s effectiveness in preventing TiB formation. Impact testing using half-size charpy bars cut from the hot pressed plate samples also allowed investigation of impact behavior. The nitrogenizing of the particle surface was shown to be unsuccessful in preventing the conversion of TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into TiB. Reaction between the Ti matrix and TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; readily occurs if the particles are not coated. The carbon coating was proven successful in preventing the conversion of TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; particles into TiB up to dwell times of 2 h at 1370 °C while also providing complete protection in a sample hot pressed at 1200°C. The carbon coating design presented was proven successful through a range of processing conditions in preventing the in situ conversion of TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into TiB providing a route to produce a metal matrix composite wherein the TiB&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; reinforcing particles remain intact and unconverted after processing. This material could lead to the production of an improved armor system.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3167</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4176&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3167</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4176</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-29T11:12:40-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4176/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5839182</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3167</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Claudia J. Rawn</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George M. Pharr, Hahn Choo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>