<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Stark-Effect Modulator for CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Laser Free-Space Communications</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Holloman</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>Lane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A Stark-effect modulator prototype has been designed and constructed to transmit an RF signal upon an infrared carrier wave produced by a CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; laser. The anticipated future use of this prototype will be to integrate it into an all-weather long-wavelength infrared (LWIR) free-space communication link. This communication system is expected to be capable of operation at 2.5 Gbits/sec over a range of &gt;6 kilometers. The Stark-effect modulator prototype is ideal to replace existing microwave and radio communication links used currently. Also, the Stark-effect modulator is a better choice than electro-optic crystal modulators and acousto-optic Bragg cell modulators because it operates at higher frequencies and is less costly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stark-effect occurs when an electric field is applied to a gas molecule that has a substantial polarizability. The electric field changes the spacing of the gas molecule energy levels. The gas molecule used is deuterated ammonia (NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D) because it has a molecular absorption resonance near the 10.59 micron wavelength line of the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; laser emission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modulator is a dielectric waveguide that is constructed of borosilicate glass, measuring 36-cm in length and having an inner diameter of 1.8-mm and an outer diameter of 3-mm. The modulator has been characterized successfully, with an experimental result agreeing with a predicted model. For the first time, an RF signal has been successfully applied to the Stark-effect modulator and successfully transmitted and detected by a nearby receiver.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2004</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3364&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2004</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3364</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T12:47:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4641065</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2004</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stuart Elston</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Donald Hutchinson, Robert Compton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>