<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evidence for an abrupt latest Miocene-earliest Pliocene climate shift preserved in a sinkhole paleolake at the Gray Fossil Site, northeastern Tennessee (Washington County)</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Shunk</lname>
<fname>Aaron</fname>
<mname>Jacob</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Records of Neogene terrestrial climate are rare for the eastern half of North America. The recently discovered Gray Fossil Site (GFS) in northeastern Tennessee (Washington County) appears to be a sinkhole paleolake that preserves such a record. Well-preserved vertebrate GFS fossils strongly suggest a Late Miocene-Early Pliocene (Hemphillian) Land Mammal Age (2:. 4.5 Ma). Three distinct facies occur within the upper 20 m of GFS lacustrine sediment. The graded facies is characterized by continuous succession of individual graded beds that average 0.8 cm thick. This facies contains &lt; I% total organic carbon (TOC), has carbon isotope composition (613C V-PDB) averaging-25.4%0 with values as positive as -24.3%o, and is interpreted to represent deposition from sporadic storm events in a water-stressed ecosystem. The laminated facies overlies the graded facies. The transition between the two facies is marked by: I) the development of a depositional pattern that grades into the laminated facies, 2) an abrupt increase from &lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5295</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6703&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5295</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6703</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847219</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5295</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven G. Driese</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>