<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>War of words: Framing of the United States in Selected Belarusian newspapers in 2009</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nmanayev@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Manayeva</lname>
<fname>Natalie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Anti-Americanism</keyword>
<keyword>Framing</keyword>
<keyword>Media Influence</keyword>
<keyword>Authoritarian press</keyword>
<keyword>Belarus</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Comparative Politics</discipline>
<discipline>Eastern European Studies</discipline>
<discipline>International and Intercultural Communication</discipline>
<discipline>International Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Journalism Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Mass Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Other Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Social Influence and Political Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Soviet and Post-Soviet Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the peculiarities of framing of the United  States in selected Belarusian newspapers during first six  months of the Obama  administration.   The concepts of anti-Americanism, authoritarian model of mass media  and framing were chosen as a theoretical framework. This study was focused on the two  main questions: first, what is the difference in how Belarusian state-run and independent  newspapers frame the U.S., and second, what is the mechanism of creating negative image  of the U.S. in Belarusian newspapers. In order to provide comprehensive answers to both  questions the multi-method approach (involving methods of content and framing analysis)  was chosen. As this study demonstrated, the state-run and independent newspapers present  a very different image of the U.S.: state-run newspapers present the U.S. within a scope of  strong negative frames. However, the picture in the independent newspapers is the  opposite: out of four general frames three were positive and one was neutral-positive. The  results of the content analysis showed that  negative images  of the United States  do  not  necessarily have to be promoted through direct judgmental statements, but could rather be  initiated by means of selecting certain negative facts for publication, often from  unidentified sources. By concentrating their attention on crime, natural catastrophes,  manipulating statistical data, omitting sources of information and selecting foreign experts  who are critically inclined against the U.S media  create a negative  image of the United  States.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/729</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1825&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>729</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1825</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-06T08:04:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1428614</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/729</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Peter Gross</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Michael R. Fitzgerald,  Dr. Dwight L. Teeter Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>