<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a smart bio-diagnostic platform for point-of-care detection by multiplexed electrokinetic sensing</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>roueslat@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Oueslati</lname>
<fname>Rania</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Microelectronics</keyword>
<keyword>Biosensor</keyword>
<keyword>Lab-on-chip</keyword>
<keyword>Embedded System</keyword>
<keyword>Nano-biotechnology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Pathogenic infections, foodborne illnesses and drug abuse pose significant public health issues worldwide, and  they  are  of  special  concern  in  developing  countries,  where  the  medical resources and public hygiene are limited.  Therefore, rapid detection and identification of these pathogens are of paramount importance for adopting treatment options and to establish adequate control measures.   The detection and identification of pathogen microorganisms still rely on complex methods, which maybe not be suitable for on-site monitoring.  Therefore, a great research  challenge  in  this  field  is  focused  on  the  development of rapid,  reliable,  specific, and sensitive methods to detect these bacteria at low cost.  Moreover, the bio-chip development for large scale screening analysis implies improved miniaturization, reduction of analysis time and cost, and multianalyte detection. In addition, simultaneous monitoring of multiple molecular interactions and multiplexed detection of several diagnostic biomarkers at very low concentrations have become important issues in advanced biological and chemical sensing. This  work  presents  the  design  of  a  portable  system  for  sensitive  and  quantitative detection  of  DNA  and  drug  biomarkers  which  will  be  highly  valuable  in  controlling  and preventing  disease  outbreaks.    First, this work investigates the development of assay protocols for highly sensitive and selective on-site detection of Drugs and bacterial DNA. This is an improvement over the priorily developed AC electrokinetics-based capacitive sensing, which is capable of detecting specific target in a point-of-care setting using micro-fabricated interdigitated electrodes.    Second,  this  work  presents  the  development  of  a  smart  bio-diagnostic  platform  for  point  of  care  detection  to  interface  with  capacitive  electrokinetic electrodes for a multiplexed sensing.  The  circuit  has  shown good  accuracy  on  various  test  devices. In association with the ACEK capacitive sensing, preliminary data are collected and successfully used to characterize physiological samples (10μl).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5705</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7471&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5705</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7471</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419559</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5705</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jayne Wu Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Benjamin J Blalock Dr., Gong Gu Dr., Anming Hu Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/Rania Oueslati</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>