<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The role of financial institutions in urban policies in Sub-Saharan Africa : the case of Senegal</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Kamiya</lname>
<fname>Hakizimana</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Over the past three decades, International Financial Institutions have participated constantly in urban policy making of most Sub-Saharan African countries. This intervention began in the 1970s when Sub-Saharan countries experiencing social, economic and political strains as result of dramatic change in their population trends called for the intervention of international agencies and donor countries. For many, the rapid urbanization of Sub-Saharan countries needed to be dealt with adequate urban policies in order to maintain a sustainable development.                                                                                                                                                      This thesis&#39;s objective is to assess how policies promoted by international agencies have impacted on urban development by using the case of Senegal, which is considered as landmark in urban development projects and provide recommendations for future urban development. In order to reach its objectives, this thesis explores urban policies that were implemented prior to IFis intervention in urban development of SubSaharan African countries. It analyzes each phase of urban policies sponsored by IFis, from the sites-and-services to urban policies that aim to enhance urban productivity. Indeed, it draws conclusions and gives recommendations for future urban development of the region.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5942</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7575&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5942</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7575</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467602</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5942</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cecilia Zanetta</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James A. Spencer, Bruce E. Tonn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Planning</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>