<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Entry-Level Instruction: High-Frequency Vocabulary and Classroom Interaction in German Textbooks</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>agrave17@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Graves</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>textbook analysis</keyword>
<keyword>teaching</keyword>
<keyword>high-frequency vocabulary</keyword>
<keyword>classroom interaction</keyword>
<keyword>foreign language</keyword>
<keyword>world language</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In elementary second language teaching, it can be difficult to decide which language materials to cover. Drawing from the insights of High-Frequency Vocabulary, Classroom Interaction, and teaching methodologies such as Communicative Language Teaching and CREED, I wish to suggest moving toward criteria for elementary language teaching that takes into account the current research as it relates to high-frequency vocabulary, the development of communicative skills in face-to-face interaction, and the more common customs of interaction as informed by the field of pragmatics.  My main argument is that we should move toward writing textbooks which emphasize high-frequency terms which are relevant to the classroom and circumlocution skills in lower-division language instruction. To that end, I first review current literature on the topics of high-frequency vocabulary, then I move onto classroom interaction, then I make connections to task-based instruction, and their effectiveness in the first two years of undergrad German language courses; finally I perform an analysis of three introductory chapters in common entry-level textbooks of German: Treffpunkt, Deutsch, Na Klar! and Sag Mal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5561</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7095&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5561</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7095</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T08:30:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>20409602</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5561</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thorsten Huth</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stephanie Ohnesorg, Maria Stehle, Bernard Issa</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>German</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>