<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SP693-Evaluate Your Beef Cattle-Handling Facilities</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-20T11:18:02-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Livestock</keyword>
<keyword>Cattle</keyword>
<keyword>Facilities</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;One of the keys to maximizing returns from a commercial cow-calf enterprise is the timely application of basic management practices. Many of these practices require that the cattle be worked several times a year. Without adequate cattle-handling facilities, these practices are either delayed or completely neglected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producers desiring to upgrade current facilities or construct or purchase new facilities may apply for a cost-share through the Tennessee Agricultural Enhancement Program administered by the Tennessee Department of Agriculture. Premise identification and Beef Quality Assurance certification are prerequisites for applying for the funds. Approval of the request must be received before items are purchased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the practices that require handling facilities for animal restraint include castration, dehorning, deworming, implanting, grub treatment, lice treatment, vaccinations, pregnancy checking, artificial insemination, application of fly tags and first aid. The result of failing to carry out these basic, economically essential cattle management practices is reduced production efficiency and reduced financial return to the cattle enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An efficient cattle-handling facility includes several critical factors. Below is a group of questions about items that contribute to an efficient beef cattle-handling system. Read and answer the questions to evaluate your system. Following each question is a value for each reply. Record the score on the line to the right of each question.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexani/45</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;amp;context=utk_agexani&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>45</label>
<document-type>beeftaep</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1044</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-20T11:17:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Animals/Livestock</publication-title>
<context-key>1281218</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexani/45</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>SP693 R05-4105-080-024-07 07-0124</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>