<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;Rapping About Authenticity&quot;: Exploring the Differences in Perceptions of &quot;Authenticity&quot; in Rap Music by Consumers.&quot;</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jwrigh12@utk.edu</email>
<institution>UTK</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Music</keyword>
<keyword>rap</keyword>
<keyword>hip hop</keyword>
<keyword>identity</keyword>
<keyword>culture</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Critical and Cultural Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Ethnomusicology</discipline>
<discipline>Social Psychology and Interaction</discipline>
<discipline>Sociology of Culture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Historically, social scientists have not only marginalized rap music as a viable unit of scholarly analysis, but failed at attempts to understand the thoughts and actions of rap music consumers. This study analyzes the connection between rap music’s (and the artists’) authenticity and how those perceptions of authenticity affect music consumers’ decision making process, thus providing a possible explanation as to why music fans purchase rap music.  The goal of this research was to see if the reasons rap music fans provide explaining the rationale behind their purchases match the images and perceptions presumably held by the general public about rap music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A snowball sample was used to survey a total of 30 rap music “experts.”  The findings from this study indicate the concept of authenticity is very important in validating not only rap music, but rap artist, rap music fans, and hip hop culture as a whole. The findings from this study provide empirical evidence supporting the importance of authenticity as a construct and the use of rap music as a unit of scholarly research analysis. By justifying the importance of authenticity to rap music and hip hop culture, this research proposes that authenticity may well be used as a means to maintain existing relationships with a fan-base and as a marketing tool used by record companies to attract new fans and generate album sales.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/760</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1041&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>760</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1041</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-12-17T14:10:25-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1092811</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/760</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Suzaanne B. Kurth</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert Emmet Jones; Hoan Bui; Debora Baldwin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>