<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Neutron Scattering Studies on Magnetism and Phonon in the Electron-doped Nd2-xCexCuO4 and Pr1-xLaCexCuO4</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kang</lname>
<fname>Hye</fname>
<mname>Jung</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We present comprehensive neutron scattering studies on the electron-doped superconductors Nd&lt;sub&gt;2-x&lt;/sub&gt;Ce&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and Pr&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;LaCe&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; to understand how magnetic properties and phonon are related to superconductivity. For the superconducting Nd&lt;sub&gt;1.85&lt;/sub&gt;Ce&lt;sub&gt;0.15&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;-axis magnetic field enhances the commensurate antiferromagnetic order, while an &lt;em&gt;ab&lt;/em&gt;-plane magnetic field induces spin-flop transition from the noncollinear to the collinear magnetic structure. The &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;-axis field-induced effect is absent in both the parent Nd&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and the as-grown nonsuperconducting Nd&lt;sub&gt;1.85&lt;/sub&gt;Ce&lt;sub&gt;0.15&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; samples. These results, combined with those on the hole-doped La&lt;sub&gt;2-x&lt;/sub&gt;Sr&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; suggest that antiferromagnetism competes with superconductivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Pr&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;LaCe&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; system, we find that quasi-2 dimensional commensurate antiferromagnetism coexists with superconductivity and 3 dimensional antiferromagnetism in the underdoped region. To determine whether the antiferromagnetic order is the competing order in high temperature superconductors, regardless of hole-doping or electron-doping, we performed field-induced experiments on the electron-doped superconductor Pr&lt;sub&gt;0.88&lt;/sub&gt;LaCe&lt;sub&gt;0.12&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4±δ&lt;/sub&gt; by applying magnetic fields along the &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;-direction and in the &lt;em&gt;ab&lt;/em&gt;-plane direction. The anisotropy of the field-induced moment demonstrates the competing nature of these two order parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inelastic neutron scattering has been performed to study the generalized phonon density of states (GDOS) of electron-doped Nd&lt;sub&gt;2-x&lt;/sub&gt;Ce&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;CuO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; with various levels of doping. Upon doping, the softening of phonon around 70 meV has been observed. However, most of the softening occurs within a few percent of Ce doping, and it is not related to the doping induced nonsuperconducting-superconducting transition.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2140</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3591&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2140</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3591</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T11:32:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4663759</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2140</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Pengcheng Dai</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Janice L. Musfeldt, James R. Thompson, Victor Barzykin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>