<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mathematical modeling of T cell clustering following malaria infection in mice</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rkelemen@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kelemen</lname>
<fname>Reka</fname>
<mname>Katalin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>malaria</keyword>
<keyword>immune system</keyword>
<keyword>T cells</keyword>
<keyword>search</keyword>
<keyword>mathematical modeling</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Immunology of Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Ordinary Differential Equations and Applied Dynamics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Malaria is the result of the immune system&#39;s unsuccessful clearance of hepatocytes (liver cells) infected by the eukaryotic pathogen of the Plasmodium genus. It has been shown that CD8 T cells are required and sufficient for protective immunity against malaria in mice [29, 36], but the mechanisms by which they find and eliminate infected hepatocytes are not known yet. Recently we reported the formation of CD8 T cell clusters consisting of up to 25 cells around infected cells [8]. Our mathematical modeling and data analysis revealed that malaria-specific T cells likely recruit each other and also non-malaria-specific T cells to infected hepatocytes in a process that is G-protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) dependent. Evidence exists for variable T-cell extrinsic factors in explaining the large variation of cluster sizes around infected cells, for which we propose further experiments to discriminate between T-cell-dependent and -independent mechanisms in cluster formation. Our results suggest that CD8 T cells specific to an ongoing infection tend to cluster around infected cells and their presence also enhances irrelevant CD8 T cells&#39; propensity to clustering. However, analysis of T cell movement tracks shows that irrelevant T cells have a significantly lower average frequency of movements towards the parasite than antigen-specific T cells. Since clusters of CD8 T cells might be more efficient at killing infected cells than a CD8 T cell alone, understanding the requirements for large T cell clusters might have important implications in the fields of immunology and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2728</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4020&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2728</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4020</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-28T18:52:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5241783</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2728</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vitaly V. Ganusov</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nathan W. Schmidt, Michael A. Gilchrist, Arnold Saxton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>