<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of Instructional Practices of Teachers of Small Classes at Various Grade Levels</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fickley</lname>
<fname>Edward</fname>
<mname>William</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study investigated the instructional practices of first and third grade teachers of small classes that were part of the Academy program established by an East Tennessee metropolitan school district for at-risk students.  Each Academy limited class size to 15.  Specifically, this study sought to understand what instructional practices Academy teachers used with their small classes, what differences or similarities existed between first and third grade teachers’ instructional practices, and what were the Academy teachers’ perceptions of how their instructional practices changed from prior experience with larger classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study employed a descriptive, collective case study design, and data were collected through non-participant observations and partially-structured, teacher interviews.  Three 30-minute observations of each of the 10 Academy teachers were conducted over several months.  Durations were recorded for the following teacher practices: direct instruction, independent seatwork, drill and practice, teacher-led question and answer, individual tutoring, cooperative learning, and inquiry-based methods.  After each observation was completed, the teacher was ranked based on a five 5 point Likert scale with 5 = extensively, 4 = frequently, 3 = occasionally, 2 = rarely, and 1 = not observed for the following instructional strategies: use of manipulatives, integration of learning centers, use of differentiated instruction, promotion of student engagement, and individual contact with students.  The observations were followed up with recorded partially-structured, teacher interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researcher concluded that Academy teachers predominately use the teacher-centered practices of direct instruction and independent seatwork with their small classes.  Teachers frequently promoted student engagement and made individual contact with students, and to a lesser extent, they integrated student-centered activities through manipulatives and learning centers.  There were no major differences between first and third grade teachers in regard to their instructional practices.  Teachers perceived that small classes strengthen the instructional practices they commonly used with larger classes.  Academy teachers believed that small classes promote the integration of manipulatives and learning centers, allow for easier evaluation of student progress, and provide additional time for re-teaching and review.  Additional findings of this study suggest that small classes create a unique, family-like atmosphere that enhances instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4550</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6249&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4550</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6249</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-31T10:12:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10691057</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4550</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Theodore W. Hipple</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Jane Connelly, Russell L. French, John R. Ray</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Instructional Technology and Educational Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>