<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Investigation of the Interaction of d-Amphetamine and Amantadine Hydrochloride Using Repeated Acquisitions with Serial Reversal Discriminations</title>
<publication-date>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
<mname>Dozier</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this series of studies was to investigate the interaction of d-amphetamine and amantadine hydrochloride employing serial discrimination reversals with repeated acquisitions.  Specifically, the blockade of the effects of d-amphetamine by amantadine hydrochloride was investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In meeting this goal, dose-response curves were determined independently for d-amphetamine and amantadine hydrochloride.  The dose-response curve for d-amphetamine indicated that the 0.5 mg/kg dosage provided for optimal discrimination of SDR, while dosages of 1.0 mg/kg and 2.0 mg/kg proved to be disruptive.  The experiments investigating amantadine hydrochloride indicated that dosages above 10 mg/kg were detrimental to the discrimination task, while dosages below 10 mg/kg seemed to have negligible effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis of the final experiment, in which amantadine hydrochloride was given as a pretreatment 90 minutes before d-amphetamine treatment, indicated that amantadine hydrochloride did not block the effects of d-amphetamine on learning.  Rather, the interaction of the two drugs appears to be synergistic in nature rather than inhibitory.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3091</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4576&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3091</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4576</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-22T20:08:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6487384</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3091</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William H. Calhoun</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Joel Lubar, Schuyler Huck, Robert Wahler, &amp; Ohmer Milton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>