<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rhizospheric mycobiota associated with &lt;em&gt;Populus deltoides&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2012-04-14T09:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Bonito</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</institution>
<lname>Schadt</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Hameed</lname>
<fname>Khalid</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</institution>
<lname>Shakya</lname>
<fname>Migun</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Ko-Hsuan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</institution>
<lname>Tuskan</lname>
<fname>Gerald</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Vilgalys</lname>
<fname>Rytas</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Populus deltoides&lt;/em&gt; is a common riparian tree species in southeastern North America. &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt; forms root associations with arbuscular, ectomycorrhizal, and endophytic fungi. To elucidate the structure of rhizospheric fungal assemblages on &lt;em&gt;Populus deltoides&lt;/em&gt; we carried out a series of field campaigns in natural &lt;em&gt;P. deltoides&lt;/em&gt; populations in NC and TN. Field studies were coupled with trap-plant experiments using cuttings of &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt;. Fungal root communities were characterized through 454 amplicon pyrosequencing. Efforts were also made to culture fungi from &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt; roots and characterize the arbuscular mycorrhizal community through spore studies. Our results indicate that in addition to hosting mycorrhizal taxa, &lt;em&gt;P. deltoides&lt;/em&gt; supports a high diversity of fungal root endophytes. In fact, endophytic fungi accounted for the majority of sequences in field and trap-plant samples, and pure culture isolates from roots. There was considerable overlap between datasets. Well represented were ascomycete taxa belonging to the &lt;em&gt;Hypocreales&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chaetothyriales&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pleosporales&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Heliotiales&lt;/em&gt;, and basidiomycete taxa belonging to the &lt;em&gt;Agaricales&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polyporales&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Atractiellales&lt;/em&gt;. Spore and molecular data indicate that &lt;em&gt;Glomerales&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Paraglomales&lt;/em&gt; are the main arbuscular mycorrhizal associates of &lt;em&gt;P. deltoides&lt;/em&gt;. Although fruitbodies of ectomycorrhizal taxa were uncommon in the field, a new truffle species was collected under &lt;em&gt;P. deltoides&lt;/em&gt; in TN and NC field sites and has been described (&lt;em&gt;Tuber mexiusanum&lt;/em&gt;). Additionally, fruitbodies of &lt;em&gt;Laccaria&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cortinarius&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Geopora&lt;/em&gt; spp. were produced in our trap-plant experiments. Other ectomycorrhizal taxa recovered in our molecular surveys included &lt;em&gt;Inocybe&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hebeloma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Thelephora&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Russula&lt;/em&gt; spp. Pure cultures of Laccaria and Thelephora spp. have been established.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/masmc2012/2012/April14/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=masmc2012&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-07-05T10:49:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Middle Atlantic States Mycological Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3057465</context-key>
<submission-path>masmc2012/2012/April14/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:20:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Toyota Auditorium, Howard H. Baker Jr. Center for Public Policy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T09:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>