<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;Take my hand, help me out:&quot;  Mental health recipients&#39; experience of the therapeutic relationship</title>
<publication-date>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Shattell</lname>
<fname>M.M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Starr</lname>
<fname>S.S.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>sthomas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Refereed Journal Articles</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>nurse-patient relationship</keyword>
<keyword>phenomenology</keyword>
<keyword>qualitative methods</keyword>
<keyword>therapeutic relationship</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to describe mental health service recipients&#39; experience of the therapeutic relationship. The research question was ‘what is therapeutic about the therapeutic relationship?’ This study was a secondary analysis of qualitative interviews conducted with persons with mental illness as part of a study of the experience of being understood. This secondary analysis used data from 20 interviews with community-dwelling adults with mental illness, who were asked to talk about the experience of being understood by a health-care provider. Data were analysed using an existential phenomenological approach. Individuals experienced therapeutic relationships against a backdrop of challenges, including mental illness, domestic violence, substance abuse, and homelessness. They had therapeutic relationships with nurses (psychiatric/mental health nurses and dialysis nurses), physicians (psychiatrists and general practitioners), psychologists, social workers, and counsellors. Experiences of the therapeutic relationship were expressed in three figural themes, titled using participants&#39; own words: ‘relate to me’, ‘know me as a person’, and ‘get to the solution’. The ways in which these participants described therapeutic relationships challenge some long-held beliefs, such as the use of touch, self-disclosure, and blunt feedback. A therapeutic relationship for persons with mental illness requires in-depth personal knowledge, which is acquired only with time, understanding, and skill. Knowing the whole person, rather than knowing the person only as a service recipient, is key for practising nurses and nurse educators interested in enhancing the therapeutic potential of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>274</fpage>
<lpage>284</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/92</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1107&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>92</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1107</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-10T10:53:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1473186</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/92</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Shattell, M.M., Starr, S.S., &amp; Thomas, S.P. (2007). “Take my hand, help me out:”  Mental health service recipients’ experience of the therapeutic relationship. &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Mental Health Nursing&lt;/em&gt;, 16. 274-284.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>International Journal of Mental Health Nursing</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>