<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Missing Women of the Beowulf-Manuscript</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>thooper@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hooper</lname>
<fname>Teresa Marie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Old English Literature</keyword>
<keyword>Beowulf</keyword>
<keyword>Nowell Codex</keyword>
<keyword>Saint Christopher legend</keyword>
<keyword>Wonders of the East</keyword>
<keyword>Letter of Alexander to Aristotle</keyword>
<keyword>Judith</keyword>
<keyword>manuscript studies</keyword>
<keyword>London BL Cotton Vitellius A.xv</keyword>
<keyword>women&#39;s representation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Literature in English, British Isles</discipline>
<discipline>Medieval Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In their introduction to &lt;em&gt;New Readings on Women in Old English Literature&lt;/em&gt;, Helen Damico and Alexandra Hennessey Olsen noted that previous work on Old English texts such as &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; were skewed towards male experience,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;and they called for a corrective turn towards women’s experiences in Old English scholarship to create a richer perspective on the literature. Many useful studies of &lt;em&gt;Beowulf &lt;/em&gt;have since answered their call, but comparable studies on the &lt;em&gt;Beowulf-&lt;/em&gt;Manuscript as a whole (London, British Library, Cotton Vitellius A.xv part 2) have been slow to arrive because of the physical state of the manuscript. Both&lt;em&gt; The Passion of Saint Christopher&lt;/em&gt; and the poem &lt;em&gt;Judith &lt;/em&gt;are missing quires which prominently featured the deeds of women. Highlighting women’s experiences in this manuscript, therefore, also requires reconstructing their presence in the physical evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the manuscript evidence, &lt;em&gt;The Passion of Saint Christopher &lt;/em&gt;would have also contained an account of the martyrs Nicaea and Aquilina in the four folios immediately preceding fol. 94r. This chapter therefore uses their story as a theoretical lens for the rest of the &lt;em&gt;Beowulf &lt;/em&gt;manuscript, which will highlight the important roles women play as cultural, religious and symbolic mediators, as well as examples of how one should properly respond to the marvelous. Nicaea and Aquilina&#39;s and role in the manuscript context of the English Christopher legend also opens up the tantalizing possibility of female readership for &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_englpubs/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1017&amp;amp;context=utk_englpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>bookchap</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1017</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-20T18:10:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>English Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16287037</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_englpubs/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Hooper, Teresa. &quot;The Missing Women of the Beowulf Manuscript.&quot; 161-75 in New Readings on Women and Early Medieval English Literature and Culture: Cross-Disciplinary Studies in Honour of Helen Damico. Leeds: Arc Humanities Press, 2019.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>DOI: 10.2307/j.ctvs32tc6.15</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>New Readings on Women and Early Medieval English and Culture: Cross-Disciplinary Studies in Honour of Helen Damico</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>