<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Positive Darwinian selection is a driving force for the diversification of terpenoid biosynthesis in the genus Oryza</title>
<publication-date>2014-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Hao</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Guanglin</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology</institution>
<lname>Köllner</lname>
<fname>Tobias</fname>
<mname>G</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jia</lname>
<fname>Qidong</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology</institution>
<lname>Gershenzon</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>fengc@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Feng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Plant secondary metabolism</keyword>
<keyword>Terpene synthase</keyword>
<keyword>Positive selection</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: Terpenoids constitute the largest class of secondary metabolites made by plants and display vast chemical diversity among and within species. Terpene synthases (TPSs) are the pivotal enzymes for terpenoid biosynthesis that create the basic carbon skeletons of this class. Functional divergence of paralogous and orthologous &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes is a major mechanism for the diversification of terpenoid biosynthesis. However, little is known about the evolutionary forces that have shaped the evolution of plant &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes leading to terpenoid diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: The orthologs of &lt;em&gt;Oryza Terpene Synthase 1&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;OryzaTPS1&lt;/em&gt;), a rice terpene synthase gene involved in indirect defense against insects in &lt;em&gt;Oryza sativa&lt;/em&gt;, were cloned from six additional &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; species. &lt;em&gt;In vitro&lt;/em&gt; biochemical analysis showed that the enzymes encoded by these &lt;em&gt;OryzaTPS1&lt;/em&gt; genes functioned either as (&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;)-β-caryophyllene synthases (ECS), or (&lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;)-β-caryophyllene &amp; germacrene A synthases (EGS), or germacrene D &amp; germacrene A synthases (DAS). Because the orthologs of OryzaTPS1 in maize and sorghum function as ECS, the ECS activity was inferred to be ancestral. Molecular evolutionary detected the signature of positive Darwinian selection in five codon substitutions in the evolution from ECS to DAS. Homology-based structure modeling and the biochemical analysis of laboratory-generated protein variants validated the contribution of the five positively selected sites to functional divergence of OryzaTPS1. The changes in the &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; product spectra of OryzaTPS1 proteins also correlated closely to the changes in &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;blends of volatile terpenes released from insect-damaged rice plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;: In this study, we found that positive Darwinian selection is a driving force for the functional divergence of OryzaTPS1. This finding suggests that the diverged sesquiterpene blend produced by the &lt;em&gt;Oryza&lt;/em&gt; species containing &lt;em&gt;DAS&lt;/em&gt;may be adaptive, likely in the attraction of the natural enemies of insect herbivores.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/76</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1076&amp;amp;context=utk_planpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>76</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1076</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-04T10:35:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>9228617</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/76</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Chen, Hao*, Guanglin Li*, Tobias G. Köllner, Qidong Jia*, Jonathan Gershenzon, and Feng Chen*. &quot;Positive Darwinian selection is a driving force for the diversification of terpenoid biosynthesis in the genus Oryza.&quot; BMC Plant Biology 14 (2014). http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12870-014-0239-x.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1186/s12870-014-0239-x</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>BMC Plant Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>