<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Investigation of the Relationship Between Academic and Athletic Satisfaction Among Division IA Student-Athletes</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Phillips</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship between academic and athletic satisfaction for Division IA intercollegiate athletes. Student-athletes (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 367; 16 teams) at a Division IA university in the Midwest completed the Athlete Satisfaction Questionnaire (ASQ) and the Student Satisfaction Inventory (SSI), in addition to a demographic survey. The data was analyzed using a variety of analytical procedures including descriptive statistics, bivariate correlation, and hierarchical regression in order to answer the research questions guiding this study:&lt;br /&gt; 1. What is the relationship between Division IA intercollegiate athletes’ satisfaction with their academic and athletic experiences?&lt;br /&gt; 2. What is the relationship between Division IA intercollegiate athletes’ satisfaction with their academic and athletic satisfaction controlling for differences by: ethnicity of athlete, gender of athlete, gender of coach, leadership style of coach, nature of sport (individual vs. team-oriented), team win/loss record, year in school, grade point average, injury incurred, and extent of games missed?&lt;br /&gt; 3. What is the difference between the satisfaction and importance scores Division IA athletes assign to questions about their academic and athletic experiences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a statistically significant relationship between academic and athletic satisfaction (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .01), even after controlling for the intervening variables. This finding suggests that academic satisfaction is a powerful predictor of athletic satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/265</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1318&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>265</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1318</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-04T13:21:55-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1132478</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/265</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Norma T. Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Leslee A. Fisher, Tricia McClam, Terrell L. Strayhorn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/PhillipsJim.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>