<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A gastric neuroendocrine carcinoma expressing somatostatin in a bearded dragon (Pogona vitticeps).</title>
<publication-date>2011-11-01T09:48:16-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lyons</lname>
<fname>Jerry</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Greenacre</lname>
<fname>Cheryl</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Duncan</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>gastric</keyword>
<keyword>inland bearded dragons</keyword>
<keyword>lizards</keyword>
<keyword>neuroendocrine carcinoma</keyword>
<keyword>pogona vitticeps</keyword>
<keyword>somatostatin</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A metastatic gastric neuroendocrine carcinoma in a 2.5-year-old inland bearded dragon (Pogona vitticeps) with a chronic history of anorexia, weight loss, depression, and acute melena is described. Histologic examination of the gastric mass revealed a densely cellular tumor arranged in nests and occasional rosettes of hyperchromatic cells with oval to spindle-shaped nuclei and minimal cytoplasm; the tumor was supported by a moderate fibrovascular stroma. Similar cells invaded through the gastric mucosa, and there were multiple hepatic metastases. The neoplastic cells were weakly immunopositive for neuron-specific enolase and moderately positive for somatostatin but were negative for chromogranin AB and gastrin. Ultrastructural studies revealed scattered neurosecretory granules in the neoplastic cells, confirming the diagnosis of a neuroendocrine carcinoma.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/57</coverpage-url>
<label>57</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1056</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T09:42:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2323835</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/57</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Jerry Lyons, Shelley Newman, Cheryl Greenacre, and John Duncan. &quot;A gastric neuroendocrine carcinoma expressing somatostatin in a bearded dragon (Pogona vitticeps).&quot; Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation 22.2 (2010): 316-320.</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.jvdi.org/cgi/content/abstract/22/2/316</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>