<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A proteomic investigation of &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species using mass spectrometry and reverse genetics</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Savidor</lname>
<fname>Alon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Organisms in the genus &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; are important plant pathogens, although understudied. &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; was first brought into human awareness with the identification of &lt;em&gt;P. infestans&lt;/em&gt; as the culprit for the Irish potato famine in the mid 1800s. Since then, over 80 &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species have been identified, many of which infect a wide variety of crops worldwide with devastating results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, much of the work aimed at controlling &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; diseases involved applied research. In recent years there has been a marked increase in molecular work on &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt;. This increase is evident not only from increased funding by agencies such as the National Science Foundation (NSF), but also from the type of research applied to &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; for the first time. The first &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species to have their genomes sequenced were &lt;em&gt;P. sojae&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P. ramorum&lt;/em&gt; at 2004. Since then the genomes of two more &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species- &lt;em&gt;P. capsici&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P. infestans&lt;/em&gt;, were also sequenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Availability of &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; genome sequences provided us with the basis necessary for a proteomic investigation of these organisms. The study presented here represents the first large scale proteomic study of any &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species. Using mass spectrometry and available or newly developed bioinformatic tools we measured the proteomes of different asexual &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; life stages. We also measured the protein complement of &lt;em&gt;P. capsici&lt;/em&gt; infected tomato plants, the so called “interactome”, in order to gain an insight into the biological processes occurring in the pathogen during infection, and in the plant in response to the pathogen. We also used data from these proteomic experiments as a part of a novel approach aimed at improving the genome annotation of those &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; species. Finally, we used different molecular techniques, including a reverse genetic technique called Targeted Induced Local Lesions in Genome (TILLING), to begin characterization of a few protein targets identified in those experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accumulated data from all our experiments identified certain molecular processes, metabolic and others, that may explain the success of &lt;em&gt;Phytophthora&lt;/em&gt; as a plant pathogen. The data from these experiments provides a platform on which future experiments can be based on to further characterize these interesting organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/503</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1568&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>503</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1568</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-22T07:07:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1160659</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/503</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kurt H. Lamour, W. Hayes McDonald</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jeffrey Becker, Loren Hauser, Neal Stewart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/SavidorAlon2.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>