<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Online Instruction Self-Efficacy Beliefs Among College Students Who Utilized Web-Enhanced Instruction</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carter</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of the study was to investigate online instruction self-efficacy beliefs among college students and the demographic influence of gender, classification rank, age, academic major, computer access, computer experience, online instruction experience, Internet experience, and the use of an online learning system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The population of approximately 1000 students enrolled at Maryville College during Fall 2003 and Spring 2004 semesters was used to conduct the study. Students were asked to complete the Tennessee Online Instruction Scale (TOIS), which consisted of items related to forty online instruction tasks and background information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings revealed that online instruction self-efficacy beliefs of students were not significantly different for academic major and classification rank. However, computer experience was significant for online instruction self-efficacy beliefs. As a result students with more computer experience developed a higher self-efficacy and those with less computer experience had lower self-efficacy beliefs. Self-efficacy beliefs were also found to be higher for students who experience more online instruction, using the Interned and an online learning system when compared to students who had less experience in inline instruction, the Internet and an online learning system,.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings have implications for instructional technologies, educators and designers who are primarily responsible for developing online instructional technology courses. Future research should consider the investigation of online instruction self-efficacy beliefs among a diverse population reflecting various academic majors, age, and classification rank.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4517</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6248&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4517</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6248</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-29T13:17:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10677531</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4517</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph Brockett, Carroll Coakley, Robert Maddox</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>