<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Factors associated with HIV testing for women during prenatal care</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Washington</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Alex</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objectives of this study were to examine the effects of demographics, cues to action, HIV risk appraisal, and practice setting on women’s use of HIV testing during prenatal care. Three hypotheses based on the general theme of the Health Belief Model were tested. Furthermore, a prediction model was tested and a cross validation analysis was conducted to determine the accuracy of the model to predict HIV testing for women during prenatal care. This study reports findings from an examination of the National Survey of Family Growth, Cycle V (N SFG) archival data. Face to face interviews were conducted using the NSFG survey instrument to screen non-incarcerated women (N=1033) ages 15 — 44 regarding childhood/young adult living arrangement history; work history; education, use of family planning and other medical services; clinic data bases; HIV testing; demographic characteristics (including race, age, marital status); child care; health insurance, number of sexual partners; and HIV risk behaviors. HIV testing was measured as a binary variable, determining whether the women received HIV testing during prenatal care.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6328</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8280&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6328</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8280</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450437</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6328</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Karen M. Sowers</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William Nugent, Rodney Ellis, Paula Carney</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>