<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Interaction between Andrew Johnson and the Press</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lowe</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Influence and Political Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to examine the unstable relationship that existed between Andrew Johnson and the press. Information collected throughout this examination can be used to understand the power of the media in regard to Andrew Johnson’s presidency. Primary documents were examined to determine how the press reacted to Johnson’s policies and actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is perhaps most remarkable about Andrew Johnson’s presidency is that he enjoyed almost unprecedented popularity and support during the first months of his term in office. Within months of his inauguration, however, nearly all politicians and members of the press held him in deepest contempt. Johnson and his closest advisors were forced to confront an event unprecedented in the executive branch of the United States. The manner in which Johnson responded to press hostility shaped the nation’s opinion of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study attempts to explain why the press displayed such a sudden reversal of opinion. By examining newspapers and magazines throughout the country, the manner in which the Radical Republicans influenced the public’s perception of Johnson can be observed. Johnson’s ability to lead the nation was ultimately inhibited by his political opponents in Washington D.C., and the press’s eagerness to present him in an unfavorable light.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4700</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6277&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4700</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6277</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-16T05:19:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10607749</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4700</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Harmon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ff839f790)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>