<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Determining 235U Enrichment Using a Dual-Energy Approach for Delayed Neutron Measurements</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>aloustea@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lousteau</lname>
<fname>Angela</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>uranium</keyword>
<keyword>enrichment</keyword>
<keyword>delayed neutrons</keyword>
<keyword>dual-energy</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Bulk uranium items are often measured using active neutron interrogation systems to take advantage of the relatively high penetrability of neutrons, providing the ability to quickly and accurately measure uranium masses in large, dense configurations. Active techniques employ an external neutron source to induce fission in the uranium and subsequently measure emitted prompt fission or delayed neutrons. Unfortunately, the emitted neutrons from &lt;sup&gt;235&lt;/sup&gt;U [uranium-235] and &lt;sup&gt;238&lt;/sup&gt;U [uranium-238] are, for all practical purposes, indistinguishable; therefore, commonly used systems such as the Active Well Coincidence Counter, the &lt;sup&gt;252&lt;/sup&gt;Cf [californium-252] Shuffler, and other systems based on measurement of prompt or delayed fission neutrons require many representative calibration standards and/or well-known isotopic information to interpret the results (i.e., extract an isotopic mass from the effective fissionable mass), thus limiting these techniques for safeguards applications. The primary objective of this research was to develop and demonstrate a dual-energy neutron interrogation technique using a &lt;sup&gt;252&lt;/sup&gt;Cf Shuffler measurement chamber for determination of uranium enrichment, thus eliminating the need for a (traditionally separate) gamma isotopic measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new technique exploits the change in fission rates as a function of interrogating neutron energy to independently determine the &lt;sup&gt;235&lt;/sup&gt;U and &lt;sup&gt;238&lt;/sup&gt;U content in the measurement item. Dual neutron interrogation energies were achieved by adding a deuterium- tritium (D-T) neutron generator into the measurement chamber of the Oak Ridge National Laboratory &lt;sup&gt;252&lt;/sup&gt;Cf Shuffler. Results from traditional &lt;sup&gt;252&lt;/sup&gt;Cf measurements and the new D-T measurements were then used to develop a relationship between uranium enrichment and the ratio of the two delayed neutron count rates. Parameter studies were performed to optimize the measurements for each source using a combination of modeling/simulation and experimental measurements. This dissertation presents the detailed development of this novel dual-energy neutron interrogation technique. The results are promising and with engineering refinements could be deployed for routine assay of certain types of materials.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4748</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6227&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4748</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6227</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-10T11:12:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10578436</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4748</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jason P. Hayward</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ron Pevey, Steven Skutnik, Charles Britton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>