<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Interaction with Choline and Pantothenic Acid with Carnitine in Humans and Rodents</title>
<publication-date>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Daily</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>William</mname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;It had been shown previous to this research that supplementation with choline and pantothenic acid results in reduced plasma concentrations and urinary excretion of carnitine in adult humans. This research demonstrated similar effects in younger human subjects and developed an animal model for future study of the interaction of choline and pantothenic acid with carnitine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rats were first used as an animal model but neither choline, pantothenic acid, nor both combined had any effect on urinary or plasma carnitine concentration. It was concluded that rats were not an acceptable model, possibly because of the high choline oxidase activity present in rat liver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guinea pigs were then tested as an animal model and were found to have reduced urinary excretion of carnitine in response to choline supplementation, but not pantothenic acid supplementation. Plasma concentrations of carnitine in guinea pigs were unaffected by either choline, pantothenic acid or both combined. It was concluded that choline was the supplement responsible for reducing plasma and urinary excretion of carnitine in guinea pigs, and that guinea pigs provide an acceptable model for future study of interactions of choline and pantothenic acid in humans.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3737</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5293&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3737</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5293</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-02T12:16:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8915497</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3737</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dileep S. Sachan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John W. Koontz, James W. Bailey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>