<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using Sport to Build Community: Service-Learning with Iraqi Refugees</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ahuffman@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Huffman</lname>
<fname>Ashleigh Morgan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sport for Development and Peace</keyword>
<keyword>service-learning</keyword>
<keyword>refugees</keyword>
<keyword>narrative inquiry</keyword>
<keyword>community-university partnerships</keyword>
<keyword>Sport for Community Development</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore the connections between Sport for Development and Peace (SDP), service-learning, and community-university partnerships through the implementation of the Service-Learning: Sport and Community Development (SCD) class. It was my hope that this research would produce a usable model, a framework for other scholars and practitioners interested in developing community-university partnerships. I wanted this project to not only answer the “why” questions for SDP and service-learning, but also the “how” questions – specifically, how to create a reflexive and collaborative partnership that balances the needs of the community and university. I wanted to create something riveting and real, something inspiring and authentic, and something more inclusive than a first-person programmer or instructor account of the experience (Darnell, 2007; Eyler &amp; Giles, 1999; Millington, 2010; Stoecker &amp; Tryon, 2009).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like the goals of the class, this research was designed to stimulate and encourage others to move toward a more critical and engaged community agenda. To do that, I needed to create a research text that readers could “keep in their minds and feel in their bodies the complexities of concrete moments of lived experience” (Ellis, 2004, p. 30). For that reason, I chose narrative inquiry (Clandinin &amp; Connelly, 2000) as the primary method of representation, coupled with performance narratives (Denzin, 2003) and poetics (Glesne, 2006; Ely, 2007).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the data collected from 49 qualitative interviews, 500 pages worth of reflective journals, and 200 pages of electronically recorded field notes, I created a visual community-university partnership model that illustrates the connections between SDP and service-learning as implemented in the SCD class. In addition to the visual model, I constructed narratives to detail the progression of the SCD experience over time, beginning with the common language of sport and ending in complete investment and reciprocity. As a result of this research, it has become clear that if implemented with intentionality, careful consideration, community collaboration, and reflexivity, that sport-based service-learning initiatives can enhance student learning, improve community welfare, and strengthen ties between the community and the university.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1085</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2271&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1085</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2271</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-07-27T09:42:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2118457</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1085</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joy T. DeSensi</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allison D. Anders, Lars Dzikus, Dulcie Peccolo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>