<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>CANINES AND CHILDHOOD CANCER: THE EFFECTS OF ANIMAL-ASSISTED THERAPY FOR PATIENTS, FAMILIES AND THERAPY DOGS</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>molly.jenkins@americanhumane.org</email>
<institution>American Humane Association</institution>
<lname>Jenkins</lname>
<fname>Molly</fname>
<suffix>MSW</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>amym@americanhumane.org</email>
<institution>American Humane Association</institution>
<lname>McCullough</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
<suffix>MA</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>ashleighr@americanhumane.org</email>
<institution>American Humane Association</institution>
<lname>Ruehrdanz</lname>
<fname>Ashleigh</fname>
<suffix>BA</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>kevin.n.morris@gmail.com</email>
<institution>American Humane Association</institution>
<lname>Morris</lname>
<fname>Kevin</fname>
<suffix>Ph.D.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLEASE USE THE PDF (available from the &quot;download&quot; link) TO FOLLOW ALONG WITH THE VIDEO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many people, animals take center stage in their daily lives, offering companionship, comfort, joy and for some, even kinship. Increasingly, greater attention has been given to the roles that animals can play in supporting the health and emotional well-being of people in need, specifically through the use of animal-assisted therapy (AAT). However, while the field of human-animal interaction (HAI) research has expanded enormously in recent years, it is still unclear whether the incorporation of animals into clinical settings is effective from a scientific standpoint. Likewise, although many studies have examined the complex bio-psychosocial impacts of childhood cancer for patients and their families, few have identified complementary therapeutic interventions to help families with the coping process. Finally, there remains a lack of sound HAI research on how AAT may affect therapy dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Canines and Childhood Cancer (CCC) &lt;/em&gt;study seeks to address these research gaps by examining the ability of AAT to impact the well-being and distress levels of pediatric oncology patients and their parents/caregivers, as well as the therapy dogs who visit them, throughout the child’s treatment process. Researchers will present the preliminary findings from a pilot trial conducted with three pediatric oncology sites, including data from patients, families and therapy dogs, as well as information on the feasibility of conducting rigorous and innovative AAT research across multiple pediatric healthcare settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CCC&lt;/em&gt; is a collaborative project between American Humane Association and Pfizer Animal Health.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1058&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1058</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-18T11:29:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3546323</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly Jenkins, MSW, Research Analyst, American Humane Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molly Jenkins&lt;/strong&gt; received her MSW from the Graduate School of Social Work at the University of Denver, where she obtained certification in animal-assisted social work from the University of Denver’s Institute for Human-Animal Connection. Her background includes experience in the child welfare, HIV/AIDS, and violence prevention fields, as well as both an educational and professional emphasis on animal behavior and veterinary medicine. As a Research Analyst at American Humane Association, her primary area of focus is human-animal interaction research. She is currently investigating the effects of animal-assisted therapy on pediatric oncology patients, their family members, and therapy dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amy McCullough, MA, National Director of Animal-Assisted Therapy, American Humane Association &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amy McCullough&lt;/strong&gt;, MA, serves as the National Director of Animal-Assisted Therapy at American Humane Association. Her responsibilities encompass the development of training curricula for handlers and clinicians in specialized settings; the development of research and outcome measurements for animal-assisted therapy; and the delivery of high-quality animal-assisted therapy services to national markets. She is also a licensed Animal-Assisted Therapy Instructor and Evaluator. She graduated from Queens University with a master’s degree in organizational communication. Currently, she is pursuing a doctorate in communication studies at the University of Denver, with a focus in developing research to demonstrate the efficacy of animal-assisted therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ashleigh Ruehrdanz, BA, Research and Evaluation Specialist and IRB Administrator, American Humane Association &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ashleigh Ruehrdanz&lt;/strong&gt;, BA, has more than six years of experience in child development, child welfare, and human-animal interaction research. As Research and Evaluation Specialist at American Humane Association, she has provided support for project design, execution and reporting. As IRB Administrator, she is responsible for ensuring that all policies, procedures and projects meet federal guidelines and requirements. Her current work focuses on a national, randomized-control trial study examining the effectiveness of animal-assisted therapy with pediatric oncology patients and their families. She is also currently pursing a master’s degree in public health from the University of Colorado at Denver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kevin Morris, Ph.D., PI for the CCC Research Study, American Humane Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kevin Morris&lt;/strong&gt; holds a Ph.D. in Molecular Biology and Biochemistry from the University of Chicago. He joined the Animal Assistance Foundation in 2009, where he began focusing his scientific skills on the advancement of animal welfare through research and analysis. He served as the Principal Investigator on a wide range of studies, including an ongoing clinical investigation of animal-assisted therapy in a child welfare environment. Dr. Morris currently serves as the Principal Investigator for the &lt;em&gt;Canines and Childhood Cancer (CCC)&lt;/em&gt; research study, a collaboration between American Humane Association and Pfizer Animal Health.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Molly Jenkins: 4848 Brandon Creek Drive/Boulder, CO 80301; 720-446-9769&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amy McCullough: 909 South Race Street/Denver, CO 80209; 303-476-3613&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashleigh Ruehrdanz: 1650 South Quivas Street/Denver, CO 80112; 303-630-9480&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Morris: 1288 South Corona Street/Denver, CO 80210; 303-564-3886&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T12:15:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>SUMMIT ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_url" type="string">
<value>//trace.lib.utk.edu/assets/VSW/2013/MollyJenkins.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_file" type="string">
<value>VSW/2013/MollyJenkins.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_streamer" type="string">
<value>rtmp://trace.lib.utk.edu:1935/stream</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>