<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Biracial students on campus: We Are America (too)</title>
<publication-date>2013-06-03T05:46:20-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sprenti1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Prentiss</lname>
<fname>Suzanne Marie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>tprentis@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Prentiss</lname>
<fname>Tyrel</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Arts and Humanities</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This interactive discussion will explore the changing face of minority students from the perspectives of a biracial student and his mother who teaches on campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incorporating 2010 Census data, personal stories, and campus initiatives, we will discuss who defines race, the importance of racial identity, and what we can do as a campus and community to provide a supportive environment for biracial and mixed-race students.  As we explore the changing face of America and the increasing racial diversity of our citizens, it is critical that we understand the implications and opportunities inherent in that change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to be biracial in America? What does being American mean to someone who identifies with more than one race and culture?  To truly be united and stand together, we need to understand and appreciate the experience of all our members of our community.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2013/Session1/4</coverpage-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1084</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-11T08:24:05-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1084/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3574867</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2013/Session1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt; Attached is a power point slide reflecting the general outline of our presentation. As it is highly interactive, we will not use PowerPoint, just a white board. We did want to provide an overview of what we intend to explore during our discussion.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>