<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Regulation of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;, a Novel Type 4 P-type ATPase, in 3T3-L1 Mouse Adipocytes</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peretich</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A recently identified phospholipid translocase, &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;, may be involved in the modulation of glucose and lipid metabolism in mouse adipocytes. Aminophospholipid translocases have previously been associated with cell signaling and intracellular protein trafficking. In this study, the role of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; in the insulin signaling pathway and adipogenesis was investigated using the murine 3T3-L1 cell line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; mRNA is highly expressed in undifferentiated cells and 2-fold down-regulated during adipogenesis. Interestingly, Western blotting showed a band for ATP10C protein at 70 kDa, a lower molecular weight than expected; ATP10C expression increased during differentiation. Possible reasons for these discrepancies will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since PPARgamma is considered to be the master regulator of adipogenesis and controls the expression of adipocyte genes, the effect of PPARgamma agonists on &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; expression was examined. The PPARgamma agonists and anti-diabetic drugs MCC555 and troglitazone both promoted adipogenesis and consequently reduced &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; expression by 5-fold and 3-fold, respectively. When used in combination with the PPARgamma antagonist GW9662, treatment rescued some of the decrease in &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; due to MCC555 or troglitazone alone. The pattern of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; expression is shown to be opposite to that of &lt;em&gt;PPARgamma&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the correlation between effectors of glucose and lipid metabolism and &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; was investigated. Treatment of 3T3-L1 adipocytes with insulin and dexamethasone showed significantly increased expression of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;; treatment with the β-adrenergic factor isoproterenol slightly decreased expression. This suggests transcriptional control of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; by hormonal factors, but not β-adrenergic factors, during differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further explore the function of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; in lipid metabolism, ATP10C silencing through transient transfection of 3T3-L1 cells was first optimized to ultimately allow the assessment of changes in proteins related to obesity and diabetes. An 84% and 77% knockdown of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; gene expression in preadipocytes and adipocytes, respectively, was achieved. To elucidate a potential role for &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;/ATP10C in the insulin signaling pathway, glucose uptake was investigated. Following &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; silencing in 3T3-L1 adipocytes, glucose uptake was significantly increased at both 24 and 48 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the results presented herein, the &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; gene and ATP10C protein have an important role in the insulin signaling pathway and may be involved in adipogenesis.,/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/426</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1459&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>426</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1459</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T14:10:34-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1148727</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/426</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Madhu S. Dhar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patricia K. Tithof, Roger C. Carroll</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/PeretichAmanda.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>