<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Stationary System with Portfolio</title>
<publication-date>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cowens12@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Owens</lname>
<fname>Christina Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This creative activity explores the possibilities of designing a professional stationary system consisting of a letterhead, envelop, resume, and business card. The process began with brainstorming about myself as an architecture student and how my style and personality can be represented through a graphic system. The logo design is very clean, simple, and playful, which reflects my personality and the way I design. It works to create a push and pull of negative space from the paper through the voids of the letters. The use of the deep red provides contrast and variety to the stationary system. As for the font family, Helvetica was chosen because it allows the text to become an extension of the circular logo. To enhance the horizontality of the logo, the text is placed to draw the eye across the page. The white space around the text adds to the balance and horizontality of the page. Though there were obstacles in the design of the stationary system, such as placement and font choice, the results of the finished system provided a system which could connect to the design of my portfolio. The portfolio reflects the cleanliness and the horizontality of the stationary system, as will as the use of the color pallet, circles and play of positive and negative space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The portfolio design also begins to explore the negative space, placement and the abstraction of architectural ideas into a graphic system, which differ from the stationary system. The portfolio is composed with an underlying grid and an overarching theme. Within the portfolio, simple and elegant graphics create a clean, yet bold, visual representation of the ideas imbued in the portfolio’s architectural content.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2015/architecturedesign/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1077&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1077</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-29T12:27:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>7046993</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2015/architecturedesign/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Architecture and Design</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Diane Fox</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>