<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Foreward: Interruptions and Intersections: Journeys to the Center of the Americas</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-24T12:48:13-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Miami School of Law</institution>
<lname>Valdes</lname>
<fname>Francisco</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>central america</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In December, 2007, a diverse group of scholars and students from various regions and institutions inaugurated a new project in knowledge production, the Study Space Seminar Series.&#39; Devoted to critical perspectives in comparative and international studies, the Study Space Seminar Series follows a decade-long history of collaboration among legal scholars and friends associated with critical outsider jurisprudence. As outlined below, this new project both reflects and expands the rich record in democratic knowledge-production undertaken by &quot;OutCrit&quot; scholars of various stripes in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss2/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1071&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>specialfeature</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1071</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-20T11:25:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5363440</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss2/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Professor, University of Miami School of Law, and Co-Director, Center for Hispanic and Caribbean Legal Studies. I begin by thanking Dr. Daniel Suman for spearheading the development of this inaugural Study Space program and Professor Colin Crawford for spearheading the organization of the Study Space Seminar Series as an ongoing project. I thank also the many local hosts and participants, who made the study schedule spectacularly fruitful and the contingent of diverse scholars noted below who participated in the program, and whose essays capture its essence. I likewise thank the LatCrit community of scholars around the world, whose imaginative labors make possible this type of collaborative experiment in knowledge production. I am also grateful for assistance from the Center for the Comparative Study of Metropolitan Growth at the Georgia State University College of Law, which helped make my participation possible. I thank also the editors of the TENNESSEE JOURNAL OF LAW AND POLICY and especially Stevie Phillips and Ashley Musselman, for the work and support that not only help us to disseminate this knowledge, but that also improve our efforts with their talents. Finally, I thank Richard Cornier for his consistent assistance in all aspects of this work. All errors rest with me.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Journeys to the Center of the Americas</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>