<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thermography Detection on the Fatigue Damage</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Bing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;It has always been a great temptation in finding new methods to &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; “watch” the material fatigue-damage processes so that in-time reparations will be possible, and failures or losses can be minimized to the maximum extent.  Realizing that temperature patterns may serve as fingerprints for stress-strain behaviors of materials, a state-of-art infrared (IR) thermography camera has been used to “watch” the temperature evolutions of both crystalline and amorphous materials “cycle by cycle” during fatigue experiments in the current research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two-dimensional (2D) thermography technique records the surface-temperature evolutions of materials.  Since all plastic deformations are related to heat dissipations, thermography provides an innovative method to &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; monitor the heat-evolution processes, including plastic-deformation, mechanical-damage, and phase-transformation characteristics.  With the understanding of the temperature evolutions during fatigue, thermography could provide the direct information and evidence of the stress-strain distribution, crack initiation and propagation, shear-band growth, and plastic-zone evolution, which will open up wide applications in studying the structural integrity of engineering components in service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the current research, theoretical models combining thermodynamics and heat-conduction theory have been developed.  Key issues in fatigue, such as &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; stress-strain states, cyclic softening and hardening observations, and fatigue-life predictions, have been resolved by simply monitoring the specimen-temperature variation during fatigue.  Furthermore, &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; visulizations as well as qualitative and quantitative analyses of fatigue-damage processes, such as Lüders-band evolutions, crack propagation, plastic zones, and final fracture, have been performed using thermography results. As a method requiring no special sample preparation or surface contact by sensors, thermography provides an innovative and convenient method to &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; monitor and analyze the mechanical-damage processes of materials and components.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2354</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3806&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2354</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3806</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-15T12:49:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4717324</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2354</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter Kaehui Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Raymond A. Buchanan, Charlie R. Brooks, John D. Landes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>