<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The use of pipe elbows as flow meters.</title>
<publication-date>1948-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Husain</lname>
<fname>Bakhteyar</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;All the previous studies of pipe elbows for use as flow meters lave led to the   conclusion that it is necessary to calibrate each elbow desired to be used as an   accurate flow meter in its service location. Considering the various advantages an   elbow meter possessed over the other types, this limitation looked like an unfair   handicap to it. This study was undertaken to investigate the possibilities of using an elbow meter   without its calibration being necessary in the service location. In this connection   more attention was devoted to the practical details of the problem than to its    theoretical aspects. References to literature, dealing with the problem on a purely   mathematical basis have, however, been given where necesaary. Due to limitations of time and material, it was not possible to make a very   exhaustive study of the problem. Only seven elbows of 2-1/2-inch nominal diameter   were studied for this work, and it is realized that the generalization of these results may, in some ways, be rather unwarranted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5802</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7480&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5802</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7480</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359280</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5802</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cecil S. Camp</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Hydraulic Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1948-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>