<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identities in Practice: Relating Identity and Instructional Practices among Middle Grades Mathematics Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hodges</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This qualitative case study documents the identities of four middle grades mathematics teachers and the influences of those identities on their instructional practices. Three sources of data were collected: interviews, observations, and the Scoop Notebook (Borko et al., 2005). Wenger&#39;s (1998) characteristics of identity provided the framework for data analysis. This view of identity aligns with situative views of learning and provided an analytic lens that allowed a focus on the development of a mathematics teaching identity in relation to the communities in which teachers participate. Both within-case analyses and a comparative analysis across contexts were conducted. The within-case analyses indicated that the perceived alignment of goals, values, and beliefs for mathematics instruction between each of the communities is an important element of developing a reform-minded identity. The comparative analysis indicated that several differences in the schools played an important role in this identity formation, including school size, socioeconomic status of students, the existence of a school-based professional teaching community, and the role of the teacher in making curriculum decisions. Three areas of teachers&#39; identities were reflected in their instructional practices: (1) teachers&#39; preparations for mathematics instruction, (2) teachers&#39; views of the role of the student, and (3) teachers&#39; use of curriculum materials and discourse as pedagogical tools. Results indicated the need for professional development to carry a dual focus on increasing teachers&#39; knowledge and skills while also attending to promoting reform-minded views at a school and district level. Ongoing opportunities for teachers to participate in a professional teaching community appear to be an important catalyst for these changes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/549</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1616&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>549</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1616</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-22T11:30:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1162177</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/549</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jo Ann Cady, Vincent A. Anfara</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lynn L. Hodge, Charles Collins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008Dissertations/HodgesThomasEdward.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>