<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nonlinear dissipative wave equations with space-time dependent potentials</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Khader</lname>
<fname>Maisa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Mathematics</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We study the long time behavior of solutions of the wave equations with absorption abs (u(t, x))[superscript p]⁻¹u(t, x) and variable damping a(t, x)u[subscript t](t, x), where p belongs to (1, n + 2/n - 2) and a(t, x) ~ a₀(1 + abs(x))⁻[superscript alpha](1 + t)⁻[superscript beta] for large abs x and t, a₀ &gt; 0, for alpha belongs to (-infinity, 1), beta belongs to (-1, 1). We established decay estimates for the energy, L² and L[superscript p]⁺¹ norm of the solutions. 1. For alpha belongs to [0, 1), beta belongs to (-1, 1) and alpha + beta belongs to (0, 1), three different regimes of decay of solutions were found depending on the exponent of the absorption term, p₁(n, alpha, beta) := 1 + 4(beta + 1)/(2(n - alpha)(beta + 1) - beta(2 - alpha)) is a critical exponent in the following sense.For the supercritical region, namely p belongs to (p₁(n, alpha, beta), (n + 2)/(n - 2), the decay of solutions of the nonlinear equation coincides with the decay of the corresponding linear problem. For the subcritical region p belongs to (1,p₁(n, alpha, beta)) the decay is much faster. Moreover, the subcritical region is divided into two subregions with completely different decay rates by another critical exponent p₂ := 1 + (2alpha)/(n - alpha). If p belongs to (1, p₂(n, alpha, beta)) the decay of solutions becomes independent of alpha and beta. 2. For alpha belongs to (-infinity, 0) and beta belongs to (-1, 1). Two different regimes of decay of solutions were found depending on the exponent of the absorption term. p₁(n, alpha, beta) := 1 + 4(1 - beta)/(2(n + alpha)(1 - beta) + beta(2 + alpha)) is a critical exponent in the following sense.For the supercritical region, namely p belongs to (p₁(n, alpha, beta), (n + 2)/(n - 2)), the decay of solutions of the nonlinear equation coincides with the decay of the corresponding linear problem. For the subcritical region p belongs to (1, p₁(n, alpha, beta) the decay is much faster. We study also the long time behavior of solutions of the wave equations with focusing - abs (u(t, x))[superscript p]⁻¹u(t, x) and variable damping a(t, x)u[subscript t](t, x), where p belongs to (1, n + 2/n - 2) and a(t, x) ~ a₀(1 + absx)⁻[superscript alpha](1 + t)⁻[superscript beta] for large abs x and t, a₀ &gt; 0, for alpha belongs to (0, 1), beta belongs to (-1, 1). A sharp critical exponents results were found depending on the exponent of the focusing term, for supercritical region, namely; p belongs to (p(n, alpha, beta) := 1 + 4(beta + 1)/2(n - alpha)(beta + 1) - beta(2 - alpha), n - 2/n + 2) the solutions are global for all small data.We also established decay estimates for the energy, L² and L[superscript p]⁺¹ norm of the solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6025</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7958&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6025</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7958</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467768</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6025</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Grozdena Todorova</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>