<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>In vitro time and temperature dependence effects of three molecular weight (53, 421 and approximately1150 kilodaton) chitosans against human noroviral surrogates</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rganapat@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Ganapathy</lname>
<fname>Radha</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Chitosan, a deacetylated chitin, is known to have a broad spectrum of antimicrobial activity. The objectives of this research were to determine the in vitro time and temperature dependent effects of chitosan with different molecular weights (53, 421 and ~1150 kDa) at two concentrations (35 percent and 0.7%) against the human noroviral surrogates, feline calicivirus (FCV-F9) and murine norovirus (MNV-1) at two temperatures (37oC and 18oC) over 2 hours. The virus titers were determined using standard plaque assays and compared to untreated virus controls. The tested chitosans were shown to decrease FCV-F9 titers, but had no observable effects on MNV- 1. Chitosan with molecular weight (M.W.) of 53 kDa at 0.35% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~1.0 log PFU/ml, whereas at 0.7% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~3.0 log PFU/ml after 2 h at 37oC and by ~1.0 log PFU/ml after both 1 and 2 h at 18oC. Chitosan with M.W. of 421 kDa at 0.35% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~1.0 log PFU/ml whereas at 0.7% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~2.0 at 37oC after 2 h. Chitosans with 421 and ~ 1150 kDa at 0.35% and 0.7% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~1.0 log PFU/ml after 2 h at 18oC. Chitosan with ~ 1150 kDa at 0.35% decreased FCVF9 titers by ~1.0 log PFU/ml whereas at 0.7% decreased FCV-F9 titers by ~2.0 log PFU/ml at 37oC after 2 h. The results show that, in general, higher temperature and longer incubation cause greater inactivation of FCV-F9, with 53 kDa chitosan showing the greatest activity. Transmission electron microscopy did not show clear evidence of capsid damage of FCV-F9 treated chitosan and chitosan’s mode of action could not be clearly elucidated. Overall, the tested chitosans showed minimal effect against MNV-1. Thus, caution must be used in interpreting the data based solely on chitosan’s effects against FCV-F9 alone for the use of chitosan as a natural antiviral agent to control foodborne viral infections.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1620</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2644&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1620</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2644</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-02-28T17:29:24-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2644/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3811934</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1620</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Doris Helen D&#39;Souza</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael P. Davidson, Svetlana Zivanovic, Melissa Kennedy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>