<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Enhancing the Sustainability of Integrated Biofuel Feedstock Production Systems</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>aashwor2@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ashworth</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Joy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>biological nitrogen fixation</keyword>
<keyword>biomass</keyword>
<keyword>forage</keyword>
<keyword>legume integration</keyword>
<keyword>switchgrass</keyword>
<keyword>sustainability</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Science</discipline>
<discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As use of second-generation biofuel crops increases, so do questions about sustainability, particularly their potential to affect fossil energy consumption and greenhouse gas emissions. Nitrogen (N)-fixing legumes interseeded into switchgrass (&lt;em&gt;Panicum virgatum&lt;/em&gt; L.) may be an alternative to inorganic fertilizer in forage-feedstock systems. Research herein is divided into four general experiments: I). N replacement and feedstock impacts from legume intercrops and biochar in switchgrass; II). N-fixation rates in intercrop systems; III). impacts of biofuel systems under enhanced climate change; and, IV). projected sustainability of regional switchgrass production. Approaches included: characterization of feedstock/forage quality traits based on legume, biochar and synthetic-N applications, and harvest timing; quantification of nitrogenease activity in legumes via two techniques (&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N [isotopic] enrichment and N-difference); and, determine impacts from regional switchgrass production, N-input sensitivities, and legume-intercropping via life cycle assessment (LCA). Results suggest pigeon pea, sun hemp, red clover, and partridge pea intercrops, and in some instances, biochar may supply analogous-N to that of synthetic fertilizers to &lt;em&gt;Panicum&lt;/em&gt; species. Specifically, selected legume fixation may exceed recommended inorganic-N levels (67 kg [kilogram] N ha&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; [hectare]) in both temperate humid and semiarid tropical pasture/feedstock systems. N-difference method may be used to measure biological fixation, as it estimated comparable fixation rates to that of benchmark &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N enrichment values. Furthermore, harvest timing can be manipulated to obtain desired feedstock traits. Specifically, overwintering harvests minimized phosphorus and potassium removal, and maximize ethanol yield, hemicellulose, and in field dry-down [10.84 vs. 24.81%&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;≤0.05)]. However, yield losses were observed (22%). Forage yields were generally more responsive to legumes, and legume intercropping may increase switchgrass forage quality (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;-1rate. Intercropping selected legumes in switchgrass may enhance forage/feedstock quality and yield while reducing non-renewable inputs and greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3320</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4420&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3320</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4420</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-14T10:16:21-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4420/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6234301</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3320</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Fred Allen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patrick Keyser, Donald Tyler, Adam Taylor</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>