<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effect of Adolescent-Parent Congruence on the College-Decision Making Process of Rural Appalachian Youth</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ataylo95@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Taylor</lname>
<fname>Anna</fname>
<mname>Lora</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Keywords: rural Appalachia</keyword>
<keyword>Social Cognitive Career Theory</keyword>
<keyword>college going</keyword>
<keyword>high school students</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Secondary Education</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore the relationship between adolescent-parent congruence on the SCCT variables of college-going self-efficacy beliefs, college outcome expectations, and college decision-making in rural Appalachian youth. The study addressed three main research questions: &lt;em&gt;What are the typical levels of adolescent-parent congruence, college-going self-efficacy, and college outcome expectations of rural Appalachian youth? How are college-going decisions impacted by the level of adolescent-parent congruence, college-going self-efficacy beliefs, and college outcome expectations of rural Appalachian youth?&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;How do rural Appalachian high school students say that adolescent-parent congruence impacts their college decisions?&lt;/em&gt; Participants in the study were high school seniors enrolled in five rural Appalachian high schools within a single Southeastern state. Data was collected through online surveys. Participants were asked to complete three scales: the Adolescent-Parent Career Congruence Scale-Revised (Sawitri et al., 2012), College Outcome Expectation Scale (Flores et al., 2008), and the College-Going Self-Efficacy Scale (Gibbons &amp; Borders, 2010). Participants were also asked to answer two open response questions and complete a brief demographic scale. Findings indicated that rural Appalachian youth have a moderate amount of congruence with their parents regarding postsecondary plans, moderately high levels of college-going self-efficacy, and high levels of college outcomes expectations. High positive correlations were found between each of these three variables. In addition, multiple variables were found to predict students’ adolescent-parent congruence including college-going self-efficacy, college outcome expectations, mother’s educational level, and gender. Finally, while students reported moderate levels of adolescent-parent congruence on the quantitative measure, they demonstrated increased incongruence when asked about incongruence in an open-ended format. Based on these findings, implications for future research, counselors, and counselor educators were provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4658</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6146&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4658</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6146</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-14T10:51:53-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/6146/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10301099</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4658</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Melinda M. Gibbons</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Joel F. Diambra, Gary J. Skolits, Erin E. Hardin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Counselor Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>