<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Friendship in Die rote Zora und ihre Bande and Peter Pan</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Moldovi</lname>
<fname>Roswitha-Maria</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>German Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Children&#39;s books often show recurring themes. One such theme is friendship. My thesis is a comparatistic work between the German book &lt;em&gt;Die rote Zora und ihre Bande&lt;/em&gt; by Kurt Held and the English book &lt;em&gt;Peter Pan&lt;/em&gt; by J.M. Barrie, as those books have recently been turned into movies recently advertising the theme of friendship.  I compare these two books for parallel friendship constellations. This research reveals two types of friendships: cross-sex friendships and same-sex friendships. In both books cross-sex friendships can be seen within a group, &#39;Zoras Bande&#39; and Wendy and the Lost Boys. I analyze these friendship constellations according to the features found in realistic friendships: companionship, reciprocity, acceptance, cultural background and other similarities.  Additionally, both books offer dyads (Zora-Branko, Zlata-Branko, Wendy-Peter) made up of a boy and a girl who stand out from the group. In comparing these dyads I use gender perception as a basis, for it reveals the similarities and differences within those dyads.  This research shows that that same-sex groups of friends&#39; share other similarities than the cross-sex friendships. Both authors basically used these group constellations (―die Gymnasiasten‖, the pirates and the Indians) as a narrative device to propel the story. In my research I came to the results that even though both books seem to be similar at core due to the similar friendship constellations, there are nonetheless some differences. I trace these differences back to the different time periods the books were written and published in.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/51</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1079&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>51</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1079</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-19T10:50:27-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1114564</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/51</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stefanie Ohnesorg</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Maria Stehle, Dan Magilow</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>German</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>