<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Applying Human Factors Principles In Aviation Displays: A Transition From Analog to Digital Cockpit Displays In The CP140 Aurora Aircraft</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aeronautical Vehicles</discipline>
<discipline>Systems Engineering and Multidisciplinary Design Optimization</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A flight test program that evaluated the results of a CP140 Aurora cockpit modernization project was conducted between May 2004 and October 2005. This paper uses the results of that test program to show how basic human factors principles were violated which led to the identification of multiple design deficiencies. This paper proposes that the failure to apply good human factors principles when designing aircraft displays can lead to unacceptable deficiencies. The result can be poor modal awareness, confusion in the cockpit, and often negative training for the pilots. In particular, four major deficiencies were analyzed to determine the specific human factors principles that were breached. The violations included a lack of concise and relevant feedback to the pilot, unclear and ambiguous annunciations, poor use of colour coding principles and logic, a lack of suitable attention capture cueing, inappropriate alert cueing, an absence of aural cueing during specific degraded modes of operation, excessive cognitive workload, and a failure to incorporate the pilot as the focal point of the display design, also known as a human centred design philosophy. Recommendations for system design enhancements are provided to ensure safe and effective operations of this prototype system prior to operational implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evaluation of the prototype system design was conducted by a flight test team from the Aerospace Engineering Test Establishment in Cold Lake, Alberta and supported by the Maritime Proving and Evaluation Unit in Greenwood, Nova Scotia. The test program encompassed a thorough review of system design documentation, abinitio training and preliminary testing in a Systems Integration Lab and 40 flight test missions. The recorded deficiencies were based upon the observations of two Qualified Test Pilots.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/185</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1217&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>185</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1217</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-09T14:56:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1138307</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/185</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rich Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stephen Corda, Peter Solies</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/PalmerRyan.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>