<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Coaching age-group swimming: Contradicting perceptions and practices</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sdavy@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davy</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>Dwyer</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>sport specialization</keyword>
<keyword>coaching</keyword>
<keyword>swimming</keyword>
<keyword>sport diversification</keyword>
<keyword>development</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The current study investigates coach’s perceptions of sport specialization in age group swimming. Eleven swim coaches working with athletes under the age of 14 were interviewed. Despite the evidence in support of sport diversification over sport specialization, the study found coaches involved in youth swimming overwhelmingly support early sport specialization. This finding contradicts the literature. Three themes emerged: (1) support of sport sampling, (2) sacrifices connected to sport participation, and (3) coaches need for control. All 11 coaches acknowledged the role of other sports in the development of their athletes, but all 11 provided explanations as to why their athletes may not, or cannot, partake in other sports or general activities. Sacrifices connected to sport participation were discussed in all 11 interviews, and included both the loss of sport variety, and social sacrifices, often times connected to the same reasons athletes may not, or cannot, find time to participate in other activities. Eight of 11 participants suggested a need for control over their athletes, both in terms of their physical activities and spare time outside of school and sport. A possible explanation for these findings is many of these coaches work within programs designed and constructed to funnel athletes through the sport on the track of early sport specialization in hopes of achieving increased performances and accomplishing elite level swimming.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4732</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5732&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4732</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5732</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-01-20T07:03:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9562875</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4732</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robin Hardin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James H. Bemiller, Steven N. Waller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>