<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1728-Weed Management in Annuals, Perennials and Herbaceous Ground Covers: Nursery Production and Professional Landscape Maintenance</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-20T13:28:36-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Weeds</keyword>
<keyword>Landscape</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Controlling weeds in production or landscape areas can be a burdensome task. The objective of an effective and effi cient weed management program is to achieve the desired level of weed control at an acceptable expense (cost). Labor is very expensive and sometimes unavailable, and may require training and supervision. Management must avoid the laborious task of physically removing weeds whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This objective is best achieved by an integration of cultural practices focused on minimizing the introduction of weed seed, followed by preemergence and postemergence herbicides (refer to page 10, Herbicide Types) applied correctly at the optimum time to achieve the most benefi t. The basic principle of this integrated approach is the same for both production and landscape areas; however, the steps to achieve the desired objective are different.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexcomhort/31</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1030&amp;amp;context=utk_agexcomhort&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>31</label>
<document-type>weedandinsect</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1030</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-20T13:28:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Commercial Horticulture</publication-title>
<context-key>1281688</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexcomhort/31</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>