<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Design and Fabrication of a Low-Cost Turbine Engine Component Testbed (TECT)</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jhartma6@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hartman</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Gas Turbine</keyword>
<keyword>Turbine Engine Design</keyword>
<keyword>Turbine Engine Testing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Heat Transfer, Combustion</discipline>
<discipline>Propulsion and Power</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With gas turbine engine testing becoming very expensive because of the increasing complexity involved with the engine, engine subsystems, and test support systems, a low-cost Turbine Engine Component Testbed (TECT) is proposed. This engine build is given the designation J1-H-02. In the present study, a small augmented gas turbine engine (GTE) is constructed. The TECT engine is built with modularity as a key design consideration to allow for flame-tube patterns and augmentor sections to be changed quickly for combustion experiments that have gained impetus due to combustion anomalies/instabilities inherent with future military engine augmentors. This testbed allows for an effective way to test new sensors or analytical techniques before full scale testing by allowing an intermediate Technology Readiness Level (TRL) at low-cost and quick schedule turnaround. The TECT was completed using a minor financial investment when matched to comparable capabilities. A data acquisition and control system was developed and tested that allows for real-time engine feedback and control schemes. The components were analyzed for the proper failure modes and performance was predicted using a combination of hand calculations and engine performance prediction software. The compressor performance was predicted using turbomachinery relationships and geometry, then compared with experimental data. The TECT engine was tested across its intended operational envelope at sea-level static (SLS) conditions, with the baseline performance data documented. The applied data reduction approaches were developed and presented.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2821</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4119&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2821</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4119</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-06-17T12:26:33-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4119/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5696482</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2821</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Trevor Moeller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Milton Davis, James Simonton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>