<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Monte Carlo Modeling of Ion Beam Induced Secondary Electrons</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>uhuh@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Huh</lname>
<fname>Uk</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Ion Microscope</keyword>
<keyword>Monte Carlo</keyword>
<keyword>Secondary Electron</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Modeling ion beam induced secondary electron (iSE) production within matter for simulating ion beam induced images has been studied. When the complex nature of ion beam interactions with matter is account for, a detailed quantitative model of the ion interactions with matter, Monte Carlo simulation will be the best choice to be able to compute and predict iSE yields faster and more accurately. In order to build Monte Carlo simulation software incorporated with a reliable database of stopping power tables, for wide variety of range of materials, there have been numerous attempts to experimentally measure ion stopping power tables and to tabulate the data. Experimental data for pure elements and compounds is almost totally absent and the ability of advanced software to calculate iSE production within matter for producing reliable predictions is limited. Despite the need having a complete set of experimental ion stopping power tables will not be easily obtained for at least several decades. This study explores the incorporation of a universal stopping power curve, calculated and published by the National Institute of Standards and Technology at Boulder, into a Monte Carlo simulation software that will be able to compute iSE yield for both pure elements and compounds. This new approach of modeling iSE generations for pure elements and compounds will contribute to quantify performance of the helium ion microscope and other ion microscopes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2832</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4138&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2832</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4138</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-16T14:10:47-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4138/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5489401</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2832</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Joy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Claudia Rawn, David Keffer, Haixuan Xu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>