<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spatial and temporal relationships between deer harvest and deer-vehicle collisions at Oak Ridge Reservation, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ampierce@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pierce</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>White-tailed deer</keyword>
<keyword>deer-vehicle collisions</keyword>
<keyword>Oak Ridge</keyword>
<keyword>TN</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Department of Energy Oak Ridge Reservation (ORR) and the nearby adjoining City of Oak Ridge, Tennessee had experienced a rise in deer-vehicle collisions (DVCs) to the point where safety for employees and residents became a concern.   I investigated the effect of hunting, land cover, road mileage, season, lunar phase, sex, and change in traffic patterns that coincide with work shifts on DVCs from 1975 - 2008.   The study area was divided into grids of 1.5 km² each for administration and data recording by managing agencies.  Statistical analyses were performed on the ORR (121 grids) and GIS analyses were performed on the entire study area that included ORR and the city of Oak Ridge (190 grids).  The number of DVCs in 1975 was 16 and reached a high of 273 in 1985.  Therefore, managers initiated a hunting program in 1985 and recorded deer harvest numbers by grid each year.  Deer harvest has been occurring from 1985 until present, except when hunting was cancelled due to security concerns after the September 11 terrorist attacks in 2001.  By 2008, the number of DVCs had decreased to 100 per year. When hunting first started in 1985, they harvested 926 deer. By 2008, that number was down to 481. I used GIS mapping to record DVCs, deer harvest per grid, landcover types, and mileage per grid to determine factors affecting DVCs on the smaller landscape. Following the initiation of annual hunts, both the annual deer harvest and the number of DVC’s have fallen, presumably because the overall deer population has declined from high pre-hunting levels.   Deer harvest appears to be related to landcover characteristics, as a higher percentage of deer were harvested from forested areas than from other landcover types, as forested areas were most prominent.  The months of October, November, and December had the highest DVC numbers.  Increased traffic during starting and leaving shift times seem to increase the number of DVCs as well.  Lunar phases only seem to significantly increase DVCs during the gestation and fawning seasons. Does are involved more frequently with DVCs than bucks during gestation, fawning and prerut, but not during the rutting season.  I expect managers can use this data to guide intensive local management aimed at reducing DVCs by increasing the number of deer harvested and increased public education.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/742</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1717&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>742</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1717</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-25T13:36:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1330221</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/742</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisa I. Muller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Graham J. Hickling, Neil R. Giffen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>