<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>TRENDS IN BORRELIA SPP. PREVALENCE IN IXODES SPP. TICKS FROM THE SOUTHEASTERN COASTAL UNITED STATES</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lmaestas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Maestas</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Paul</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Ixodes scapularis</keyword>
<keyword>Ixodes affinis</keyword>
<keyword>Borrelia</keyword>
<keyword>Lyme disease</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biodiversity</discipline>
<discipline>Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Entomology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Genetics</discipline>
<discipline>Parasitology</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Lyme borreliosis (LB) cycle, involving &lt;em&gt;Ixodes scapularis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Bbss&lt;/em&gt;), is well documented in the northeastern US, where LB is becoming increasingly prevalent. In coastal North Carolina, &lt;em&gt;I. affinis&lt;/em&gt; has been shown to have a higher incidence of &lt;em&gt;Bbss&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis&lt;/em&gt;. My objectives were, to assess changes in prevalence of &lt;em&gt;Bbss&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Ixodes &lt;/em&gt;spp. along a transect from Virginia to Florida, and to assess the value of dogs and mesomammals as sentinels for spread of&lt;em&gt; Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt; sensu lato.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ixodes&lt;/em&gt; spp. were collected at sites from 37.4&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; N to 30.0&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; N in 2011-12. Veterinary clinics from Virginia, to Florida were asked to collect ticks from dogs, and mesomammals were livetrapped in South Carolina and checked for&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;ticks. Positive samples were identified to species by nested PCR and sequenced using the 16S-23S rRNA intergenic spacer genes. A subset of ticks was subjected to 12/16S rRNA genetic procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Overall, 46 ticks were positive for &lt;em&gt;Bbsl.&lt;/em&gt; Species identify of 22 &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt; DNA samples sequenced was 54% &lt;em&gt;Bbss&lt;/em&gt;, 32% &lt;em&gt;B. bissettii&lt;/em&gt;, and 13% &lt;em&gt;B. miyamotoi&lt;/em&gt;. All &lt;em&gt;Bbsl-&lt;/em&gt;positive &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis &lt;/em&gt;for which 12S analysis was completed belonged to the ‘American’ lineage of ticks. Genetic clustering (F&lt;sub&gt;ST&lt;/sub&gt; values) was evident among &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis &lt;/em&gt;positive ticks, indicating an association between infection and haplotype. A total of 370 &lt;em&gt;Ixodes&lt;/em&gt; spp. ticks were collected from dogs and mammals. Only four were &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt;-positive (one &lt;em&gt;I. affinis&lt;/em&gt; from a white-tailed deer in Virginia and two &lt;em&gt;I. affinis&lt;/em&gt; from dogs in North and South Carolina respectively). No &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;I. affinis&lt;/em&gt; ticks were obtained from mesomammals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;The pronounced prevalence gradient, whereby &lt;em&gt;Bbsl&lt;/em&gt; was not found in ticks on vegetation south of 35.2˚N cannot be explained by an absence of vectors.&lt;em&gt; Ixodes affinis &lt;/em&gt;was&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;collected in low numbers yet comprised half of the infected ticks identified, highlighting the importance of this species for sylvatic cycles of &lt;em&gt;Bbsl&lt;/em&gt;. Our furthest-south record of a &lt;em&gt;Borrelia&lt;/em&gt;-infected tick was from a dog, demonstrating that dogs can indeed be useful as sentinels for LB. Findings indicate that the risk of locally-acquired &lt;em&gt;Bbss&lt;/em&gt; infection in the coastal southeast is at present low.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2433</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2894&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2433</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2894</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-21T14:51:10-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2894/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4251776</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2433</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Graham  J. Hickling</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Debra L. Miller, Rebecca T. Trout Fryxell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>