<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Survival and Home Range Estimates of Pen-Raised Northern Bobwhites in Buffer Strip and Non-Buffer Strip Habitats</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:39:02-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Maryland Eastern Shore</institution>
<lname>Oakley</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Maryland Eastern Shore</institution>
<lname>Bounds</lname>
<fname>Dixie</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Maryland Eastern Shore</institution>
<lname>Mullet</lname>
<fname>Theodore</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tudor Farms, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Gruen</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>buffer strips</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>habitat analysis</keyword>
<keyword>home range</keyword>
<keyword>Maryland</keyword>
<keyword>mortality</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>radiotelemetry</keyword>
<keyword>survival</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We investigated the effect of agricultural buffer strips on survival and home range estimates of pen-raised northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) at Tudor Farms on the Eastern Shore of Maryland. In September 2000 we released groups of bobwhites into 9 buffer strip (treatment) areas and 9 non-buffer strip (control) areas among 11 agricultural farms. Each group consisted of 4 radiomarked bobwhites and 26 non-radiomarked bobwhites. To maintain contact with the established coveys, additional radiomarked bobwhites (n = 177) were introduced into the coveys as radiomarked birds died. Survival for bobwhites released in buffer strip areas was lower (P &lt; 0.001) than survival in non-buffer strip areas. None of the radiomarked bobwhites released in the buffer strip areas survived past 27 weeks, whereas 11% of radiomarked bobwhites in non-buffer strip areas survived to 27 weeks and 1 bird survived to 41 weeks. Predation was the primary mortality factor (88%), followed by unknown causes (7%), stress (2%), hunting (2%), and road kill (1%). Mean fall and winter home range (95% minimum convex polygon) for 21 bobwhite coveys was 24.2 +- 3.5 ha, ranging from 1.7 to 65.8 ha. Home range areas of bobwhite coveys in buffer strips (n = 12, x¯ +- 15.0 2.7 ha) was significantly smaller (P = 0.002) than non-buffer strip coveys (n = 9, x¯ = 36.4 +- 4.9 ha). We conclude that the smaller home ranges in buffer strip areas seem to indicate better habitat quality; however, high mortality rates of pen-raised bobwhites limited our ability to confirm this.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol5/iss1/13</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1268&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>13</label>
<document-type>penreared_quail</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1268</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472014</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol5/iss1/13</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>