<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Who Is To Blame? Attribution Theory In The Automotive Industry</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-11T12:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jedwar64@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Automotive manufacturers have a fiduciary duty to the consumer not only to provide transportation from point A to point B; their duty encompasses much more than that. The manufacturer is expected to design, produce, and market vehicles that protect the driver and passengers from bodily harm in the case of an accident. However, sometimes the manufacturer fails in this duty. When this happens, it is imperative that the manufacturer is clear about where and what went wrong. The manufacturer is expected to find an amicable solution to the problem and implement change where needed. We seek to look at what can go wrong, and has gone wrong before, and ask consumers to reflect upon these occurrences and to give a final judgment on who should be held accountable for these injustices. Additionally, we looked at how parts made internally or by an outside supplier change can the consumer’s views.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2016/business/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1093&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1093</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-05T14:16:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>8429963</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2016/business/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Management</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Timothy Munyon</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-04-11T12:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>