<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Suggestion and Suggestibility: A Factor Analysis</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tasso</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to examine the domains of suggestion and suggestibility using factor analytic methodologies.  Previous investigations, all of which were carried-out between forty and sixty years ago, yield equivocal results.  The present study used nine behavioral measures of suggestibility and hypothesized that three distinct factors would emerge.  It was hypothesized that hypnosis, Chevreul pendulum and body-sway would load on the first factor, the odor test, progressive weights, and placebo responsiveness on the second factor, and conformity, persuasibility, and interrogative suggestibility to load on the third factor.  110 college students participated in the study.  Factor analyses failed to result in three factors, meaning our &lt;em&gt;a priori &lt;/em&gt;hypothesis of three distinct factors had to be rejected.  Furthermore, two and three-factor models were also rejected.  Thus, no clearly delineated factor structure of suggestibility emerged, indicating that the domain of suggestibility seems to be neither a single attribute or trait, nor does it appear to consist of a related group of abilities.  Implications of findings and areas for future research are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4587</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6296&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4587</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6296</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-25T11:57:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10805278</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4587</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Nash</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard A. Saudargas, Laurence P. James, Robert G. Wahler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>