<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Materiality Guidance in the Context of Insider Trading: A Call to Action</title>
<publication-date>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Materiality</keyword>
<keyword>Insider Trading</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Ethics and Professional Responsibility</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  article reflects upon certain negative effects associated with the  ambiguity of the current legal standard for materiality in the insider  trading context and suggests and demonstrates an approach to mitigating  these negative effects. Specifically, after describing and illustrating  the concept of materiality and its application in the insider trading  context, this article identifies and assesses applicable regulatory  policies, showing that these policies do not dictate an imprecise  definition of materiality. Next, the article explains certain negative  impacts on stockholder value emanating from the lack of predictability  and certainty in interpreting and applying the existing materiality  standard, including negative impacts created by continued speculative  and abusive class action litigation. The article then suggests and  illustrates an approach for fashioning materiality guidance, consistent  with applicable policy and existing regulatory principles. The suggested  approach is designed to enhance predictability and certainty in  interpreting and applying the concept of materiality in insider trading  regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/28</coverpage-url>
<label>28</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1032</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-01T12:04:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2041951</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/28</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Materiality Guidance in the Context of Insider Trading: A Call to Action. American University Law Review, Vol. 52, 2003. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=489024</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=489024</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>