<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Analysis of terrestrial and Martian volcanic compositions using thermal emission spectroscopy</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wyatt</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Bruce</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation comprises four separate parts, revised from individual research papers, which address the Mars Global Surveyor (MGS) Thermal Emission Spectrometer (TES) investigation objective of determining and mapping the composition and distribution of surface minerals and rocks on Mars from orbit. Each part is self-contained and addresses a specific aspect of this objective while collectively building on results of the previous studies. In Part 1, laboratory thermal infrared spectra (5-25 μm, at 2 cm-1 spectral sampling), deconvolved modal mineralogies, and derived mineral and bulk rock chemistries of basalt, basaltic andesite, andesite, and dacite were used to evaluate and revise volcanic rock classification schemes. Modal mineralogies derived from linear deconvolution of terrestrial volcanic rocks were compared to modes measured by an electron microprobe phase-mapping technique to determine the accuracy of linear deconvolution in modeling specific mineral abundances. One-cr standard deviations of the absolute differences between modeled and measured mineral abundances range from 2.4 to 12.2 vol %, with an average standard deviation of 4.8 vol % being in agreement with average uncertainties calculated in previous studies. Weighted average compositions of feldspars in the deconvolution generally overlap the measured ranges of plagioclase compositions and the presence of low-calcium and high-calcium pyroxenes was correctly identified.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6341</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8293&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6341</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8293</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450456</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6341</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Harry Y. McSween Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Theodore Labotka, Jeffery Moersch, Kenneth Orvis, Lawrence Taylor</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>