<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Queering the Reform/Revolution Dyad: A Spatiotemporal Dialectic</title>
<publication-date>2015-10-13T19:36:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sumon.sharif@email.wsu.edu</email>
<institution>Washington State University</institution>
<lname>Sharif</lname>
<fname>Raihan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;All ages deal with the debate between reform and revolution in the contexts of their&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;distinctive challenges, problems, and prospects. While reflecting on today’s sociopolitical&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;realities in the U.S., this paper identifies a theoretical stagnancy in academia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that deters any radical praxis for revolution. Addressing some key theoretical stances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;within the reform/revolution dyad, the paper argues that any criticism of “revolution in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a linear future” is no easy approval for “reform in a static present” either. Also,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;replacing the “apocalyptic future” with the “here and now” of the progressive present&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is perhaps inadequate without critically reflecting on the “quality” of the “present”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper does not recommend any specific prescriptive means but outlines a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;speculative prospect of “here and now” for revolution. It critiques theoretical stances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of a number of postcolonial and poststructuralist thinkers and argues that these&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;stances eventually get appropriated within the hegemonic reform-based justice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;underpinning neoliberalism. It argues that using the work of Henry Lefebvre, David&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvey, and Doreen Massey, a spatiotemporal dialectic for revolution can be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;developed which in turn also embraces revolutionary visions of Alain Badiou. The&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;paper explains how this dialectic reveals an inadequacy in the politics of reform and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;adjustment within theories of James C Scott, Michel de Certeau, Homi K Bhabha,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michel Foucault and Gilles Deleuze. It shows how liberal justice discourses that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;routinely promote reform in an attempt to misguide revolutionary potentials manage to find a comfort zone in the politics of difference. Specifically, the paper invests in the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;interstice between two types of theories to queer the longstanding reform-revolution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dyad.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol6/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1083&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1083</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-13T19:23:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>7713310</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol6/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>