<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Heritability and Genetic Gain of Seed Protein, Oil, and Yield among RIL of Soybean</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bwiggin1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wiggins</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>soybean</keyword>
<keyword>heritability</keyword>
<keyword>protein</keyword>
<keyword>oil</keyword>
<keyword>yield</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Breeding and Genetics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Soybean is a remarkable crop that is used in many aspects of our everyday lives. The seed protein is used primarily for livestock feed, though it is becoming more available as a meat substitute for human consumption. Soybean oil is used in many products such as plastics, foods, and industrial products. Seed yield is the major trait that is selected for in a breeding program. A population of 239 F&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; derived RIL from the cross of USG 5601T × U99-310255 was used to calculate heritability estimates by parent offspring regression and on an entry mean basis. This population was grown in 2009 as unreplicated F&lt;sub&gt;4:5&lt;/sub&gt; plant rows at the East Tennessee Research and Education Center (ETREC) in Knoxville, TN. In 2010, the F&lt;sub&gt;4:6&lt;/sub&gt; generation was grown as two replications with two locations, ETREC and Highland Rim Research and Education Center (HRREC) in Springfield, TN. In 2011, the F&lt;sub&gt;4:7&lt;/sub&gt; generation was grown at ETREC, HRREC, and at the Research and Education Center at Milan (RECMLN) in Milan, TN. Averaged over two years (2010 and 2011) and 5 environments exhibited a range of 1928.7 to 3033.6 kg ha&lt;sup&gt;-1 &lt;/sup&gt;with a mean of 2325.7 kg ha&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;for seed yield, 398.4 to 451.8 g kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with a mean of 426.8 g kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; for seed protein concentration, and 201.1 to 224.6 g kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; with a mean of 213.7 g kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; seed oil concentration. On an entry mean basis, a heritability estimate of 0.85 for seed protein concentration was observed. However, a parent-offspring regression of F&lt;sub&gt;4:6&lt;/sub&gt; to F&lt;sub&gt;4:7&lt;/sub&gt; revealed an estimate of 0.43 (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;= 0.26). For seed oil concentration, heritability estimate on an entry mean basis was 0.78 and the parent-offspring regression was 0.11 (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=0.01). Seed yield exhibited heritability estimates of 0.23 (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=0.09) and 0.38 for parent-offspring regression and entry mean basis respectively. Genetic gains were calculated for all traits through selections for the top 5, 10, 15, and 20% of RILs for seed yield, seed protein, and seed oil concentration. Improvements in these traits were achieved singularly and could be selected for multiple traits when phenotypic correlations are considered.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1248</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2348&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1248</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2348</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-30T10:02:45-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2348/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2713927</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1248</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vincent R. Pantalone</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Fred Allen, Dennis West</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>