<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Antibacterial Activity and Chemical Characterization of Resin from &lt;i&gt;Sciadopitys verticillata&lt;/i&gt; (Thunb.) Siebold and Zuccarini</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dyates4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yates</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>Ira</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sciadopitys</keyword>
<keyword>resin</keyword>
<keyword>pinene</keyword>
<keyword>antimicrobial</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Pathology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sciadopitys verticillata&lt;/em&gt; produces white viscous resin that is unique among the conifers. This research investigated effects of resin on bacteria from different ecological niches and the chemical composition of the resin. Each bacterial species was evaluated separately for response to winter- and summer-collected resins. Exposure to winter-collected resin reduced numbers of colonies of &lt;em&gt;Bacillus cereus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Erwinia amylovora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium tumefaciens&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and increased numbers of &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonascampestris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas fluorescens&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas syringae. &lt;/em&gt;Summer-collected resin affectedpopulation growth of two bacterial species; population counts of &lt;em&gt;E. amylovora&lt;/em&gt; decreased and those of &lt;em&gt;P. fluorescens&lt;/em&gt; increased. Selected strains of &lt;em&gt;P. fluorescens&lt;/em&gt;are active against &lt;em&gt;E. amylovora&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR), gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GCMS), and pyrolysis GCMS were used to characterize chemical composition of resin of &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt;. Resin contained aldehydes, aromatics, olefins, alkoxy groups, ethers, alkyls, and carbonyls. Dimethyl sulfoxide extracts of resin containedα-pinene, tricyclene, and β-pinene (approximately 95% of total volatilesin GCMS analysis). In FTIR analysis, functional groups consistent with previous reportswere identified. Analysis supported the proposals that &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; resin is chemically similar to Cupressaceous resins but no Pineaecous resins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principal component analysis, coupled with pyrolysis GCMS spectrometry data, was used to screen for differences among &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; trees grown in eastern Tennessee. Resin from four of six different source trees had no obvious differences. Differences in pyrograms of resins from two genetically identical trees that received different amounts of light were functional groups normally associated with photosynthesis products; these products were low in abundance (1% or less) and low molecular weight. Principal component analysis was coupled with FTIR to evaluate differences between resin collected from &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; and Frasier fir.Fraser fir was distinct from &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; and did not contain the spectral signature of &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; and other resins from plants believed to be related to &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research is the most comprehensive study of resins collected from &lt;em&gt;S. verticillata&lt;/em&gt; to date&lt;em&gt;. C&lt;/em&gt;hemical basis of antimicrobial activity was not fully elucidated. Future research will address the role of chemical composition and resin concentration on antibacterial activity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4118</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5352&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4118</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5352</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-17T09:46:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8745423</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4118</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kimberly D. Gwinn</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bonnie H. Ownley, Earnest C. Bernard, William E. Klingeman III, Nicole Labbe</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>