<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Relationships between Self-Compassion, Self-Blame, Disengagement Coping, PTSD, and Depression in Women Following Adult Sexual Assault</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lhamrick@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hamrick</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>sexual assault</keyword>
<keyword>self-compassion</keyword>
<keyword>PTSD</keyword>
<keyword>self-blame</keyword>
<keyword>disengagement coping</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study investigated the associations between self-compassion, self-blame, disengagement coping, and PTSD and depression symptom severity in a volunteer sample of women (&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt; = 207) who experienced one or more incidents of forced sexual contact in adulthood. The mean age of the participants was 27.07 (&lt;i&gt;SD&lt;/i&gt; = 9.62), and the majority identified as Caucasian (85.5%). Participants completed a survey assessing trauma history, post-traumatic stress disorder symptom severity, depression symptom severity, disengagement coping, self-blame attributions, and self-compassion. The results from the hierarchical regression analyses showed that CSA history, characterological self-blame (CSB), behavioral self-blame (BSB), and disengagement coping significantly predicted PTSD symptom severity, and CSB and self-compassion significantly predicted depression symptom severity. Mediational analyses showed that the relationship between self-compassion and PTSD was fully mediated by disengagement coping, CSB, and BSB, and the relationship between self-compassion and depression was partially mediated by CSB. These findings have potential implications for the focus of treatment with survivors of adult sexual assault.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5019</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6426&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5019</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6426</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-08T14:23:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13276690</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5019</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gina P. Owens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Joseph Miles, Dawn M. Szymanski</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>