<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Efficiency of Pointing Dogs in Locating Northern Bobwhite Coveys</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-24T14:19:55-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Albany Area Quail Management Project</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University</institution>
<lname>Stribling</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University</institution>
<lname>Speake</lname>
<fname>Dan</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We studied the efficiency of pointing dogs in locating coveys of northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) using radiotelemetry from 1992-1997 on 2 private hunting plantations in southwest Georgia. During these 5 hunting seasons, 169 hunts generated data on 838 &quot;encounters&quot; with 254 separate radio-marked coveys. Pointing dogs located 53% of the available coveys, 25% of which were never seen by the hunters due to evasive behavior by the birds. An additional 12% of encountered coveys were seen by the hunters even though they were never located by the dogs. This resulted in the hunters seeing a total of just over half (53%) and shooting into approximately one-third (32%) of the total radio-marked coveys they encountered. An evaluation of &quot;false pointing&quot; was conducted by examining cases when dogs pointed radio-marked coveys that were never seen by the hunters. Most (58%) of these unproductive points were caused by coveys running away from pointing dogs, but were also attributed to wild flushes (28%) and pointed coveys that held tight and refused to flush (14%). The percentage of radio-marked coveys seen by hunters was highly variable from day-to-day (x = 53%, range = 0-100%), but fairly consistent between years (x = 53%, range = 40-63% ). Information obtained using pointing dogs appears to be more practical for measuring population trends than it is as a census technique.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol4/iss1/25</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1142&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>predation_and_hunting</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1142</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-24T13:24:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10469985</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol4/iss1/25</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>