<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Homburgvirus LP-018 Has a Unique Ability to Infect Phage-Resistant Listeria monocytogenes</title>
<publication-date>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Song</lname>
<fname>Yaxiong</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peters</lname>
<fname>Tracey</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bryan</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hudson</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Denes</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Listeria phage LP-018 is the only phage from a diverse collection of 120 phages able to form plaques on a phage-resistant Listeria monocytogenes strain lacking rhamnose in its cell wall teichoic acids. The aim of this study was to characterize phage LP-018 and to identify what types of mutations can confer resistance to LP-018. Whole genome sequencing and transmission electron microscopy revealed LP-018 to be a member of the Homburgvirus genus. One-step-growth curve analysis of LP-018 revealed an eclipse period of ~60–90 min and a burst size of ~2 PFU per infected cell. Despite slow growth and small burst size, LP-018 can inhibit the growth of Listeria monocytogenes at a high multiplicity of infection. Ten distinct LP-018-resistant mutants were isolated from infected Listeria monocytogenes 10403S and characterized by whole genome sequencing. In each mutant, a single mutation was identified in either the LMRG_00278 or LMRG_01613 encoding genes. Interesting, LP-018 was able to bind to a representative phage-resistant mutant with a mutation in each gene, suggesting these mutations confer resistance through a mechanism independent of adsorption inhibition. Despite forming plaques on the rhamnose deficient 10403S mutant, LP-018 showed reduced binding efficiency, and we did not observe inhibition of the strain under the conditions tested. Two mutants of LP-018 were also isolated and characterized, one with a single SNP in a gene encoding a BppU domain protein that likely alters its host range. LP-018 is shown to be a unique Listeria phage that, with additional evaluation, may be useful in biocontrol applications that aim to reduce the emergence of phage resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_foodpubs/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1012&amp;amp;context=utk_foodpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1012</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-05-26T09:31:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Food Science and Technology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>17864157</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_foodpubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.3390/v11121166</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>