<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>H. L. Mencken as a Philogist</title>
<publication-date>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Herrin</lname>
<fname>Roberta</fname>
<mname>Teague</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation examines H. L. Mencken&#39;s attitudes toward language and the forces that shaped those attitudes. This study also traces the development of &lt;em&gt;The American Language, &lt;/em&gt;assesses the influence of this work on language studies in America, and examines Mencken&#39;s place in the field of linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three types of material are surveyed in this study: the body of H. L. Mencken&#39;s writing that reflects his attitudes toward language; the definitive secondary material which focuses on Mencken&#39;s interest in American English; and the background material necessary to establish a social, historical, political, and linguistic context for Mencken&#39;s ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study concludes that H. L. Mencken&#39;s attitudes toward American English were shaped by a number of factors--his upbringing in the middle-class household of a German-American cigar maker, his experiences as a journalist, his early reading in &lt;em&gt;Dialect Notes&lt;/em&gt;, his experience as a magazine editor and essayist. Though Mencken became adept enough in language study to produce &lt;em&gt;The American Language&lt;/em&gt;, his chauvinistic treatment of American English and his methods of collecting information barred him from the ranks of the professional linguists. He was--and is--considered an amateur, a dilettante, a man unsophisticated in linguistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mencken&#39;s lasting value is that he set before a growing community of linguists a work which inspired other philologist to collect and analyze. The thesis of &lt;em&gt;The American Language&lt;/em&gt; was but one of many catalysts for American linguistic study in the twenties and thirties. It is important because it came from a sophisticated man of letters who twitted the professionals into action.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2917</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4349&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2917</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4349</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-07T10:33:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6213414</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2917</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John H. Fisher</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas Heffernan, Henry Kats, Barney Reaves</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>