<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of Oven Roasting at 200 and 300 ° F. on the Microbiology of Beef Roasts</title>
<publication-date>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Marilyn</fname>
<mname>Sue</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Abbreviated Summary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I. SCOPE OF THE STUDY:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine the effect of oven roasting at 200 and 300&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;0 &lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/em&gt;F. on the microbiology of high and low finish rib and top-round beef roasts. Rib roasts averaged 10.2 and 6.7 pounds and top-round roasts averaged 6.3 and 5.5 pounds for high and low finish respectively. Roasts cooked at 200&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. were heated to an end point of 152&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. and roasts cooked at 300&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. to 158&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F.  Samples taken aseptically from the middle of a center slice of each of the forty roasts were analyzed microbiologically for the presence of aerobic microorganisms and clostridia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;II.PRINCIPAL FINDINGS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roasts cooked at 200&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. required significantly longer cooking time per pound than their pair-mates cooked at 300&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. (P&lt;.001 for high finish rib and top-round and P&lt;.01 for low finish rib and top-round).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of two strains of &lt;em&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;faecalis &lt;/em&gt;that were recovered from a high finish rib cooked at 200&lt;sup&gt;0 &lt;/sup&gt;F. and from a low finish top-round cooked at 300&lt;sup&gt;0 &lt;/sup&gt;F., the hypothesis, that there would be sufficient lethal heat under the conditions of this study to kill all nonsporeforming microorganisms, appears to be acceptable. Cooking times at both 200 and 300&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. provided large margins of safety for the destruction of staphylococci and &lt;em&gt;Salmonellae&lt;/em&gt;, which are often causative agents of food poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All microorganisms were recovered at low levels. This study indicated that roasting at 200&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F. as a means of increasing tenderness of beef cuts proposes no additional microbiological hazards over roasting at 300&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; F., a conventionally accepted temperature for roasting beef.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3828</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5306&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3828</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5306</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-08T11:24:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8941563</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3828</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bernadine Meyer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. Orvin Mundt, Frances A. Schofield</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>