<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Markov set-chains as models of plant succession</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Samuels</lname>
<fname>Corey</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this dissertation I examine Markov set-chains as a new approach for modeling plant succession. Set-chains are an extension of Markov chains, due to Hartfiel (1991, 1998), that makes it possible to model succession when transition probabilities are uncertain or fluctuating. In Markov set-chains each transition probability is expressed as an interval containing the range of all possible values for that parameter. In turn, a setchain predicts community composition as a range of possible frequencies for each species. First, I give an introduction to Markov set-chains and methods for iterating and finding their asymptotic behavior. I demonstrate the formulation and computation of a set-chain with an example from a grassland restoration experiment. Next, I use setchains to investigate the dynamics of experimental grassland plots planted with different species diversities. The set-chain predicts that plots with more planted species will vary less in composition than those with fewer species. I analyze a restricted, two-state setchain and show that these differences in variability reflect variability thresholds that identify four distinct regions of parameter-space. These regions delineate which transition probability intervals lead to widening, or narrowing, distribution intervals as the system develops. Finally, I use simulations to investigate several questions about how uncertainty propagates from data to parameter estimates and predictions in Markov set-chains. Markov set-chains are an important contribution to our understanding of what controls variability in ecological systems; they may be useful tools for getting more predictable outcomes from ecological restoration and construction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2075</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3513&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2075</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3513</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T09:36:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4639460</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2075</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Kot</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mitch Cruzan, James A. Drake, Robert V. O’Neill, Daniel Simberloff, Jake Weltzin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>