<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Students’ of Color Experiences in a Service-Learning Program at a Community College: 
A Critical Study</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Shanna</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Students of Color</keyword>
<keyword>Critical Race Theory</keyword>
<keyword>Community Cultural Wealth</keyword>
<keyword>Mixed-Methods Research</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;While community colleges serve the majority of Students of Color in higher education, a large percentage of these students drop out of college and do not graduate or transfer to four-year institutions.  This problem is well-documented and has been the focus of multiple initiatives (i.e., first-year experience courses, cohort learning, professional advisers, student success coordinators) within higher education (Bailey &amp; Alfonso, 2005; Bailey, Jeong, &amp; Cho, 2010; Hatch, Mardock-Uman, &amp; Garcia, 2018; Hyman, 2018; Tinto, 1999; Topper, 2019).  This transformative-emancipatory mixed-methods study was conducted at a large community college in the southeastern United States, and offered a critical examination of whether or not service-learning involvement influenced graduation rates for Students of Color at community colleges, and how.  The quantitative results from the study supported the literature by indicating service-learning participation and cumulative GPA increased the likelihood of graduation for Students of Color.  There was a negative relationship between identifying as a Student of Color and graduation.  The qualitative findings indicated Students of Color attributed service-learning with their ability to succeed in college; however, students also reported racialized experiences within the service-learning experience.  This study expanded the literature by exploring ways in which service-learning contributed to Students’ of Color Community Cultural Wealth (Yosso, 2005).   Due to the complex nature of service-learning and the innumerable differences between individual student’s experiences, there is no simple way to illustrate the ways in which service-learning influences success in courses, graduation rates, or future success in a career.  However, these findings can serve as empirical evidence to support the further exploration of Students’ of Color experiences within service-learning courses and programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5713</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7479&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5713</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7479</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419570</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5713</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dorian McCoy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Norma T. Mertz, Terri Ishitani, Michelle Christian</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>