<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Processing and Phase Formation in Zr-Based Bulk-Metallic Glass-Forming Alloys</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wall</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Bulk-metallic glasses have established a formidable presence in the scientific community in recent years, due to a number of properties that are uncharacteristic of metallically-bonded materials. One of the fundamental challenges facing researchers in this field is to develop new and improved processing methods with the ultimate goal of facilitating a large-scale industrial integration of the materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research described herein is directed toward the pursuit of developing and improving upon the current state-of-the art in the science of bulk-metallic glass processing. A number of research and development projects were undertaken in this pursuit. First, the technology to process bulk-metallic glasses at the University of Tennessee was developed and successfully implemented. Second, bulk-metallic glasses were produced using aerodynamic levitation, which showed an improvement over the accessible cooling rates achievable employing other containerless-processing methods. Third, erbium was found to be a superior dopant to other rare-earth elements to neutralize the oxygen in a Zr-based glass-forming alloy. The alloy was found to form a glass in the presence of up to 16,000-atomic-ppm oxygen by microalloying with Er, with a relatively minor effect on the thermal and mechanical integrity of the materials. Fourth, metastable intermetallic phases were identified in as-cast VIT-105 alloy materials that contained oxygen, using diffraction. The diffraction study included the whole pattern fitting of diffraction from crystalline species in a BMG, an analytical approach that, if existing at all in the literature, is quite rare. Furthermore, this study included a novel approach to fitting diffraction from the glass. Fifth, oxygen-stabilized analogues to intermetallic phases were found in the superheated-liquid state. The presence of Er was found to inhibit surface reoxidation, revealing its mechanism for the neutralization of oxygen. The results were used to propose a model for heterogeneous nucleation and the so-called &quot;overheating threshold&quot; in the alloy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/293</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1346&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>293</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1346</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-05T10:55:39-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1133789</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/293</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hahn Choo, Chain T. Liu, Dayakar Penumadu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/WallJamesJ.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>