<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Supporting Clients’ Ability to Navigate the Ethics Surrounding the Treatment of Cancer in Animals</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-13T09:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>stoewend@uoguelph.ca</email>
<institution>University of Guelph</institution>
<lname>Stoewen</lname>
<fname>Debbie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Work</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Supporting clients’ ability to navigate the ethics surrounding the treatment of cancer in animals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a society, our relationship with animals has evolved, with companion animals today often esteemed as valued members of the family. With the human-animal bond shown to correlate with the quality of veterinary health care sought,&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; demands for improved veterinary health care over the past three decades have challenged the profession to provide ever-increasing levels of sophistication in medical services.&lt;sup&gt;2, 3&lt;/sup&gt; This has resulted in the development of specialty fields of practice,&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; such as veterinary oncology, to provide comprehensive, state-of-the art care. Oncological treatment modalities have evolved to include what are now considered traditional in veterinary cancer intervention: surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, and immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these societal-driven advancements, attitudes towards the treatment of cancer in animals vary, as identified in recent qualitative and quantitative studies.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; For clients, this creates substantial psychological dissonance as they attempt to care for their pet while pushing against a current of spoken and unspoken criticism and judgment. Such dissonance is an added burden for clients already traumatized by the diagnosis of a serious, life-threatening cancer. As social workers, it raises the imperative to be aware of this phenomenon – sourced from contradictory ethics on the treatment of cancer in animals – and support clients’ ability to successfully navigate the cancer journey while being cognizant of one’s own attitudes. Diverse societal mindsets concerning resources, the human-animal bond, and animal welfare challenge the larger ethics that define the limits of intervention.  &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;Lue TW, Pantenburg DP, Crawford PM. Impact of the owner-pet and client-veterinarian bond on the care that pets receive. &lt;em&gt;J Am Vet Med Assoc &lt;/em&gt;2008;232:531-540.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Dennis JS. Referrals: What, where, and why. &lt;em&gt;Vet Med&lt;/em&gt; 1997;92.:954-961.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Villalobos, A. (with Kaplan L). &lt;em&gt;Canine and Feline Oncology: Honoring the Human-Animal Bond. &lt;/em&gt;Ames, Iowa: Blackwell Publishing, 2007.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Rollin BE. The use and abuse of Aesculapian authority in veterinary medicine. &lt;em&gt;J Am Vet Med Assoc&lt;/em&gt; 2002;220:1144-1149.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Stoewen DS. Clients’ Service Expectations and Practitioners’ Treatment Recommendations in Veterinary Oncology. PhD Thesis, 2012.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april13/3</coverpage-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1063</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-19T15:15:28-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utvswsummit/article/1063/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3551284</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april13/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Debbie Stoewen has a DVM and MSW, and most recently, a PhD in epidemiology, specializing in veterinary communication and decision-making. She is interested in promoting the many bridges between veterinary medicine and social work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Guelph, recent PhD graduate, DVM, MSW, PhD&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;2 Welsh Drive, R.R.#3, Ayr, Ontario, Canada, N0B 1E0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(519)632-8365&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T09:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CUMBERLAND ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_url" type="string">
<value>//trace.lib.utk.edu/assets/VSW/2013/DebbieStoewen2.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T09:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_file" type="string">
<value>VSW/2013/DebbieStoewen2.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_streamer" type="string">
<value>rtmp://trace.lib.utk.edu:1935/stream</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T09:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Ethical dilemmas in social work and animals</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>