<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Influence of Atmospherics on Consumer Perceptions of Service Quality, Merchandise Price, and Merchandise Quality Influencing Behavioral Intentions: A Retailing Study of Outlet Malls</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Holmes</lname>
<fname>Alycia</fname>
<mname>Fogle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavior and Ethology</discipline>
<discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examines the influence of atmospherics on consumer perceptions of service quality, merchandise price, and merchandise quality influencing behavioral intentions in an outlet mall environment. The research design was a survey method and data were collected through a mall intercept questionnaire. A pilot test of the instrument was conducted with 43 subjects. The final questionnaire contained 30 items and a demographic section. A total of 586 questionnaires were collected from three different outlet malls. The results indicated that the atmospheric variables and the human variable of crowding are related to consumer’s perceptions of the service quality, merchandise price, and merchandise quality at an outlet mall. However, the atmospheric variables and the human variable of crowding were determined to not have a significant relationship to consumer behavioral intentions at the outlet mall. Other findings indicate that the consumer perception of service quality was determined to be significantly related to consumer behavioral intentions. However, the consumer perceptions of merchandise price and merchandise quality at the outlet mall were determined to not have a significant relationship with consumer behavioral intentions. Managerial and theoretical implications are discussed along with future research suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/192</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1239&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>192</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1239</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-01T10:10:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1127519</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/192</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ann Fairhurst, Youn-Kyung Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Laura Jolly, Lisa Fall</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/HolmesAlyciaFogle.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>