<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Endocytic trafficking is required for neuron cell death through regulating TGF-beta signaling in &lt;i&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>zwang8@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Zixing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>neuronal cell death</keyword>
<keyword>TGF-beta</keyword>
<keyword>endocytosis</keyword>
<keyword>MARCM</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Genetics and Genomics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Programmed cell death (PCD) is an essential feature during the development of the central nervous system in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; as well as in mammals.  During metamorphosis, a group of peptidergic neurons (vCrz) are eliminated from the larval central nervous system (CNS) via PCD within 6-7 h after puparium formation.  To better understand this process, we first characterized the development of the vCrz neurons including their lineages and birth windows using the MARCM (Mosaic Analysis with a Repressible Cell Marker) assay.  Further genetic and MARCM analyses showed that not only Myoglianin (Myo) and its type I receptor Baboon is required for neuron cell death, but also this death signal is extensively regulated by endocytic trafficking in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt;.  We found that clathrin-mediated membrane receptor internalization and subsequent endocytic events involved in Rab5-dependent early endosome and Rab11-dependent recycling endosome differentially participate in TGF-β [beta] signaling.  Two early endosome-enriched proteins, SARA and Hrs, are found to act as a cytosolic retention factor of Smad2, indicating that endocytosis mediates TGF-β [beta] signaling through regulating the dissociation of Smad2 and its cytosolic retention factor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1141</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2273&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1141</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2273</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-07-28T10:56:23-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2273/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2120746</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1141</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jae Park</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cynthia Peterson, Bruce McKee, Naima Moustaid-Moussa, Mariano Labrador</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>