<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Selected Characteristics of High and Low Performance Rated Extension Agents Responsible for The Tennessee Agricultural Extension Special Program in Food for Youth</title>
<publication-date>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kosoko</lname>
<fname>Beverly</fname>
<mname>Daniels</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study were to characterize High and Low performance rated Agents, to determine the relationship between performance rating level, attitude toward the assignment and other attributes of SPIFFY Agents in Tennessee.  It was also proposed to identify selected aspects of the SPIFFY programs conducted by High and Low rated Agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The population of this study included all 37 SPIFFY Agents in the State of Tennessee.  The data were collected by means of a mail questionnaire.  A secondary source of data consisted in personnel records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of the study indicated that level of performance was consequentially related to marital status, place of residence as youth, family income background as youth, youth participation in scouting, in-service training received, lack of prior work experience and/or Extension related work experience, and areas of Home Economics proficiency.  Findings further showed that level of performance was consequentially related to current participation in community activities, and kinds of volunteer work done.  It also was indicated that level of performance was consequentially related to assignment of responsibilities of SPIFFY Agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was revealed that attitudes toward working conditions and other aspects of the SPIFFY assignment also could affect performance level.  The assignment seemed to have only a small negative influence on family life; distance traveled to and from work seemed to have at least some negative effect on performance level on a consequentially larger percent of Low rated performers than High rated performers.  Also, larger percents of Low performance rated Agents felt their places of work were only &quot;fair&quot; or &quot;poor&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implications and recommendations also were included.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3057</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4455&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3057</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4455</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-13T08:19:20-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6522576</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3057</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cecil E. Carter, Jr. &amp; Ester Hatcher</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>