<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The sin of synecdoche : David Quammen&#39;s epistemology and literary science journalism</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Gorss</lname>
<fname>Jason</fname>
<mname>Brian</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Journalists face a difficult task. They must report events with objectivity and context to help readers make informed decisions. Literary journalists add to their burden by trying to mingle reporting with artfulness, while still maintaining credibility with their audience. Literary journalists who write about science have yet another audience to keep in mind: the scientific community. They must maintain the respect and trust of scientists by accurately explaining their research and the scientific process. How can a science writer balance these competing demands of creativity and credibility? David Quammen, an essayist who has written extensively about science and the natural world, offers a good platform to begin exploring the issues. In addition to his large body of work that is both artistic and technical, Quammen has had much to say about the role of epistemology and factuality in science writing. One of the tools Quammen uses extensively in his science writing is synecdoche – a figure of speech in which the part is used to represent the whole. Quammen&#39; s definition of synecdoche includes the figurative use of objects or living things, not just words. But there is a potential problem with synecdoche: it is basically a form of generalization, and generalization in science is only allowable after many replications. This is the &quot;sin of synecdoche.&quot; But is it truly a sin? By examining Quammen&#39;s exhortations about epistemology and his use of synecdoche, this thesis will explore the role of synecdoche in science writing and determine if, in the proper hands, it can be an artful and reliable way for a science writer to perpetuate his rhetorical ends.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5229</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6637&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5229</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6637</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847077</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5229</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Littmann</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>