<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The seasonality of two parasitoids (&lt;i&gt;Spathius agrili&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Tetrastichus planipennisi&lt;/i&gt;) of the emerald ash borer, &lt;i&gt;Agrilus planipennis&lt;/i&gt;, and a survey for native natural enemies of the Emerald Ash Borer in eastern Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nhooie@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hooie</lname>
<fname>Nicholas</fname>
<mname>Andrew</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Agrilus planipennis</keyword>
<keyword>Spathius agrili</keyword>
<keyword>Tetrastichus planipennisi</keyword>
<keyword>parasitoid</keyword>
<keyword>biological control</keyword>
<keyword>Fraxinus</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Entomology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The emerald ash borer (EAB), &lt;em&gt;Agrilus planipennisi&lt;/em&gt; Fairmaire (Coleoptera: Buprestidae), is an invasive species of bark borer native to eastern Asia whose primary habitat and food sources are trees in the genus &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus&lt;/em&gt;. EAB is a major pest of all North American &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus &lt;/em&gt;species and is responsible for mortality of millions of trees across its current North American range of 23 U.S states and 2 Canadian providences. After the discovery of EAB in Tennessee in 2010, parasitoid releases were started under the national EAB Biological Control Program. A research project was initiated in 2012 to 1) study the seasonality of the gregarious larval ectoparasitoid &lt;em&gt;Spathius agrili&lt;/em&gt; Yang and the gregarious larval endoparasitoid &lt;em&gt;Tetrastichus planipennisi &lt;/em&gt;Yang in the climate of eastern Tennessee, 2) determine the overwintering ability of the parasitoids in field releases, and 3) survey for potential native natural enemies of EAB. In 2013 a single generation of &lt;em&gt;S. agrili &lt;/em&gt;developed from egg to pre-pupa in ca. 22 days before overwintering. Adult individuals of &lt;em&gt;S. agrili&lt;/em&gt; from the same generation were found to have successfully overwintered in July 2014. No &lt;em&gt;T. planipennisi&lt;/em&gt; successfully parasitized or overwintered. In 2013, &lt;em&gt;S. agrili&lt;/em&gt; were successfully recovered from two field sites for the first time in eastern Tennessee after a single year of releases and successfully overwintering, indicating the ability of this species to establish. As in the previous study, no &lt;em&gt;T. planipennisi&lt;/em&gt; were recovered. Three native parasitoids, &lt;em&gt;Spathius floridanus&lt;/em&gt; Ashmead, an undetermined species of &lt;em&gt;Spathius&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Atanycolus cappaerti&lt;/em&gt; Marsh &amp; Strazanac, all known to be associated with EAB, were recovered at field sites. These recoveries represent the first documentation of these three native species associated with EAB in the southern U.S. These findings will help demonstrate the utility of &lt;em&gt;S. agrili&lt;/em&gt; in the southern U.S. as a part of the national EAB Biological Control Program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3157</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4164&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3157</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4164</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-17T05:08:16-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4164/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5801226</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3157</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paris L. Lambdin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jerome Grant, Mark Windham</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;added dedication and aknowledgements&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Entomology and Plant Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>