<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Predicting Academic Performance on High-Stakes Tests: Development of the Brief Behavior, Academic, and Social Screener (B-BASS)</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tfrankl5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Franklin</lname>
<fname>Trisha</fname>
<mname>Danielle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>screening</keyword>
<keyword>assessment</keyword>
<keyword>high-stakes testing</keyword>
<keyword>response to intervention</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>School Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In order to develop the Brief Behavior, Academic, and Social Screener (B-BASS), an experimental measure for identifying students at risk for academic underachievement and for predicting performance on high-stakes tests, data were obtained from elementary teachers for 198 third- through fifth-grade rural elementary students in the Southeastern United States. Teachers provided ratings on items within the following global domains: cognitive ability, social/emotional traits, socioeconomic and family characteristics, and executive functions using a brief, practical, contextually appropriate format, one sensitive to local norms. Results reveal strong test-retest correlations (&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt; indices &gt; .95) and moderate to high inter-correlations among the items. Based on a multiple linear regression analysis, B-BASS domain scores account for 81.4% and 66.2% of the variance in North Carolina End-of-Grade Tests of English Language Arts/Reading and Mathematics, respectively. These values are impressive given the brief administration time of the B-BASS, approximately 1 minute per student. Based on a stepwise analysis, two items significantly predict English Language Arts/Reading; specifically, Reading Ability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) and Effort (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .005). Predictors of Mathematics in order of magnitude are Math Ability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) and Hyperactivity (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001). According to discriminant function and ROC curve analyses, B-BASS items also significantly predict proficient vs non-proficient status from the ELA (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) and Math (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) EOGs, with true positive rates of 93.9% and 85.4%, respectively. B-BASS composites predict 78.5% of variance in ELA EOG scores, with the strongest predictors being Academic Ability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001), Social Adaptability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .05), and Executive Function (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .005). For the EOG Mathematics scores, the strongest composite predictors, in order of magnitude, are: Academic Ability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001), Overall Ability (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .05), Home Support (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .05), and Executive Function (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .05); these domain scores predict 66.2% of the variance. Composites also predict significantly categorical status (proficient vs non-proficient) on the ELA (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) and Math (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) EOGs; classification accuracy was determined to be 92.9% and 91.4%, respectively. Implications of using B-BASS are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4621</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6183&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4621</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6183</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-15T18:38:30-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/6183/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10311915</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4621</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry M. Bell, Tara C. Moore, David F. Cihak, Bruce A. Bracken</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>School Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>