<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Where are the Resources?: Discussing Mental Health in Students of Color on UTK’s Campus and the Call for Action</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-22T11:56:16-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>zcummin1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cummings</lname>
<fname>Zhannae</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dwalke61@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Walker</lname>
<fname>Diandra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Mental Health</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Counselor Education</discipline>
<discipline>Multicultural Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Race and Ethnicity</discipline>
<discipline>Sociology of Culture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Racial minority groups experience disparities in mental health and are prone to having more detrimental outcomes than their white counterparts. Current events have heightened the exposure of racial injustices experienced by communities of Black, Indigenous and people of Color (BIPOC). Given this context, the elimination of mental health disparities in people of Color requires critical attention and diligent work more so now than ever before. Culture, climate, and intrinsic bias leave some institute of higher education more challenged in promoting and supporting education for students of Color. Therefore, the purpose of this presentation is to educate participants about mental health in racial minority groups and highlight resources that are available to students of Color on and off campus. The discussion in this session will focus around what are “effective” mental health resources while addressing the lack of accessibility in these communities. This will tie in to how mental health can affect other areas of a person’s health, such as spiritual and physical, which can cause additional stress on students of Color attending predominantly white institutions (PWIs). A call to action will end the session on what additional mental and physical health resources the participants believe students should have access to while attending the University of Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2021/session3/2</coverpage-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1257</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-05T12:28:23-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1257/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>20941596</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2021/session3/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Zhannae Cummings has a BS in Exercise Science and Secondary Education from Lee University. Now at the University of Tennessee, Zhannae is a 2nd year MPH student concentrating on Community Health Education and completing a Health Policy Certificate. As a research assistant, Zhannae focuses on rape prevention education across Tennessee. As a teaching assistant she supports Public Health introductory courses for undergraduates. Upon graduation, Zhannae plans serve low socioeconomic Black communities as a Health Educator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diandra Walker graduated from the University of Dayton with a BSE in Exercise Science and a BS in Psychology. She is currently a second-year master’s student at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville studying Kinesiology with a concentration in Sport Psychology and Motor Behavior. She also serves as a Graduate Research Assistant in the Office of Multicultural Student Life. In this position, she co-advises two student organizations within the office, co-instructs the Diversity Educator Training Course and leads the mental health initiative, #LIFT_ME. She hopes to take her education to the next level and aspires to help others achieve their goals in their respective fields.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Monitor</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>Participants will gain knowledge in how mental health is perceived in the Black community
Participants will take away an understanding of the resources available to students on UTK’s campus
Participants will understand the strengths and challenges of the lack of resources available</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;In order to manifest hope, health and healing, students need to be aware of the mental health resources available to them to get to a place where they are able to be successful in the completion of their degree. Our presentation highlights disparities in mental health care that need to be addressed in order for students of Color to better navigate their own journey toward manifesting hope, health and healing. At the end, we will provide participants with a deep-dive into the mental health resources as well as allow participants to vocalize additional resources that should be accessible on UT’s campus.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>