<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identification of purinyl-cobamide as a novel corrinoid cofactor of tetrachloroethene reductive dehalogenases in &lt;i&gt;Desulfitobacterium&lt;/i&gt; spp.</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mbi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bi</lname>
<fname>Meng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>purinylcobamide</keyword>
<keyword>corrinoid</keyword>
<keyword>desulfitobacterium</keyword>
<keyword>reductive dechlaorination</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Microbiology and Microbial Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Corrinoids (e.g. vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;) [cyanocobalamin] are a group of structurally similar, cobaltcontaining tetrapyrrole compounds involved in a number of important biochemical reactions. In organohalide respiration, vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; analogues carrying different lower bases are obligate cofactors for the reductive dehalogenases (RDases) that catalyze reductive dechlorination reactions. The focus of this research was on the isolation and characterization of a novel natural corrinoid cofactor that enables the dechlorination-coupled energy conservation in organohaliderespiring &lt;em&gt;Desulfitobacterium &lt;/em&gt;strains. Analysis of the purified corrinoid in the cyano form using a combination of high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), UV-Vis [Ultraviolet–visible spectroscopy] and ultra-performance liquid chromatography-high-resolution mass spectrometry (UPLC-HRMS) demonstrated that this novel corrinoid is different than the currently known naturally occurring corrinoids in the lower base structure. Analysis by &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;N [nitrogen isotope 15] isotope labeling methods suggested a lower base with the molecular formula C&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;N&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; [purine] (ligand form). Proton (&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H) and correlation spectroscopy (COSY) NMR [Nuclear magnetic resonance] experiments corroborated that purine is the lower base, and Co&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;-purinyl-Co&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;-cyanocobamide [cobalt alpha-purinyl-cobalt beta-cyanocobamide] (purinylcobamide) is a novel corrinoid. The dechlorination-supporting function of purinylcobamide was validated using corrinoid-auxotrophic &lt;em&gt;Dehalobacter restrictus &lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Dhb&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;em&gt;Dehalococcoides mccartyi &lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Dhc&lt;/em&gt;) pure cultures expressing distinct RDases. Indistinguishable bacterial growth and dechlorination rates compared to vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;-amended cultures were observed in &lt;em&gt;Dhb &lt;/em&gt;but not &lt;em&gt;Dhc &lt;/em&gt;cultures, demonstrating iv distinct cofactor requirements. Overall, the discovery of purinylcobamide emphasizes that the diversity and functions of corrinoids, especially the lower base structures to organaohalide-respiring bacteria, need to be fully understood to implement successful bioremediation for chlorinated solvents contamination.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3561</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4948&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3561</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4948</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-11-10T20:40:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7830846</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3561</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank E. Loeffler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Alison Buchan, Karen lloyd, Qiang He</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>