<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Conceptual design and layout of the balance of plant for a generation IV nuclear power plant using the Westinghouse International Reactor, Innovative &amp; Secure (IRIS)</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Wesley</fname>
<mname>Charles</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research is to develop a conceptual design and layout of a balance of plant for a Generator IV nuclear power plant using the Westinghouse International Reactor, Innovative &amp; Secure (IRIS). This encompasses the background research of the nuclear primary system, selection of important components, mathematical modeling of the system and components, solid modeling of the components, layout of the system, and visualization. The system is 1000 MW thermal and 360 MW electric. It has six feed water heaters and dual reheat with one high pressure and one low-pressure tandem compound turbogenerator unit. The sizes and the weights of these components along with the piping involved with the layout are determined. The final layout of the plant is 100 meters long by 40 meters wide with an approximate weight of 7400 tons. Drawings of the layouts and the components are created along with the solid models. With these results the further development of the system as well as the fabrication and modularization studies can be pursued. The study also can be used to find areas in the plant design that warrant further development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6016</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7649&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6016</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7649</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467678</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6016</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence Townsend</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Laurence Miller, Fred Mynatt</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>