<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>THE EFFECTIVENESS OF MIXED REALITY-BASED INTERVENTION FOR CHILDREN WITH AUTISM SPECTRUM DISORDERS: A META-ANALYSIS AND SINGLE-CASE STUDY</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bkim23@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>Byungkeon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The development of technology has led to the development of various software and application as well as computer-based devices, and is extending its influence even to the mixed reality domain. These technologies are being used actively in the education field for students without disabilities as well as for students with disabilities. In recent years, the instructional application of technology has been accelerated by the development and dissemination of hand-held smart devices. These technologies are increasingly promoting the participation of students with ASD in education and rehabilitation programs. Currently, the number of apps developed as interventions for students with ASD is consistently on the rise, and researchers are presenting findings through various experimental studies showing whether these technologies can effectively educate and involve students with ASD in a learning process. The purpose of this dissertation was to investigate the effects of mixed reality-based intervention studies to date and to provide evidences for teaching effectiveness from examining the areas less covered by researchers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4842</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6382&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4842</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6382</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-08T14:09:17-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13276558</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4842</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David F. Cihak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mari Beth Coleman-Lopatic, Yujeong Park, Christopher H. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>