<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>2011 Rothrock Lecture</title>
<publication-date>2011-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Feldner-Hoehne</lname>
<fname>Felicia</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Yarn</lname>
<fname>Barbara Lynne</fname>
<mname>Ivey</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The ETLA Board is pleased to present the 2011 Rothrock Speakers,  Felicia Felder-Hoehne, a research librarian at the University of  Tennessee, and her sister, Dr. Barbara Lynne Ivey Yarn, MD, a renowned  anesthesiologist, former scientific researcher in mammalian genetics at  ORNL, and pain management specialist.  They will discuss their early  experiences with libraries, their education in the segregated schools of  Knoxville, their careers, and the changes they’ve witnessed.  The  lecture will explain some of the motivation the sisters received from  their elders and outstanding teachers, the parental guidance so critical  to their philosophy of service, the duties and rewards of civic  involvement instilled in them by the pioneers of the Civil Rights  Movement, and their desire to help others—to give something back to  their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lecture will be of interest to those seeking a better  understanding of Knoxville African American history and will introduce  useful resources to those researching the Knoxville African American  community.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_rothrock11/1</coverpage-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>audiovideo</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-24T09:05:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>2011 Rothrock Lecture</publication-title>
<context-key>2074827</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_rothrock11/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>https://stream.lib.utk.edu/embed/stream.php?file=instruction/rrl.mp4&amp;w=960&amp;h=540</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>