<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Two Essays on Momentum Strategy and Its Sources of Abnormal Returns</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>yzhang16@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Zhang</lname>
<fname>Yu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Momentum Strategy</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation studies the sources of the momentum abnormal returns.  The first essay attempts to find the relative role of cross-sectional and time-series variances in generating returns from the momentum strategy.  By decomposing the returns from the momentum strategy both theoretically and empirically, the first essay finds that own-stock autocovariance is an important source in generating momentum returns.  More interestingly, the own-stock autocovariance comes primarily from the loser portfolio.  This finding provides another explanation to the recent finding that the loser portfolio is the driving force of the momentum abnormal returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the above discovery from the first essay, the second essay attempts to find out the underlying reason for the important asymmetric own-stock autocovaraince from the loser portfolio.  We find that this return predictability comes from the short-selling constraints and risks.  Stocks with more severe short-selling constraints prevent pessimistic information from being released into the stock prices more quickly; and thus causes those stocks to be overpriced and auto-correlated in their returns.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/931</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1959&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>931</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1959</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-17T12:27:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1453091</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/931</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George C. Philippatos</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Phillip Daves, Larry Fauver, Jan Rosinski</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>