<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Authentic, Resilient &amp; Tenacious (ART): The Power of Black Female Leadership</title>
<publication-date>2020-01-13T13:17:21-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jsamuel@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Samuel</lname>
<fname>Javiette Vashann</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Power of Black Female Leadership</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Many women aspire to be leaders. Women in general, and black women in particular are frequently faced with addressing systemic barriers and obstacles as they pursue leadership opportunities. Difficult conversations related to gender equity, gender fairness, and historical causes of underrepresentation in leadership positions are the norm. It is important to cultivate deeper relationships and interactions with each other while dealing with these issues as we provide a platform for those who share a common interest in increasing the number and skills of female leaders in their fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop will focus on aspects of authentic leadership and explore ways to support and empower black women to excel personally and professionally. Practical tips, tools, and strategies will be provided as Dr. Samuel encourages participants to be their best self in their field, on campus, at work, and in the community. The workshop will encourage professional development and address mentoring as a mechanism to identify and achieve personal, educational, and professional aspirations. At a time when we have up to five generations in the workforce, it is critical to help women at all stages understand the ART of advancement and success.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2020/BIC20/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1253&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1253</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-07T07:47:16-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>16124214</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2020/BIC20/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Javiette Samuel serves as Assistant Vice Chancellor for Diversity and Engagement. She has over 20 years of professional experience at land-grant universities including PWIs and HBCUs. She leads efforts to create and strengthen partnerships between the University of Tennessee, faculty, staff, students, and external stakeholders while cultivating relationships with key partners and advancing the diversity and inclusion agenda. Samuel works with units across campus by connecting UT’s knowledge with the community in mutually beneficial ways; provides resources to assist university and community partners in addressing issues of concern to society; and supports internal and external partnerships that generate, apply, transmit, and preserve knowledge. She has served as an administrator at the University of Kentucky and Kentucky State University. She also spent nearly nine years at Tennessee State University as an Extension Specialist/Associate Professor/Program Leader focusing on research-based outreach and evidence-based programs. In all of her work she has built and sustained meaningful networks, partnerships, equity-minded practices, and culturally-grounded pedagogies that can be enacted to foster the success of all stakeholders. Samuel earned her bachelors, masters and doctorate from the University of Tennessee, Knoxville.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will examine the intersectionality of gender and race as it relates to leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will explore leadership characteristics such as authenticity, resilience, and tenacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will identify opportunities for networking, empowerment, and getting involved in leadership programs at their institutions, workplace, and community organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The workshop relates to the conference theme &lt;em&gt;Breaking the Cycle of a People Divided&lt;/em&gt; because it addresses some of the issues and barriers that can often divide underrepresented groups (i.e. gender, inequity, class). It will offer some tips and solutions for addressing the aforementioned.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>