<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Quantum Mechanical Study of the Decomposition of CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;  in the Presence of AlF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jiang</lname>
<fname>Bangwu</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Keffer</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The effect of AlF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; on the decomposition of CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; is investigated using ab initio theory. Previous work by Pancansky et al. [Pacansky, J.; Waltman, R. &lt;em&gt;J. J Fluorine Chem.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1997&lt;/strong&gt;, 83, 41] showed that AlF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; significantly reduces the activation energy of the decomposition of CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; due to the strong electrostatic interaction between the aluminum trifluoride and the reactant. In this work, a new transition-state structure and reaction mechanism have been identified for the decomposition of CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in the presence of AlF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. This new mechanism shows that AlF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; functions by accepting a fluorine atom from one carbon and simultaneously donating a fluorine atom to the other carbon. We show that the same pathway is obtained independently of the level of theory. The reaction rate, generated via statistical mechanics and transition-state theory, is 2−3 orders of magnitude higher for the new transition state when compared to that of the old one. The study was also performed for CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OCF&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CF&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in order to ascertain the effect of chain length on the reaction mechanism and rate. We find that an analogous transition state, with lower activation energy, provides the lowest-energy path for decomposition of the longer chain.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_chembiopubs/31</coverpage-url>
<label>31</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-21T06:58:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>1323178</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_chembiopubs/31</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Bangwu Jiang, David J. Keffer, Brian J. Edwards. (2008). A Quantum Mechanical Study of the Decomposition of CF3OCF3 and CF3CF2OCF2CF3 in the Presence of AlF3. 
The Journal of Physical Chemistry A, 112 (12), 2604-2609</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/jp0768017</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>