<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Small Scale Population Structure of Pityopsis ruthii and P. graminifolia var. latifolia</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sbogges1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Boggess</lname>
<fname>Sarah</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Pityopsis ruthii</keyword>
<keyword>Pityopsis graminifolia var. latifolia</keyword>
<keyword>Microsatellites</keyword>
<keyword>Population analyses</keyword>
<keyword>Genetic diversity</keyword>
<keyword>Endangered plant</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pityopsis graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var.&lt;em&gt; latifolia &lt;/em&gt;(Michx.) Small var. &lt;em&gt;latifolia &lt;/em&gt;(Fern.) or narrowleaf silkgrass is an herbaceous perennial native to the southeastern United States and northern Central America. &lt;em&gt;Pityopsis ruthii &lt;/em&gt;(Small) Small is an endangered plant endemic to the Hiwassee and Ocoee Rivers in Polk County, Tennessee. Little is known about the genetic diversity and population structure of both &lt;em&gt;Pityopsis&lt;/em&gt; species as well as the phylogenic relationships between the species. In this study, 16 microsatellite loci were used to assess genetic diversity and population structure of 261 individuals of &lt;em&gt;P. ruthii&lt;/em&gt; (n=167) and &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var.&lt;em&gt; latifolia &lt;/em&gt;(n=76)&lt;em&gt;. Pityopsis ruthii &lt;/em&gt;is characterized as a diploid whereas &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var.&lt;em&gt; latifolia &lt;/em&gt;is characterized as a tetraploid&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Because of unknown ploidy&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;of &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var. &lt;em&gt;latifolia, &lt;/em&gt;Polysat, a package in program R, was used to infer ploidy of the individuals. Arlequin and GenAlEx were utilized to calculate genetic diversity measurements. The genetic software STRUCTURE and BAPS used Bayesian cluster analyses to group individuals based on multilocus genotypes, and were used to evaluate the genetic structure and gene flow. Samples of &lt;em&gt;Pityopsis ruthii&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var.&lt;em&gt; latifolia &lt;/em&gt;were analyzed as one data set and separated by species to ensure accurate results. Analyses in GenAlEx for all data sets resulted in low Shannon’s information index (I=0.13-0.14), and expected heterozygosity ranged from 0.08-0.09. Analysis of molecular variance indicated that the majority of the variation is within populations with moderate to higher genetic differentiation when &lt;em&gt;P. ruthii&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var&lt;em&gt;. latifolia&lt;/em&gt; are analyzed together or &lt;em&gt;P. ruthii&lt;/em&gt; alone ([genetic differentiation] Φ&lt;sub&gt;PT&lt;/sub&gt; =0.13 and 0.18, respectively). Low levels of genetic differentiation (Φ&lt;sub&gt;PT&lt;/sub&gt; =0.02) were found when &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var.&lt;em&gt; latifolia &lt;/em&gt;was analyzed independently. STRUCTURE revealed three clusters with &lt;em&gt;P. ruthii &lt;/em&gt;clustering by watershed and &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var&lt;em&gt;. latifolia &lt;/em&gt;resulting in one cluster. When analyzed separately, &lt;em&gt;P. graminifolia &lt;/em&gt;var. &lt;em&gt;latifolia&lt;/em&gt; indicated presence of three clusters with considerable admixture in each cluster. Analysis with BAPS provided similar results as found with STRUCTURE when a fixed K was selected. Understanding the population structure and genetic diversity will aid in the creation of guidelines for conservation programs of &lt;em&gt;P. ruthii. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2596</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3664&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2596</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3664</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-12T12:19:26-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3664/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4702260</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2596</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert N. Trigiano</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Phillip A. Wadl, William E. Klingeman, Alan S. Windham</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Entomology and Plant Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>