<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using MOM:TIPS as a Short-Term Inservice with Four Day-Care Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tanner</lname>
<fname>Kathryn</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Four day-care teachers were introduced to Methods of Mothering: Training in Parenting Styles (MOM:TIPS), which is a parent-training program that has never been used with teachers.  Modules addressing Self-Management, Disciplining/Monitoring, Nurturing, and Teaching Concepts were presented in an inservice training.  Four workshops and available one-to-one consultations occurred over the period of one month.  Each teacher was evaluated as a single-case in an A-B design using direct observations and self-report questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Self-Management, each teacher reported that she makes daily schedules and follows a routine, but Teachers A, D indicated that they rarely or never used the steps involving more methodical, record-keeping methods.  With Disciplining/Monitoring, Teachers B, C showed modest increases in Catching Good Behavior.  With Nurturing, Teachers A, B were observed Smiling and engaging in Active Contact more often; Teacher C showed higher percentages of Active and Passive Contact during the Training Period.  Teacher B’s increases continued at Follow-Up.  A Spearman’s rho analysis found significant correlations between children’s positive responses and certain affectionate behaviors with each teacher.  With Teaching Concepts, Teachers A, D used each step during Baseline; Teachers B, C were observed implementing the steps either during Training or Follow-Up.  Each self-report indicated frequent implementation of most of the strategies and that overall teaching styles were generally congruent with MOM:TIPS.  Methodological limitations are addressed and recommendations are provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4588</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6294&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4588</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6294</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-25T11:49:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10805180</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4588</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Donald Dickinson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sandra Twardosz, Thomas W. George, Katherine Greenberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>