<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Influence of Texture and Grain Size on the Plastic Anisotropy in a Wrought Mg Alloy: Synchrotron X-ray Diffraction and Visco-plastic Self-consistent Modeling</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ywang62@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Yi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Magnesium</keyword>
<keyword>Grain size</keyword>
<keyword>Texture</keyword>
<keyword>Slip</keyword>
<keyword>Twin</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Metallurgy</discipline>
<discipline>Structural Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The combined effects of texture and grain size on the yielding and hardening behavior in a hot-rolled AZ31B Mg alloy were studied by using synchrotron x-ray diffraction and visco-plastic self-consistent (VPSC) simulation methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the influence of texture on Hall-Petch relationships (namely, critical resolved shear stresses and hardening parameters) in a Mg alloy was investigated to establish a constitutive basis for the VPSC simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, the changes in dominant deformation mechanisms (basal, prismatic, and pyramidal slip as well as extension twin) and their relative interactions were studied systematically as a function of the initial texture using a VPSC scheme. The simulation results provide basic understanding of the effect of texture on the hardening behaviors in terms of the interaction of various active deformation mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the interplay between the texture and grain size effects on the activation of multiple deformation mechanisms and the plastic anisotropy was studied by incorporating the Hall-Petch Relationship in the VPSC modeling scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the influence of {1012} extension twin on the texture and microstructure evolution was investigated to understand physical implications of the simulation results. Specifically, the hardening anisotropy introduced by extension twin was studied with a focus on dislocation-twin interactions in terms of texture hardening, size hardening, and glissile-to-sessile transition hardening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current study provides a basic micromechanical understanding of the effects of complex interactions among texture, loading path, and grain size on the yielding and hardening behavior of a wrought Mg alloy through plasticity simulations and diffraction measurements. The results would help improving the formability and advancing manufacturing techniques of wrought Mg alloy components for structural applications.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3179</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4319&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3179</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4319</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-09-09T12:52:45-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4319/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6096086</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3179</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hahn Choo</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Yanfei Gao, Peter K. Liaw, Dayakar Penumadu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>