<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hikers in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park - Their Attitudes, Characteristics, and Implications for Management</title>
<publication-date>1973-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Marsh</lname>
<fname>Gary</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main objective of this study was to obtain information about trail users, primarily hikers, in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park (GSMNP), which would aid decision-makers in managing the wilderness resource for optimum benefits from hiking trails. I nformation was gathered by the use of a questionnaire to determine various socioeconomic characteristics of users, their motivations for hiking, and their attitudes toward trail use and management within the GSMNP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The questionnaire was administered in a personal interview with respondents as they were hiking on selected trails within the park. Five-hundred and fifty-eight interviews were completed at eleven sampling locations within the park in five sampling periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chi-square tests were used to test various relationships of socio-economic data, user preferences, and attitudes toward management of the resource area. In most cases simple frequency distributions and percentages sufficed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hikers tended to travel in small groups usually consisting of three to four members per party and were generally young to middle-aged adults. Overnight hikers&quot; length of stay was generally four to five days on trips into the backcountry. The study supported the findings about many of the socio-economic characteristics of hikers in other wilderness-type areas. Users tended to have college educations, have higher incomes in comparison to the regional population, and have urban residences. Hikers were aware of other hiking areas and opportunities other than the GSMNP but hiked infrequently in these other areas. The majority of users spent over half of their total hiking experience within the GSMNP. Accessibility, uniqueness of the area, and certain status motive preferences were prime motivational factors of hikers coming to this National park, Attitudes toward limiting use of overnight shelter facilities within the backcountry were generally favorable. Horse use of trails and hiking on these same trails were generally thought to be noncompatible uses among the respondents interviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain implications for management were derived from this study. Educational programs should be developed and coordinated among all recreational organizations and agencies. Redistribution of use within the park could possibly be accomplished with such measures as: closing Highway 441 to traffic within the park and providing public conveyance; and providing exclusive dayhiking trails by using proper site design, planning, and reinforcing certain trails. Further research, including in-depth studies of hikers, is needed to determine various psychological and physical carrying capacities of the hiking resource. Trail management will continue to be less than fully effective and efficient without more complete knowledge about the resource and the people who use it.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2528</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3894&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2528</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3894</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-12T15:05:18-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4921216</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2528</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kerry F. Schell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John C. Rennie, Edward R. Buckner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Forestry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1973-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>