<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The relationship of job stress and job satisfaction in the service work environment</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Stevens</lname>
<fname>Cynthia</fname>
<mname>Dawn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main purpose in conducting this study was to examine the relationship between certain job characteristics, personal demographics, and job stress among service worker employees. Another purpose was aimed specifically at providing current data concerning the elements of work that could induce job stress through job dissatisfaction, thus updating the body of knowledge on the subject. Lastly, by increasing the body of knowledge concerning the problems associated with service worker work, human resource professionals are better informed of suggested areas in need of improvement. In return, they can better attend to and facilitate employees&#39; health and quality of life issues.  The researcher surveyed 300 participants who were service workers in East Tennessee. The respondents were sent a booklet containing demographic questions and two surveys: the Job Satisfaction Survey for assessing overall level of job satisfaction and the Job Stress Survey for assessing total job stress of the total participants. Statistical methods utilized in this study included calculating mean, standard deviations, one-way analysis of variances (.05 level of probability with 95% confidence interval), multiple analyses of variances, and Tukey tests for significance. Finally, the Pearson r test was used to test any relationships between job characteristics, personal demographics, and Job Satisfaction Survey or Job Stress Survey.  Major findings of the study showed that (a) employees with a college degree encountered a higher level of total job stress than those with only a high school degree or those no longer pursuing an educational goal; (b) employees with college degrees seemed to experience stress more frequently; ( c) employees with college degrees appeared to be less satisfied with their job than those with a lesser degree or no high school degree; ( d) there appears to be a trend that as overtime increases so does levels of stress; ( e) employees asked to work overtime three or more times each week had significantly higher levels of stress due to the frequency of the requests; and (f) employees who received an award of appreciation for service or performance had a significantly higher level of satisfaction than those who did not receive any form of recognition. Finally, results showed that as any type of stress increased, job satisfaction decreased.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5298</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6706&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5298</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6706</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847227</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5298</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>