<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Relationship Between Teachers’ Beliefs and Observed Practices: The Voices of Two Head Start Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sphelps4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Phelps</lname>
<fname>Stephani</fname>
<mname>Michelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>teacher beliefs</keyword>
<keyword>teacher practice</keyword>
<keyword>early childhood education</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Pre-Elementary, Early Childhood, Kindergarten Teacher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined Head Start teachers’ interactions with children in relation to teachers’ beliefs about decision making and roles in various classroom activities. The purposes of this study were to (a) document preschool teachers’ verbal interactions with children and (b) explore the relationship between teachers’ beliefs and their classroom practices. Participants were from two Head Start classrooms in East Tennessee, which included two teachers and 40 children ranging in age from 3-5 years. Approximately two hours of focal child observations were completed for each child over the course of 7 months. Observations captured teachers’ interactions with focal children. Two semistructured interviews with teachers were completed to gain insight into their beliefs and perceptions about their decision making and classroom roles. The qualitative findings indicate that both teachers’ held similar child-centered beliefs. The quantitative findings revealed specific observed practices that illuminated their reported personal beliefs. Implications for future research and practice include (a) the value of a focal-child and interview methodology for investigating the relationship of teachers’ beliefs and practice; and (b) the value of examining teachers’ personal-practical knowledge for understanding the linkages between teachers’ pedagogical and relational knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4064</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5064&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4064</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5064</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-23T13:10:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8200029</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4064</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Jane Moran</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hillary N. Fouts, Julia Jaekel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Child and Family Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>