<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Untangling Motivation and Performance: Examining the Impact of Feedback, Expectancy, and Resilience on Performance</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ejenki10@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Jenkins</lname>
<fname>Erica</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>resilience</keyword>
<keyword>motivation</keyword>
<keyword>performance</keyword>
<keyword>performance feedback</keyword>
<keyword>expectancy theory</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study explored the relationship between motivation and performance by examining factors, such as feedback and individual differences, posited to influence motivation and performance. The most damaging form of performance feedback, destructive critical, was contrasted with constructive critical feedback to determine its impact on motivation. Expectancy theory, a mainstay theory in research on motivation, served as the theoretical framework to study motivation. An individual difference variable, resilience, was examined in relation to performance. These relationships were explored through the lens of both actual and perceived performance. An online quasi-experiment was conducted to examine these relationships, in which participants were asked to complete a task, receive feedback and then complete the task a second time. This study expanded understanding of the motivation-performance relationship and provided epistemological depth to the individual variables being studied.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5519</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6992&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5519</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6992</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914314</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5519</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joan R. Rentsch</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michelle Violanti, John Haas</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>