<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Influence of Point-of-Purchase Cafeteria-Based Nutrition Education Program on High School Students</title>
<publication-date>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gamio</lname>
<fname>Magali</fname>
<mname>O.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Male and female high school students participated in an intervention designed to promote behavior change in food selection. The students were divided in two groups. Group I received the point-of-purchase cafeteria-based nutrition education program, and Group II received the point-of-purchase cafeteria based nutrition program plus a brief classroom nutrition education intervention. Evaluation instruments included pre-test, post-test 1, and post-test 2 written questionnaires, which included food practices, nutrition knowledge, attitudes and their perceptions about the school food service and the point-of-purchase intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For behavior change, there was a significant Time Effect for females Group II with a significant decrease in both fat and vitamin C. Both genders in Group II had a significant decrease in energy intake. Males in Group II had a significant decrease in their fat intake and intakes of calcium and vitamin D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the comparison of the subjects&#39; mean nutrient intakes at lunch intakes showed that energy for both males and females was below one-third of the RDA, the standard for the National School Lunch Program. For calcium and iron males met one-third of the RDA, while females did not. For vitamins A and C, both genders were above the standard while for vitamin D, both genders were below the RDA. Both genders were above the ≤30% guideline for proportion of energy from fat; 34% and 31% for males and females, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For nutrition knowledge, there was no significant difference for Time Effect or for Group Effect for either gender. For nutrition attitudes, there was a significant decrease in positive nutrition attitudes only for males Group II. For Group Effect, no significant difference was found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frequency of selection for certain targeted foods showed that for Group I there was a significant increase in their selection of fresh fruit. And for females in Group II, there was a significant increase in their selection of low fat milks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Expected taste&quot; was the reason the students gave for choosing the foods they did on the designated days. Three-fourths of the students states that the Best Choice signs near the serving line &quot;were a good idea&quot;. Recommendation for greater changes in behavior, knowledge, and attitudes include a longer, more focused classroom nutrition education component and cafeteria serving styles which allow students more choices, especially among vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3765</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5415&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3765</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5415</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-07-29T12:43:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8899042</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3765</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jean D. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jim Moran, Carl Dyer, Mark McGrath</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>