<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Exploration of Transitioning Registered Handler-Animal Therapy from the Institution to the Community</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>analeah.green@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Walden University</institution>
<lname>Green</lname>
<fname>Analeah</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Affairs, Public Policy and Public Administration</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The older adult population is growing across the nation. Many older adults reside in New York State and choosing to age-in-place or in their community. While traditional talk therapy services are provided through community-based organizations, minimal attention has been given to animal assisted therapy (AAT). AAT has primarily been utilized in institutional settings, leaving a gap in service delivery to older adults aging in the community. Guided by the human-companion animal bond (HCAB) conceptual framework and the theoretical frameworks by Ferdinand Tönnnies (&lt;em&gt;Gemeinschaft &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Gesellschaft) &lt;/em&gt;and Emile Durkheim (mechanic and organic solidarity), survey data on attitudes and perceptions of animal handlers for AAT and the concept of community care will be explored using a qualitative, phenomenological research study design. Data will be analyzed using content analysis for themes in order to better understand the experiences of registered handlers. Due to physical limitations and a variety of losses associated with the aging process, the mental health and emotional stability of older adults require attention from community-based programs in which aging-in-place elders are receiving services to aide them in living independently and safely in their home. This study will effect social change by providing opportunity to explore integrating AAT into existing community based infrastructures to meet the emotional and psychological needs of aging New Yorkers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/18</coverpage-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1046</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-11-16T08:41:32-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3474030</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Analeah Green holds a Bachelor of Arts degree in Sociology from the State University of New York College at Cortland and a Master of Social Work (MSW) degree from New York University. She is a PhD candidate in Human Services, specializing in Administration and Leadership with Walden University. As a Licensed Master of Social Work in New York State she has worked in a case management capacity assessing and providing concrete services to a range of client populations. She is currently working on her dissertation titled “An Exploration of Transitioning Registered Handler-Animal Therapy from the Institution to the Community.”&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Analeah Green&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;153-30 79th Street&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Beach, NY, 11414&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home: 718-843-0662&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cell: 646-357-6842&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CUMBERLAND ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Poster: Scheduled poster session</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T16:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>