<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A computer administered version versus paper-and-pencil administered version of the MMPI-A</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hays</lname>
<fname>Shannon</fname>
<mname>Kathleen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Within the context of a counterbalanced design, 102 students from a high school and a large university in the southeast were administered two versions of the Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory-Adolescent (MMPI-A): a computer-administered version (CA) and a paper-and-pencil version (PAP). Time between testing sessions was approximately one week. Differences in individual scale means between the CA and PAP were calculated using paired t-tests, with the Bonferroni correction procedure; no mean differences were significant (p. &gt; .05). To determine if the scale distributions were similar, tests of homogeneity of variance were conducted using Hartley&#39;s homogeneity of variance tests; there were no differences in the shapes of the scale distributions (p. &gt; .05). Pearson product-moment coefficients were calculated for each scale to determine if the relative rankings were similar; coefficients for every scale were positive and statistically significant (p. &lt; .01). Implications of the findings of this study are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6241</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8193&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6241</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8193</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450336</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6241</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William H. Calhoun, Thomas W. George, Theodore W. Hipple</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>