<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effectiveness of Computer Assisted Instruction of Chapter I Students in Secondary Schools</title>
<publication-date>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davidson</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Lloyd</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The major purpose of this study was to determine the effectiveness of computer assisted instruction in the mathematics classroom. Mathematics achievement scores of Chapter I students receiving only traditional instruction were compared to mathematics achievement scored of Chapter I students using computer assisted instruction. Chapter I students from grades 9, 10, 11, and 12 at Fulton High School, Knoxville, Tennessee, were chosen. Form J of the Metropolitan Instructional Mathematics Test was administered to establish the initial level of students&#39; mathematical achievement. Thirty-six students were in the control group and 18 were in the experimental group. The 18 students in the experimental group utilized computers in mathematics instruction and the 36 students in the control group did not use computers. To control for variation, each group was taught by the same teacher, used the same books, curriculum guide and materials. Both groups were tested after a 13-week program by the Metropolitan Instructional Mathematics Test, Form J. The scores of both the computer assisted instruction group and the control group were compared by using an Analysis of Covariance. The results of this analysis indicated that computer assisted instruction did not result in significant gains in mathematics achievement of Chapter I Students.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3285</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4834&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3285</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4834</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-05-20T12:17:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7123341</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3285</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Arnold R. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Dewey H. Stollar, A. Paul Wishart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>