<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Primary and Secondary Immunocompetence in Mixed Allogeneic Chimeras</title>
<publication-date>2003-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tonami@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Onami</lname>
<fname>Thandi</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Adams</lname>
<fname>A.</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Walsh</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Shirasugi</lname>
<fname>N.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Pearson</lname>
<fname>T.</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Ahmed</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Larsen</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Immune System Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Immunity</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology and Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology of Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunopathology</discipline>
<discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Virus Diseases</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Targeted disruption of T cell costimulatory pathways, particularly CD28 and CD40, has allowed for the development of minimally myeloablative strategies for the induction of mixed allogeneic chimerism and donor-specific tolerance across full MHC barriers. In this study we analyze in depth the ability of mixed allogeneic chimeras in two strain combinations to mount effective host-restricted and donor-restricted antiviral CD4 and CD8 responses, as well as the impact of development of mixed chimerism on the maintenance of pre-existing memory populations. While antiviral CD8 responses in mixed chimeras following acute viral infection with lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus Armstrong or vaccinia virus are largely host-restricted, donor-restricted CD8 responses as well as host- and donor-restricted CD4 responses are also readily detected, and virus is promptly cleared. We further demonstrate that selection of donor-restricted T cells in mixed chimeras is principally mediated by bone marrow-derived cells in the thymus. Conversely, we find that mixed chimeras exhibit a deficit in their ability to deal with a chronic lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus clone 13 infection. Encouragingly, pre-existing memory populations are largely unaffected by the development of high level mixed chimerism and maintain the ability to control viral rechallenge. Our results suggest that while pre-existing T cell memory and primary immunocompetence to acute infection are preserved in mixed allogeneic chimeras, MHC class I and/or class II tissue matching may be required to fully preserve immunocompetence in dealing with chronic viral infections.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>2382</fpage>
<lpage>2389</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/21</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1021&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>21</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1021</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-02-08T12:18:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3764010</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/21</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>The Journal of Immunology</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>