<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Synopic Evaluation of Water Quality for Little Yellow Creek in Cumberland Gap National Historic Park</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Thomas</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This purpose of this study was to evaluate the water quality monitoring program in use in Cumberland Gap National Historic Park. Over 10 years of historical water quality data was compiled into a Microsoft Access database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water quality parameters considered indicative of ecosystem or fish health were used to evaluate the program. All sample sites were analyzed by the watershed they corresponded to. The sample mean, normalized confidence interval width, and normalized variance were calculated in order to compare parameters at sites in corresponding watersheds. The percentages of values exceeding EPA and literature water quality standards were also calculated to evaluate the monitoring network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water quality parameters were compared, and a more frequent sampling interval was suggested for various parameters at different network sites. Furthermore, parameters with significant exceedances of water quality standards were also recommended for increased sampling. Cadmium exceeded standards at four sites, all on Little Yellow Creek. Chromium and copper both exceeded acceptable levels at two sites on Little Yellow Creek. Mercury exceeded criteria at site YC1. Dissolved oxygen was recorded at low levels a significant number of times at YC5. Levels of pH did not meet standards at five sites from the entire network. Alkalinity did not meet water quality criteria at twelve of the sites.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4639</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6195&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4639</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6195</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-15T06:06:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10306897</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4639</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randall W. Gentry</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. Bruce Robinson, John S. Schwartz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>