<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Retrieval of Nano-Size Particles from a Solid Substrate</title>
<publication-date>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Podila</lname>
<fname>Krishna</fname>
<mname>Prasad</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mechanical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The retrieval of nano-size particles from suspects and crime scenes can significantly enhance surveillance and crime investigation. The Thesis deals with extensive study of free surface energy coupled with Hertzian contact energy under different conditions between a nano-sized particle and a substrate and the various methods of dislodging the particle. Using the Johnson-Kendall-Roberts (JKR) theory, a physical spring-mass-damper model is defined. Mathematical equations are formulated and solved with non-linear equations simulating the real world situation. Using Newmark’s β method, the system is solved for response of free and forced vibrations taking moisture to be responsible for damping. Key assumptions such as the particle and substrate are perfectly elastic and damping force is linear have been applied. Then a parameter study is conducted on two types of particles. The results have been summarized along with suggestions for future work.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2323</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3724&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2323</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3724</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-16T12:03:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4729021</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2323</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Don W. Dareing</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. A. M. Boulet, John D. Landes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>