<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A strategy for land conservancies to promote sustainable development practices</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Southerland</lname>
<fname>Patricia</fname>
<mname>Kay</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore the possibilities of land conservancies expanding their roles to promote sustainable development practices. Information was collected from national land conservancies through appropriate research methods. Interviews were conducted of the three land conservancies in the United States that are successfully promoting sustainable practices into conservation-based developments. Common elements were identified and a case study was conducted of the Foothills Land Conservancy of East Tenneseee. The director and selected board members were interviewed as to their expertise, skills and interest in expanding the FLC&#39;s role to promote sustainable development practices.   Research revealed that land conservancies are an appropriate agency to engage in promoting sustainable development practices due to the wide range of expertise among the members and staff. However, there are several key elements, which are essential to managing a program of this magnitude. They consist of a knowledgeable staff in various disciplines that correlate with conservation based development practices and an experienced administrator to oversee staff, funding and outreach programs. Another key element is an aggressive fund-raising strategy and an aggressive outreach program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5297</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6705&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5297</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6705</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847225</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5297</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Peine</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Planning</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>