<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Practices and Routines in SIWI Lessons that Develop Skills in Reading</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pskerrit@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Skerrit</lname>
<fname>Paulson</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Strategic Interactive Writing Instruction</keyword>
<keyword>Reading</keyword>
<keyword>Writing</keyword>
<keyword>Deaf and Hard of Hearing</keyword>
<keyword>Literacy</keyword>
<keyword>Reading-Writing Connection</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The average performance of Deaf and hard of hearing (D/hh) students on test of reading comprehension is several grade equivalents below their high school hearing peers. The reading-writing connection is one way to address the literacy challenges of D/hh learners. This study explored that connection in instruction that was driven with a high fidelity to the principles of Strategic Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI). The data for this study came from two grade three classes involved in the second half of a Year II project that was part of a 3-year Institute of Education Sciences-funded project to develop SIWI for use with D/hh students. The video footage of 18 and 31 SIWI lessons spanning two units of instruction in a TC and Bilingual classroom respectively were examined using a comingling of inductive and interpretive analysis and utilizing Spradley’s nine semantic relationships to determine the instructional and learner practices and routines that supported development of word recognition skills. A detailed narrative of the 49 lessons was provided and the following instructional and learner practices and routines were identified: engaging students in cognitively demanding discourse that featured extended discourse and persistence in questioning; a high volume of repeated and wide reading; high volume of writing; multiple representation of words with an emphasis on fingerspelling; and attending to language input. Recommendations made included: adding a high volume of repeated and wide reading as a major pillar of SIWI; informal and standardized reading assessments; individual students should lead the rereading and writing of English sentences; include research as part of planning for writing; and use the back translation approach to signing English text. There is need for further study in the following areas: a comparative analysis of the strategies used in the lowest and highest performing classes; a study that controls for individual practices and routines using multiple regression analysis to determine the variance as predictors of word recognition; an in-depth exploration of recasting; and an analysis of individual student interactions with the practices and routines in the bilingual setting and the relationship of those interactions to gains in word recognition skills.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3609</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4981&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3609</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4981</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-09-22T07:51:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7624558</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3609</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kimberly Ann Wolbers</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Deborah A. Wooten, Stergios Botzakis, Schuyler W. Huck, Richard L. Allington</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>