<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Distance Sampling to Assess Post-Grazing Northern Bobwhite Recovery in South Texas</title>
<publication-date>2017-11-08T08:29:09-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rachelasmith14@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University, Kingsville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>leonard.brennan@tamuk.edu</email>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University, Kingsville</institution>
<lname>Brennan</lname>
<fname>Leonard</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>fidel.hernandez@tamuk.edu</email>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University, Kingsville</institution>
<lname>Hernández</lname>
<fname>Fidel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University, Kingsville</institution>
<lname>Perotto-Baldivieso</lname>
<fname>Humberto</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>distance sampling</keyword>
<keyword>post-grazing recovery</keyword>
<keyword>south Texas</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Natural Resources and Conservation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Northern bobwhite (&lt;em&gt;Colinus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) require habitat structure with substantial grass cover for nesting, predator avoidance, and thermal refuge. During the past 2 decades, many land managers have reduced or completely eliminated livestock across South Texas rangelands with the goal of improving bobwhite habitat. How bobwhites respond to post-grazing habitat recovery is unknown. Our objective is to investigate how bobwhites respond to the vegetative changes following removal of grazing. Our study is being conducted on a private ranch in Jim Hogg County, Texas and involves 3 different areas of post-grazing habitat recovery: a 1,246 ha area rested from grazing for 15 years; a 1,133 ha area rested 3 years from high grazing (7 ha/AU); and a 1,254 ha area rested 3 years from moderate grazing (14 ha/AU). Distance sampling surveys will be conducted on the 3 areas during December 2015 and 2016. Transects will be placed 400 m apart spanning all 3 study. Data collected during these surveys will be used to estimate bobwhite density on the 3 study areas and will be compared between sites and years. We hypothesize that the 15 years post-grazing area will have higher and more evenly distributed bobwhite density than the 3 years post-grazing at high intensity or medium intensity area.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol8/iss1/72</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1540&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>72</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_pop_estimation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1540</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-11-01T08:56:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10980615</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol8/iss1/72</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Distance Sampling to Assess Post-Grazing Northern Bobwhite Recovery</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>