<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthesis and Morphology of Well-Defined Mixed Homopolymer Brushes Grafted on 150 - 180 nm Silica Particles</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cbao@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bao</lname>
<fname>Chunhui</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Mixed homopolymer brushes, composed of two distinct homopolymers randomly or alternatively immobilized by one end on a solid substrate, exhibit intriguing phase behavior. This dissertation work focuses on synthesis and morphology study of well-defined mixed brushes grafted on 150 – 180 nm silica particles. The brushes were grown from asymmetric difunctional initiator (Y-initiator)-functionalized silica particles by using two “living”/controlled polymerization techniques. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1 is an introduction to mixed brushes. Chapter 2 presents a study on the effect of overall grafting density (s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt;) [Sigma overall] on morphology of mixed poly(&lt;em&gt;tert&lt;/em&gt;-butyl acrylate) (P&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;BA)/polystyrene brushes synthesized by sequential surface-initiated atom transfer radical polymerization of &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;BA and nitroxide-mediated radical polymerization (NMRP) of styrene from Y-initiator-functionalized particles. By changing the mass ratio of Y-initiator to silica particles in the initiator immobilization step, a series of brush samples with different s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt; values but similar molecular weights (MW) were synthesized. Transmission electron microscopy showed that at s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt; ³ 0.34 chains/nm&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;[chains/nanometer square], the brushes formed “rippled” structures after cast from chloroform. The normalized ripple wavelength (&lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt;) scaled with s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-0.47&lt;/sup&gt; [sigma overall to the -0.47 power] in the s&lt;sub&gt;overall &lt;/sub&gt;range of 1.06 to 0.54 chains/nm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3 describes a study on the effect of MW on morphology of mixed P&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;BA/PS brushes on silica particles. A series of samples with different average MWs, from 13.8 to 33.1 kDa, but comparable s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt; were made and their morphologies were investigated. For samples cast from chloroform, &lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt; scaled with MW&lt;sup&gt;0.70&lt;/sup&gt; [MW to the 0.7 power] in the studied MW range. For uniformly collapsed mixed brushes cast from water, &lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt; was proportional to MW&lt;sup&gt;0.56&lt;/sup&gt; [MW to the 0.56 power].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4 presents the synthesis of mixed brushes from Y-initiator-functionalized silica particles by surface-initiated ring-opening polymerization and NMRP. The s&lt;sub&gt;overall&lt;/sub&gt; of mixed brushes can be tuned by varying the mass ratio of Y-initiator to silica particles in the initiator immobilization step. Chapter 5 describes the synthesis of two polymer brush acid catalysts and their applications for fructose dehydration to 5-hydroxymethylfurfural in water. Both brush catalysts exhibited a higher catalytic activity than the corresponding free polymer catalysts. Chapter 6 presents conclusions and future work.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3290</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4726&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3290</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4726</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-27T10:58:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6742768</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3290</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bin Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jimmy Mays, Michael Best, Shanfeng Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>