<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1463 Tree Crops for Marginal Farmland - Christmas Trees</title>
<publication-date>2002-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Christmas Trees</keyword>
<keyword>Finances</keyword>
<keyword>Crops</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Growing Christmas trees can be a profitable use for marginally productive farmland. Though more labor-intensive than other tree crops, a Christmas tree crop can return a profit in as little as five to seven years. In addition, Christmas tree production requires little up-front capital investment. Most production operations require only hand tools or common farm machinery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most industry experts predict that Christmas tree markets will remain stable. However, there is a surplus of Christmas trees in many regions of the United States. To be competitive, growers must efficiently produce high-quality trees of the species that consumers demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Christmas trees will continue to remain popular, particularly given their convenience, cleanliness and improved design (making them appear natural). Growers of natural Christmas trees must capitalize on tradition, freshness, aroma, and in the case of choose-and-cut operations, the family experience of &lt;em&gt;bringing one home&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfores/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfores&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>forestry</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-30T13:24:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Forestry, Trees, and Timber</publication-title>
<context-key>1254264</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfores/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1463-1M-2/02(Rev) E12-4915-00-015-02</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>