<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identifying Successful Competitive Intelligence Practices Used in Nonprofits: A Survey of Competitive Intelligence Strategies Used by Professional Fundraisers to Enhance Fundraising Success</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gillis</lname>
<fname>Heidi</fname>
<mname>H</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Competitive intelligence is a popular technique used to gain a competitive advantage in for-profit businesses. This research examines the use of competitive intelligence in nonprofits, particularly how competitive intelligence is used or can be used to enhance fundraising success. A web based survey polled members of the Association of Fundraising Professionals on their uses of specific competitive intelligence strategies, particularly environmental scanning, use of focus groups and database research. It was found that non-profits are using some competitive intelligence methods, but find a lack of time, lack of funds, and lack of staff are prohibiting factors in implementing a full-scale competitive intelligence process. Those who have implemented some competitive intelligence methods have found them to result in increased fundraising success, particularly with increased prospect identification, improved targeted asks (direct solicitations of donors), and an overall increase in donations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1949</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3307&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1949</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3307</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-24T10:32:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4618209</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1949</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kendra Albright</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael Pemberton, Carol Tenopir</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Information Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>