<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1580 2010 Weed Control Manual for Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Weeds</keyword>
<keyword>Crops</keyword>
<keyword>Forages</keyword>
<keyword>Pesticides</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This manual contains the 2010 University of Tennessee weed control recommendations for corn, grain sorghum, cotton, soybeans, burley and dark tobacco, wheat, forage crops, sunflowers and farm ponds. These recommendations are based on results of research and demonstrations conducted by the Agricultural Experiment Station and the Agricultural Extension Service. Decisions regarding recommendations are made by the University of Tennessee Weed Control Committee and are based on available data at various locations in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication contains pesticide recommendations that are subject to change at any time. The recommendations in this publication are provided only as a guide. It is always the pesticide applicator&#39;s responsibility, by law, to read and follow all current label directions for the specific pesticide being used. The label always takes precedence over the recommendations found in this publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of trade or brand names in this publication is for clarity and information; it does not imply approval of the product to the exclusion of others that may be of similar, suitable composition, nor does it guarantee or warrant the standard of the product. The author(s), the University of Tennessee Institute of Agriculture and University of Tennessee Extension assume no liability resulting from the use of these recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexcrop/64</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1063&amp;amp;context=utk_agexcrop&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>64</label>
<document-type>weedsherbicide</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1063</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-30T12:53:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Field &amp; Commercial Crops</publication-title>
<context-key>1254149</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexcrop/64</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1580-6M-12/09(Rev) R12-5110-092-003-10</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>