<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Accuracy of the Progressive Aerobic Cardiovascular Endurance Run to Estimate Aerobic Fitness in Youth</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sscott8@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>Stacy</fname>
<mname>Nicole</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>PACER</keyword>
<keyword>youth</keyword>
<keyword>aerobic fitness</keyword>
<keyword>VO2peak</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The FITNESSGRAM’s Progressive Aerobic Cardiovascular Endurance Run (PACER) test is a commonly used field test to estimate peak oxygen uptake (VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt;) in youth.  However, little research has been conducted to determine the influence of weight status on the accuracy of the equations used to estimate VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt;.  &lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: To assess the agreement between VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; measured using indirect calorimetry during the PACER and estimated VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; in normal weight and overweight youth and to determine the influence of weight status on the accuracy of estimated VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; in 10-15 year old youth.  &lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: The study included 101 participants that were classified as normal weight (n=78) or overweight (n=23) according to BMI percentiles for age and sex.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Participants completed the PACER, a progressive, multistage, 20-meter shuttle run to volitional exhaustion. VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; was measured during the PACER test using a portable gas analysis system (Oxycon Mobile, CareFusion, Inc.). Estimated VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; values were calculated based on PACER performance using the Leger et al. and Mahar et al. equations.  Paired samples t-tests were used to determine if significant differences existed between estimated and measured VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt;.  Independent t-tests were performed to compare the normal weight and overweight groups.  Accuracy was determined using Bland-Altman plots.  &lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;:  The Leger et al. (44.3 +4.6 ml/kg/min) and Mahar et al. (46.8 +4.8 ml/kg/min) estimated values were significantly lower than measured VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; (49.0 +8.7 ml/kg/min) in the normal weight group. There were no significant differences between measured VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; (38.8 +7.1 ml/kg/min) and predicted values (40.5 +2.5 and 38.2 +6.1 ml/kg/min; Leger et al. and Mahar et al., respectively) for the overweight group.  For the normal weight group, the standard error of the estimate (SEE) was Leger 5.44 ml/kg/min (Leger) and 5.33 ml/kg/min (Mahar). The SEE was 5.77 ml/kg/min&lt;sup&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;(Leger) and 4.54 ml/kg/min&lt;sup&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;(Mahar) for the overweight participants. &lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;: It appears that the prediction of VO&lt;sub&gt;2peak&lt;/sub&gt; from either equation based on PACER performance varies among weight status group and may be inaccurate for normal weight youth, but acceptable for overweight youth.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1205</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2287&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1205</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2287</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-12T07:35:48-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2287/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2658246</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1205</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dawn P. Coe</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr., Dixie L. Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>