<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Evaluation of Short-term Mesocarnivore Control for Increasing Hatch Rate in Northern Bobwhites</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:47:16-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University</institution>
<lname>Lyons</lname>
<fname>Eddie</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Angelo State University</institution>
<lname>Frost</lname>
<fname>Jason</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Department of Wildlife and Fisheries Sciences, Texas</institution>
<lname>Rollins</lname>
<fname>Dale</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Angelo State University</institution>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>Cody</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>mesomammal abundance</keyword>
<keyword>nesting success</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>predator control</keyword>
<keyword>Rolling Plains</keyword>
<keyword>Texas</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the efficacy of short-term trapping on scent-station visitation rates for some nest predators and survival of artificial nests with chicken eggs at 4 sites in west Texas from 1998-2001. Trapping of predators was conducted with cage traps for 30 days just prior to nest initiation (mid-May through mid-June) at a trap density of 1 trap/20 ha. Each site included a treatment (trapped) and control (non-trapped) area that comprised approximately 250 ha. Scent stations were employed before and after trapping to assess impacts of trapping on predator activity/abundance. Simulated nests (using 3 chicken eggs) were established 1-2 days after trapping ended, and monitored weekly to estimate visitation rate. We removed an average of 69 mesomammals per year (n = 274 across all sites), within a 30-day-trapping period. We detected no consistent declines in scent-station visitation rates of target species before or after trapping. We did not detect an increase in survival of artificial nests. We conclude that short-term trapping efforts on small areas used in this study did not reduce the overall predator community enough to affect scent-station visitation rates or survival of artificial nests.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol6/iss1/47</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1346&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>47</label>
<document-type>survival_and_predation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1346</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472097</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol6/iss1/47</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>