<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Park Usage in Relationship to Available Features and Amenities in a Large Urban Park</title>
<publication-date>2020-04-14T16:55:17-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hclauss@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Clauss</lname>
<fname>Hannah Bradford</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Epidemiology</discipline>
<discipline>Other Public Health</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt;  The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship between park features and park use in a large urban park.  At 45.33 acres, West Hills Park has amenities such as athletic courts and fields, picnic areas, and a 1.9-mile paved trail.  &lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt;  Park usage was assessed using the System for Observing Play and Recreation in Communities tool that measures use by gender, age, ethnicity, and moderate to vigorous physical activity (MVPA).  Data was collected in 18 zones over four days with three observations per day (morning, midday, and evening).  Park features, amenities, and condition, were assessed using the Environmental Assessment of Public Recreation Spaces (EAPRS) tool. &lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; In total, 440 individuals were observed using the park.  The EAPRS score was 31.78, a high rating.  68.3% of park users were at a MVPA level.  Athletic courts had the highest percentage of MVPA users (46.8%) followed by open spaces (20.7%) and playgrounds (20.1%).  Sedentary behaviors were observed near pavilions.  &lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt;  MVPA levels are related to the type and condition of park amenities.  Park directors may increase MVPA at the design phase of park development by selecting high-intensity amenities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2020/books/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1282&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1282</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-08-05T12:38:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>15061600</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2020/books/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Eugene Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>