<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular Evolution of MADS-box Genes in Cotton (&lt;em&gt;Gossypium&lt;/em&gt; L.)</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Wusheng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Breeding and Genetics</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the molecular evolution of floral developmental MADS-box genes in diploid and allotetraploid cotton (&lt;em&gt;Gossypium&lt;/em&gt;, Malvaceae). We isolated and characterized both cDNA and genomic DNA sequences of four MADS-box genes, &lt;em&gt;B-sister, APETALA3 (AP3), PISTILLATA (PI&lt;/em&gt;, two copies) and &lt;em&gt;AGAMOUS (AG)&lt;/em&gt;, in seven &lt;em&gt;Gossypium&lt;/em&gt; species (2 A-genome species, 2 D-genome species, 1 C-genome species and 2 AD-genome species) as well as an outgroup species, &lt;em&gt;Gossypioides kirkii&lt;/em&gt;. We then studied the expression patterns of each gene by reverse-transcriptase PCR (RT-PCR) in each flower part for different flower stages of &lt;em&gt;G. arboreum&lt;/em&gt; (A-genome), &lt;em&gt;G. raimondii&lt;/em&gt; (D-genome) and &lt;em&gt;G. hirsutum&lt;/em&gt; (AD-genome). We found that these MADS-box genes are evolving independently at the DNA sequence level but exhibit highly variable expression patterns in allotetraploid &lt;em&gt;G. hirsutum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These MADS-box genes contain highly conserved exon lengths and exon/intron structures, high nucleotide identity with homologs in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Antirrhinum majus&lt;/em&gt;, and conserved gene phylogeny within the genus &lt;em&gt;Gossypium&lt;/em&gt;. All the genes exhibit evidence of codon bias. The &lt;em&gt;AP3&lt;/em&gt; gene in &lt;em&gt;Gossypium&lt;/em&gt; appears to be subject to positive selection, while the &lt;em&gt;PI-small&lt;/em&gt; copy of the &lt;em&gt;PI&lt;/em&gt; gene appears to be subject to strong functional constraints together with a very low mutation rate. Within &lt;em&gt;G. hirsutum&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;B-sister&lt;/em&gt; gene exhibits gene silencing of the A-subgenomic homoeolog and the &lt;em&gt;PI-big&lt;/em&gt; copy of the &lt;em&gt;PI&lt;/em&gt; gene has experienced pseudogenization by insertion of a copia-like retroelement. The &lt;em&gt;AP3, PI-small&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AG&lt;/em&gt; genes show biased expression patterns in &lt;em&gt;G. hirsutum&lt;/em&gt;. These MADS-box genes also demonstrated developmentally regulated expression patterns in &lt;em&gt;G. arboreum, G. raimondii&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;G. hirsutum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/231</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1281&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>231</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1281</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-03T14:29:01-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1131234</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/231</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randall Small</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Karen Hughes, Barry Bruce, Beth Mullin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/LiuWusheng.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>