<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Principals&#39; perceptions of an evaluation system in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Mobley</lname>
<fname>Janet</fname>
<mname>Dyer</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to describe principals&#39; attitudes toward the Tennessee Model for Local Evaluation, the extent to which principals understand the performance standards, how well they perceive the model identifies effective teachers, and problems they have encountered. The researcher surveyed administrators attending Tennessee Academies for School Leaders (TASL) sessions. A questionnaire was utilized to collect data to answer the five research questions guiding the study. Results indicated administrators believed that instructional supervision should be for the purpose of improving instruction rather than the evaluation of teachers. Although administrators felt the principal should have the primary responsibility for teacher evaluation, additional personnel share the responsibility. Administrators also felt that instructional needs identified through the supervision process should be considered in planning staff development activities, although they did not agree the principal should adapt assessment strategies based on the experience and ability of the teacher. Administrators indicated they did not fully understand the performance levels on the summative report. Additionally, many indicated they did not feel confident with technical aspects of the state model. Administrators indicated the procedures for implementing the state model were feasible in a variety of school settings. Although administrators felt the initial training was excellent, new administrators are receiving less extensive, abbreviated training sessions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6273</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8225&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6273</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8225</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450370</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6273</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gerald C. Ubben</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>