<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>First Annual Report of the Agricultural Experiment Station of the University of Tennessee, for 1888, to the Governor.</title>
<publication-date>1888-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>University of Tennessee Agricultural Experiment Station</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>agricultural experiment station</keyword>
<keyword>ag research</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agannual/72</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1004&amp;amp;context=utk_agannual&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>72</label>
<document-type>annualreport</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1004</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-01-25T12:03:14-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Annual Report</publication-title>
<context-key>2470820</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agannual/72</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Knoxville, Tenn., Jan. 12th, 1889.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To His Excellency, Robert L. Taylor, Governor of Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sir: - We have the honor to submit to you herewith the Annual Report of Agricultural Experiment Station of the University of Tennessee, in accordance with the Act of Congress commonly known as the &quot;Hatch Experiment Act,&quot; and the Act of the General Assembly of Tennessee, accepting the same and bestowing them upon this Experiment Station. Section 5 of the first mentioned Act contains the following: &quot;It shall be the duty of each of said Stations, annually, or on before the first day of February , to make to the Governor of the State or Territory in which it is located, a full and detailed report of its operations, including a statement of receipts and expenditures; a copy of which report shall be sent to each of said Stations, to the said Commissioner of Agriculture, and to the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Act of the General Assembly of Tennessee, Laws of 1887, ch. 220, accepted this donation and bound the State and us to conform to its requirements. This report is presented to you in conformity with this requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoping that it will prove satisfactory to your Excellency, we remain, with great respect,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your obedient servants,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Board of Control and the Board of Trustees:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chas. W. Dabney, Jr. President.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S. H. Smith, Secretary.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1888-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>