<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effect of the Number of Pigs Per Pen on the Performance of Growing-Finishing Swine</title>
<publication-date>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hodges</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Data collected on 140 market hogs at the Knoxville Experiment Station, Knoxville, Tennessee, were used to determine the effect of the number of pigs per pen on performance of growing-finishing swine. In Trial I pigs were fed for an average of 108 days and in Trial II pigs were fed for an average of 91 days. In both trials pigs were fed in groups of 4, 6, 8, or 10 pigs per pen with space allowances of 23.8 square feet, 15.8 square feet, 11.9 square feet, or 9.5 square feet per pig, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average daily gains in Trial I were 1.48, 1.52, 1.46, and 1.48 pounds per head per day for Treatments I, II, III, and IV, respectively. No significant difference between treatments (variation in floor space) was noted with respect to any traits measured (Trial I). However, significant (P &lt; 0.05) differences were observed between barrows and gilts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Trial II, average daily gains were 1.71, 1.63, 1.63, and 1.62 pounds per head per day for Treatments I, II, III, and IV, respectively. Performance of the pigs by treatment in Trial II was not significantly different as were the results of Trial I. There was a significant (P &lt; 0.05) difference in the performance of the pigs by sex and by weight groups; however, the overall results of Trial II were similar to that of Trial I.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3125</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4498&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3125</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4498</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-20T08:41:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6544262</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3125</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank B. Masincupp</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J.B. McLaren, J.A. Corrick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>