<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Analyses of the Effects of an Exotic Lizard (&lt;em&gt;Anolis sagrei&lt;/em&gt;) on a Native Lizard (&lt;em&gt;Anolis carolinensis&lt;/em&gt;) in Florida, Using Islands as Experimental Units</title>
<publication-date>2000-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Campbell</lname>
<fname>Todd</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The green anole, &lt;em&gt;Anolis carolinensis&lt;/em&gt; (Sauria: Polychrotidae), North America&#39;s only native anole, was abundant in even the most disturbed urban environs of Florida until recently. The Cuban brown anole, &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt;, was introduced to six Florida ports in the 1940s. Since then, it has become the most abundant lizard in peninsular Florida, has spread into Georgia and two other southeastern states, and has been blamed for the decline of &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt;. Because &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt; declines soon after the arrival of &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt;, it has been difficult to identify the mechanisms involved. I studied the effect of &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt; on dredge-spoil islands along the east coast of Florida. By introducing small numbers of &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; to two very different islands, I contrasted their colonizing abilities, densities, and body conditions in two different habitat types. Stomach content analyses of the two species in sympatry indicated that they consume very similar proportions and taxa of arthropods, and that they consume each other&#39;s hatchlings in natural situations. In 1995, I introduced &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; onto three islands occupied by &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt;, and used three islands containing native &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt; as controls. Over four summers, I monitored populations using capture-mark-recapture techniques, and collected body, microhabitat, and spatial data. Green anole densities and habitat parameters were similar over time on the controls. On the treatment islands, &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; became dense in all habitat types, &lt;em&gt;A. carolinensis&lt;/em&gt; declined as &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; expanded, and survivors shifted their perch heights and utilized different habitats than they did prior to the introductions of &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt;. The decline was due to a lack of recruitment in subsequent years, suggesting that asymmetric intra-guild predation was involved in the rapid decline of green anoles. Sympatric green anole populations remained viable only in habitat patches containing dense understory vegetation, which may have provided more food and ameliorated the effects of hatchling predation Green anoles might remain viable in urban or disturbed environs where &lt;em&gt;A. sagrei&lt;/em&gt; attains very high densities, as long as sufficient understory vegetation is present to ensure successful recruitment of hatchling green anoles to adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4722</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6326&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4722</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6326</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-01-17T13:56:26-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>11378255</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4722</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Arthur C. Echternacht, Thomas G. Hallam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jim Drake, Sally Horn, Susan Riechert</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>