<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Perceptions of the Tennessee State Legislature Toward University of Tennessee Extension</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Koon</lname>
<fname>Martin</fname>
<mname>Roscoe</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to determine the perceptions of the Tennessee State Legislature toward University of Tennessee Extension and to identify factors that might affect these perceptions. The population for this descriptive study included 131 members of the Tennessee State Legislature. Members of the Tennessee Legislature were selected for study because current and future programs of University of Tennessee Extension are directly affected by the legislator’s perception of University of Tennessee Extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respondents were primarily white and male between the ages of 40 and 69. Respondent’s party affiliation was split pretty even between democrats and republicans. The majority of respondents lived in cities and represented rural districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characteristics were analyzed for their relationship to their familiarity with UT Extension, their perceived effectiveness of UT Extension, their exposure to UT Extension, and their participation in UT Extension programs. It was found that respondents were fairly familiar with the programs. They saw UT Extension programs as somewhat effective. Lastly the respondents had low exposure to the programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly the independent variables were examined for a relationship to the perceived effectiveness of UT Extension. The most important find of this study was found while looking at these relationships. It was found that the most important ways to increase perceived effectiveness of UT Extension by Tennessee State Legislators are to increase familiarity with and exposure to UT Extension programs. Though participation is important it is not necessary for a high correlation to perceived effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1719</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3068&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1719</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3068</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-19T11:58:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4463317</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1719</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carrie Fritz, John Peters</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>