<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Inquiry into Supply Chain Strategy Implications of the Sharing Economy for Last Mile Logistics</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Castillo</lname>
<fname>Vincent</fname>
<mname>Emanuel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>supply chain management</keyword>
<keyword>logistics</keyword>
<keyword>crowdsourcing</keyword>
<keyword>retail logistics</keyword>
<keyword>simulation</keyword>
<keyword>optimization</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As the prevalence of e-commerce and subsequent importance of effective and efficient omnichannel logistics strategies continues to rise, retail firms are exploring the viability of sourcing logistics capabilities from the sharing economy. Questions arise such as, “how can crowdbased logistics solutions such as crowdsourced logistics (CSL), crowdshipping, and pickup point networks (PPN) be leveraged to increase performance?” In this dissertation, empirical and analytical research is conducted that increases understanding of how firms can leverage the sharing economy to increase logistics and supply chain performance. Essay 1 explores crowdsourced logistics (CSL) by employing a stochastic discrete event simulation set in New York City in which a retail firm sources drivers from the crowd to perform same day deliveries under dynamic market conditions. Essay 2 employs a design science paradigm to develop a typology of crowdbased logistics strategies using two qualitative methodologies: web content analysis and Delphi surveys. A service-dominant logic theoretical perspective guides this essay and explains how firms co-create value with the crowd and consumer markets while presenting a generic design for integrating crowdbased models into logistics strategy. In Essay 3, a crowdsourced logistics strategy for home delivery is modeled in an empirically grounded simulation optimization to explore the logistics cost and responsiveness implications of sharing economy solutions on omnichannel fulfillment strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4917</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6458&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4917</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6458</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:13:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13415017</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4917</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John E. Bell, Diane A. Mollenkopf</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bogdan C. Bichescu, Terry L. Esper, Theodore P. Stank</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>