<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>OMAKUVA : Welcome Home</title>
<publication-date>2014-04-15T17:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mdaprile@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>D&#39;Aprile</lname>
<fname>Marianela</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Poetry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This project delves into the possibilities of using poetry, its reading and its creation, as a form of architectural research. Cities and landscapes have long inspired poets and writers — so, is it possible to reverse this process?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose Pablo Neruda’s poetry for analysis because of its imagery : the sea, stones and forests -- all evocative of the Finnish landscape. I also wrote poetry in order to more directly express the ultimate goals of the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this phase of research, I first familiarized myself with the Finnish landscape — cultural and designed. Through the combination of first-hand experience and second-hand poetic analysis, a design with the goals of accommodating both emotional and pragmatic needs emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal for a new home for the University of Tennessee Finland Summer Architecture Institute engages the active fabric of Helsinki by providing an anchor point for students -- a place where they can retreat from their surroundings to become fully immersed in their studies, their ideas and each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Located in Hietaniemi, Helsinki, on Lapinlahti Bay, the pavilion embraces the water to the West and the city center to the East. The pavilion, which contains a living room, a kitchen, a hallway lined with writing nooks and thirteen rooms, is supported by a care-taker’s cottage and a sauna overlooking the bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single incision into the stone on the South side of the pavilion creates an intimate courtyard in which students and faculty can gather to enjoy the Finnish summer.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2014/architecturedesign/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1035&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1035</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-15T12:10:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>5484417</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2014/architecturedesign/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Architecture and Design</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-04-15T17:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2014-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>