<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>2p or not 2p:The 14O(α,2p) 16O Reaction Rate and Its Implications on Nova and X-ray burst Nucleosynthesis</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dessieux, Jr.</lname>
<fname>Luc</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;During explosive hydrogen burning, the catalytic CNO cycle suffers depletion by additional thermonuclear capture reactions on the members of the cycle. This &quot;break out&quot; from the β-limited CNO cycle has been suggested to occur in novae and X-ray bursts for temperatures greater than 0.4 GK [3,26,28]. At these temperatures α captures can occur on the CNO waiting point isotopes through the nuclear reactions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F, &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,γ) &lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;Ne, and &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;Ne(α,γ) &lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt;Na [3]. An additional reaction, &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p)&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O has been suggested as a possible break out path from the CNO cycle [49]. To investigate the astrophysical significance of the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p)&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O reaction for the isotopes that are synthesized during novae outbursts and X-ray bursts, the unknown rate of this new reaction and the accepted rate of &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F have been varied using a scaling factor from negligible (10&lt;sup&gt;-9&lt;/sup&gt; of the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F accepted rate), to a value exceeding the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate by a factor of 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. If this new rate is found to have significant astrophysical implications, it could be investigated with a radioactive beam at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory’s Holifield Radioactive Beam facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a nova occurring on a 1.35 M[circle symbol] white dwarf, we found that varying the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F reaction rate by 12 magnitudes (ranging from 10&lt;sup&gt;-9&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; times the accepted rate) has an insignificant effect on the final abundances produced. When the unknown &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p) &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O reaction rate is added into the reaction rate library with a value assumed equal to the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate and the rate varied by 12 magnitudes, no significant effect was observed on the final abundances. The effect on the 1.25 M[circle symbol] ONeMg white dwarf was even smaller, and still smaller for the 1.00 M[circle symbol] C-O white dwarf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the X-ray burst case, variation of the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F reaction rate over 12 magnitudes revealed four distinct groupings of results from the scaled rate. When the rate is reduced by factors between 10&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; and 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; an enrichment of 20%-30% is observed in the CNO isotopes and A=20-50 mass region when compared to the case using the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate. The energy production is consistent with that of the calculation with the accepted rate. At factors greater than unity compared to the accepted rate, we observed a 20%-30% depletion in the CNO isotopes. When the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α, p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate is mildly dominant (10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt; of the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate), we observed an enrichment in both the CNO isotopes and the A=20-50 mass region by a factor up to 7, while the A=51-72 mass region is depleted by a factor up to 7. When the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α, p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate is not dominant (10&lt;sup&gt;-7&lt;/sup&gt; or less of the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate), we observed a depletion in both CNO isotopes and the A=20-72 mass region by factors up to 60, due to a one second delay in energy production caused by the reduced rate. &lt;sup&gt;56&lt;/sup&gt;Ni is a good candidate for observation as depletion and enrichment occurs in the A=51-72 mass region as a function of the scaled rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p) &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O rate is added to the reaction rate library with a value assumed equal to the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate, and than varied in the same manner as the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate, we observed three distinct groupings of behavior for X-ray bursts. When the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p) &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;rate is reduced by a factor of 10&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; or less, we find no change in nucleosynthesis or energy production when compared to the case using the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate. When the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p) &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O rate is set equal in strength to the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate, we observed a depletion of less than 10% in &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O and &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O. The energy production is consistent with that of the accepted rate. At factors greater than unity compared to the accepted &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate, we observed a depletion of up to 33% and 25% in &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O and &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O respectively. The energy production is consistent with that of the known &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F rate . During the X-ray burst the &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,p) &lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;F reaction is pivotal for energy generation, while the unmeasured &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;O(α,2p) &lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;O reaction has an insignificant effect on energy production and final abundances during the X-ray burst.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2056</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3413&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2056</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3413</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-01T10:59:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4652828</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2056</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mike Guidry</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Soren Sorensen, Michael Smith, C.C. Shih, Raphael Hix</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>