<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Consumer Perceived Value and Subjective Norm on the Adoption of Mobile Data Services: A Cross-cultural Comparison of American and Korean Consumers</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Kiseol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Despite the explosive growth of mobile phone subscribers and rapid adoption of mobile data services worldwide, the usage of mobile data services is highly variable across countries. This study attempted to reveal the differences in mobile data service adoption behavior between American and Korean consumers since it has been reported that the national culture and usage of mobile data services between the two countries is different, but mobile penetration rate is similar between the two countries. This study attempted to explain the differences in mobile data service adoption behavior between American and Korean consumers in regarding the effects of consumer perceived value and subjective norm on the adoption of mobile data services. The hypothesized research model based on Technology Acceptance Model was constructed to explore differences in mobile data service adoption behavior between American and Korean consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instrument equivalence was established by a backward and forward translation process. Data were collected via online and sample was comprised of American (n=200) and Korean (n=200) consumers. Measurement equivalence was assessed by multiple group structural equation modeling after data collection. Structural equation modeling method was used to examine hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results revealed that consumer perceived value explained the differences in consumer behavioral intention to use mobile data services between American and Korean consumers. Moreover, the results indicated that consumer emotional value is the most important value driving to use mobile data services for both countries. However, subjective norm on mobile data service adoption behavior was not supported in the study. Finally, the research model proved that the Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) is also applicable for a Korean sample. This study contributes to increasing the knowledge of consumer values driving to use mobile data services in each country and provides the applications and directions for success in mobile markets.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2049</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3485&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2049</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3485</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-25T14:23:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4630040</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2049</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Laura D. Jolly</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ann E. Fairhurst, Youn-Kyung Kim, Hee-Jin Lim, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>