<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Melatonin Inhibits In Vitro Serotonergic Phase Shifts of the Suprachiasmatic Circadian Clock</title>
<publication-date>1999-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prosser</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Suprachiasmatic nucleus; Circadian rhythm; Melatonin; Serotonin; Neuropeptide Y; Cyclic AMP; Brain slice</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Cell Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The suprachiasmatic (SCN) circadian pacemaker generates 24 h rhythms of spontaneous neuronal activity when isolated in an acute brain slice preparation. The isolated pacemaker also retains its capacity to be reset, or phase-shifted by exogenous stimuli. For example, serotonin  (5-HT) agonists advance the SCN pacemaker when applied during mid subjective day, while neuropeptide Y (NPY) agonists and melatonin advance the pacemaker when applied during late subjective day. Previous work has demonstrated interactions between NPY and 5-HT agonists, such that NPY can block 5-HTergic phase advances, while 5-HT agonists do not prevent NPY-induced advances. Due to a number of similarities in the actions of melatonin  and NPY in the SCN, it seemed possible that melatonin and 5-HT might interact in the SCN as well. Therefore, in this study potential interactions between melatonin and 5-HT  agonists were explored. Melatonin inhibited phase advances by the 5-HT  agonist, (+)DPAT, and this inhibition was decreased by co-application of tetrodotoxin. Conversely, melatonin was unable to block phase advances by the cyclic AMP analog, 8BA-cAMP. Finally, neither 5-HT agonists nor 8BA-AMP were able to block melatonin-induced phase advances. These results demonstrate a clear interaction between melatonin and 5-HT  in the SCN, and suggest that melatonin  and NPY may play similar roles with respect to modulating the phase of the SCN circadian pacemaker in rats.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/10</coverpage-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1009</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-10T06:06:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1352692</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Rebecca A. Prosser, Melatonin inhibits in vitro serotonergic phase shifts of the suprachiasmatic circadian clock, Brain Research, Volume 818, Issue 2, 13 February 1999, Pages 408-413, ISSN 0006-8993, DOI: 10.1016/S0006-8993(98)01295-5.
(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-3VR1297-V/2/0a353dc928c1f6172fba6be670735f78)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1999-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-3VR1297-V/2/0a353dc928c1f6172fba6be670735f78</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>