<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Population of low-lying levels in the one-neutron halo nucleus 11Be via the neutron transfer reaction 10Be(d,p)</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kschmit1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Schmitt</lname>
<fname>Kyle Thomas</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Historically, measurements of differential cross-sections for the neutron transfer reaction (d, p) on stable targets have been an important tool for extracting spectroscopic information. In particular, it is possible to make orbital angular momentum assignments and extract spectroscopic factors for ground states and excited states by comparing measurements to cross sections calculated for pure single-particle states. In recent years, the advent of rare isotope beams have made it possible to apply this method to increasingly exotic nuclei. As nucleon separation energies decrease along the path to the proton and neutron drip lines, many new reaction channels are opened. Out of the open channels arise complications for theoretical calculations that are not well understood. The archetypal one neutron halo nucleus &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;Be has been an important test case for theoretical studies, being within the reach of ab initio theory and relatively near the valley of particle stability while possessing several exotic properties. Although its ground state properties have been studied thoroughly, spectroscopic factors for the first excited state are not well understood. Additionally, little is known about the low-lying resonances. The current study has been performed to provide an extensive data set for the reaction &lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;Be(d, p) in inverse kinematics, including elastic and inelastic scattering channels important for optical model parameterizations. Differential cross-sections have been measured at equivalent deuteron beam energies of 12, 15, 18, and 21.4 MeV. Results are compared to previous measurements in inverse kinematics at 12 and 25 MeV. The data are also used to evaluate the Distorted Wave Born Approximation and Adiabatic Distorted Wave Approximation methods for cross section calculations and spectroscopic factors are extracted in each case.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1223</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2335&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1223</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2335</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-10-05T09:56:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2275772</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1223</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kate L. Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Witold Nazarewicz, Lee Riedinger, Lawrence Townsend</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>