<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Relationship Among Self-Esteem, Self-Efficacy, and Training Performance at a Government-Funded Nuclear Operations Complex in East Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sharp</lname>
<fname>Garland</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Human Resources Management</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to examine the relationship among self-efficacy, self-esteem, and training performance. This study was similar to a study conducted by Mone, Baker, and Jeffries in 1995. Using college students, Mone et al. (1995) tried to determine which construct, self-efficacy or self-esteem, more accurately predicted academic success. This study&#39;s purpose was to determine if relationships existed among self-efficacy, self-esteem, and training performance in an industrial training situation using employees in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A self-esteem and self-efficacy instrument along with a written test were used to gather data from the entire population (N=75) of workers at a government funded nuclear operations complex. The Coopersmith Self-Esteem Instrument (SEI) measured self-esteem in this study. A Grade Self-Esteem Scale adopted from the study conducted by Mone et al. in 1995 measured self-efficacy in this study. A written post-test measured training performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inferential statistics including correlation and regression was used to obtain the correlation among self-efficacy, self-esteem, and training performance. Using an SPSS Statistical Analysis program, a Pearson r correlation was obtained for the sample population among self-efficacy, self-esteem, and training performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings disclosed that there was a significant positive relationship between self-esteem and training performance. There was also a significant positive relationship between self-efficacy and training performance. Finally, the findings disclosed that there was a significant positive relationship between self-esteem and self-efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3002</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4381&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3002</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4381</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-10T13:41:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6444836</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3002</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jackie Dejonge, Debbie L. Mackey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>