<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of Kisspeptin on Regulation of Growth Hormone</title>
<publication-date>2011-09-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bwhitloc@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Whitlock</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Berry College</institution>
<lname>Daniel</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Wilborn</lname>
<fname>Robyn</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Maxwell</lname>
<fname>Herris</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Steele</lname>
<fname>Barbara</fname>
<mname>P</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Sartin</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>KISSPEPTIN</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Endocrinology</discipline>
<discipline>Large or Food Animal and Equine Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Other Neuroscience and Neurobiology</discipline>
<discipline>Reproductive and Urinary Physiology</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Physiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Kisspeptin ( KP ), a neuroendocrine regulator of reproduction, is hypothesized to be an integrator of metabolism and hormones critical to the regulation of reproduction. Lactation is associated with enhanced growth hormone (GH) responsiveness and reduced fertility. Our study was designed to determine the effects of lactation on KP-stimulated GH and luteinizing hormone (LH) secretion. Five non-lactating and five lactating dairy cows were used in the study. Experiments were conducted with lactating cows at weeks 1, 5 and 11 after parturition. The experimental treatments ( saline and KP [100 and 400 pmol / kg body weight]) were given intravenously and blood was collected and plasma was stored until later assay to determine concentrations of GH, LH, progesterone and non-esterified fatty acids. We found that neither dose of KP stimulated an increase in GH secretion. The low dose of KP increased (P &lt;0. 05) LH concentrations only in lactating cows. The higher dose of KP elicited an increase in circulating LH concentrations in both lactating and non-lactating cows. The lower dose of KP increased (P &lt; 0. 05) the area under the curve for LH only in cows during week 5 of lactation, and the area under the curve of LH following the highest dose of KP was greater (P &lt; 0. 05) in cows during week 5 of lactation than that for the other groups of cows. In summary, lactation status and stage of lactation did not change the sensitivity of the GH system to KP. However, an effect of stage of lactation on KP-stimulated LH secretion was detected in the dairy cows. Study of the KP system during lactation in dairy cows may provide critical insights into the mechanisms for lactation associated changes in the reproductive axis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>131</fpage>
<lpage>140</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_animpubs/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;amp;context=utk_animpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T08:15:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Animal Science Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3763260</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_animpubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-09-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Animal Science and Biotechnology</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>