<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Calcinosis circumscripta in the antebrachiocarpal joint of a horse</title>
<publication-date>2011-11-01T09:48:19-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Toth</lname>
<fname>Ferenc</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schumacher</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>horse</keyword>
<keyword>arthrotomy</keyword>
<keyword>calcinosis circumscripta</keyword>
<keyword>haemarthrosis</keyword>
<keyword>antebrachiocarpal joint</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A 4-year-old, Spanish Mustang mare was evaluated because of a swelling on the dorsolateral aspect of its right carpus. The horse had no gait abnormalities. During radiographic examination of the carpus, a granular, radiopaque mass, approximately 3 cm in diameter, adjacent to the proximal row of carpal bones, was observed. The mineralised mass, which was located within the antebrachiocarpal joint, was removed through an arthrotomy with the horse anaesthetised. Histological features of the mass showed it to be overlain by partially denuded synovium, and included large deposits of mineral surrounded by multinucleated giant cells and separated by septa of mature fibrous connective tissue. These features were typical of calcinosis circumscripta. Swelling of the carpus resolved after the surgery, but the horse was lost to follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/58</coverpage-url>
<label>58</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1057</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T09:42:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2323836</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/58</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Ferenc Toth, James Schumacher, and Shelley Newman. &quot;Calcinosis circumscripta in the antebrachiocarpal joint of a horse&quot; Equine Veterinary Education 21.11 (2009): 584-588.</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.2746/095777309X472046/abstract</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Equine Veterinary Education</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>