<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Aqueous extracts of Hibiscus sabdariffa as antimicrobials in foods</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>khiggin4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Higginbotham</lname>
<fname>Kristen</fname>
<mname>Liane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Hibiscus sabdariffa</keyword>
<keyword>antimicrobial</keyword>
<keyword>foodborne pathogens</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hibiscus sabdariffa&lt;/em&gt; L.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;is a tropical shrub species cultivated in multiple countries and is mainly produced for its red calyces that are used for a tea beverage. Aqueous, lyophilized extracts of &lt;em&gt;Hibiscus&lt;/em&gt; were examined for their chemical composition and antimicrobial activity against &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7, &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus, &lt;/em&gt;methicillin-resistant &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus &lt;/em&gt;(MRSA)&lt;em&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Listeria monocytogenes. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lyophilized, dialyzed extracts of commercially aquired calyces were examined in microbiological medium and milk at various fat levels for antimicrobial activity against &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 and &lt;em&gt;S.aureus. &lt;/em&gt;Extracts were either filtered or autoclaved to sterilize and tested in microbiological medium. Autoclaved extracts were more effective in microbiological medium and were subsequently tested in ultrahigh temperature-processed (UHT) milk with various fat percentages. &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 was inactivated after 96 h using 60 mg/ml extracts in all milk fat levels while &lt;em&gt;S. aureus &lt;/em&gt;was inactivated after 168 h using 40 mg/ml extracts in both skim and whole milk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lyophilized, undialyzed extracts were tested as an antimicrobial rinse on hot dogs against &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;and MRSA&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Inoculated hot dogs were rinsed with autoclaved extracts (0, 120 and 240 mg/ml) for 5, 15, 30, or 60 min and stored for 0 or 24 h. Reductions of ca. 3.7 log CFU/g and 5.5 log CFU/g were observed for &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;and MRSA respectively when rinsed in extracts at 240 mg/ml for 60 min and after 24 h.&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extracts produced from commercial brands were compared to greenhouse grown varieties of &lt;em&gt;Hibiscus&lt;/em&gt;. Anthocyanin and phenolic contents were determined to compare chemical profiles. Extracts at 60 mg/ml were adjusted to pH 7, autoclaved, and antimicrobial activity was determined against &lt;em&gt;S. aureus &lt;/em&gt;ATCC 27708. Growth of &lt;em&gt;S. aureus &lt;/em&gt;was inhibited when grown in the presence of extracts at 60 mg/ml at pH 7&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Phenolic content remained similar after autoclaving; however autoclaved extracts had less anthocyanin content than filtered extracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H. sabdariffa &lt;/em&gt;extracts were effective against foodborne pathogens in a microbiological media and in two food systems, UHT milk and as an antimicrobial rinse on hot dogs. &lt;em&gt;Hibiscus&lt;/em&gt; extracts have the potential to be a natural alternative to antimicrobials currently used in foods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2608</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3119&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2608</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3119</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-28T08:53:00-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3119/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4518420</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2608</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles N. Stewart Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Svetlana Zivanovic, P. Michael Davidson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>