<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Bridging the Gap-Connecting the Community</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-08T12:20:40-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>areece@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Reece</lname>
<fname>Anton</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2012/Session3/1</coverpage-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1070</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-02-10T07:25:05-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1070/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>2510110</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2012/Session3/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Few speakers can captivate, touch, motivate and challenge varied audiences as Anton has.  Having spoken to over 600 varied audiences in New York, Texas, Kentucky, Illinois, Missouri, Mississippi, Tennessee, Pennsylvania, Virginia, Arizona, and Mexico.  These audiences include corporations, colleges, high schools, youth organizations, churches and prisons, provides Anton with critical empowerment material.  All of these are illuminated by his rich style of articulation and homespun humor. Hailing from the Caribbean Country of Barbados, Anton draws from his communication roots and skills as a former employee with the Voice of Barbados Radio, a guest anchor for the Caribbean Broadcasting Television news. In addition, regular guest on WPSD TV, WKYX radio, Channel 2 Minority Focus host, and commentator on various television and radio programs in Kentucky.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anton is an honors graduate with a B.A in Broadcasting News and a M.A in Counseling, from Eastern Kentucky University,  twenty four hours above his masters from Murray State University and is a doctoral student in Educational Psychology at U.T Knoxville.  Anton has a legacy of firsts,  as the  first  Minority Affairs Coordinator  in the University of  Kentucky Community College System in 1990.  From 1999 - 2003, Anton created history again by becoming the first African American Dean of Student Affairs in Paducah Community College/Paducah Junior College  history.  At that time the only African American Dean of Students in the state 28 Kentucky Community and Technical colleges.  Anton is currently the Director of the Student Success Center and Co-chair of the Diversity Council at the University of Tennessee, in Knoxville.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>