<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SP652 Decking Lumber Options</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Lumber</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Wood Science and Pulp, Paper Technology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;If you are thinking of building a deck, you face many choices including what decking boards to use.  There are many factors to consider, and there is no perfect option.  Considering the pros and cons of each product will help you decide which decking board to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fact sheet briefly describes each type of decking material and discusses some of the pros and cons of each.  Some of the important factors in choosing decking boards for your project include price, availability, construction flexibility, maintenance and environmental impact.  Each ofthese factors will be addressed in the discussion of each material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main types of boards that can be used to make decks: preservative-treated wood, naturally durable wood and wood/plastic composite (WPC) lumber.  Untreated, non-durable wood such as pine is not recommended for building decks.  In some parts of the country untreated wood can last for a few years; but in the warm, humid climate of Tennessee, untreated wood will quickly rot anad won&#39;t last long enough to justify any cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfores/40</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1039&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfores&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>40</label>
<document-type>timber</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1039</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-31T08:05:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Forestry, Trees, and Timber</publication-title>
<context-key>1255779</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfores/40</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>SP652-1.5M-12/05 E12-4915-00-004-06 06-0031</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>