<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Origin and Tectonic Evolution of the Southern Appalachian Neoacadin Crystalline Core: Evidence from the Geology of the Gilreath 7.5-Minute Quadrangle, North Carolina</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Crystal</fname>
<mname>Gayle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Detailed geologic mapping of the Gilreath 7.5-minute quadrangle recognizes the northernmost continuation of the Brindle Creek fault, a terrane boundary that separates Neoproterozic-Ordovician metasedimentary and metavolcanic rocks of the western Tugaloo terrane (western Inner Piedmont) from Silurian-Devonian metasedimentary rocks and Devonian-Mississippian anatectic granitoids of the Cat Square terrane (eastern Inner Piedmont). The Brindle Creek fault is folded in the study area and exposes the Ordovician Brooks Crossroads Granite in a reentrant. Low high-field strength element concentrations and a flatter rare earth element patterns typical of western Inner Piedmont granitoids, support a footwall setting for the Brooks Crossroads Granite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New geochemical analyses of Inner Piedmont amphibolites reveal a mixed volcanic arc and E-type MORB signature for eastern Inner Piedmont amphibolite. These preliminary data suggests the Cat Square terrane may have originated in a back-arc basin influenced by E-type MORB volcanism during the waning stages of Middle Ordovician-late Silurian volcanic arc magmatism in the western Inner Piedmont.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subduction of the Inner Piedmont beneath a W- to NW-advancing Carolina superterrane resulted in possible early kyanite-grade metamorphism (7.0 to 8.7 kbars and 630 to 695°C), followed by sillimanite I and II grade metamorphism. High-temperature, upper amphibolite facies metamorphic conditions, in conjunction with pervasive migmatization, the presence of meso- and map-scale sheath folds, ubiquitous top-to-the SW shear-sense indicators, and protomylonitic to ultramylonitic deformation fabrics, suggests Inner Piedmont thrust sheets deformed as a viscous mass during SW-directed flow in a sub-simple shear to extreme simple shear stress regime. These data support models that reconcile the SW-directed arcuate trend of Inner Piedmont stretching directions, with a tectonically forced flow path resulting from oblique subduction of Inner Piedmont thrust sheets beneath the W- to NW-advancing Carolina superterrane. Flow was deflected to the southwest as Inner Piedmont thrust sheets buttressed against a primordial Brevard fault zone. Truncation of the Popular Springs and Big Warrior sheath folds against the Brindle Creek fault indicates SW-directed displacement of ductile, Inner Piedmont crystalline thrust sheets was prior to final emplacement of Cat Square terrane rocks.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4514</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6037&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4514</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6037</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-17T08:38:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10027621</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4514</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert D. Hatcher, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harry Y. McSween, Theodore C. Labotka</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Large file 63MB&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>