<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Taking New Steps Against Digital Sampling: The Sixth Circuit Lays Down the Law on Digital Sampling, but Will it Really Improve Industry Practices?</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-03T14:35:16-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Randall</lname>
<fname>Kelly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>digital sampling</keyword>
<keyword>sixth circuit</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In Bridgeport Music, Inc. v. Dimension Films,&#39; the Sixth Circuit tackled an issue that has been plaguing the music industry for nearly two decades. Digital sampling is a staple of the rap and hip-hop creative process, but there is very little precedent on or clarity about how to determine if sampling infringes on a sound recording copyright. In Bridgeport I, the defendant, No Limit Films, released the film I Got the Hook Up (Hook Up) and included the song &quot;100 Miles and Runnin&#39; (&quot;100 Miles&quot;) on the film soundtrack. As with many typical rap songs, &quot;100 Miles&quot; sampled from another song. The plaintiff, Westbound Records, Inc. (&quot;Westbound&quot;), claimed co-ownership of the sound recording copyright to the sampled song, &quot;Get Off Your Ass and Jam&quot; (&quot;Get Off&quot;), by George Clinton, Jr. and the Funkadelics. Although No Limit Films obtained an oral license from the co-owners of &quot;100 Miles&quot; to use the song in the film soundtrack, Westbound claimed that &quot;100 Miles&quot; contained an unauthorized sampling of &quot;Get Off.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol2/iss3/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>policynotes</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1044</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-03T14:25:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5257315</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol2/iss3/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>J.D. Candidate 2007, University of Tennessee College of Law;
B.Mus. 2000, Vanderbilt University, Blair School of Music. Author also served as Editor-in-Chief of the TENNESSEE JOURNAL OF LAW &amp; POLICY.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Digital Sampling</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>