<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Rise of the Democratic Socialists of America: A Qualitative Analysis of the Contributing Factors to Insurgent Mobilization</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>glowery1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lowery</lname>
<fname>Grady</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>social movements</keyword>
<keyword>democratic socialism</keyword>
<keyword>mobilization</keyword>
<keyword>insurgents</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although there are other more conventional means through which aggrieved populations can voice their concerns, social movements have long served as important vehicles for articulating and advancing a group&#39;s interests and claims. Indeed, some of the most significant developments in the history of the modern era are bound up with social movements. As a result, social movement analysts are interested in understanding the protests, conflicts, and other forms of resistance that have challenged the prevailing social order. Scholarly interest in collective action has engendered a proliferation of empirical studies, igniting a series of theoretical debates. These debates are animated around concerns regarding movement emergence, the significance of formal organizations, and the role of elites in social movements. Contemporary movement scholars have underscored the ubiquitous presence of social movements in modern society as an exemplar of their continuing significance as vital agents in generating social change. The Bush administration’s neoconservative foreign policy, the Great Recession, and persistent social inequalities once again inspired the launch of a myriad of protest activities. Inspired in part by Bernie Sanders’ runs for the presidency, a new wave of activists mobilized under the banner of democratic socialism as tens of thousands of them joined the Democratic Socialists of America. This dissertation argues that Sanders, along with likeminded politicians, represents an opportunity for the growth and development of a unique version of socialism in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6079</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7115&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6079</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7115</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-04T07:35:40-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/7115/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>18787376</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6079</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jon Shefner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michelle Christian, Asafa Jalata, Anthony J. Nownes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>