<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Epidemiology of the lymphatic-dwelling filarioid nematode Rumenfilaria andersoni in free-ranging moose (Alces alces) and other cervids of North America</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grunenwald</lname>
<fname>Caroline</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</institution>
<lname>Carstensen</lname>
<fname>Michelle</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources</institution>
<lname>Hildebrand</lname>
<fname>Erik</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Elam</lname>
<fname>Jacob</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Helsinki</institution>
<lname>Laaksonen</lname>
<fname>Sauli</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Production Animal and Wildlife Health Research Unit</institution>
<lname>Oksanen</lname>
<fname>Antti</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>rgerhold@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gerhold Jr.</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Rumenfilaria andersoni</keyword>
<keyword>Cervids</keyword>
<keyword>Lymphatic filariasis</keyword>
<keyword>Bioinvasion</keyword>
<keyword>Parasite translocation</keyword>
<keyword>Moose (Alces alces)</keyword>
<keyword>White-tailed deer (Odocoileus virginianus)</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background: Moose (&lt;em&gt;Alces alces&lt;/em&gt;) are a culturally and economically valued species in Minnesota, where the northeast population has decreased by 60 % since 2006. The cause of the decline is currently unclear; however, parasites, predation, and climate change have all been implicated. Nematode parasites are important pathogens in North American moose, potentially causing severe disease and mortality. Recent spread of &lt;em&gt;Rumenfilaria andersoni&lt;/em&gt;, a filarioid nematode of moose, has been documented in Finnish cervids; however, little is known about the epidemiology of this parasite in North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: To investigate the prevalence and distribution of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt;, 584 blood samples were collected from live-captured and dead animals and screened microscopically for the presence of microfilariae using a modified Knott’s test. Microfilariae were identified based on morphological characteristics. A subset of Knott’s-positive animals was subjected to polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with filarioid-specific primers targeting the first internal transcribed spacer region (ITS-1) of the rRNA gene cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results: &lt;em&gt;Rumenfilaria&lt;/em&gt; microfilariae were present in 20.5 % of Minnesota moose (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 352), with slight fluctuations observed over four years. Minnesota white-tailed deer &lt;em&gt;(Odocoileus virginianus)&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 2) and moose (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 44) from Alaska, Montana, Washington, Maine, and New Hampshire also harbored &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt;, suggesting this parasite occurs widely throughout North American moose herds, and white-tailed deer can serve as a patent host. Sequence analysis of cervid blood (moose, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 15&lt;em&gt;;&lt;/em&gt; white-tailed deer, &lt;em&gt;n =&lt;/em&gt; 1) confirmed the identity of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; and revealed the existence of two distinct clades. Genetic comparisons of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; isolates from North America and semi-domesticated Finnish reindeer found the two groups to be closely related, supporting previous hypotheses that &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; was recently introduced into Finland by the importation of deer from the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: To the best of our knowledge these observations represent the first report of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; within the contiguous United States and reveal this nematode as a common parasite of North American moose and white-tailed deer. Although the implications of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; infection on moose health is unclear, increased awareness of this parasite will help prevent unintentional introduction of &lt;em&gt;R. andersoni&lt;/em&gt; into naïve populations via the translocation of wild and captive cervids.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/109</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1108&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>109</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1108</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-14T06:53:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>9266286</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/109</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Grunenwald, C. M., Carstensen, M., Hildebrand, E., Elam, J., Laaksonen, S., Oksanen, A., &amp; Gerhold, R. W. (2016). Epidemiology of the lymphatic-dwelling filarioid nematode Rumenfilaria andersoni in free-ranging moose (Alces alces) and other cervids of North America. Parasites &amp; Vectors, 9(1), 450.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1186/s13071-016-1740-x</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Parasites &amp; Vectors</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>