<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Female Investors and Securities Fraud: Is the Reasonable Investor a Woman?</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>materiality</keyword>
<keyword>reasonable investor</keyword>
<keyword>female investor</keyword>
<keyword>male investor</keyword>
<keyword>sex</keyword>
<keyword>gender</keyword>
<keyword>10b-5</keyword>
<keyword>securities</keyword>
<keyword>fraud</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Gender</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Other Feminist, Gender, and Sexuality Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  paper extends existing scholarship that questions the existing  materiality standard used under Rule 10b-5 (and elsewhere in U.S.  securities regulation) and its touchstone notion of the reasonable  investor.  Specifically, the paper asks and answers a seemingly  straightforward, yet provocative, question: Is the reasonable investor a  woman?  The paper then preliminarily explores the potential  significance of its key findings - that women and men exhibit different  investment behaviors and achieve different investment outcomes, and that  the resulting female investor profile is closer to existing conceptions  of the reasonable investor than the resulting male investor profile.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As  women become larger players in the securities markets, it may be  comforting to know that they are relatively well protected by existing  conceptions of the reasonable investor.  However, the knowledge that  women are not completely protected by these existing conceptions and  that men are less well protected than women under the current reasonable  investor paradigm gives us pause and forces us to reconsider inaction.   To that end, this paper continues an ongoing academic and practical  conversation about when changes in investor protection should be  undertaken and how those changes can best be made if they are to be  undertaken - not just for the benefit of women or men, but for the  benefit of all underprotected investors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/16</coverpage-url>
<label>16</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T09:21:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035199</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/16</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Female Investors and Securities Fraud: Is the Reasonable Investor a Woman? (September 3, 2008). William &amp; Mary Journal of Women and the Law, Vol. 15; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 77. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1262915</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1262915</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>