<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Toward an Understanding of Best Practices in Student-Athlete Leadership Development Programs: Student-Athlete Perceptions and Gender Differences</title>
<publication-date>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Navarro</lname>
<fname>Kristina</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Malvaso</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>student-athletes</keyword>
<keyword>intercollegiate athletics</keyword>
<keyword>leadership development</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Student-athletes often know how to recognize leadership but struggle to master  techniques to exemplify leadership characteristics during their college experience.  As Division I athletics now serve as the front porch to American institutions, the  visibility of Division I student-athletes has drastically increased. With this visibility  comes enhanced responsibility to represent oneself, one&#39;s team, and one&#39;s university.  In turn, it is of heightened interest for higher education and intercollegiate  athletics practitioners to understand how to best foster leadership skills for this  unique population that garners enhanced media attention. This mixed-method  case study considers the perceptions of 221 Division I freshmen student-athletes  who completed a formal peer mentorship and leadership development program  at a large Southeastern institution. A survey was employed to analyze the relationship  between gender and student-athletes&#39; perceived effectiveness of the program&#39;s  curricular components. Findings displayed no widespread significant impact of  gender on perceived effectiveness. Recommendations are presented to enable  practitioners nationwide to improve student-athlete leadership development programs  considering gender differences and the student-athlete voice.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jasm/vol7/iss3/10</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1329&amp;amp;context=jasm&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1329</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-08T09:06:34-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Journal of Applied Sport Management</publication-title>
<context-key>20479280</context-key>
<submission-path>jasm/vol7/iss3/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>