<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>MISSING: Black males in the classroom</title>
<publication-date>2013-06-03T05:46:29-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dancar@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Ancar</lname>
<fname>Desiree Nicole</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Bilingual, Multilingual, and Multicultural Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In 2012 the U.S. Department of Education reported statistics showing while 17% of public school students were African-American, only 7% of public school teachers were black and less than 2% of those teachers were black males. Shown in another way, less than 1 in 50 educators in the public school sector are African American males.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of black male teachers is complex and multifaceted; however, the consequence remains the same. More black male teachers in the classroom equates to more black male leaders for young black male students to model themselves after. Young males deserve the opportunity to see older black men in a role seldom advertised or applauded by the media—one of success, intelligence, and transformational leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teach For America has worked specifically to diversify their applicant pool and draw in more black males. In a program presented at the Black Issues Conference 2013: Divided We Fall, Together We Stand, I hope to convey the message of the lasting impact that outstanding black male leadership can have in a classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program will include current and former Teach For America African American male corps members. The set up will include a look into the state of Black males in Tennessee and a question and answer session after the speakers have spoken about their experiences as former students, teachers and current leaders in the state.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2013/Session2/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1085&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1085</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-11T11:53:21-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1085/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3575498</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2013/Session2/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>