<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of First, Second and Third Chromosome on the Promoter Activity of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; Gene of Drosophila Melanogaster</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mukherjee</lname>
<fname>Anirban</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The mechanism of insect &lt;em&gt;CYP&lt;/em&gt; gene regulation is largely unknown. In the present investigation, I used &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; as a model insect to understand the role of X, 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosomes on the promoter activity of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; gene. Two reporter transgenic strains, 0.8luc110 H-ry and 0.8luc14, carrying 0.8luc-A8 reporter transgene (chimera of 0.8-kb upstream DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; and the firefly &lt;em&gt;luciferase&lt;/em&gt; gene) on the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosomes of &lt;em&gt;ry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;506&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively were used. The X, 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; and 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosomes of these two transgenic lines were replaced with corresponding chromosomes from DDT-resistant 91-R strain (overproducer of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt;). The effect was determined by measuring luciferase activity. Results showed that the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosome of the 91-R strain had a strong and the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosome had a weak stimulatory effect on &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; expression. The effect of the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; chromosome was strongly inhibitory only if the 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosome from 91-R and the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; chromosome from the ry&lt;sup&gt;506&lt;/sup&gt; strains were present in the genome. Chromosomal effect on the Inducibility of 0.8-kb &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; promoter DNA by phenobarbital and barbital was also examined. It was found that these compounds could induce the promoter significantly if the genome had X or second chromosome from the ry&lt;sup&gt;506&lt;/sup&gt; or 91-R strain. However, no induction was observed when the third chromosome of 91-R was present in the genome but the third chromosome of the ry&lt;sup&gt;506&lt;/sup&gt; strain supported barbiturate inducibility of the &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; promoter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further investigate if &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; is regulated by other genes, I studied the effect of third chromosome-linked DHR96 (mammalian CAR/RXR homolog) mutation on the promoter activity of the 0.8Kb upstream DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cy6a8&lt;/em&gt;. I found that the DHR96 mutation gave 7-12 fold higher constitutive expression of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; compared to the wild type strain in all developmental stages. This investigation concludes that &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; expression in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; is influenced by all three major chromosomes and the third chromosome-linked &lt;em&gt;DHR96&lt;/em&gt; gene has a negative effect on &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; expression.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/472</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1508&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>472</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1508</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-18T11:58:50-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1153767</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/472</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mariano Labrador, Jae H. Park</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/MukherjeeAnirban.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>