<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Neuropeptide Y Blocks Serotonergic Phase Shifts of the Suprachiasmatic Circadian Clock In Vitro</title>
<publication-date>1998-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prosser</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Suprachiasmatic nucleus; Circadian rhythm; Serotonin; Neuropeptide Y; Cyclic AMP; Brain slice</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Cell Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The mammalian circadian pacemaker in the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN) can be reset in vitro by various neurochemical stimuli. This study investigated the phase-shifting properties of neuropeptide Y (NPY) and serotonin  (5-HT) agonists when applied alone, as well as their combined effects on clock resetting. These neurotransmitters have both been shown to advance the SCN clock in vitro when applied during the daytime. By monitoring the SCN neuronal activity rhythm in vitro, I first confirm that the 5HT&lt;sub&gt;1A&lt;/sub&gt;/5HT&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;  agonist (+)DPAT maximally advances the SCN clock when applied at zeitgeber time 6 (ZT6). Conversely, NPY  only phase advances the neuronal activity rhythm when applied at ZT 10. This effect occurs through stimulation of Y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; receptors. NPY, again acting through Y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; receptors, blocks (+)DPAT-induced phase shifts at ZT 6, while neither (+)DPAT nor 5-HT affect NPY-induced phase shifts at ZT 10. NPY appears to block (+)DPAT-induced phase shifts by preventing increases in cyclic AMP. These data are the first to demonstrate in vitro interactions between daytime resetting stimuli in the rat, and provide critical insights into mechanisms controlling circadian clock phase.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/12</coverpage-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-10T06:39:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1352712</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Rebecca A. Prosser, Neuropeptide Y blocks serotonergic phase shifts of the suprachiasmatic circadian clock in vitro, Brain Research, Volume 808, Issue 1, 12 October 1998, Pages 31-41, ISSN 0006-8993, DOI: 10.1016/S0006-8993(98)00808-7.
(http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-3TYNNB5-5/2/b3de7110131b52165749399596a39cdb)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6SYR-3TYNNB5-5/2/b3de7110131b52165749399596a39cdb</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>