<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Selaginella and the Satyr: Euptychia westwoodi (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae) Oviposition Preference and Larval Performance</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Kansas</institution>
<lname>Hamm</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fordyce</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Lepidoptera</keyword>
<keyword>herbivory</keyword>
<keyword>specialist</keyword>
<keyword>larvae</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Members of the plant genus &lt;em&gt;Selaginella&lt;/em&gt; (de Beauvois 1805) have few known insect herbivores even though they are considered by some to be ‘living fossils’, with extant taxa virtually indistinguishable from 300 Mya fossils. Butterflies are well-known herbivores, and the satyrs are among the most speciose of them despite having radiated ∼35 Mya ago. Nearly all satyrs feed on grass or sedges, but members of the Neotropical genus &lt;em&gt;Euptychia&lt;/em&gt; Hübner 1818 feed on &lt;em&gt;Selaginella&lt;/em&gt;; little is known about the degree to which this butterfly favors this ancient plant over those that its close relatives utilize. To advance our knowledge of &lt;em&gt;Euptychia &lt;/em&gt;natural history, we conducted a series of experiments to examine oviposition preference and growth rates across a series of potential host plants on a &lt;em&gt;Euptychia westwoodi&lt;/em&gt; population in Costa Rica. We found that &lt;em&gt;Euptychia westwoodi&lt;/em&gt; Butler 1867 exhibit a strong preference to oviposit on &lt;em&gt;Selaginella eurynota&lt;/em&gt; over the sympatric &lt;em&gt;Selaginella arthritica&lt;/em&gt;, though they perform equally well as larvae on both plants. We did not observe oviposition on a sympatric grass that is commonly consumed by close relatives of &lt;em&gt;E. westwoodi&lt;/em&gt;, and when larvae were offered the grass they refused to eat. These results suggest that&lt;em&gt;E. westwoodi&lt;/em&gt; in Costa Rica exhibit a strong preference for &lt;em&gt;Selaginella&lt;/em&gt; and may have lost the ability to feed on a locally abundant grass commonly used by other Satyrinae.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/67</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1066&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>67</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1066</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-13T12:39:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>9264082</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/67</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons BY-NC 4.0 license&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Hamm, C. A., &amp; Fordyce, J. A. (2016). Selaginella and the Satyr: Euptychia westwoodi (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae) Oviposition Preference and Larval Performance. Journal of Insect Science, 16(1), 39.
doi: 10.1093/jisesa/iew018</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1093/jisesa/iew018</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Insect Science</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>