<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Thermally Robust and Redox Active Catalysts: Studying Their Behavior for Ethylene and L-lactide Polymerization</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lbrown75@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Brown</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Ashley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>polymer</keyword>
<keyword>catalyst</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Inorganic Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Organic Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Polymer Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The development of homogenous single-site catalysts has significantly impacted the field of organometallic chemistry. The well-defined structures of homogenous catalysts make it less cumbersome to understand and develop methods to tailor these compounds for specific catalytic processes. Currently, polymerization catalysis is a major division in organometallic chemistry due to the global demand for polymeric materials such as polyethylene (PE) and polypropylene (PP), based on their low-cost feedstock, remarkable mechanical properties, and their use in a wide range of applications. However, bioplastics have become a highly sought-after alternative to conventional petrochemical-based plastics due to their biodegradability and derivatization from renewable resources. Specifically, polylactic acid (PLA) has shown tremendous promise for a variety of applications including medical and packaging products. With such a high demand for these materials, there is a great desire to understand and to be able to control the polymerizations of monomers such as ethylene and lactide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dissertation will describe several advances the Long group has taken toward designing advanced single-site catalysts for the polymerization of ethylene and L-lactide. In our studies, we have determined that catalyst design can have a major impact on polymerization behavior and catalyst stability. More specifically, our group has been particularly successful in (1) designing thermally robust catalysts for ethylene polymerization and (2) designing redox-switchable catalysts for L-lactide polymerization. To date, our group has published several fundamental studies encompassing thermally robust catalysts for polyethylene and the development of redox-switchable catalysts for PLA. A portion of these results will be described herein.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4387</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5845&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4387</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5845</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-24T10:44:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9744664</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4387</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brian K. Long</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael D. Best, Ziling Xue, S. Michael Kilbey II</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>