<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Removal of Sulfur Dioxide and Nitric Oxide From a Flue Gas Stream By Two Sodium Alkalis of Various Sizes</title>
<publication-date>1980-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carson</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this research effort was to examine the dry removal of SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO from a flue gas stream by injecting two sodium additives into a pilot bag house system. The additives tested were NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; dusts with mass mean diameters ranging from approximately 30 to 200 microns. The Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; was obtained by decomposing the NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; (with heat) prior to testing. The bag house temperature was maintained at either 250 or 300 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was demonstrated that 70% SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; removal can be attained with NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; powders that have mass mean diameters of 32 and 52 microns at stoichiometric ratios of 0.8 and 1.3, respectively. The rate of mass transfer limited the desulfurization capacity of NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; powders with mass mean diameters greater than 50 microns. The rate of chemical reaction limited the SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; removal capability of the smallest NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; additive tested (mass mean diameter = 32 microns). Decomposition of NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; to Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; in bulk before injection yielded poorer SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also demonstrated that 7 to 36% of the NO was removed simultaneously with SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by the NaHCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; additives with mass mean diameters smaller than 120 microns. This removal was inversely dependent on the system temperature. No appreciable NO removal was observed with Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; injection.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/937</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2182&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>937</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2182</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-09-13T13:08:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2235496</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/937</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Wayne T. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f702f8fc2d8)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1980-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>