<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cellular and population plasticity of helper CD4(+) T cell responses</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Magombedze</lname>
<fname>G</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Reddy</lname>
<fname>P</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Eda</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ganusov</lname>
<fname>V</fname>
<mname>V</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>CD4+ T cells</keyword>
<keyword>Johnes disease</keyword>
<keyword>differentiation</keyword>
<keyword>mathematical modeling</keyword>
<keyword>plasticity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Vertebrates are constantly exposed to pathogens, and the adaptive immunity has most likely evolved to control and clear such infectious agents. CD4(+) T cells are the major players in the adaptive immune response to pathogens. Following recognition of pathogen-derived antigens naïve CD4(+) T cells differentiate into effectors which then control pathogen replication either directly by killing pathogen-infected cells or by assisting with generation of cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) or pathogen-specific antibodies. Pathogen-specific effector CD4(+) T cells are highly heterogeneous in terms of cytokines they produce. Three major subtypes of effector CD4(+) T cells have been identified: T-helper 1 (Th1) cells producing IFN-γ and TNF-α, Th2 cells producing IL-4 and IL-10, and Th17 cells producing IL-17. How this heterogeneity is maintained and what regulates changes in effector T cell composition during chronic infections remains poorly understood. In this review we discuss recent advances in our understanding of CD4(+) T cell differentiation in response to microbial infections. We propose that a change in the phenotype of pathogen-specific effector CD4(+) T cells during chronic infections, for example, from Th1 to Th2 response as observed in Mycobactrium avium ssp. paratuberculosis (MAP) infection of ruminants, can be achieved by conversion of T cells from one effector subset to another (cellular plasticity) or due to differences in kinetics (differentiation, proliferation, death) of different effector T cell subsets (population plasticity). We also shortly review mathematical models aimed at describing CD4(+) T cell differentiation and outline areas for future experimental and theoretical research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;doi: 10.3389/fphys.2013.00206&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biolpubs/32</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1031&amp;amp;context=utk_biolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>32</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1031</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-01-10T08:51:45-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- General Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4979291</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biolpubs/32</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Front Physiol. 2013; 4: 206, Published online 2013 August 16. doi:  10.3389/fphys.2013.00206</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-01-10T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>