<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>In Search of the Undergraduate Library (video)</title>
<publication-date>1984-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>danream@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Virginia Commonwealth University</institution>
<lname>Ream</lname>
<fname>Dan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Undergraduate Library</keyword>
<keyword>Jack Reese</keyword>
<keyword>LeRoy Graf</keyword>
<keyword>Bain Stewart</keyword>
<keyword>Smokey VI</keyword>
<keyword>Leigh Davis</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1984, evacuation of the Hodges Undergraduate Library, at the corner of Volunteer Boulevard and Andy Holt Avenue, was completed in order to build a new Hodges main library in that same location. Collections and services of the Undergraduate Library were split and moved into the ground floor of the Humanities &amp; Sciences classroom building and (about two blocks north) the lower floors of the Dunford Hall dormitory. Students and faculty returning to campus after the summer needed to be informed about the relocated library and a poster campaign starring Chancellor Jack Reese and professors LeRoy Graf and Bain Stewart was produced to publicize the move ( see &lt;a href=&quot;http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/61/ &quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/61/ &quot;&gt;http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/61/ &lt;/a&gt; for the posters involved. ) During that fall quarter, 1984, this video production in collaboration with UTK Television Services was made for airing on the UT-sponsored Knoxville PBS television station, during the weekly Sunday evening primetime program about the university, hosted by Jane Pope. In addition to the abovementioned Reese, Graf, and Stewart, the 14-minute video production starred the UT mascot, Smokey VI and 1984 homecoming queen Leigh Davis, along with Dave McClure, Lucretia McCulley, Bill Ward and several other library staff in a storyline in which Smokey finds the missing Undergraduate Library.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/62</coverpage-url>
<label>62</label>
<document-type>audiovideo</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1071</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-09T08:10:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Other Library Publications and Works</publication-title>
<context-key>2141721</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libfpubs/62</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>https://stream.lib.utk.edu/embeds/stream.php?file=instruction/ugl2.mp4&amp;w=640&amp;h=480</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>