<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Training with the Nutrition Section of the Division of Health, Wisconsin Department of Health and Social Services</title>
<publication-date>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Linda</fname>
<mname>Lane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper is based on objectives accomplished during seven weeks of field training with the Nutrition Section of the Division of Health, Wisconsin Department of Health and Social Services. These objectives included studying the organization and function of the Nutrition Section, developing consultation techniques, identifying areas for professional development, and further defining a philosophy of public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characteristics influencing health programs in Wisconsin, the organization of the Division of Health and the Nutrition Section, and the functions of the district nutritionist are discussed. Reviewing this material aided the student in her study of the nutrition program as a component of an official health agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of activities from field training illustrate the roles of the public health nutritionist. The roles are defined as administrator, counselor, consultant, and educator. An analysis of the student&#39;s professional development in each of the defined roles is reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By analyzing the field training, the student defines the public health nutritionist as a member of the public health team who must combine idealism with practicality to provide effective nutrition education. The field training provided an excellent opportunity for the student to learn that she, too, can function as a nutritionist in a public health agency.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3839</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5318&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3839</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5318</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-10T13:00:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8959339</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3839</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cyrus Mayshark, John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>