<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Do Foreign Language Learning, Cognitive, and Affective Variables Differ as a Function of Exceptionality Status and Gender?</title>
<publication-date>2013-07-23T12:05:57-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Bell</lname>
<fname>Sherry</fname>
<mname>Mee</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>McCallum</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
<mname>Steve</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Relationships between foreign language learning and four characteristics— anxiety, aptitude, attitudes and attributions for success—were investigated for 95 students enrolled in introductory level Spanish classes at a large, southeastern university in the United States. Examination grades resulted in significantly positive correlation with an aptitude measure and significantly negative correlation with luck attributions for foreign language success (p &lt; .05). Students identified as gifted tended to score higher than those with learning disabilities on exams, though not significantly higher, perhaps as a result of the small sample size and highly variable performance of the gifted students (p &lt; .05). In addition, the gifted students reported less anxiety (p &lt; .04). Females reported higher anxiety (p &lt; .001) than males though they earned (non-significantly) higher scores (than males) on exams (p &gt; .05). Modern Language Aptitude Test Part IV and luck attributions significantly predicted exam grades within a multiple regression analysis. In a second multiple regression analysis, only effort and ability attributions significantly predicted anxiety. Results underscore the importance of understanding and addressing both cognitive and affective variables in learning a new language.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1219&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1219</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-23T11:39:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>4339131</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Function of Exceptionality Status and Gender</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>