<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Delivery of Community Mental Health Services through a 5-Session Group Therapy Module</title>
<publication-date>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>annielee.jones@va.gov</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Annie</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore one possible way to facilitate change in low-income groups through the use of a time-limited group therapy program. It was hoped that through the documentation of change with each case in the study it would be shown that change was possible for low-income persons utilizing psychotherapy, especially with realistic assessment of problems and the setting of realistic goals by the client and therapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessment data was obtained for each case through these instruments: A. Problems Checklist; B. Personal Data Sheet; C. The Zung Self-Rating Depression Scale; D. The Levenson Internal-External Scale; E. The Profile of Mood States; F. Bernreuter&#39;s Self-Sufficiency Scale; G. The Somatic Symptom Rating Scale; H. The FIRO-COPE Scale; I. The Global Improvement Rating Scale; and J. Self-statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was found that three out of four low-income women who completed the treatment were reported as being quite a bit better to very much better. After treatment, these women were also much more capable of utilizing community resources to facilitate the achievement in their goals. Whereas prior to treatment they were ineffective in this area. It was also found that realistic assessment through the listing of problems prior to treatment and Global Improvement ratings from significant observers were the most valid measures used in the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it was demonstrated that realistic assessment of goals, and a time-limited group treatment program were effective in facilitating considerable improvement in some low-income women.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1380</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2748&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1380</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2748</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-10-31T08:46:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3436324</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1380</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leo Droppleman</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Wesley G. Morgan, Kenneth R. Newton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>