<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Analysis of Supportive Campus Environments and First-Generations-Student Learning Outcomes</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>Michael</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research utilized ten years of National Survey of Student Engagement (NSSE) data to identify differences between first- and non-first-generation students’ relationship with supportive campus environment variables and learning outcomes. The dataset included 3,796 non-first-generation and 1,844 first-generation students that attended a research intensive public institution between 2003 and 2011. The main dependent variable was a composite measure of student learning gains across four areas: writing, speaking, thinking critically and analyzing numerical or statistical information. The results indicated that while supportive campus environments are critical for all students, first-generation students showed higher and more consistent statistical associations with campus environment variables measuring faculty and peer relationships as compared to non-first-generation students that showed highly significant relationships with variables measuring support from campus administration or support personnel. This finding could lend support to theories that first-generation students come to campus with less social capital related to the inner workings of university environments and as a result rely more heavily on peer and faculty relationships for increased learning outcomes as compared to non-first-generation students.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4826</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6366&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4826</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6366</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-08T14:09:17-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13276486</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4826</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Terry Ishitani</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. Patrick Biddix, Michael Fitzgerald, Norma T. Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-16T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>