<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Reforming Eminent Domain in Tennessee After Kelo: Safeguarding the Family Farm</title>
<publication-date>2014-03-12T13:11:04-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Pemberton</lname>
<fname>Beau</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>eminent domain</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Take a journey back in time to the summer of 2005. Visualize a seventy-five year old, widowed grandmother living on her farm in rural Middle Tennessee. This thirty acre farm in the middle of the county is all that she has left to call her own. The world has grown around her farm for many years, inviting mini-malls, restaurants, condominiums, and interstate ramps on all sides of this picturesque setting. Now, imagine the grandmother&#39;s shock when she receives a letter from the local Economic Development Board notifying her that it is going to condemn her property via eminent domain as part of the county&#39;s Master Economic Redevelopment Plan.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol4/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1059&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1059</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-10T10:43:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5310565</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol4/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>J.D. candidate, University of Tennessee College of Law, graduating in May, 2008, with a Concentration in Business Transactions; B.A., summa cum laude, 2005, The University of Tennessee at Martin. The author would like to thank Dr. Otis Stephens, and his assistants, for their invaluable guidance and input on this essay. The author dedicates this essay to his wife, Stacey, and daughter, Sarah Elizabeth, and expresses his thanks for their support and patience while writing this piece.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-03-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Reforming Eminent Domain</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>