<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Recreational Reading Program in a Sixth Grade Classroom</title>
<publication-date>1949-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bowers</lname>
<fname>Nellie</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From the Introduction&lt;/em&gt;) The importance of reading, both as a school subject and as a recreational activity, has been generally recognized by persons engaged in the teaching profession. Reading is basic to a mastery of many other school subjects, since comprehension of another subject may depend upon ability to read. The emphasis that has been given to reading is evident from the extensive literature that has been published in recent years, particularly since the publication in 1925 of the Twenty-fourth Yearbook of the National Society for the Study of Education, (38)* Part I, &quot;The Improvement of Reading.&quot; In this volume objectives were set forth and procedures for their realization were outlined rather effectively. Throughout the volume, emphasis was placed upon the provision of rich and varied experience through wide reading, the fostering of permanent interests in reading as a leisure activity, and the development of desirable attitudes and effective habits and skills. Excellent suggestions were included for helping the poor reader.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4387</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5883&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4387</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5883</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-06T11:22:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9796119</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4387</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Beverley E. Holaday</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hazel M. Lambert, Priscilla Lantz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1949-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1949-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>