<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modern Chinese Development of Latin America</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-15T08:42:56-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>alejtrip@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Tripp</lname>
<fname>Alexander</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Comparative Politics</discipline>
<discipline>International Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Latin American Languages and Societies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;China, a rising global hegemon, has become increasingly interested in close economic and political relations with Latin America since the turn of the century. These relationships have been centered around two traits, foreign direct investment (FDI) and the export of raw materials. China has fully invested itself into the region in order to develop and maintain the production of certain goods necessary for upkeep of its massive population and industrializing economy. I test the significance of four prominent raw materials in Chinese trade with Latin America to determine their impact on Chinese FDI. Using this method, I gather and gauge the strength of Chinese relations with certain Latin American countries, explaining the specific features of China’s greatest partners in the region, as well as nations with lesser, though more unique, relationships, and finally some nations with no relations (or recognition) of the Chinese superpower whatsoever. My findings explicate the massive significance of Chinese investment into the region, hinting at what these relations could mean for the future of the region, and whether or not Chinese investment is as beneficial as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1241&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1241</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-15T07:45:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14259362</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Political Science</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Drs. Richard Pacelle and Gary Uzonyi</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>