<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Field Experience in Public Health Nutrition with the Nutrition Section of the Florida Division of Health</title>
<publication-date>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bailey</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The field course described in this thesis was completed between September 23 and November 8 in 1974 while with the Nutrition Section of the Florida Division of Health. The purpose of this field course was to integrate academic theory and practical application in the field of public health nutrition. In addition, the field course was to provide an opportunity for developing methodology in disseminating nutritional concepts to the general public in a most practical manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience was designed to allow the author to familiarize herself with the philosophy and principles of public health. Through observation and participation in the nutrition program, both at the state and local level, the author was able to develop her professional skills in public health nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the opportunity given by the field course, the author grew in self-confidence and was strengthened in her personal abilities to perform and initiate the responsibilities of a future public health nutritionist.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4003</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5489&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4003</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5489</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-22T08:37:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9171714</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4003</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel W. Hubbard</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Robert H. Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1975-03-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>