<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Asian Longhorned Tick</title>
<publication-date>2019-09-09T07:08:39-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Grove</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>RFryxell@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fryxell</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hickling</lname>
<fname>Graham</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Vail</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ivey</lname>
<fname>Jennie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Asian longhorned tick (Haemophysalis longicorns Neumann; alternative names include Asian longhorned tick, Asian tick, bush tick, New Zealand cattle tick) is a species of hard tick in the family Ixodidae. It is native to eastern China, Japan, the Russian Far East and Korea. It has also established in Australia, New Zealand and several Pacific islands, where it is considered a severe exotic pest of livestock. In late 2017, the United States Department of Agriculture’s National Veterinary Services Laboratories (NVSL) confirmed the presence of the Asian longhorned tick in the United States. These ticks were first identified in New Jersey, but have since been found in archival samples from West Virginia as far back as 2010. The origin of the tick in the US remains unknown. Some possible routes of entry include entering on domestic pets, horses, livestock or humans. The real impact of the introduction of this tick into the US is not clear at this time, but animal health officials are concerned about potential detrimental impacts on livestock and wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_forepubs/30</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=utk_forepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>30</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1036</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-09-09T07:07:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>UT Extension publication</publication-title>
<context-key>15290135</context-key>
<withdrawn>2019-09-10</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_forepubs/30</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication contains pesticide recommendations that are subject to change at any time. The recommendations in this publication are provided only as a guide. It is always the pesticide applicator&#39;s responsibility, by law, to read and follow all current label directions for the specific pesticide being used. The label always takes precedence over the recommendations found in this publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of trade or brand names in this publication is for clarity and information; it does not imply approval of the product to the exclusion of others that may be of similar, suitable composition, nor does it guarantee or warrant the standard of the product. The author(s), the University of Tennessee Institute of Agriculture and University of Tennessee Extension assume no liability resulting from the use of these recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Grove, Daniel; Fryxell, Rebecca T.; Hickling, Graham; Vail, Karen; and Ivey, Jennie, &quot;W 826 Asian Longhorned Tick&quot; (2019). UT Extension</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>