<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Experiences with the Nutrition Section of the Division of Health, Wisconsin Department of Health and Social Services</title>
<publication-date>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hine</lname>
<fname>Roberta</fname>
<mname>Jean</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis is based upon the observations and experiences during eight weeks with the Nutrition Section of the Division of Health, Wisconsin Department of Health and Social Services. The purpose of the field training was to complement academic training at The University of Tennessee and to supplement concurrent field experiences in Knox County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variety of experiences aide the student in her study of the nutrition program as a component of organized health services. Information was obtained on history, organization and programs of the Division of Health and the Nutrition Section through selected readings, conferences, conversations, and observations. Observations of a participation in the activities of the Nutrition Section increased the student&#39;s knowledge of the role of the public health nutritionist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the field experience, the student gained an understanding of the bureaus and sections of the Division of Health and observed the integration of nutrition services into the total public health program. She had the opportunity to participate in a project involving health professionals and staff from the Southwest Community Action Program. An increased awareness was gained of the importance of planning nutrition programs to meet the needs of the population served. The field training provided an excellent opportunity to examine the unique expertise the public health nutritionist brings to the public health team.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3832</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5309&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3832</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5309</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-08T14:43:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8943727</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3832</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John T. Smith, Cyrus Mayshark, Mary Rose Gram</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>