<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Allometry of the Palate of Archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; and Modern &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>1985-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Leigh</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research examines several aspects of allometry in the palate of archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; and modern &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. The allometry of the modern human palate is described. Comparisons between quantitative methods and comparisons between different types of samples are undertaken. Additionally, the allometry of the archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; palate is described and analyzed. Finally, allometric comparisons between these groups are made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The samples employed in this study consist of 132 Amerindian (Arikara) crania and 21 archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; (primarily Neandertal) crania. Quantitative methods used for analyzing these groups include least-squares regression, reduced major axis regression, and principal components analysis. Analysis of covariance and principal components analysis are used to compare allometric relationships between the groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this research indicate that least-squares regression techniques supply information which is generally substantiated by principal components analysis. Comparisons between samples indicate that static samples (samples derived from a single age group) do not provide the same information as ontogenetic samples (derived from several different age classes. These results are similar in both groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important aspect of this study concerns the allometric relationships between modern and archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;. Comparisons suggest that archaic &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; begin growth at larger sizes than modern &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;, and that this difference holds throughout the growth period. Complementary multivariate analyses indicate that the pattern or general size increase between these two groups is very similar.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4161</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5619&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4161</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5619</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-28T11:43:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9319801</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4161</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Fred H. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Jantz, William M. Bass, P. Willey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1985-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>