<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Small woodland owners in Sequatchie County, Tennessee : problem A: Characteristics of Sequatchie County small woodland owners and their farms : problem B: Management practices of Sequatchie County small woodland owners : problem C: Factors influencing woodland management adoption by Sequatchie County small woodland owners : three related problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Steele</lname>
<fname>Mack</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study was the first of three related problems regarding small woodland owners in Sequatchie County, Tennessee. It was conducted for the purpose of determining the characteristics of small woodland owners in the county. A random sample of 50 owners were selected; and the farmers were classified by the SCS technician, Extension Leader and Associate Extension Agent into high (20) or low (30) adopters depending upon whether they were inclined to be among the first to adopt recommended practices or not. The findings revealed that the average small woodland owner in Sequatchie County had the following characteristics: (1) was 51. 3 years of age; (2) had completed 12. 0 grade; (3) reported a median gross family income of $9,143.00; (4) was &quot;very well&quot; or &quot;fairly well&quot; known by the interviewer; and the owner was &quot;friendly&quot; or &quot;somewhat friendly&quot; toward the survey.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6058</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7697&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6058</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7697</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074439</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6058</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cecil E. Carter, John B. Sharp, Franklin Leuthold</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>