<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Regulation of Apolipoprotein C-III Gene Expression by Nuclear Receptors Hepatocyte Nuclear Factor 4 Alpha and Chicken Ovalbumin Upstream Promoter Transcription Factor II, but not Retinoids in Hepatic Cells</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mhowel14@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Howell</lname>
<fname>Meredith</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>vitamin a</keyword>
<keyword>retinoids</keyword>
<keyword>lipid metabolism</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Molecular, Genetic, and Biochemical Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Retinoic acid (RA) treatment induces hyperlipidemia in humans and animals. RA regulates the expression levels of various genes through the induction, repression, or coactivation of nuclear receptors, mediating its effects. RA-induced hyperlipidemia has been attributed to the induction of apolipoprotein CIII (gene, &lt;em&gt;Apoc3&lt;/em&gt;), which inhibits lipoprotein lipase activity (LPL). We have shown that vitamin A (VA) status and retinoid treatment regulates hepatic lipogenic gene expression, suggesting that the induction of lipogenic genes may also contribute to hyperlipidemia. To test the hypothesis that retinoids may not affect &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;expression, we analyzed the expression levels of &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA in response to retinoid treatments or adenovirus- mediated over-expression of nuclear receptors mediating RA responses in primary rat hepatocytes and HL1C rat hepatoma cells using real-time PCR. We report that retinoids did not induce &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA expression in these cells. The over-expression of hepatocyte nuclear factor 4 alpha (HNF4α [alpha]) or chicken ovalbumin upstream promoter transcription factor 2 (COUP-TFII) significantly induced or inhibited the &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA level, respectively. Therefore, it is concluded that retinoid treatment could not directly induce &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA levels in rat hepatocytes. Instead, the hepatic expression of &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA may be controlled by the expression levels of HNFα and COUP-TFII. Furthermore, the mRNA level of &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;in isolated and cultured hepatocytes of Zucker Lean (ZL) and Zucker Fatty (ZF) was not significantly changed. However, the &lt;em&gt;Rarb and Srebp-1c &lt;/em&gt;mRNA levels, two RA-responsive genes, are significantly higher in the liver tissue and isolated hepatocytes from ZF rats thanthat from ZL rats. Therefore, we conclude that RA-induced hyperlipidemia may not be attributed to the direct induction of &lt;em&gt;Apoc3 &lt;/em&gt;mRNA level in hepatocytes by RA, but at least in part to the RA-mediated induction of lipogenic genes such as &lt;em&gt;Srebp1-c.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2424</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2664&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2424</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2664</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-01T10:05:33-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2664/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3816324</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2424</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Guoxun Chen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, Ling Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>