<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Model for the Application of Test and Evaluation Concepts by the Air Element of the Canadian Forces During the Materiel Acquisition and Support Lifecycle</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Crosby</lname>
<fname>Troy</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Systems Engineering and Multidisciplinary Design Optimization</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Recent experience has proven that the Test and Evaluation (T&amp;E) terms and responsibilities described in Department of National Defence and Canadian Forces policies and orders – particularly those related to the Category flight test system – are poorly understood and frequently in conflict with contemporary approaches to Materiel Acquisition &amp; Support.  As a result, financial and airworthiness authorities may not be recognizing the benefits inherent to the timely application of T&amp;E by the Air element of the Canadian Forces during the Materiel Acquisition &amp; Support lifecycle.  At the same time, the on-going inconsistent application of T&amp;E is resulting in frustration between T&amp;E agents and project managers, in the inefficient use of resources, and in delays in achieving project objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes a rationalized model for Air T&amp;E as it relates to the Materiel Acquisition &amp; Support lifecycle.  The model has been developed by linking legal requirements and the Department of National Defence accountability framework with T&amp;E concepts that are consistent with current airworthiness and financial management policies, and with Materiel Acquisition &amp; Support milestones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementation of these Air T&amp;E concepts will provide clarity and consistency to Materiel Acquisition &amp; Support processes leading to needed operational capability being fielded as quickly and cost effectively as possible; project management staff and Air T&amp;E agents will benefit from a common basis from which to plan T&amp;E activities.  Additionally, clarification of the associated roles and responsibilities will focus available resources where they are needed, and when they will have the most consequence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1934</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3292&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1934</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3292</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-23T13:18:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4615433</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1934</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. U.P. Solies</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ralph Kimberlin, Mr. Richard Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>