<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Regulation of Neuropeptide Corazonin and Its Functional Analyses in Drosophila Melanogaster</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Choi</lname>
<fname>Seung-Hoon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medical Biochemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Neuropeptides regulate diverse physiological processes, including homeostatic metabolism, behavior, reproduction, and development. The neuropeptide &lt;em&gt;Corazonin&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt;), was first isolated from American cockroach, &lt;em&gt;P. americana&lt;/em&gt;, as a potent cardioactive substance, and has been shown to exert diverse functions in different insects. In &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; expression is limited to three groups of neurons; totaling only 26 neurons out of ~10,000 neurons in a third instar larval central nervous system (CNS). In adults, &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; is expressed in 6-8 pairs of protocerebral neurons and 2 pairs of male specific abdominal ganglion. To gain insight into such tight regulatory mechanisms of &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; gene transcription, &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; promoter activity was dissected &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;. The promoter bashing experiments yielding various 5‘-upstream sequences show that there are separate &lt;em&gt;cis&lt;/em&gt;-acting elements that are highly conserved phylogenetically, which speaks to its functional significance in the activation of &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; transcription. In larval stage, a 504-bp upstream region is sufficient to activate &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; in all endogenous neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further dissection revealed two important regions; one between -419-bp and -504-bp region for the expression in dorsal medial neuron (DM). The other located between - 241-bp and -380-bp is responsible for dorsal lateral (DL) and ventral nerve cord (VNC) expression. The latter region can be subdivided into three DL-specific and two VNCspecific &lt;em&gt;cis&lt;/em&gt;-acting elements. For DL-specific expression, two out of any three combination were needed; however, VNC needed two elements altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, basal transcription factor binding site TATA box showed minor role for &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; expression. In contrast to the larval expression, 321-bp upstream region is sufficient to activate &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; in all adult neurons. For the male-specific abdominal ganglion (&lt;em&gt;ms-aCrz&lt;/em&gt;) expression, the &lt;em&gt;cis&lt;/em&gt;-acting element was found to be in a region between -250-bp and - 290-bp. Overall, the data show that transcriptional regulatory mechanisms for &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; expression are not uniformed among &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt;-containing neurons, which further indicates that their neuronal functions might be different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To identify the roles of &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;, several fly behaviors were tested; ethanol-related responses, olfactory sensing responses and circadian rhythmic behaviors. &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; cell deficient (Crz-CD) flies and &lt;em&gt;Crz receptor&lt;/em&gt; knock down (CrzR-KD) flies showed significantly delayed recovery from ethanol-induced sedation compared to control flies. Such hangover phenotype was ethanol specific. This result suggests that &lt;em&gt;Drosophila Crz&lt;/em&gt; involves in ethanol-related responses. Further analyses suggest that Crz-CD, CrzR-KD and CrzR mutation did not affect aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) at transcription level, but reduced ALDH enzyme activity. &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; is also associated with olfactory signaling, as Crz-CD and CrzR-KD flies are unable to find odor source, such as live yeast paste. Previously, Crz neurons located in the vicinity of nerve terminals originated from circadian pacemaker &lt;em&gt;Pdf&lt;/em&gt;-expressing neurons, which indicate &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; neurons as part of circadian circuit. However, circadian locomotor rhythmic behavior of Crz-CD, Crz over-expression and CrzR-KD flies show normal circadian rhythmic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/25</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1055&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1055</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-12-21T08:50:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1095400</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/25</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jae H. Park</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly, Mariano Labrador, Ana Kitazono, Jung Han Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>