<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Selective perspectives of implementing computer technology in K-12 education in the State of Kuwait</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Safar</lname>
<fname>Ammar</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Through this research, the author examined the opinions and attitudes of virtually every segment of the Kuwaiti society (i.e., administrators, teachers, students, parents, and community members) toward the use of computers and technology in K-12 education. A Likert scale questionnaire was the primary vehicle for data collection. This questionnaire was designed to find out value judgments for issues such as implementing computer technology as an independent subject in K-12 schools versus integrating computer technology in all other subjects. A stratified random sample was secured from all five Kuwaiti govemorates (i.e., regions) from 70 schools. The overall number of participants who received the study&#39;s survey was 1,190. Of the questionnaires distributed, 1, 165 were returned, for a return rate of 97.89 percent. Both descriptive statistics procedures (e.g., frequency, mean, and standard deviation) and inferential statistics procedures ( e.g., factor analysis, analysis of variance (ANOVA), Tukey&#39;s HSD multiple comparisons, and t-test) were conducted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6379</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8353&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6379</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8353</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:39:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24074650</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6379</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward L. Counts</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>E. Dale Doak, Schuyler Huck, Lawrence Husch,</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>