<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Producing Independent Film</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-18T11:58:14-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ssteele9@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Steele</lname>
<fname>Sydney</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Film and Media Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The job of a Producer is elusive to many people. Their work goes unnoticed by the general population, but they are the back bone of film. They are an integral part of the 5 stages of filmmaking: Development, Pre-Production, Production, Post Production, and Distribution. During my research with the film, &lt;em&gt;Light From Light&lt;/em&gt;, I shadowed the producer’s through these stages to get a proper understanding of producing. Even on a low-budget independent film, such as this one, a clever producer navigates most issues to ensure that the director completes his true vision for the story. Independent producing requires more work, in some ways, than studio producing because there is no guaranteed funding, no safety net, and no guaranteed distribution. They are a creative force that offers notes to the director during the writing process, filming, and editing. They are a business force that secures funding, contract the cast and crew, and navigate the industry to get the film distributed to audiences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/24</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1266&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1266</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-18T09:00:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14295127</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts and Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Cinema Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Paul Harrill</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>