<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Problem Solving Strategies of Selected Managers</title>
<publication-date>1982-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ihlenfeld</lname>
<fname>Carl</fname>
<mname>James</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study were (1) to describe the problem-solving steps followed by selected managers; (2) to examine the reasons supporting problem solving behavior; and (3) to compare the managers&#39; problem-solving processes with selected models of problem solving. Managers from metropolitan Knoxville and Johnson City, Tennessee, were chosen using non-random methods of selection. Twelve individuals were selected for study. Criteria for selection were based on job title and job description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal interviews by the researcher were the primary means of data collection. The interviews were tape recorded and later transcribed verbatim. Transcripts were then submitted to a method of analysis known as ACTS analysis, which was developed for this purpose by a team of researchers engaged in a research project at the University of Tennessee sponsored by the National Institute of Education. Data from the ACTS analysis were analyzed further by frequency counts, comparisons of data within the sample, and comparisons of data selected models of problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major finding of the research was that past experience and external environmental influences were key determinants of problem-solving strategies and reasonings among the sample group. Other factors found to influence problem-solving processes were the problem situation, organizational policies and regulatory dictates, time and common sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second major finding was that approximately one-half of the subject group appeared to follow a problem solving-process similar to one selected as a model. Additionally, many of the cases studied contained similarities in approach to that described in a well-known work on managerial problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall objective of this study was not to solve a particular problem, but to explore a particular subject area and generate topics for future inquiry. A second goal was to test a new method of analysis to determine its effectiveness. The ACTS method proved to be extremely effective in eliminating extraneous information from a narrative and reducing the data to the lowest, simplest form. Its effectiveness was limited, however, in uncovering the reasonings behind behavior. Another methodology needs to be developed to accomplish this task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is evident from this study that much more research in the area of problem solving is required. This is especially true of the relationship between past experience and problem solving. More research into problem-solving processes is also indicated. The comparisons of the sample groups&#39; processes with those selected as models for this study indicate strong similarities. It remains to be seen if this finding was limited to this group only or if similar results would apply to a more universal sample.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3011</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4388&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3011</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4388</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-12T11:56:59-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6457889</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3011</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John M. Peters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Malcom McInnis, Robert Maddox</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>