<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Welcome Home</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-18T06:27:21-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cschulz1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schulz</lname>
<fname>Chelsea</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Marketing</discipline>
<discipline>Real Estate</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Hearth &amp; Home Renovation and Design, LLC is a real estate investment, renovation and home design company serving the greater Nashville Area market. Hearth &amp; Home acts primarily in the following three industries: real estate, flipping/renovation, and design. Through synergistic actions across all of these industries, Hearth &amp; Home delivers superior customer value to home-buyers. Hearth &amp; Home has identified several strategic competitive advantages which are found through key partnerships, design and brand equity. Key partnerships will lead to mutually beneficial cost efficiencies. Design will create distinction and opportunities to retain customers longer than competitors. Brand equity will be built through a sophisticated content-driven marketing campaign; these marketing efforts address a gap in the market and serve as a differentiator among competitors. Through each step of the process, the Hearth &amp; Home brand represents superior quality. This is recognizable not only in the quality of construction and design efforts, but also in the customer service delivered during each and every interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/business/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1208&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1208</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-05-03T09:03:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>12065976</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/business/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Marketing</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Lynn Youngs</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>