<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Community College Student Experiences in a Tuition-Free Scholarship Program</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rmilam@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Milam</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>Murph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Tennessee Promise</keyword>
<keyword>tuition-free scholarship program</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Tuition-free college scholarship programs are rapidly sweeping the country in higher education. Tennessee Promise, the first statewide program, was implemented in 2015. Currently, there are at least 16 statewide programs with more in the planning stages. This study addressed the need to understand how students experienced college when tuition was not an issue. The purpose of the study was to understand the experience of Tennessee Promise students at a community college as they navigated entry and continuance as scholarship recipients. Utilizing a basic qualitative approach, nine Tennessee Promise scholarship recipients who had successfully completed their second semester or beyond were interviewed. Cultural Historical Activity Theory (CHAT) served as the study’s theoretical framework with activity systems analysis guiding data interpretation. Seven themes were revealed through the voices of the students: (1) decision to participate; (2) application process; (3) program continuance requirements; (4) program challenges; (5) community service experiences; (6) mentorship experiences; and (7) program outcomes. The findings included the study participants’ appreciation for the opportunity to attend college tuition-free, their dependence on positive family support, and their agreement about the smooth application process and the benefits of community service. Findings also surfaced challenges with the mentorship program, understating last-dollar scholarships, the Promise payment process, and communication. Even though this study provided only a glimpse into what students experience at one college in one statewide program, the documented accomplishments and strategies to increase college completion through Tennessee Promise provides insights for the design and implementation of tuition-free programs in other locations and with different program designs. Implications for practice applicable to other free college programs and recommendations for future research are provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5773</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7539&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5773</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7539</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419669</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5773</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patrick Biddix, Lisa Yamagata-Lynch, Mary Catherine Hammon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>