<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of ozone treatment on quality of orange juice</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Angelino</lname>
<fname>Paul</fname>
<mname>David</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Orange juice and orange juice fractions were treated with ozone to determine the effect that ozone has on ascorbic acid, color and Saccharomyces cerevisiae (predominant spoilage yeast in orange juice). Several foodborne disease outbreaks associated with fruit juices over the past decade have brought about new regulations by FDA requiring juice processors to implement a Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point (HACCP) program and a 5-log reduction of pertinent pathogenic organisms. Those unable or unwilling must provide a warning statement on the product package stating the possible hazards associated with consumption of the product. High-temperature short-time (HTST) pasteurization is predominately used in milk and fruit juice processing. However, the high cost associated with this method has led to research on less expensive methods to achieve a 5-log reduction of pertinent pathogenic organisms. Ozone is a possible alternative to HTST pasteurization. Ozone has long been used in treatment of water supplies and as a sanitizer. Recently, ozone treatment has been shown to be an effective method in achieving a 5-log reduction of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in apple cider and Salmonella in orange juice.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6200</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8152&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6200</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8152</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450287</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6200</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>P. Michael Davidson, F. Ann Draughon, John R. Mount, Luther R. Wilhelm</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>