<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>When patients attack: The experience of inpatient mental health counselors after a physical attack from a patient</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>eburns9@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Burns</lname>
<fname>Evan</fname>
<mname>Montgomery</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>counselor</keyword>
<keyword>inpatient</keyword>
<keyword>physical attack</keyword>
<keyword>psychological</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Mental health professionals who work at inpatient facilities are at an increased risk of physical attacks from patients (Beech &amp; Leather, 2006; Campbell et al., 2011; GAO, 2016; Gillespie et al., 2010). Research on physical attacks in the human services field has focused on other mental health professionals, such as psychiatric nurses and social workers; research looking specifically at mental health counselors is lacking. The purpose of this qualitative study, through Interpretative Phenomenological Analysis, was to understand the lived experiences of mental health counselors after a physical attack from a patient. The research interviewed four mental health counselors who experienced a physical attack from one of their patients. Through analysis of the interviews, five main themes emerged: negative patient factors, strong facility reaction, positivity from experience, psychological damage, and assigning blame. Implications for policy and practice were considered and suggestions and recommendations for future research were provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5251</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6795&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5251</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6795</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T08:36:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>14342727</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5251</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Shawn L. Spurgeon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Casey Barrio Minton, Jennifer Morrow, Marian Roman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Counselor Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>