<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Core competencies of professional service providers in federally funded education programs</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Marmon</lname>
<fname>Dora</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this national study was to identify core competencies for administrators and other professional service providers in selected federally funded education programs. The population was administrators of Talent Search, Upward Bound, and Student Support Services projects. A proportional stratified random sample of 579 administrators received the survey; 354 responded. The usable response was 346 (59.8%). A researcher-developed instrument was revised according to advice of a national panel of experts. The instrument was piloted and again revised prior to the national survey. The overall Cronbach&#39;s alpha for the instrument was .97. The 100-item questionnaire was divided into 18 core competency categories: Administration, Admissions, Advising, Curricula, Extra-curricula, Financial Aid, Follow Up and Evaluation, Grantwriting, Information, Interpersonal Skills, Leadership, Motivation, Planning, Professional Development, Public Relations, Recruitment, Teaching, and Technology.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6267</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8219&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6267</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8219</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450364</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6267</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Julia A. Malia, Connie Hollingsworth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>