<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Luxe-Bargain Shopping: Consumer Orientations, Perceived Values, Satisfaction, and Future Intentions</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lim</lname>
<fname>Chae</fname>
<mname>Mi</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Hospitality Administration and Management</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study was designed to examine the phenomenon of “massclusivity” of luxury (i.e., increased accessibility and affordability of luxury) in the current luxury market. To do so, this study introduced the concept of “Luxe-Bargain Shopping,” which referred to purchasing a luxury brand at a bargain, and developed an empirical framework that portrayed both luxury consumption and the bargain process. The specific research objectives of this study were to: (1) investigate whether luxury-related consumer orientations (i.e., prestige sensitivity and fashion leadership) influence perceived product values (i.e., social, emotional, and quality values); (2) investigate whether bargain-related consumer orientations (i.e., price mavenism and sale proneness) influence perceived process values (i.e., transaction value); (3) investigate whether perceived product and process values predict satisfaction with Luxe-Bargain Shopping; (4) examine whether satisfaction with Luxe-Bargain Shopping influences future intentions to buy the luxury brand at a bargain; (5) examine whether perceived product and process values influence future intentions to buy the luxury brand at a bargain; (6) examine whether perceived product and process values influence future intentions to buy the luxury brand at full price; and (7) examine the moderating role of shopper type in the relationship between perceived values and future intentions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study was conducted in the context of luxury apparel or accessories. An online survey methodology was employed to collect the data and 500 completed responses were used for the data analyses. Both the luxury-related consumer orientations and bargain-related consumer orientations were found to be important consumer characteristics that predict perceived values generated in Luxe-Bargain Shopping. The perceived value influenced future  intention to purchase the luxury at a bargain indirectly through satisfaction. However, the direct links between perceived values and future intention to buy the luxury brand at a bargain were not supported in this study. The relationships between perceived values and future intentions to buy the luxury brand at full price were found to be significant. The shopper type was not a significant moderator between perceived values and future intentions. Research implications, managerial implications, and suggestions for future research based on the findings were provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/68</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1098&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>68</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1098</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-12-22T12:27:52-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1096767</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/68</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Youn-Kyung Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ann E. Fairhurst, Rodney C. Runyan, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Retail, Hospitality, and Tourism Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>