<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>De la esclavitud a la libertad: La historia de una esclava afromexicana</title>
<publication-date>2021-05-13T09:46:10-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mgjackso@go.olemiss.edu</email>
<institution>University of Mississippi Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Jackson</lname>
<fname>Margaree</fname>
<mname>G</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>esclavitud</keyword>
<keyword>cimarronaje</keyword>
<keyword>afrolatino</keyword>
<keyword>afromexicana</keyword>
<keyword>siglo XVII</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Africana Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Ethnic Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Fiction</discipline>
<discipline>Latin American History</discipline>
<discipline>Latin American Languages and Societies</discipline>
<discipline>Modern Languages</discipline>
<discipline>Poetry</discipline>
<discipline>Women&#39;s History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;x-x-x-x-x-x-docs-internal-guid-9780f2db-7fff-7046-d212-ac06932fa2e7&quot;&gt;Resumen: “De la esclavitud a la libertad: La historia de una esclava afromexicana,” es una colección de poemas descolonizados contados desde la perspectiva de una mujer afromexicana ficticia del siglo XVII. La protagonista, Maricela Rivas, es una esclava que nació en la plantación azucarera Nuestra Señora de la Concepción, una plantación verdadera ubicada en Veracruz, México. Su historia se basa en las pocas historias que existen sobre la vida de la mujer afromexicana que formaba parte esencial de la sociedad y cultura mexicana pero que le falta representación y una voz. Estos poemas le dan una voz y perspectiva al personaje, la mujer negra, que faltamos en la historia. Cuentan los desafíos y los triunfos de la gente afromexicana a través de la perspectiva de la heroína de la colección.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: “From Slavery to Freedom: The Story of an Afro-Mexican slave” is a collection of decolonized poems told from the perspective of a fictional Afro-Mexican woman from the 17th century. The protagonist, Maricela Rivas, is a slave who was born on the sugar plantation Nuestra Señora de la Concepción, an actual plantation located in Veracruz, Mexico. Her story is based on the few accounts that exist about the lives of the Afro-Mexican women who formed an essential part of Mexican culture and society but lack representation and a voice. These poems give a voice and a perspective to the Black women that we lack in history. They tell the challenges and the triumphs of the Afro-Mexican people through the lens of the heroine of the collection.  &lt;p id=&quot;x-x-x-x-x-x-docs-internal-guid-da93c329-7fff-2449-3031-e144be3546d2&quot;&gt;Sobre la autora: Margaree Jackson es una estudiante de posgrado en la Universidad de Mississippi. Está trabajando en una maestría en lenguas modernas con una especialización en el español. Jackson es una autoproclamada poeta de liberación que desea contar las historias de mujeres afro con el fin de llevar a cabo la liberación de sistemas de opresión. Disfruta hacer investigaciones sobre las niñas y las mujeres de ascendencia africana en las Américas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the author: Margaree Jackson is a graduate student at the University of Mississippi. She is working toward an M.A. in Modern Languages with a specialization in Spanish. Jackson is a self-declared liberation poet who desires to tell the stories of Black women with the goal to bring liberation from systems of oppression. She enjoys conducting research on girls and women of African descent in the Americas.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/vernacular/vol6/iss1/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1080&amp;amp;context=vernacular&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>peer_reviewed</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1080</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-07T09:26:55-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/vernacular/article/1080/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Vernacular: New Connections in Language, Literature, &amp; Culture</publication-title>
<context-key>20465862</context-key>
<submission-path>vernacular/vol6/iss1/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-07T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xd5ef4b8)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>De la esclavitud a la libertad</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>