<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Experimental Study of Spinning Tension and Its Relation to Fiber Properties and End Breakage</title>
<publication-date>1963-11-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Landstreet</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>Busch</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;From the Statement of the Problem&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Abbreviated&lt;/em&gt;]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end-breakage rate is a function of many variables, some of which can be controlled and some of which cannot. Spindle speed, ring diameter, yarn number, yarn twist, and fiber properties are some of the controllable variables. Ring wear, traveler wear, and yarn irregularity are variables that cannot be controlled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experiments conducted in a spinning laboratory can be carried out under test conditions that are impossible to duplicate in a textile mill. The disadvantage is that to get reproducible results long-term experiments are required if conventional test methods are used. The experiments become expensive and time consuming. There is little recorded data relating fiber properties, yarn tension, and end-breakage rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study of spinning tension as it affects yarn properties required the development of special instruments and techniques. Two devices were built and used. One was a mechanical tension meter attached directly to the spinning frame. The second was an adaptation of a strain gage, strain gage amplifier, and continuous strip-chart recorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects of spindle speed and traveler weight on spinning tension were studied. Spinning frame adjustments were worked out to give desired tensions, and the effect of these tensions on yarn physical properties analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific objectives of this study were:&lt;br /&gt;1.To develop an instrument which would measure spinning tension over a wide range. &lt;br /&gt;2. To work out combinations of spindle speed, traveler weight, and yarn number producing predetermined yarn tension. &lt;br /&gt;3. To develop an accelerated end-breakage rate test for laboratory use. &lt;br /&gt;4. To use the accelerated end-breakage rate test to measure the effects of fiber length, tenacity, and fineness on the ability of a yarn to support a load while spinning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present study was also to serve as a guide to further experiments involving fiber properties and end-breakage rates.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3132</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4515&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3132</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4515</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-21T09:08:31-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6548401</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3132</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Anna Jean Treece</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Chambers, Lois E. Dickey</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Polymer Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1963-11-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1963-11-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>