<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Garden is Always Greener...</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-08T12:50:54-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>whall002@fiu.edu</email>
<institution>Florida International University</institution>
<lname>Hall</lname>
<fname>Billy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>food movements</keyword>
<keyword>urban agriculture</keyword>
<keyword>alternative development</keyword>
<keyword>gentrification</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nature and Society Relations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This essay builds upon a case study of community gardening in Miami to explore the extent to which these gardens are contributing to, and possibly triggering, processes of gentrification within low to lower-middle income neighborhoods. Through a literature review of recent urban planning policy and development in Miami and relevant discourse on the neoliberalization of food, food politics, food justice activism, and gentrification, I situate Miami’s gardens within a complex, multi-scalar web of ideas and processes. I show how the interaction of these forces, varying dramatically with respect to place, is implicit in the motivations for each garden’s development and creates a unique context for the production of a “garden community.” I then critically examine the impacts these gardens – and the respective communities they produce – have within the larger community of the neighborhoods and places in which they are located. Secondly, with the intent to help bridge the disconnect between food justice and broader social movements, I engage the Environmental Justice Movement literature as a pathway toward exploring possibilities for mitigating gentrification and the physical displacement of vulnerable people. Thus, by learning from the key factors vital to the successes of the Environmental Justice Movement, food justice advocates can better conceptualize and build alternative food initiatives &lt;em&gt;with, &lt;/em&gt;and not &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;, marginalized communities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol1/iss1/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1011&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-11T22:40:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>2010636</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol1/iss1/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>This material was developed in collaboration with the Miami-Dade Urban Long Term Research Area program under National Science Foundation Grant No. BCS-0948988. I would like to thank Dr. Laura Ogden and Dr. Gail Hollander for lending much insight and critical feedback throughout the research process and the writing of this paper. Additionally, I would like to express gratitude to all of the interviewees and participants in this research, as well as to Sheila Sutton, Lindsey Nieratka, Liliano Helo, Sean Koester, and Jennifer Matas whose ideas, comments, and energy helped steer the direction of this project.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>The Garden is Always Greener</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>