<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modeling and Analysis of the DuPont Access Bridge</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Naiyu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Civil Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis evaluates the lateral wheel load distribution on a two-span experimental highway bridge, examines the continuity of the superstructure over the center pier, and investigates the connection between bridge girders and abutments. Simplified finite element models of the bridge superstructure with different boundary conditions were made during the research to simulate the bridge behavior and verify the field data. Live load distribution factors for moment from the model with a rotational spring connection between bridge girders and abutment correlated well with factors from field measurements, and they were compared with factors from other methods currently in use such as AASHTO 1996, Henry’s Method, and AASHTO LRFD Specifications.  Moment transferred from strain measurements close to the center pier also compared favorably with the output from the single girder computer model with continuous boundary condition over the center pier and a rotational spring boundary condition at the ends. Therefore, the splice connection over the center pier appears to have created full continuity between the two spans.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2543</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3809&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2543</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3809</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-18T11:16:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4739075</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2543</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edwin G. Burdette</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David W. Goodpasture, J. Harold Deatherage</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>