<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The role of trust and authority in the citation behaviour of researchers.</title>
<publication-date>2015-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>clare.v.thornley@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Thornley</lname>
<fname>Clare</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>watkinson@btinternet.com</email>
<institution>CIBER Research Ltd.</institution>
<lname>Watkinson</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>Dave.Nicholas@ciber-research.eu</email>
<institution>CIBER Research Ltd.</institution>
<lname>Nicholas</lname>
<fname>Dave</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Volentine</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>CIBER Research Ltd.</institution>
<lname>Jamali</lname>
<fname>Hamid</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>CIBER Research Ltd.</institution>
<lname>Herman</lname>
<fname>Eti</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Allard</lname>
<fname>Suzie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Levine</lname>
<fname>Kenneth</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>citation behavior</keyword>
<keyword>information resources</keyword>
<keyword>trust</keyword>
<keyword>researchers</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper reports on an interview-based citation behaviour study, part of a wider study of trust in information resources, investigating why researchers chose to cite particular references in one of their publications. Their motivations are explored, with an emphasis on whether they regarded the reference as an authoritative and trustworthy source, and, if so, to what extent and why. Method. Semi-structured critical incident interviews were carried out with eighty-seven researchers from the UK and the USA. Analysis. The answers were analysed using qualitative techniques and then grouped under descriptive headings of the types of reasons for citation provided. These were then used to create a table of these types of reason and the frequency of their use. Results. The motivations for citing were found to be complex and multi-faceted but, in nearly all cases, researchers do regard the authority and trustworthiness of the cited source as an important factor in choosing to cite it. This suggests that citation is at least partly an acknowledgement of the intellectual influence of the content of the cited source. It was also found, however, that researchers have strong social networks of trust and collaboration. They make considerable use of these in receiving and gathering information for research and thus context is also important in their eventual citation decisions. Conclusions. Citing behaviour does include an acknowledgement of useful intellectual content, but this process cannot be separated from the researcher&#39;s position in networks of trusted social and research influence. The digital transition has provided tools to help maintain and develop these social networks and it has also made it easier for researchers to investigate the credentials of the sources of documents. This suggests that the current distinction in the literature between normative and constructionist theories of citation behaviour may not capture the nuanced and complex relationship between these two factors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/157</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1069&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>157</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1069</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-10-05T18:14:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15499476</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/157</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Thornley, C., Watkinson, A., Nicholas, D., Volentine, R., Jamali, H. R., Herman, E., Allard, S., Levine, K. J. &amp; Tenopir, C. “The role of trust and authority in the citation behaviour of researchers.” Information Research, 20(3),” paper 677, September 2015.</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Information Research</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>