<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Can Text Analysis of TAT Protocols Differentiate Patients Operating at Neurotic, Borderline, and Psychotic Levels of Personality Organization?</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ptullis@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tullis</lname>
<fname>Paul</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Level of Personality Organization</keyword>
<keyword>Thematic Apperception Test</keyword>
<keyword>Text Analysis</keyword>
<keyword>Linguistic Inquiry Word Count</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined whether computerized text analysis of Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) protocols could differentiate patients operating at neurotic, borderline, and psychotic levels of personality organization (LPO). From a large University psychological clinic archival database, I identified fifty-­‐two (N = 52) patients whose files: a) contained verbatim TAT responses; and b) included diagnosis indicative of neurotic, borderline, or psychotic LPO. Verbatim TAT transcriptions were input and analyzed using Linguistic Inquiry Word Count (LIWC) software. I hypothesized that 1) The use of cognitive words would be more common among the TAT protocols of the neurotic patients than among the protocols of the borderline and psychotic patients; 2) the use of negative emotion words and negation words would be more prominent among the psychotic and borderline patient protocols than among the neurotic patients. A limited number of psychotic protocols meeting selection criteria required me to eliminate the psychosis category in the analysis; however, the results of one-­‐way ANOVA found that the neurotic group used cognitive words during TAT administration at a significantly higher rate than did the borderline group. The effect size for this difference was moderate to large.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4757</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5432&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4757</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5432</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-05T11:46:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8934638</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4757</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Nash</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Heather Hirschfeld, Timothy Hulsey, Garriy Shteynberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>