<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular-Level Investigation of Critical Gap Size between Catalyst Particles and Electrolyte in Hydrogen Proton Exchange Membrane Fuel Cells</title>
<publication-date>2008-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>J.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cui</lname>
<fname>S.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Keffer</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Fuel Cell</keyword>
<keyword>Electrode</keyword>
<keyword>Electrolyte</keyword>
<keyword>Interface</keyword>
<keyword>Nafion</keyword>
<keyword>Molecular Dynamics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Molecular dynamics simulations have been performed to study the structure and transport at the electrode/electrolyte interface in hydrogen-based proton exchange membrane fuel cells. We examine the wetting of catalyst surfaces that are not immediately adjacent to a Nafion membrane, but rather are separated from the membrane by a hydrophobic gap of carbon support surface (graphite). A mixture of Nafion, water and hydronium ions is able to wet small gaps (7.4 Å) of graphite and reach the catalyst surface, providing a path for proton transport from the catalyst to the membrane. However, for gaps of 14.8 Å, we observe no wetting of the graphite or the catalyst surface. Using a coarse-grained model, we found that the presence of a graphite gap of 7.4 Å width slowed down the transport of water by at least an order of magnitude relative to a system with no gap. The implication is that catalyst particles that are not within nominally 1 nm of either the proton exchange membrane or recast ionomer in the electrode leading to the membrane do not possess a path for efficient proton transport to the membrane and consequently do not contribute significantly to power production in the fuel cell.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_chembiopubs/50</coverpage-url>
<label>50</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1055</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-26T07:22:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>1331158</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_chembiopubs/50</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>AU: J. Liu
AU: S. Cui
AU: D. J. Keffer
TI: Molecular-Level Investigation of Critical Gap Size between Catalyst Particles and Electrolyte in Hydrogen Proton Exchange Membrane Fuel Cells
SO: Fuel Cells
VL: 8
NO: 6
PG: 422-428
YR: 2008
CP: Copyright © 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim
ON: 1615-6854
PN: 1615-6846
AD: Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN 37996-2200, USA
DOI: 10.1002/fuce.200800001
US: http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/fuce.200800001</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119818623/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>