<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Surveillance of Luncheon Meats for the Occurrence of &lt;em&gt;Listeria monocytogenes&lt;/em&gt; in Grocery Stores in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stevens</lname>
<fname>Jacob</fname>
<mname>Henry</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The current United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) and Department of Health and Human Services Food and Drug Administration (FDA) policy of ‘zero tolerance’ for &lt;em&gt;Listeria monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;in ready to eat (RTE) foods has prompted the food industry to increase food safety and sanitation practices in order to reduce and inhibit the growth of &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes&lt;/em&gt;. In order to better understand the point of contamination of luncheon meats&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; a survey of its occurrence was performed in grocery stores throughout Tennessee. Approximately 1000 manufactured-packaged and 1000 deli-sliced luncheon meat samples were analyzed using the USDA-FSIS analytical method with minor modifications over a 10-month period. The overall occurrence of the organism was 0.8%. There were a significantly higher percentage (PL. monocytogenes was never recovered; in a few cases the population exceeded 110 MPN/g. Chromogenic agar provided more rapid confirmation of &lt;em&gt;L. monocytogenes &lt;/em&gt;than modified oxford agar (MOX) agar. Results from this study showed that increased food safety practices are needed in grocery store deli environments in order to reduce occurrence of lunchmeat due to excessive, yet necessary handling.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1805</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3158&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1805</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3158</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-06T09:47:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4559414</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1805</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>F. Ann Draughon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Golden, Svetlana Zivanovic</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>