<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Examining Consensual Non-Monogamy among Emerging Adult Samples: A Collection of Studies</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ksizemo1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sizemore</lname>
<fname>Kayla</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>consensual non-monogamy</keyword>
<keyword>gender</keyword>
<keyword>emerging adulthood</keyword>
<keyword>mixed methods</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Using multiple methodologies, this collection of manuscripts examined various components of CNM during the period of emerging adulthood. Manuscript one presents a systematic review and critique of the methodology used in research on CNM attitudes and desire among emerging adults between 1974 and 2016. Several methodological characteristics were reviewed across 18 empirical articles, including sample characteristics, recruitment and sampling strategy, measurement, and overall methodology and focus. Despite general commentary among researchers in this field, this review concludes that CNM research has shown little improvement with regard to its methodological limitations since the 1970’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second manuscript contributes to the extant CNM literature by addressing several limitations within the field. Specifically, this paper is among the first to qualitatively measure CNM desire. A mixed-methods approach was used to examine a sample of emerging adults’ (ages 18-29; &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 549) responses to a question about CNM desire. Results from a qualitative content analysis revealed three distinct groups (&lt;em&gt;Unwilling, Willing,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Open-Minded)&lt;/em&gt;. Further, several subthemes emerged within each group that helped illuminate why emerging adults are (or are not) willing to engage in CNM. Quantitative analyses considered the relationship between group membership, gender, and perceived adulthood status. A greater proportion of women were in the &lt;em&gt;Unwilling&lt;/em&gt; group, and a greater proportion of men were in the &lt;em&gt;Willing&lt;/em&gt; group. No group differences were found for comparisons based on perceived adulthood status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manuscript three utilized multi-group structural equation modeling to test a conceptual model of CNM desire among emerging adults (ages 18-29; &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 890). Based on the theory of emerging adulthood and the extant literature, proposed correlates included experimentation/possibilities during emerging adulthood, sexual identity exploration, and casual sex attitudes. Results indicated that these predictors were all related to willingness to engage in CNM. Also, the pathway from emerging adult experimentation/possibilities to willingness to engage in CNM was differentially mediated across gender. For women there was a positive indirect pathway from experimentation/possibilities to CNM through sexual identity exploration. However, for men this path was mediated through casual sex attitudes. Together, this collection of manuscripts sought to identify and address important limitations in CNM methodology.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3965</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5265&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3965</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5265</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-25T09:01:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8516452</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3965</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Spencer B. Olmstead</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kristina Gordon, John Orme, Elizabeth Johnson, Carin Neitzel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Child and Family Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>