<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mechanisms of methanogenic microbial community assembly: dissecting anaerobic digester as a model</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lcao5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Cao</lname>
<fname>Liu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Anaerobic DigestionSyntrophyMethanogenesis</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Second, DDC strategies for both primary and secondary frequency regulation were studied. The control strategy has the following features. 1) The target load reduction amount can be achieved in a decentralized manner, while the control parameters are updated by the control center. Therefore, the control strategy is easy to implement in the hardware. 2) The daily demand profiles of thermostatic loads are modeled. 3) The load recovery process is considered in the control strategy. Consequently, the aggregate loads can provide flexible frequency control capability without causing significant power rebound. Therefore, demand side control is an essential compensation for traditional frequency regulation approaches and can improve the frequency response of the bulk power system. Furthermore, this dissertation also conducts an economic analysis on demand response (DR). Based on a large-scale customer survey, we estimate the expense of frequency regulation and peak load reduction via incentive-based demand response (IBDR). The results provide useful suggestions for utility companies when implementing IBDR programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5607</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7253&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5607</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7253</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T19:12:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>18911645</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5607</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Chris Cox, Qiang He</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Terry Hazen, Jun Lin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2022-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>