<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Laser Processing of Refractory Metal - Refractory Carbide Alloys</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rajput</lname>
<fname>Deepak</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objective of the present study was to laser process a refractory metal – refractory carbide alloy based on W-Ti-C ternary system for severe service applications. The key concept was to cast a eutectic alloy of tungsten and titanium carbide/carbonitride straight from the melt through laser materials processing route. In the present study, a WTi- C ternary alloy has been laser processed into three-dimensional objects and surface protective coatings. Two novel fabrication systems were designed to build threedimensional objects, namely tower nozzle solid freeform fabrication system and axissymmetric laser powder deposition system. W-Ti-C alloy based protective coatings were deposited on graphite substrates, through laser melting of pre-placed powder mixture, to widen the use of carbon structural elements for high temperature applications. A method for depositing W-Ti-C alloy on steel using multi-intermediate layers strategy is discussed and the preliminary results are presented in this study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/485</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1521&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>485</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1521</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-22T09:11:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1161144</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/485</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William H. Hofmeister</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jacqueline Anne Johnson, Lloyd M. Davis, William H. Hofmeister</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/RajputDeepak.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>