<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Productivity, Quality, and Cost Relationships in a Healthcare Foodservice System</title>
<publication-date>1990-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Buchan</lname>
<fname>Roberta</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A pilot study was conducted in a 165-bed combination hospital-nursing home with a conventional food production system to develop a system to measure productivity, quality, and cost of meals and service and to determine the relationship among those variables. Measurement of these variables was made from December, 1988 to September, 1989. Historical productivity and cost data were obtained from departmental records for the time period from January, 1986 through November, 1988.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mean productivity was 14.4 ± 1.5 labor minutes paid per meal equivalent. The mean total cost per meal was $1.59 ± .23. The mean overall percent quality index was 88 ± 5. Major quality problems related to temperature control of food at point of service and delivery and cleanliness and orderliness of equipment and work areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple linear regression analysis showed no significant relationship between Quality Index and Productivity Indexes, between Productivity Indexes and Cost per meal Index, and between Quality Index and Cost per meal Index. Multiple linear regression showed that Productivity Index and Quality Index do not predict Cost per meal Index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides a comprehensive system that could be used by other dietitians to set standards for productivity, cost, and quality variables and to monitor performance related to these variables in their operations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3998</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5487&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3998</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5487</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-21T08:09:12-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9161507</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3998</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jeannie Sneed</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jean D. Skinner, Betty R. Carruth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1990-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1990-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>