<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Artificial Neural Network for Spectrum unfolding Bonner Sphere Data</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hou</lname>
<fname>Jia</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The use of Bonner Sphere Spectrometer (BSS) is a well-established method of measuring the energy distribution of neutron emission sources. The purpose of this research is to apply the Generalized Regression Neural Network (GRNN), a kind of Artificial Neural Network (ANN), to predict the neutron spectrum using the count rate data from a BSS. The BSS system was simulated with the MCNP5 Monte-Carlo code to calculate the response to neutrons of different energies for each combination of thermal neutron detector and polyethylene sphere. One hundred and sixty-three different types of neutron spectra were then investigated. GRNN Training and testing was carried out in the MATLAB environment. In the GRNN testing, eight-one predicted spectra were obtained as outputs of the GRNN. Comparison with standard spectra shows that 97.5% of the prediction errors were controlled below 1%, indicating ANN could be used as an alternative with high accuracy in neutron spectrum unfolding methodologies. Advantages and further improvements of this technique are also discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/143</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1175&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>143</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1175</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-09T11:34:33-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1137742</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/143</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Laurence F. Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ronald E. Pevey, J. Wesley Hines</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/HouJia.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>