<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of Tennessee State Park Governance: Public Involvement, Agency Accountability and Conservation Implications</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Long</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Mallinson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A primary challenge for governance in our democracy is one of creating governing arrangements and structures that can pursue policies and other decisions that are effective (meet the public interest) and efficient. The history of Tennessee State Parks’ strategic direction and management is fraught with political interests guiding these decisions. This allows the political power to be concentrated in the executive and legislative arms of government and is subject to special interest economic and political influences. The civic/public sector has had little influence on these decisions. Given these conditions, the agency is particularly vulnerable to political battles between the executive and legislative branches of government, as witnessed in the tax and budgets struggles of recent years in Tennessee, resulting in the temporary closings of fourteen state parks. Results also include disinvestments over time in management systems, questionable strategic decisions regarding high-end capital expenditures for resort development, and incentives for legislators to push for the development of recreational structures in their home districts regardless of environmental or strategic impacts on the Tennessee State Parks system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A literature review, a Survey of State Park Directors, and personal interviews with persons affiliated with Tennessee State Parks governance were conducted to determine the past history of Tennessee State Parks governance, what models and processes lead to good governance, and specifically how strategic management plans, advisory committees, and process for public involvement impact agency accountability and the protection of park and natural areas. The results of this research led to findings and recommendations for an independent and comprehensive decision-making model for state park governance and a reliable and sufficient funding source for the Tennessee State Parks system.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2246</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3592&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2246</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3592</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T09:06:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4692281</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2246</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David Ostermeier</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. Mark Fly, Sherry Cable</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Forestry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>