<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Antecedents and Consequences of Global Supply Chain Process Integration</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Omar</lname>
<fname>Ayman</fname>
<mname>Amin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business</discipline>
<discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Global business executives and researchers recently highlight the importance of understanding the dynamics of supply chain process integration in a global context. The literature still lacks studies that provide a comprehensive understanding of the major antecedents and consequences of supply chain process integration from a global perspective. This dissertation builds on several theoretical foundations such as the resource based view (RBV), the relational view (RV) of the firm and transaction cost analysis (TCA) to develop a framework that explains the drivers and outcomes of global supply chain process integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This global study responds to these challenges through exploring the antecedents and consequences of global supply chain process integration for 320 supply chain and purchasing managers that source from over 33 countries. A theoretical framework is proposed that builds on research in strategic management, supply chain management, and international business and tests 8 proposed hypotheses. One new construct – global supply chain process integration – is developed and tested. Another construct, logistics performance, is modified from its existing form in the current literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significant results and good fit indices tested with structural equation modeling generate a number of interesting implications for global supply chain managers and researchers. For executives and strategists who are concerned about better managing their supply chains, this study provides insights for how manufacturing firms can develop a competitive edge through a higher level of flexibility by integrating its supply chain processes with its global suppliers. The study also provides empirical evidence on how supplier flexibility in a global environment can lead to improvements in process and firm performance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/496</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1560&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>496</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1560</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-19T11:57:23-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1156510</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/496</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John T. Mentzer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Theodore P. Stank, Matthew B. Myers, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/OmarAyman1.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>