<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Training performance transfer between web-based instruction and traditional classroom training</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dalton</lname>
<fname>Gabe</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the study was to compare learners&#39; perceptions of transfer of related training between WBI learners and traditional learners. Secondly, the survey investigated demographic factors to determine any differences between WBI learners and traditional learners. The Training Performance Transfer (Petty &amp; Farris, 2001) was used to gather data for the study. Respondents were undergraduate and graduate students enrolled in Human Resource Development classes at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville for the Fall 2001 semester. A total number of 324 surveys were e-mailed to the potential respondents, 127 surveys were completed for a 39% response rate. Descriptive statistics including mean and frequencies were gathered for the demographic data to discover respondents&#39; perceptions of transfer of related training. Pillai&#39;s Trace, a multivariate of analysis test was used to determine perceptions of transfer of related training between WBI learners and traditional learners. A test of between subjects effects was used to investigate differences between WBI learners and traditional learners based on the five subcategories of the survey (peer support, supervisor support, motivation, self-efficacy, and organization environment). The major findings implicated (a) there are no significant differences in perceptions of transfer of related training for WBI learners vs. traditional learners and (b) there are no significant differences in perceptions of transfer of related training for WBI learners and traditional learners based on the demographic factors: years of fulltime work experience, years experience as supervisor, gender, level of education, age, number of previous online college courses completed, current occupational status, and online course experience.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5907</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7540&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5907</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7540</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467563</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5907</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Debbie L. Mackey, Doo H. Lim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>