<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Measuring Change in Psychotherapy Using the MMPI-2 and the Holt Measure of Primary Process Manifestation</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ktoman@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Toman</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Psychodynamic Psychotherapy</keyword>
<keyword>MMPI-2</keyword>
<keyword>Holt Measure of Primary Process Manifestation</keyword>
<keyword>change</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined personality change in subjects after Long Term Psychodynamic Psychotherapy, defined as 10 months or longer of continuous therapy, at a University outpatient psychology clinic. Assessment measures used were the MMPI-2 and the Holt Measure of Primary Process Manifestation. An archival search of patient records over 7 years was conducted for files that included 1) adults 18 years or older, 2) attended therapy for at least 10 consecutive months or longer and 3) contained 2 completed MMPI-2 tests and/or 2 completed Rorschach Inkblot Tests. The sample included 17 patient files with 1 set of tests given as part of the initial psychological evaluation (Time 1) and the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; test completed after at least 10 months of continuous therapy or prior to the termination of therapy as per the therapists’ discretion (Time 2). Results were analyzed using paired &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;-tests to compare sample means and Bonferroni correction applied to reduce probability of obtaining a Type I error. Significant differences from Time 1 of testing to Time 2 of testing were reported on the MMPI-2 Clinical scales Hypochondriasis (&lt;em&gt;Hs&lt;/em&gt;), Depression (&lt;em&gt;D&lt;/em&gt;), Hysteria (&lt;em&gt;Hy&lt;/em&gt;), and Psychastenia (&lt;em&gt;Pt&lt;/em&gt;). No significant differences were reported on the Holt Measure of Primary Process Manifestation. Previous research on personality change following long term psychodynamic therapy was supported using the MMPI/MMPI-2 and Intrapsychic or Structural Change issues were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2739</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3904&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2739</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3904</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-11-17T19:30:20-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/3904/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4829590</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2739</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Nash</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John W. Lounsbury, William A. Poppen, Robert G. Wahler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>