<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ethylene Stimulates Nutations That Are Dependent on the ETR1 Receptor</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Binder</lname>
<fname>Brad</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>O&#39;Malley</lname>
<fname>Ronan</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Wuyi</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Zutz</lname>
<fname>Tobias</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Bleecker</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Ethylene influences a number of processes in Arabidopsis (&lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt;) through the action of five receptors. In this study, we used high-resolution, time-lapse imaging to examine the long-term effects of ethylene on growing, etiolated Arabidopsis seedlings. These measurements revealed that ethylene stimulates nutations of the hypocotyls with an average delay in onset of over 6 h. The nutation response was constitutive in &lt;em&gt;ctr1-2&lt;/em&gt; mutants maintained in air, whereas &lt;em&gt;ein2-1&lt;/em&gt; mutants failed to nutate when treated with ethylene. Ethylene-stimulated nutations were also eliminated in &lt;em&gt;etr1-7&lt;/em&gt; loss-of-function mutants. Transformation of the &lt;em&gt;etr1-7&lt;/em&gt; mutant with a wild-type genomic &lt;em&gt;ETR1&lt;/em&gt; transgene rescued the nutation phenotype, further supporting a requirement for ETR1. Loss-of-function mutations in the other receptor isoforms had no effect on ethylene-stimulated nutations. However, the double &lt;em&gt;ers1-2 ers2-3&lt;/em&gt; and triple &lt;em&gt;etr2-3 ers2-3 ein4-4&lt;/em&gt; loss-of-function mutants constitutively nutated in air. These results support a model where all the receptors are involved in ethylene-stimulated nutations, but the ETR1 receptor is required and has a contrasting role from the other receptor isoforms in this nutation phenotype. Naphthylphthalamic acid eliminated ethylene-stimulated nutations but had no effect on growth inhibition caused by ethylene, pointing to a role for auxin transport in the nutation phenotype.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/43</coverpage-url>
<label>43</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1042</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-02T08:48:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1532947</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/43</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Brad M. Binder, Ronan C. O&#39;Malley, Wuyi Wang, Tobias C. Zutz, and Anthony B. Bleecker 
Ethylene Stimulates Nutations That Are Dependent on the ETR1 Receptor 
Plant Physiol. 142: 1690-1700.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/gca?sendit=Get+All+Checked+Abstract%28s%29&amp;SEARCHID=1&amp;VOLUME=142&amp;FIRSTPAGE=1690&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;gca=pp.106.087858</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>