<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Barriers to Recreation for Individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) as Perceived by Recreation Service Providers</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dpk878@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Webb</lname>
<fname>Kelsey</fname>
<mname>Phillips</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This project sought to understand the experiences of service providers, particularly the barriers that were encountered in serving individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). ASD is a developmental disorder that manifests uniquely in each individual and impacts all aspects of life for those who receive this diagnosis. This project proposed the utilization of a preliminary survey and semi-structured interviews to collect data from recreation service providers. The literature surrounding access to recreation for individuals with ASD is limited, especially from the experiences and perspectives of service providers. The researchers found that barriers to recreation for those with ASD perceived by recreation service providers fell into seven major themes. These themes were then categorized into three types of constraints: interpersonal, intrapersonal, and structural. This project examined the perspectives and experiences of local service providers and attempted to begin closing the gap in the literature surrounding recreational participation by those with ASD. The study was conducted in a Southeastern city in the United States, in a pilot study that could be replicated in communities across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5645</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7179&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5645</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7179</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-11T13:30:06-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>20540231</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5645</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Angela Wozencroft</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jason Scott, Steven N. Waller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2023-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>