<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mechanisms of Carnitine-Mediated Modulation of Aflatoxin B&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-DNA Adduct Formation</title>
<publication-date>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yatim</lname>
<fname>Ayub</fname>
<mname>Mohd</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this study was to investigate the possible mechanism(s) of L-carnitine-mediated modulation of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-DNA adducts formation. The first part of the study investigated the effect of increased doses of carnitine on AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; binding to macromolecules, AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; uptake, activity of glutathione S-transferase (GST), and total glutathione concentrations in freshly isolated hepatocytes. Carnitine dose was significantly correlated with the formation of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-DNA adduct ( r = -0.68;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.0002 ), AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-protein adduct (r = 0.58;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.017), but not AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-RNA adduct (r = 0.14;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; = 0.604). There was no effect of carnitine on the uptake of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; by the hepatocytes or on the activity of GST. Carnitine protected AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-induced reduction of total glutathione concentration in the hepatocytes, which may contribute to the overall protective effect of carnitine. The second part of the study investigated the effect of carnitine on the binding of microsomal-activated AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to exogenous DNA and protein. Carnitine significantly decreased the binding of activated AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to DNA. It is postulated that carnitine reduced this binding by inhibiting the AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-epoxide formation and/or binding of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-epoxide to DNA. This effect of carnitine was not very specific because acetylcarnitine and γ-aminobutyric acid were equally effective in reducing AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-DNA adduct formation; however, choline and glycine had no effect. Carnitine enhanced the binding of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; as well as microsomal-activated AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to rat plasma proteins and bovine serum albumin. This mode of carnitine actions is proposed to be another mechanism of carnitine-mediated reduction of AFB&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-DNA adduct formation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3793</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5452&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3793</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5452</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-17T07:24:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8988587</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3793</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dileep S. Sachan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ann Draughon, Walter R. Farkas, Naima Moustaid, Mary Sue Younger</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>