<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>La construcción literaria de la identidad de Puerto Rico: El país de cuatro voces</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lparke11@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parker</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>Ybonne Figueroa</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>identidad</keyword>
<keyword>lenguaje</keyword>
<keyword>voz jíbara</keyword>
<keyword>voz hispanófila</keyword>
<keyword>voz mulata</keyword>
<keyword>voz de la diáspora</keyword>
<keyword>decolonialidad</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Arts and Humanities</discipline>
<discipline>Latin American Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Other Spanish and Portuguese Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Spanish and Portuguese Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Spanish Linguistics</discipline>
<discipline>Spanish Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation studies how language in Puerto Rican literature has been instrumental in reconstructing national identity in the context of the Island’s colonial histories. Bearing in mind that colonialism not only produced economic and political domination, but also epistemic control over cultural values and practices in general, Puerto Rican writers have used language to resignify a national imaginary that continues to be elusive and contradictory. To demonstrate how language in literature has become a site of struggle for decolonization, this study analyzes four representative voices from the nineteenth and twentieth century which construct distinct, yet complementary, identities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter one focuses on the strategies used by the voice of the &lt;em&gt;jíbaro&lt;/em&gt; which speaks from the colonial difference while under the Spanish Empire to appropriate a new identity in works such as “Las coplas del jíbaro” by Miguel Cabrera and&lt;em&gt; El Gíbaro by &lt;/em&gt;Manuel A. Alonso. Chapter two examines the voice of the &lt;em&gt;creolized Spanish speaker&lt;/em&gt; who seeks traditional Hispanic roots in the writings and discourses of Pedro Albizu Campos and the essays of Antonio S. Pedreira. Chapter three analyzes the voice of the &lt;em&gt;mulatto&lt;/em&gt; with a focus on the Afro-Caribbean inheritance in several poems from &lt;em&gt;Tuntún de pasa y grifería &lt;/em&gt;by Luis Palés Matos and &lt;em&gt;Dinga y Mandinga&lt;/em&gt; by Fortunato Vizcarrondo. Chapter four considers the issues of migration, Spanglish and code-switching through the voice of the &lt;em&gt;diaspora&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;La carreta &lt;/em&gt;by René Marqués, “La guagua aérea” by Luis Rafael Sánchez and “Pollito Chicken” by Ana Lydia Vega.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical concepts of decoloniality as a means of reading literature and identity are at the core of this dissertation. Colonial difference, subversive complicity and epistemic processes of transformation illuminate new ways of conceptualizing Puerto Rico’s on-going struggle for decolonization.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1805</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2823&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1805</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2823</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-22T12:21:21-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2823/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3606030</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1805</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Handelsman</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Greg Kaplan, Luis Cano, Jana Morgan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Modern Foreign Languages</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>