<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Stand Up and Be Counted</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:36:46-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kimberly.smith@2020census.gov</email>
<institution>US Census Bureau</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Demography, Population, and Ecology</discipline>
<discipline>Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Human Ecology</discipline>
<discipline>Politics and Social Change</discipline>
<discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
<discipline>Public Affairs</discipline>
<discipline>Race and Ethnicity</discipline>
<discipline>Regional Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;“Stand Up and Be Counted”- The presentation spotlights the US Census over 200 years, the American minority by the numbers, and wielding the 2020 census as a tool for the next decade of minority political and social empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter: &lt;/strong&gt;Kimberly Smith, MBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company: &lt;/strong&gt;US Census Bureau&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop is designed to improve the awareness of civic responsibilities and participation in the decennial 2020 census. The information discussed will educate the audience on the history and process of the census, as well as, the impact of census data on minority communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation will begin with census introductory information and then move on to involve the audience in an interactive, participatory activity. Audience members will participate in a live “census” poll. The presentation will continue with further census introductory information and discussion of the “mock” census data’s hypothetical impact on federal collegiate grant funding. The presentation will conclude with time for follow up questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content for the presentation was obtained from the US Census Bureau and the George Washington University websites. Sources for content are provided throughout the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aimed for students/ UT community members interested in expanding their education on civic responsibilities, politics and current events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is particularly relevant to people interested in making a social/political difference in their community that will span the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educate audience on the reality of minority communities from the Census Bureau perspective. Build an awareness of the upcoming decennial 2020 census and empower the audience to use their involvement in the 2020 census to make a lasting difference in their community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By participating in this workshop attendees will take away:  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;A packet of US Census Bureau informational materials- brochures, employment information, access to online census tools&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;An understanding of the history of the census and its connection to the political and social climate of the country&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;A better understanding of the community and society they live in.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;An understanding of their civic responsibilities as American citizens to the government and their community&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The knowledge of their power to make a 10-year difference through one 10-minute survey&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/3</coverpage-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1219</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-11T12:42:35-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1219/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13610315</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>