<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Principal’s Role in the Implementation of a One-to-One Initiative: A Case Study of Two Schools</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ccutter@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cutter</lname>
<fname>Casey</fname>
<mname>Michael</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>one-to-one Initiatives</keyword>
<keyword>principal leadership of one-to-one initiatives</keyword>
<keyword>instructional technology</keyword>
<keyword>principal leadership of instructional technology</keyword>
<keyword>laptop initiatives</keyword>
<keyword>principal leadership of laptop initiatives</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Elementary and Middle and Secondary Education Administration</discipline>
<discipline>Elementary Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;While the popularity of one-to-one initiatives and the body of research concerning their effectiveness continues to grow, there have been few research studies conducted on how a principal leads a one-to-one initiative (Cowie, Jones &amp; Harlow, 2011; Dexter; 2007; Hayes and Greaves, 2013). The purpose of this qualitative study was to examine how a principal can lead, support and influence the implementation of a one-to-one initiative. Stryker and Burke’s (2000) role identity theory provided the theoretical framework for this multi-site case study of two intermediate schools in the same district that were in their first year of implementing a one-toone initiative. The qualitative data collected from both sites during the study included 32 interviews, observations, documents and archival records. The qualitative data was examined through the lens of the two research questions and the role identity theory and various codes emerged during the analysis of the data. The codes were sorted into the twelve a priori roles that were identified during the literature review: visionary, digital expert, manager of resources, model of technology use, technology supporter, leader or organizational, structure and policy change, leader of change in pedagogy and learning, leader of cultural change, evaluator of technology, encourager and supporter, family and community engager and leader of ethics in technology. The role of HR Harriet or HR Harry was added to the twelve a priori roles after reviewing and coding the qualitative data. While both principals took on each of the thirteen roles at some point during the initiative, the principals’ roles of visionary, leader of change in pedagogy and learning, leader of cultural change, leader of organizational, structural and policy change, encourager and supporter and model of technology use had the biggest impact on the initiative. As principals lead, support and influence teachers in the implementation of a one-to-one initiative, they will benefit from establishing a strong vision, eliciting support from all stakeholders, and focusing on preparation to create successful one-to-one initiative change. The study developed the Principal One-to-One Leadership (POTOL) model, which illustrates how a principal can lead, influence and support the implementation of a one-to-one initiative.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4454</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5772&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4454</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5772</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-19T21:15:17-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9714437</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4454</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Pamela S. Angelle</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary L. Derrington, Kerry K. Robinson, Lisa Yamagata-Lynch</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>