<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Water conservation behaviors in Georgia the effects of place</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>Amber</fname>
<mname>Kay</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sociology</keyword>
<keyword>Water conservation</keyword>
<keyword>Droughts</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This piece is an examination of water conservation responses to the 2007 Georgia drought. The research questions for the study are: (1) Are those living in close proximity to the harshest drought conditions more likely to engage in water conservation behaviors than those not in close proximity to the conditions? (2) Are those living in close proximity to the harshest drought conditions more likely to report a greater likelihood of engaging in water conservation behaviors in the future? In other words, it is a question of actual versus intended behaviors. The data for the study come from the 2007 Peach State Poll, a telephone survey of 800 adult Georgia residents, administered from November 19 to December 2, 2007. The respondents were asked if they were very likely, somewhat likely, not at all likely, or already are engaging in one of seven water conservation behaviors. To analyze the data, I used negative binomial regression and ordinary least squares or OLS regression. I found that those who reside in the exceptional, extreme, or severe drought area were engaging in significantly more water conservation behaviors than those not residing in those areas. I also found that there is no effect of place on intended engagement in water conservation behaviors, suggesting that context and crisis has much to do with response. Furthermore, I found that certain demographic factors mediate the effects of place. Specifically, people who are older, female, white, have a modest income, and have a substantial income are likely to engage in water conservation behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5757</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7379&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5757</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7379</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467522</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5757</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stephanie Bohon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>