<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Administration and Practice of Public Health Nutrition in the Arkansas State Department of Health</title>
<publication-date>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hinton</lname>
<fname>Agnes</fname>
<mname>Willoughby</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report provides an analysis of the student&#39;s experiences during eight weeks of field training with the Nutrition Service of the Arkansas State Department of Health. The purpose of this field experience was to supplement the student&#39;s academic training in Public Health Nutrition. The experience was designed to help the student strengthen her philosophy and understanding of public health by introducing her to the following aspects of an official health agency: (1) the practice of public health at the state and local level, (2) the administrative organization of public health nutrition, and (3) the practice of public health nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arkansas State Department of Public Health was chosen as the training agency as it has an established nutrition program which offers opportunities to observe the functioning of nutrition in the total health program. Experience in dealing with other professional personnel within the agency as well as in other agencies was also offered. In addition, the student was given the opportunity to develop her abilities in carrying out applied nutrition programs with both professional and nonprofessional groups and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience provided the author with the following: (1) an overview of the total state health program and the role of nutrition in this program, (2) an understanding of the overall functioning of a local health department, (3) observation of some of the administrative responsibilities involved in a state nutrition program, and (4) an opportunity to observe and participate in direct and indirect services in conjunction with nutrition staff members and other paramedical personnel. Through academic training and the field experience, the student has developed knowledge, techniques, and skills which will be most helpful in her future practice of public health nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3835</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5310&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3835</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5310</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-09T09:00:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8948595</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3835</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;missing page 16&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>