<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The rural-urban interface : challenges for the extension system</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Burden</lname>
<fname>Ray</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the study was to describe how two county Extension Services successfully changed their service orientation from rural/agricultural to urban/suburban in an exemplary manner. The research questions guiding the study were: How did each of the two selected county Extension Services successfully change their service orientation from rural/agricultural to urban/suburban; and what were the common success factors that can be identified from the two case studies? Case study method was used to secure the richest, thickest data and the widest array of insights into the phenomenon of successful transition from rural to urban. Drawing on recommendations from knowledgeable individuals within the Extension Service system, Waukesha county, Wisconsin and Gwinnett county, Georgia were chosen as exemplars of the successful transition. Data were gathered from in-depth interviews with county and state faculty and staff, including Extension Service and county government officials, and written documents which were then analyzed using a coding schema to identify thematic areas. Then the cases were examined for common themes. Three broad factors (themes) were identified as critical to the successful transition in Waukesha county: leadership, forced change, and the influence of changing demographics. Three broad themes were also identified as critical to the successful transition in Gwinnett county: leadership, gradual change, and an appreciation for the traditional role of Extension.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6208</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8160&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6208</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8160</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450299</context-key>
<withdrawn>2021-06-21</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6208</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Norma Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Grady Bogue, Robert B. Cunningham, Randol Waters, Roy Lesley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>