<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cost Comparisons Considering Herd Size, Transport Distance, and Nitrogen versus Phosphorus Application Rates for Liquid Dairy Waste Transport and Application Systems</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Daugherty</lname>
<fname>Adam</fname>
<mname>Shane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A cost estimation model was developed that compares the economics associated with different animal waste transport and application systems used by confined animal operations. The model was constructed from data collected from individual farmers, equipment manufacturers, and gleaned from waste management system manuals. The model was developed to provide animal waste transport and application cost estimates for both liquid and dry waste management systems. The model was developed in Microsoft Excel. Using facility specific information, the model estimates the costs associated with various components of manure transport and application systems. Specifically, the model enables comparisons of capital costs, annual operating costs, and annual fixed costs for the components of various manure transport and application systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study provides cost comparisons for the transport and application of dairy waste slurries based on both phosphorus and nitrogen application rates. Cost estimates are made for several common dairy waste transport and application systems. Five dairy herd sizes ranging from 50 to 2,000 cows using 19 transport and application systems were evaluated. For each dairy herd size, the costs associated with the transport and application system combinations were determined for transport distances of 0.5, 1.5, and 4.5 miles for both nitrogen and phosphorus-based application rates. Total annual economic cost, transport and application cost per acre, annual cost per cow, and net fertilizer value per acre based on nutrient requirements for a 20-ton per acre corn silage crop were calculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results indicate that depending on transport and application system choice, transport distance, and operation herd size, transport and application costs were at times different between phosphorus and nitrogen-based applications. No differences between transport and application costs were found between nitrogen and phosphorus-based applications when using individual hauling and drag hose systems for a given herd size and transport distance. Phosphorus-based applications costs were estimated to be from 5 to 60% more than nitrogen-based applications when using irrigation systems for the transport and application of the animal manure. While phosphorus-based applications were more expensive than nitrogen-based applications in some cases, the less expensive application standard did not always produce the greatest net fertilizer value. The greatest net fertilizer value produced by a given transport and application system varied between phosphorus and nitrogen-based applications depending on application method, transport distance, and herd size. Dairy operations larger than 200 cows economically favored the implementation of phosphorus standards for all applications of animal manures over small dairy operations. Pumping systems were found to be less sensitive to increases in transport distance than hauling systems once herd size exceeded 200 cows. Overall, hauling systems produced the lowest costs and highest net fertilizer values for operations of 200 cows or less. The waste volume produced by these operations produced an annual transport and application operational time that was justifiable. Once herd size exceeded 200 cows it was not justifiable to handle the larger waste volume using hauling systems, and the pumping systems began to produce lower transport and application annual costs and higher net fertilizer values.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1964</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3322&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1964</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3322</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-26T08:06:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4632599</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1964</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert T. Burns</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tim L. Cross, D. Raj Raman, George F. Grandle</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biosystems Engineering Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>