<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Naïve T Cells Re-Distribute to the Lungs of Selectin Ligand Deficient Mice</title>
<publication-date>2010-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tonami@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Onami</lname>
<fname>Thandi</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Harp</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Immune System Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Immunity</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology and Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunology of Infectious Disease</discipline>
<discipline>Immunopathology</discipline>
<discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Virus Diseases</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: Selectin mediated tethering represents one of the earliest steps in T cell extravasation into lymph nodes via high endothelial venules and is dependent on the biosynthesis of sialyl Lewis X (sLe(x)) ligands by several glycosyltransferases, including two fucosyltransferases, fucosyltransferase-IV and -VII. Selectin mediated binding also plays a key role in T cell entry to inflamed organs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;METHODOLOGY/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS: To understand how loss of selectin ligands (sLe(x)) influences T cell migration to the lung, we examined fucosyltransferase-IV and -VII double knockout (FtDKO) mice. We discovered that FtDKO mice showed significant increases (approximately 5-fold) in numbers of naïve T cells in non-inflamed lung parenchyma with no evidence of induced bronchus-associated lymphoid tissue. In contrast, activated T cells were reduced in inflamed lungs of FtDKO mice following viral infection, consistent with the established role of selectin mediated T cell extravasation into inflamed lung. Adoptive transfer of T cells into FtDKO mice revealed impaired T cell entry to lymph nodes, but selective accumulation in non-lymphoid organs. Moreover, inhibition of T cell entry to the lymph nodes by blockade of L-selectin, or treatment of T cells with pertussis toxin to inhibit chemokine dependent G-coupled receptor signaling, also resulted in increased T cells in non-lymphoid organs. Conversely, inhibition of T cell egress from lymph nodes using FTY720 agonism of S1P1 impaired T cell migration into non-lymphoid organs. CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE: Taken together, our results suggest that impaired T cell entry into lymph nodes via high endothelial venules due to genetic deficiency of selectin ligands results in the selective re-distribution and accumulation of T cells in non-lymphoid organs, and correlates with their increased frequency in the blood. Re-distribution of T cells into organs could potentially play a role in the initiation of T cell mediated organ diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/29</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1029&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>29</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1029</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-02-03T12:36:14-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3764018</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/29</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article has been funded by the University of Tennessee&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/open-access/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Harp JR, Onami TM (2010) Naïve T Cells Re-Distribute to the Lungs of Selectin Ligand Deficient Mice. PLoS ONE 5(6): e10973. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0010973</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>PLoS One</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>