<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of Novel Synthetic Methods Utilizing Group III and IV Reagents</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dong</lname>
<fname>Gang</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation summarizes the development of novel synthetic methods involving Group III &amp; IV reagents. These newly discovered reactions include the rhodium-catalyzed direct cross-coupling of allylic alcohols with aryl- and vinylboronic acids; palladium-catalyzed coupling reaction of Baylis-Hillman acetate adducts with both potassium organotrifluoroborate reagents and organosiloxanes; efficient syntheses of functionalized allylmetals such as allylboranes, allylsilanes, and allylgermanes; application of allylboranes to the synthesis of homoallylic alcohols; syntheses of 4-(1-alkynyl)-2(5H)-furanones and coumarins; utilization of potassium alkynyltrifluoroborates in the synthesis of conjugated enediynes; and application of potassium alkynyltrifluoroborates as reagents in the Petasis reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new synthetic methodologies involving Group III &amp; IV reagents developed in this dissertation are important transformations in modern organic synthesis. Mild reaction conditions and a tolerance for various organic functional groups are advantages of these methodologies. The ability to recycle the catalytic system in some cases is another attractive feature for ionic liquids-involved methods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1945</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3376&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1945</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3376</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-19T10:17:21-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4601651</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1945</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George W. Kabalka</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard M. Pagni, Ziling (Ben) Xue, Engin Serpersu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>