<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular Characterization of a Gene Encoding Insulin-Like Peptide 5 (ILP5) in Drosophila virilis</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-04T08:48:51-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nlikoure@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Likourentzos</lname>
<fname>Nikolas</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jhpark@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Park</lname>
<fname>Jae</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Drosophila</keyword>
<keyword>insulin</keyword>
<keyword>insulin-like peptide 5</keyword>
<keyword>gene sequencing</keyword>
<keyword>peptide prediction</keyword>
<keyword>diabetes</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Bioinformatics</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The study of the insulin-like peptides of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; can provide insight of their similarities to mammalian insulin and their potential usage in treating human insulin-related diseases. In this study, we isolated and characterized cDNA encoding insulin-like peptide (ILP) 5 in &lt;em&gt;D. virilis&lt;/em&gt; by using RNA purification, reverse transcription, and RACE protocols. Subsequently, various bioinformatic softwares were employed to predict peptide structure. The &lt;em&gt;ILP5&lt;/em&gt; gene (587 base pairs) codes for 121 amino acids that make up prepro-ILP5. After maturation, functional ILP5 is a peptide of two 25 amino acid chains, A- and B-chain, connected by two disulfide bonds. Sequencing genomic DNA of the &lt;em&gt;D. virilis&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;ILP5&lt;/em&gt; gene identified an intron within the gene. The peptide sequence of &lt;em&gt;D. virilis&lt;/em&gt; ILP5 shows similarities to other ILPs of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; and the predicted structure to mammalian insulin, supporting that the cysteine residues of the insulin peptide are necessary for the function of the peptide in all organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol10/iss1/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1393&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1393</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-21T12:44:22-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/pursuit/article/1393/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>14313975</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol10/iss1/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>The authors would like to thank Joe May at the UT sequencing facility for sequencing the genomic and complementary DNA of the DvILP5 gene.
The authors would also like to thank Larry Matthew Calloway and Liliana Likourentzos for peer-reviewing this article.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xc429418)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Gene sequencing and structure prediction of ILP5 in D. virilis</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>