<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Collegiate Education for Nursing: History of The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, College of Nursing, 1971-1984</title>
<publication-date>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Droppleman</lname>
<fname>Patricia</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Throughout history a paucity of historical research in nursing, by nurses, has been reported. This study, &quot;Collegiate Education for Nursing: History of The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, College of Nursing&quot; traces the historical strands of one collegiate nursing program. Three research questions were examined and analyzed i.e., the reasons for program development, the method of program development and the impact of program development. Certain historical events and phenomena spanning two centuries were investigated in order to answer these questions. The study also examined the forces--social, political and economic--and the individuals who shaped the history of the college of nursing and determined its character. It concluded that both quantitatively and qualitatively nursing had advanced in Tennessee and in Knoxville since the inception of the collegiate program and that significant growth and achievement occurred ·within the college in a relatively brief period of time.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6040</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7680&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6040</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7680</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-20T12:46:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23933044</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6040</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sylvia E. Hart</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Maureen Groer, Mildred Fenske</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nursing</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>