<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Recyclable Materials in Food Service Facilities and Energy Recovery Possibilities</title>
<publication-date>1982-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kopp</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;An identification of recyclable materials in food service facilities with potential energy recovery possibilities was determined by a mail questionnaire and on-site observations/interviews of food service facilities. Thirteen hospital food service departments, twenty-four restaurants, and eighteen combined hospital food services and restaurants responded to the questionnaire entitled, Current Energy Practices and Possibilities for Recycling of Materials in Food Service Facilities. Five facilities--two hospital food service departments and three restaurants--participated in the observations to examine actual practices of energy recovery through recycling processes. A second purpose of the study was focused on identifying the recycling method with approximate costs and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy recovery through recycling or reusing food production materials was not widely practiced, due to the unattractive payback period relative to current energy usage and charges. It was found that grease products were the most frequently recycled material in both types of food service facilities via the sale of these waste products to a commercial fat rendering company. Glass products were reused. Food trimmings and overproduction of food were generally reused in soups, casseroles, and stews. The recycling of paper, plastic, styrofoam, metal, liquid food waste, heat, and water was not used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correlations were made between the types of energy recovery methods considered to produce a cost savings, and the types of energy conservation measures presently used in these food service facilities. Most respondents indicated potential recovery possibilities through methods of recycling heat from cooking and refrigeration equipment, dish-machine, air conditioning and other systems; and its link to reducing energy consuming activities as a conservation measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for energy conservation opportunities through recycling or reuse of food production materials were suggested as potential solutions to the energy situation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3974</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5457&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3974</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5457</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T09:18:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9124323</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3974</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Jo Hitchcock</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harold W. Henry</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>