<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Comparisons of traditional and block schedules on the ACT mathematics test and algebra I state examinations</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Carter</lname>
<fname>Malon</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine if there were significant differences in mathematical academic achievement relative to scheduling practices of Tennessee public high schools located in the metropolitan cities of Chattanooga, Knoxville, Memphis, and Nashville. The public high schools identified would have consistently implemented a traditional schedule, an accelerated (4X4) block schedule, or an alternating (NB) block schedule for the academic years 1998-1999, 1999-2000, and 2000-2001. Results from the ACT Mathematics Test and the High School Subject Matter Test (HSSMT) in Algebra I were used as measures of mathematical academic achievement. Furthermore, the study was designed to seek insights on college students&#39; perceptions of their high school&#39;s schedule relative to instruction received in their high school Algebra I class. These perceptions were gained through questionnaires. The questionnaires were administered to college students enrolled in state operated institutions of higher education in the cities identified for this study in the Spring Semester of 2002. These college students were registered for one of the following mathematics courses: Basic Mathematics, Elementary Algebra, Intermediate Algebra, College Algebra, Pre-calculus (Trigonometry), and Calculus with Analytic Geometry I.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6213</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8165&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6213</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8165</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450304</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6213</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Donald J. Dessart</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lyle M. Craig, Lawrence S. Husch, Vena M. Long</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>