<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Methodology and Sampling System for Monitoring Nonpoint Source Pollution from Land Uses</title>
<publication-date>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Staley</lname>
<fname>Bryan</fname>
<mname>Fleet</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Limited research has been done in developing a nonpoint source methodology and monitoring system that enables the quantitative evaluation of land use impacts on water quality in a single watershed. The development of a methodology and sampling system that specifically targets the runoff component of streamflow is important in determining which types of land uses contribute most to water quality degradation. In addition, an established monitoring strategy and sampling system will provide for the collection of water quality data when the pollution potential is greatest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both a monitoring methodology and a computer controlled sampling system have been developed that utilize flow proportional stream sampling based on hydrograph slope. A 6,2 1 6-ha (24-mi&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) watershed in eastern Tennessee was used as a case study to evaluate effectiveness of both the NPS monitoring methodology and sampling system. The methodology developed provided an effective analysis of the watershed for NPS pollution potential; however, field operation of the sampling system proved problematic due to the type of computer used despite successful laboratory testing. More research is needed in order to further test and develop an appropriate nonpoint source sampling methodology and system that is founded on the mechanisms driving the addition of pollutants into the watershed system.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1862</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3217&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1862</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3217</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-13T13:02:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4584776</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1862</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ronald E. Yoder</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>C. R. Mote, Daniel Yoder, Paul Denton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biosystems Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>