<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Water Ice Films in Cryogenic Vacuum Chambers</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jlabello@utsi.edu</email>
<lname>Labello</lname>
<fname>Jesse Michael</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>physics</keyword>
<keyword>space simulation</keyword>
<keyword>AEDC</keyword>
<keyword>contamination</keyword>
<keyword>cryodeposit</keyword>
<keyword>Blender</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Optics</discipline>
<discipline>Other Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;﻿The space simulation chambers at Arnold Engineering Development Complex (AEDC) allow for the testing and calibration of seeker sensors in cryogenic, high vacuum environments. During operation of these chambers, contaminant films can form on the components in the chamber and disrupt operation. Although these contaminant films can be composed of many molecular species, depending on the species outgassed by warm chamber components and any leaks or virtual leaks (pockets of gas trapped within a vacuum chamber) that may be present, water vapor is most common, and it will be the focus of this dissertation. In this dissertation, some properties of the water molecule and low pressure ice are reviewed with a focus on the optical properties. The method of angular coefficients is utilized to calculate flux distributions for general three dimensional situations and the program written is applied to a model of the AEDC 10V space simulation chamber. The optical effects of varying amounts of contamination on a generic germanium window and gold mirror, along with the effects on two components specific to the space chambers, is determined. Also, an experiment to measure the thickness and other properties of contaminant films is discussed, and initial results are given for the first two tests of the experimental setup.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1201</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2364&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1201</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2364</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-04T07:30:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2330366</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1201</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Christian G. Parigger</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Horace W. Crater, Trevor M. Moeller, Lloyd M. Davis, Norman Mannella</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>