<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of a Programed Instruction Device for the Utilization of Scientific Principles in the Teaching of Food Science</title>
<publication-date>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Marovich</lname>
<fname>Patricia</fname>
<mname>Ervin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Since the publication of Skinner&#39;s (1954) discussion of teaching machines in relation to programed instruction, considerable attention has been directed to the use of programed instruction as a teaching tool. In its simplest form a &quot;program&quot; consist of a body of information presented in a series of small steps and requiring active response on the part of the student. Immediate knowledge of correctness of response is essential to the student&#39;s progress (Deterline, 1962). Most writers on the subject agree as to the desirability of a reasonably small number of errors. According to Evans &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (1960) this goal is attainable through careful programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programed instruction has been used in such diverse fields as education, industry, and government (Komoski, 1962). Functional programs have been developed in some areas of education, particularly in the field of science. To the writer&#39;s knowledge no program is currently available in the area of food science. The purpose of this study was to develop and evaluate a workable tool for the utilization of scientific principles in a food science course.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3721</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5273&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3721</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5273</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-07-25T08:24:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8873980</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3721</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ada Marie Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bernadine Meyer, Jane R. Savage</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>