<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of the Joint Stand Off Weapon (JSOW) Moving Target Capability: AGM-154 Block Three program</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Turco</lname>
<fname>Kyle</fname>
<mname>Travis</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;U. S. Naval Tactical Aviation capabilities are continually analyzed for capability gaps. This analysis has identified the need for a medium range standoff weapon with moving target capability. Technology advancements in Global Positioning System guided weapons, data link systems, and aircraft sensors can make time critical targeting of moving targets during interdiction operations possible with aircraft like the F/A-18 E/F Super Hornet. The Joint Stand Off Weapon “C” (JSOW C) variant met the criterion as an established system that could be evolved to enable this capability. The F/A-18 E/F has been identified as the threshold platform for JSOW Block Three program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A systems engineering approach was used to analyze subsystem alternatives for their contribution to mission accomplishment, and their impact on program cost, risk, and schedule. Each alternative was given an overall assessment, and the most desirable solutions were combined to form the recommended design. Information was drawn from preliminary data made available by ongoing industry trade studies that are evaluating viable technologies. Critical insight was also gained during preparation live weapon demonstrations that are being planned to investigate design concepts. It is anticipated that the results and analysis of these demonstrations will provide significant support for the JSOW Block Three design recommended by this thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JSOW Block Three program has begun to develop a data link capable weapon system with a seeker for terminal guidance. The seeker is needed to overcome the relatively large target location error of current tactical targeting systems to accomplish the mission. It is also desired that the seeker enable autonomous aimpoint selection and target recognition. The JSOW Block Three weapon must integrate a data link system that will employ the newly defined Weapon Data Link Network (WDLN) architecture, which is being specifically designed to support data link weapons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preliminary analysis indicates that Tactical Data Link 16 and an Ultra High Frequency (UHF) variable message format data link are the viable alternatives and both systems are compatible with the F/A-18 E/F. This thesis recommends and supports a Link 16 solution. The variable message format is less suitable for the task. However, the results of the planned ASuW demonstration’s use of the Variable Message Format (VMF) may justify reconsideration. Initially the current seeker appears only capable of the very minimum requirements. The Block Three JSOW may require a complex software solution to enable land moving targets and autonomous target recognition. The suggested alternative is an improved or dual mode seeker that will enable these capabilities while minimizing overly complex algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F/A-18 E/F Cockpit Vehicle Interfaces (CVI) for the weapon are being designed ahead of the weapon, and interface control design decisions must be front loaded so the threshold platform will support initial deployment of the weapon without costly software revisions. A timely and rigorous flight test program of what may be the first deployed network weapon will ensure a successful integration program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JSOW Block Three program has a well-defined mission and must choose a design that enables that mission. Fully funding the development and testing of the JSOW Block Three program is a must for the continued success of the United States Navy’s Naval Aviation Enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1819</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3174&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1819</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3174</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-11T10:28:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4574853</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1819</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard J. Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>U. P. Solies, Stephen Corda</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>