<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ecological Life-history of &lt;em&gt;Lonicera japonica&lt;/em&gt; Thunb.</title>
<publication-date>1955-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Leatherman</lname>
<fname>Anna</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study deals with the ecology of &lt;em&gt;Lonicera japonica&lt;/em&gt; Thunb., a woody vine generally known as Japanese honeysuckle, which is regarded as a troublesome weed in southeastern United States. The investigator chose this species, because it could be studied in both southeastern United States and southern California. Relatively few species can grow so well in two areas whose climatic conditions and soils are so vastly different as they are in these two widely separated regions. Japanese honeysuckle, which grows profusely in southeastern United States, grows well under irrigation in southern California, but it does not become a pest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two main objectives: first, to study the distribution, recognized variation, and economic importance of the species throughout the United States; and second, to make a detailed study of the ecological life-history of the vine. Information contributing to the first objective was secured chiefly by writing to botanists in every state in the United States, by reviewing the literature, by visiting nursery establishment, and by making observation in the field. Some field data were contributed by botanists from The University of Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aid in accomplishing the second objective, outlines prepared by the British Ecological Society (1941, 1947), an outline for trees and shrubs (Pelton 1951), a paper on the ecological life cycle of seed plants (Pelton 1953), and an outline suggested for germination reports (D. B. Lawrence, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 1947) have been helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second objective required a review of the literature, systematic field observations, and a series of greenhouse observations and measurement. The greenhouse observations and some field measurements were done at The University of Tennessee June 1952 to August 1953. Additional observations were made during the school years 1953-1955 at Upland College, Upland, California. The study of root development was made during the summer of 1954 at The University of Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1626</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3122&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1626</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3122</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-02T14:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4277705</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1626</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Royal E. Shanks</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>A. J. Sharp, James T. Tanner, Fred H. Norris, L. F. Seatz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1955-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1955-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>