<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Health literacy: setting an international collaborative research agenda</title>
<publication-date>2009-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Protheroe</lname>
<fname>Joanne</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wallace</lname>
<fname>Lorraine</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Rowlands</lname>
<fname>Gillian</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>DeVoe</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>E</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Health Information Technology</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health literacy is an increasingly important topic in both the policy and research agendas of many countries. During the recent 36&lt;sup&gt;th &lt;/sup&gt;Annual Meeting of the North American Primary Care Research Group, the authors led an audio-taped 3-hour forum, &quot;&lt;em&gt;Studying Health Literacy: Developing an International Collaboration&lt;/em&gt;,&quot; where the current state of health literacy (HL) in the United States (US) and United Kingdom (UK) was presented and attendees were encouraged to debate a future research agenda.  &lt;h4&gt;Discussion of Forum Themes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate centred around three distinct themes, including: (1) refining HL definitions and conceptual models, (2) HL measurement and assessment tools, and (3) developing a collaborative international research agenda. The attendees agreed that future research should be theoretically grounded and conceptual models employed in studies should be explicit to allow for international comparisons to be drawn.  &lt;h4&gt;Summary and Authors Reflections&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of HL research and its possible contribution to health disparities is becoming increasingly recognised internationally. International collaborations and comparative studies could illuminate some of the possible determinants of disparities, and also possibly provide a vehicle to examine other research questions of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utgradmedpubs/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;amp;context=utgradmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-07T09:07:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- UT Graduate School of Medicine</publication-title>
<context-key>4401001</context-key>
<submission-path>utgradmedpubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>BMC Family Practice 2009, 10:51 doi:10.1186/1471-2296-10-51</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-07T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>