<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Returning Discipline to the Discipline: A Model Procedure for Reviews in Anthropology, Social Sciences, and Other Related Disciplines</title>
<publication-date>2018-03-14T08:42:37-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>superlemp@alumni.stanford.org</email>
<lname>Lempert</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This piece uses participant observation of and research into disciplinary procedures to reveal that review policies in anthropology, other ‘social sciences’, and related disciplines have become arbitrary and politicised with little to protect professional standards of a discipline and to avoid conflicts of interest that prejudice scholarship. To address the problem, this piece takes the initial step towards establishing procedural standards. The piece offers a model procedure to incorporate in journal article and book publisher review policies, applying legal approaches to anti-corruption and procedural fairness along with key human resources principles to measure skills and competence. It also applies best practices from experiences from peer review failures in the natural sciences. This procedure offers standards to test the quality of policies of journals and publishers while offering journals and publishers the opportunity to demonstrate compliance. This focus on process is part of a larger effort to reestablish clear standards in anthropology (as a social science and humanities) as well as in related disciplines through which disciplines can hold themselves accountable and measure ‘progress’ while seeking to resolve internal debates over content.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol8/iss1/10</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1110&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1110</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-03-14T08:06:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>11772026</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol8/iss1/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>