<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unintentional Death Rates in Selected Medical Districts among Males living in the United Arab Emirates</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asandal@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ali</lname>
<fname>Amina Ahmed Sandal</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Rate of deaths of unintentional injury</keyword>
<keyword>Medical Districts the United Arab Emirates</keyword>
<keyword>Chi square analysis</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT The purpose of this research study is to determine if the rate of unintentional injury death in selected medical districts differs significantly among citizen and non-citizen males ages 20-65 living in the United Arab Emirates (UAE). A profile of unintentional injury deaths was generated by specific cause for the six medical districts of Ajman, Dubai, Fujairah, Ra’s al-Khaimah, Sharjah and Umm al-Qaiwain managed for the UAE Ministry of Health for the years 2006-2008. During this time period the six medical districts reported a total of 14,101 deaths. Males were found to represent 73.9 per cent of the deaths reported by the six medical districts managed by the UAE Ministry of health for the years 2006-2008. Non –citizen males represented 74.8 per cent of the male fatalities reported by the six medical districts managed by the UAE Ministry of health for the years 2006-2008. Fatality rates for males ages 20-65 were generated and analyzed by citizen status and season of the year. This age group represented 6,141 deaths. In the two medical districts with the highest population (Dubai &amp; Sharjah) unintentional injury deaths represented 77.1% of the total unintentional deaths reported by all the six medical districts managed by the UAE Ministry of Health for the years 2006-2008. A Chi-Square found the rate of fatalities among 20-65 years old male citizens and non-citizens in the six medical districts managed by the UAE Ministry of Health for the years 2006-2008 differed significantly by cause of unintentional injury death. The observed rate of death from accidental falls for non-citizen 20-65 males was found to be higher than expected for male citizens in the same age group. The observed unintentional injury death rate for males ages 20-65 caused by motor vehicle &amp; traffic accidents and for accidental poisoning found the death rate for UAE citizens to be higher than the rate for non-citizens living in the UAE. The results of this study demonstrate the need for the reporting and analysis of unintentional deaths at the medical district level in the UAE by subgroups such as citizen status and age group.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/846</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1810&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>846</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1810</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-06T21:40:07-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1810/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1301721</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/846</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Susan Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. June Gorski, Dr. Gregory Petty, Dr. Gene Hayes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Public Health</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>