<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effect of Magnetic and Configurational Ordering on the Specific Heat of a Nickel-50 Atomic Per Cent Palladium Alloy</title>
<publication-date>1967-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bingham</lname>
<fname>Ronald</fname>
<mname>Eugene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Alloy systems in which local order exists have been extensively studied in recent years, and these studies have increased greatly the understanding of the effect of local-ordering on the physical, mechanical, and thermodynamic properties of these alloy systems (9, 14, 26).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the present time, in the Department of Chemical and Metallurgical Engineering at The University of Tennessee, studies of the phenomenon of order-disorder in several alloy systems are being made through x-ray diffuse scattering, electrical resistivity, and specific heat anomalies. This investigation is a continuation of these studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that the reader may understand the basis for research on the nickel-palladium system and the interpretation of the results, the author had divided his introductory remarks into two sections. The first section reviews previous experimental work on the nickel-palladium system and the conclusions reached by the investigators. The second section is a rather brief introduction into the theory of specific heats with an emphasis placed upon the effects of order-disorder reactions on the specific heat.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3545</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4960&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3545</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4960</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-12-16T14:24:16-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7954938</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3545</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>C. R. Brooks</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>E. E. Stansbury, Julius Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1967-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1967-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>