<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Micropropagation of &lt;em&gt;Populus trichocarpa&lt;/em&gt; ‘Nisqually-1’ and genetic engineering &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt; with CaMV35s-AtWBC19, CaMV35s-AgNt84 and -60CaMV35s-GUS genes</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kang</lname>
<fname>Byung-guk</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In Chapter one, we described development of a highly efficient micropropagation protocol from greenhouse-grown shoot tips of ‘Nisqually-1’. The optimal micropropagation protocol involves growing &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; shoots in plant growth regulator free Murashige and Skoog (MS) basal medium supplemented with 3% sucrose, 0.3% Gelrite and 5–10 g∙L&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; of activated charcoal. Plants grown on this medium were significantly longer, and contained significantly higher concentrations of chlorophyll. In chapter II, we transferred the plant-originated &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis Atwbc19&lt;/em&gt; gene encoding an ATP binding cassette transporter which confers resistance to aminoglycoside antibiotics. Transgenic plants were confirmed by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with Atwbc19- specific primer pair. The expression was confirmed by the reverse transcription PCR. Transgenic plants were tested for aminoglycoside antibiotic resistance. The level of resistance conferred by CaMV35S-&lt;em&gt;Atwbc19&lt;/em&gt; is similar to that conferred by nptII gene. Therefore, plant-ubiquitous &lt;em&gt;Atwbc19&lt;/em&gt; gene can serve an alternative gene as a plant transformation selective marker gene to current bacterial antibiotic-resistance marker genes and alleviate the potential risk for horizontal transfer of bacterial resistance genes in transgenic plants. In Chapter III, we transformed a &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt; clone with the enhancer trapping vector, pD991. All 250 transgenic lines were screened and 71 of them (28%) showed positive staining. They showed various patterns of the reporter gene expression, including expression in one tissue and simultaneously in two more tissues. These results confirmed the previously reports that enhancer trap lines can be produced in &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt;, and these enhancer trap lines can be used for future gene cloning and studying gene expression in &lt;em&gt;Populus&lt;/em&gt;. In Chapter IV, we transformed with the heavy metal binding protein &lt;em&gt;agNt84&lt;/em&gt; gene. Seven putative transgenic lines were confirmed by PCR with the &lt;em&gt;agNt84&lt;/em&gt; specific primers and two lines shoot tips of transgenic- and non-transgenic plants grown on cadmium (Cd) -containing rooting media to evaluate of Cd resistance. 33% of shoot tips from one line and 44% of those from another transgenic line survived on medium containing 250 mM Cd, respectively, but only 22% of the non-transgenic shoot tips survived on rooting medium with 150 mM Cd at week 8. Also, the Cd analysis by ICP-OES indicated that the transgenic plants which were grown on 100 mM Cd medium accumulated about 45% more Cd in the tissue than non-transgenic plants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/609</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1677&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>609</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1677</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-23T13:22:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1165902</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/609</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Zong-Ming (Max) Cheng</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Janice Zale, Feng Chen, Robert Trigiano</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>