<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Analysis of the second five year plan of India with implications for the home science program in higher secondary schools (multipurpose) with special reference to West Bengal State.</title>
<publication-date>1960-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Sen</lname>
<fname>Bani</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A plan is essentially the result of purposive thinking and aims in a well-thought-out development. Plans may be of different kinds--as individual, group, regional, or national. The national plan may belong to one of two categories, distributional plan and developmental plan. The distributional plan comes only when there is sufficient wealth to distribute. This can be seen in countries like the U.S.A. and the United Kingdom. Russia, during recent years, has been demonstrating the value of short term developmental planning to the world. After independence, the Government of India decided to launch short developmental plans in the country. But there is a fundamental difference between the two; Russia&#39;s planning was under Communist regime. In Russia a sort of compulsion was felt, whereas in India there was planning for a sovereign republic with a democratic set-up.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5815</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7493&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5815</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7493</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359295</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5815</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ilene Brown</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Phyllis Ilett, Virginia S. Hardie</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Home Economics Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1960-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>