<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of Bipolaris species, their effects on switchgrass biomass yield and chemical components</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>oadedire@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Fajolu</lname>
<fname>Oluseyi</fname>
<mname>Lydia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Biomass yield</keyword>
<keyword>Chemical composition</keyword>
<keyword>Disease resistance</keyword>
<keyword>Genetic characterization</keyword>
<keyword>Pathogenicity</keyword>
<keyword>Virulence diversity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Entomology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Switchgrass (&lt;em&gt;Panicum virgatum&lt;/em&gt; L.) is a promising biofuel crop; however, limited attention has been directed toward switchgrass pathogens and their impact on biomass yield. &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris &lt;/em&gt;is one of the fungal pathogens that pose a potential threat to switchgrass production in the U.S. This research is focused on the impact of &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris&lt;/em&gt; on switchgrass. The research objectives were 1) Assessment of isolates of four &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris &lt;/em&gt;species for morphology and virulence diversity on switchgrass and impact on biomass yield, 2) Assessment of &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris&lt;/em&gt; infection on switchgrass chemical components, 3) Assessment of switchgrass germplasm for disease resistance, and 4) Genetic characterization of &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris&lt;/em&gt; species. Twenty-five representative isolates of &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris oryzae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;B. sorokiniana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;B. spicifera&lt;/em&gt;, and&lt;em&gt; B. victoriae&lt;/em&gt; varied in morphology and virulence on switchgrass. &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris oryzae &lt;/em&gt;was the most virulent species and &lt;em&gt;B. spicifera &lt;/em&gt;was the least. Low, intermediate and high virulence groups were identified across all isolates. Low-virulent isolates had limited negative impact on switchgrass whereas high-virulent isolates greatly impacted switchgrass, even at low inoculum density. High-virulent isolates should be targeted for disease resistance development in switchgrass. However, these virulence groups had similar effect on switchgrass chemical components. &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris&lt;/em&gt; infection resulted in a significant increase in ash and lignin contents of switchgrass biomass, and a decrease in carbohydrate content, thereby reducing biomass fitness for conversion to drop-in fuels. Out of the nine switchgrass germplasms screened for disease resistance, six, namely Germplasm A, Germplasm B, Germplasm C, ‘Alamo’ (Bamert), ‘Trailblazer’, and ‘Summer’, were moderately resistant to &lt;em&gt;B. spicifera&lt;/em&gt; (LA18) or &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;oryzae&lt;/em&gt; (SK12), whereas none of the germplasms had resistance to &lt;em&gt;B. sorokiniana&lt;/em&gt; (APCNR34) and &lt;em&gt;B. victoriae&lt;/em&gt; (JA12). The moderately resistant germplasms can further be explored as resistance donors in breeding programs for development of cultivars with biofuel-valuable traits. Simple sequence repeats markers were developed from a small insert genomic library for &lt;em&gt;B. sorokiniana&lt;/em&gt;. Sixteen polymorphic loci used to characterized fifteen &lt;em&gt;B. sorokiniana &lt;/em&gt;isolates successfully cross-amplified at least one isolate of &lt;em&gt;B. victoriae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;B. spicifera&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. oryzae&lt;/em&gt;. These markers are valuable for genetic variability studies of &lt;em&gt;Bipolaris&lt;/em&gt; species and a useful tool to formulate breeding strategies for development of resistant switchgrass cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1581</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2762&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1581</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2762</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-11-03T10:09:02-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2762/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3445547</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1581</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bonnie H. Ownley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kimberly D. Gwinn, Robert N. Trigiano, Nicole Labbe, Arnold M. Saxton, Phillip A. Wadl</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-11T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>