<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>High-Density Lipoprotein Status of Adolescent Females and Its Relation to Diet and Selected Cardiovascular Risk Factors</title>
<publication-date>1982-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bush</lname>
<fname>Marilyn</fname>
<mname>Julie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A sample of 78 black and white female subjects, age 16 ± 0.5 years, was evaluated for plasma concentrations of high-density-lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) and the relationship of these concentrations to dietary variables and selected cardiovascular risk factors. Blood samples were drawn from fasted subjects. A heparin-Mn&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; solution was used to precipitate non-high-density Apo-B associated lipoproteins in the plasma, and the resultant supernatant fluid was analyzed for high-density-lipoprotein cholesterol by direct determination. Total cholesterol was also measured in plasma by a direct determination method. Nutrient intake was assessed by 24-hour dietary recall. Anthropometric variables evaluated in relation to HDL-C included weight, height, tricep skinfold, arm circumference, ponderal index, relative weight, and an obesity index based on factorial analysis of weight, tricep skinfold, arm circumference and height. Other factors evaluated in relation to HDL-C were blood pressure, activity level, smoking frequency, alcohol consumption, and use of oral contraceptives. Total cholesterol values from previous assessments of the same population were compared with the present values to identify a trend in the lipid profile of the population over a period of seven years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No significant difference was found between mean HDL-C values for blacks and whites. Mean HDL-C values for both races were near the upper end of the normal range (30 to 70 mg/dl), while total cholesterol mean values were near the lower end of the normal range (120 to 230 mg/dl). Intakes of total protein, animal protein, vegetable protein, total carbohydrate and starch were significantly inversely related to concentration of HDL-C. None of the other factors evaluated were significantly associated with HDL-C. Total cholesterol data collected at four different ages revealed a trend of rising total cholesterol levels until adolescence, at which time these levels fell sharply.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3977</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5454&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3977</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5454</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T08:20:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9123988</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3977</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gail W. Disney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>