<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Urban Centers in Oromia: Consequences of Spatial Concentration of Power in Multinational Ethiopia</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ajalata@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jalata</lname>
<fname>Asafa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Published Articles</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>African Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other International and Area Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Race, Ethnicity and Post-Colonial Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper examines the essence and characteristics of cities and urban centers in Oromia and the major consequences of the centralization and spatial concentration of Habasha (Amhara-Tigray) political power in a multinational Ethiopia. It speci!cally demonstrates how the integration of indigenous Oromo towns into the Ethiopian colonial structure and the formation of garrison and non-garrison cities and towns in Oromia consolidated Habasha political domination over the Oromo people. Ethiopian colonial structure limited the access of Oromo urban residents, who are a minority in their own cities and towns, to institutions and opportunities, such as employment, education, health, mass media and other public services. In addition to exclusion, the Oromos have been prevented from developing autonomous institutions, organizations, culture, and language, and have been subordinated to the institutions and organizations of the Habasha colonial settlers in their own cities, towns, and homeland.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>39</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_socopubs/95</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1095&amp;amp;context=utk_socopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>95</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1095</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-28T20:32:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Sociology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3764286</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_socopubs/95</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Oromo Studies</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>