<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Essays on State Lottery Demand and Revenue Earmarks</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kara.mitchell@belmont.edu</email>
<institution>UT</institution>
<lname>Mitchell</lname>
<fname>Kara</fname>
<mname>Diane Smith</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>state lottery</keyword>
<keyword>earmarks</keyword>
<keyword>elasticity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Public Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Since the first modern state-sponsored lottery was instituted in New Hampshire in 1964, lotteries have proliferated to 42 states and the District of Colombia.  With little exception, research has shown that these lotteries are a highly regressive form of taxation.  However, this body of research does not take into account a theoretical finding that the manner in which collected funds are earmarked impacts participation patterns.  The goal of this dissertation is to test this finding empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first analysis, I use sales data from the Tennessee Education Lottery and scholarship data from the TEL Scholarship program to test this theory directly.  I find that instant game sales are increasing in the number of scholarships awarded in a given county and that the implicit tax incidence is less regressive than in certain other states.  Theory does not hold for Powerball sales.  This may be due to a misconception that buying into a multi-state game does not directly subsidize programs in Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second analysis, I focus on the Texas Lottery, which began as a revenue stream for the state’s General Fund, but eventually became a dedicated revenue stream for K-12 education.  I exploit this change to test for a structural break in the demand for two lottery games.  Then, I extend an existing theory of lottery demand to take this structural break into account.  I find that there is a structural break at the time the earmark is implemented, and that the lottery is less regressive after the earmark.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1207</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2317&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1207</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2317</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-17T21:55:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2170459</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1207</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael K. Price</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Don Bruce, William Neilson, Nicholas Nagle</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>