<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Does Winning Eurovision Impact a Country&#39;s Economy?</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:56:10-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kbard@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bard</lname>
<fname>Kendall</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this thesis is to explore the relationship that winning Eurovision has on several different economic metrics in a particular country. Drawing between 100 and 600 million viewers every year, The Eurovision Song Contest is the longest-running televised singing competition in the world, and has occurred annually since 1956. Furthermore, Eurovision is the most popular international televised event, other than sporting events such as the Olympics and the World Cup. Despite this, limited research has been completed on Eurovision’s economic impact specifically. For this thesis, data on various economic indicators was collected through the World Bank’s World Development Indicators database from 1960 through 2017, for all countries that have either won or hosted the contest (a total of 26 unique countries). Regressions were then completed using Stata to show statistical significance between winning/hosting the competition and a country’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/business/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1168&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1168</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-16T08:06:12-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11967248</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/business/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Scott Holladay</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>