<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Factors Affecting Job Satisfaction of Radiologic Sciences Faculty: Implications for Recruitment and Retention</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lsatter3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Satterfield</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Job Satisfaction Factors</keyword>
<keyword>Radiologic Sciences</keyword>
<keyword>Faculty Retention</keyword>
<keyword>Faculty Recruitment</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The need to recruit and retain radiologic sciences faculty is essential to meet the increasing demand for radiologic technologists. Nevertheless, a faculty shortage is precluding radiologic sciences programs from admitting qualified students and it is predicted to only get worse. Seventy-five percent of the educative body of radiologic sciences is older than 52 years and will approach retirement age in the immediate future. While there is an extensive amount of research conducted on the role of faculty, faculty challenges, faculty recruitment, and job satisfaction, little is known about the indicators of job satisfaction among radiologic sciences faculty that motivate them to remain in the educator role. This study will attempt to identify job satisfaction factors that influence radiologic sciences faculty retention. The study will employ a survey design method and the population will consists of program directors and faculty in Joint Review on Education in Radiologic Technology (JRCERT) accredited programs. The implications of this study are related to identifying job satisfaction factors that would influence recruitment of appropriate individuals who would remain in education long term, and help alleviate the healthcare educator shortage in the radiologic sciences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3467</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4644&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3467</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4644</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-18T10:48:25-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4644/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6682682</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3467</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>J. Patrick Biddix</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Karen D. Boyd, Bob Rider, Dennis Ciancio, Norma Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>