<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Full-Text Retrieval: Systems and Files</title>
<publication-date>1994-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electronic publishing</keyword>
<keyword>e-journals</keyword>
<keyword>library automation</keyword>
<keyword>library technology</keyword>
<keyword>information retrieval</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Much of the development in the first 30 years of library automation has been in solving the problem of identifying relevant sources. Automation of the library&#39;s card catalog provides a finding tool for the library&#39;s collections. The books, journals, films, and other materials located through the catalog still mostly reside in their original form, with no direct connection to the automated finding tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the early development in electronic publishing was also aimed solely at identifying information sources. Secondary publishers, notably publishers of indexing/abstracting serials, were the first to provide their resources in electronic form. Throughout the 1970s and much of the 1980s, indexing/abstracting (bibliographic) databases were predominant in the online database world. The first CD-ROM databases for libraries were many of these same bibliographic files. Traditionally (and still) bibliographic databases are the most widely used type of electronic resource in libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in the mid-1980s, due to great increases in disk storage capacities and better document conversion techniques, full texts of certain types of documents became more widely available. In the 1990s,full-text databases (files) are the most rapidly growing type of commercially available database. Better text-retrieval software is leading to more locally created full-text databases as well. Perhaps in this decade we will at last electronically solve the document delivery problem as well as the document location problem.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/336</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1427&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>336</label>
<document-type>bookchap</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1427</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-07T10:29:57-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16129494</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/336</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Carol Tenopir. “Full-Text Retrieval: Systems and Files,” in: Advances in Library Automation and Networking, vol. 5, Joe A. Hewitt and Charles W. Bailey, Jr., eds. Greenwich, CT: JAI Press, 1994. Pp. 43-71.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Advances in Library Automation and Networking, vol. 5</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>