<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Electronic Reference Options: How They Stack up in Research Libraries</title>
<publication-date>1992-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Neufang</lname>
<fname>Ralf</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electronic reference</keyword>
<keyword>CD-ROM</keyword>
<keyword>databases</keyword>
<keyword>OPAC</keyword>
<keyword>online catalogs</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Electronic reference in a variety of forms is becoming a reality in libraries today. Whether it is online, CD-ROM, or databases loaded from magnetic tapes or a combination of several options, patrons have access to more electronic resources than ever before. We recently surveyed research libraries in the U.S. and Canada to see which electronic reference options they offer. ARL libraries may not be typical because they tend to be heavy users of technology and have relatively large budgets, but they can be considered trendsetters. What these libraries are offering now will be found in all types of libraries within the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic and other &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-gale-com.proxy.lib.utk.edu/ps/retrieve.do?tabID=T002&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchResultsType=SingleTab&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=1&amp;docId=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;docType=Article&amp;sort=RELEVANCE&amp;contentSegment=ZGPP-MOD1&amp;prodId=ITOF&amp;contentSet=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;searchId=R2&amp;userGroupName=tel_a_utl&amp;inPS=true#&quot; id=&quot;x-x-glossaryID1&quot; title=&quot;Related articles for&#39;Research libraries&#39;&quot;&gt;research libraries&lt;/a&gt; have been in the forefront of electronic database access since &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-gale-com.proxy.lib.utk.edu/ps/retrieve.do?tabID=T002&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchResultsType=SingleTab&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=1&amp;docId=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;docType=Article&amp;sort=RELEVANCE&amp;contentSegment=ZGPP-MOD1&amp;prodId=ITOF&amp;contentSet=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;searchId=R2&amp;userGroupName=tel_a_utl&amp;inPS=true#&quot; id=&quot;x-x-glossaryID5&quot; title=&quot;Related articles for&#39;Online searching&#39;&quot;&gt;online searching&lt;/a&gt; first became available in the early 1970s. They were some of the first libraries to offer intermediary online services, and by 1979 almost half (49%) of academic research libraries offered intermediary services [1]. In the mid-1980s some research libraries added end-user online searching on systems such as BRS/After Dark or DIALOG&#39;s Knowledge Index [2]. These systems usually supplemented, but did not replace, intermediary search services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CD-ROM databases were added to reference departments starting in the mid-1980s. By 1987 approximately 30% of &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-gale-com.proxy.lib.utk.edu/ps/retrieve.do?tabID=T002&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchResultsType=SingleTab&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=1&amp;docId=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;docType=Article&amp;sort=RELEVANCE&amp;contentSegment=ZGPP-MOD1&amp;prodId=ITOF&amp;contentSet=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;searchId=R2&amp;userGroupName=tel_a_utl&amp;inPS=true#&quot; id=&quot;x-x-glossaryID2&quot; title=&quot;Related articles for&#39;Academic libraries&#39;&quot;&gt;academic libraries&lt;/a&gt; in the United States had databases on CD-ROM [3]. In just one more year the percentage increased to almost 60%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it predates even online intermediary searching, end-user searching of databases loaded on an in-house computer has become popular with the recent widespread use of online public access &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-gale-com.proxy.lib.utk.edu/ps/retrieve.do?tabID=T002&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchResultsType=SingleTab&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=1&amp;docId=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;docType=Article&amp;sort=RELEVANCE&amp;contentSegment=ZGPP-MOD1&amp;prodId=ITOF&amp;contentSet=GALE%7CA11839792&amp;searchId=R2&amp;userGroupName=tel_a_utl&amp;inPS=true#&quot; id=&quot;x-x-glossaryID4&quot; title=&quot;Related articles for&#39;Catalogs&#39;&quot;&gt;catalogs&lt;/a&gt; (OPACs). An increasing number of database producers are entering into agreements with OPAC vendors so magnetic tapes of reference databases will be compatible with a library&#39;s OPAC [4]. A 1990 survey by ALA found about 8% to 35% of all academic libraries had databases loaded on their OPACs [5]. The low end was for two-year and liberal arts colleges; the high end for doctorate-granting institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many research libraries now offer two or even three or four of electronic options for database searching. In May 1991 we surveyed the libraries that are members of the Association for Research Libraries (ARL) to discover how many offer each four electronic options and how the addition of each new option impacts the others. We also asked for information on what the libraries are offering now and what they plan to do in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presents the survey results and paints a factual picture of electronic reference in 1991 in ARL libraries. In addition to the facts,&quot; many respondents responded with detailed comments about how electronic reference sources are changing their libraries, their workload, and their users. In a later article we will discuss these issues based on more in-depth interviews with selected librarians.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/96</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1131&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>96</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1131</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-11-09T17:56:01-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15741208</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/96</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Online Vol. 16</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>