<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessing Food Insecurity Prevalence and Associated Factors among College Students Enrolled in a University in the Southeastern United States</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wooten</lname>
<fname>Ruth</fname>
<mname>Zegel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>food insecurity</keyword>
<keyword>college students</keyword>
<keyword>financial support</keyword>
<keyword>previous food insecurity</keyword>
<keyword>undergraduate vs. graduate</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background:&lt;/b&gt; Food insecurity is defined as the inability to access adequate and nutritious food. There is a relatively small, but growing body of published research on the prevalence of food insecurity among college students, with most studies finding food insecurity prevalence to be higher on college campuses than in states in which studies were conducted. Two published studies at large, public universities in the Southeast found inconsistent rates of food insecurity, 14% and 46%.&lt;b&gt;Objective:&lt;/b&gt; To assess rates of food insecurity among college students enrolled in campuses of a large public university system in one state in the Southeastern United States and identify factors that are associated with experiencing food insecurity.&lt;b&gt;Methods:&lt;/b&gt; A cross-sectional study design was used. An online survey was administered to eligible, enrolled students (n=38,586), 5,593 responded (14% response rate). After applying exclusion criteria (freshman standing, &lt;18 years old, not a college student, incomplete Adult Food Security Survey Module answers), the final sample size was 4,842. Descriptive statistics were conducted to calculate food insecurity status and identify sample characteristics. Associations between food security status and independent variables were assessed using bivariate analyses (chi square and ANOVA tests), which were further assessed using multivariate logistic regression.&lt;b&gt;Results:&lt;/b&gt; Among students in this sample, a high rate (36%) of food insecurity was identified, which was more than double the rate (13%) of the general population in the same state. When controlling for race, ethnicity, gender, age, and campus attended, factors that were significantly associated with increased likelihood of food insecurity included previous food insecurity, financial factors, and a GPA &lt;3.85. Seniors were significantly more likely to be food insecure than graduate students (OR=1.41). No significant relationships were identified between food insecurity prevalence and meal plan participation, sophomores, and juniors.&lt;b&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/b&gt; This research identifies high rates of food insecurity among college students enrolled in a large public university system in the Southeastern US, as well as select factors related to food insecurity, demonstrating the need for creation of interventions and programs to assist college students experiencing food insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5095</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6502&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5095</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6502</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:06:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414879</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5095</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Elizabeth T. Anderson-Steeves</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sarah E. Colby, Marsha L. Spence</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>