<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Craniometric Relationships among Plains Indians: Culture-Historical and Evolutionary Implications</title>
<publication-date>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Key</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study presents a broad picture of Plains Indian biological relationships on the basis of craniometric data. It employs a sample of 860 individuals distributed temporally from the Paleo-Indian Period into historic times and distributed geographically among the states of North Dakota, South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas, Iowa and Missouri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sample was analyzed within a culture-historical framework utilizing a variety of statistical methodologies: some conventional, some implemented here in the face of small samples and unbalanced designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show strong evidence of biological continuity on the Plains stretching from the Paleo-Indian Period, through the Plains Archaic Period and into the Plains Woodland. The Middle Missouri-Mandan sequence appears to be strongly rooted in the Plains Woodland, suggesting an &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; development for the Middle Missouri Tradition. However, most of the phases of the Initial Middle Missouri Variant show greater affinities to Great Oasis and later Chiwere-Siouan groups than the Middle Missouri Tradition proper. It is possible that the Initial Middle Missouri Variant is not a Mandan-Siouan manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the Middle Missouri Tradition, the Central Plains Tradition is fundamentally distinct from the earlier Plains Woodland complexes. It appears to be an intrusion onto the Plains, perhaps from a Woodland or Mississippian base in the south.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a remarkable temporal trend evident in the Caddoan lineage stretching from the Central Plains Tradition into the Coalescent Arikara and Pawnee sequence. It is characterized by a complex of morphological features generally associated with a lowering of the cranial vault, and appears to coincide with the movement of the Caddoan speakers up the Missouri River. In the absence of a more all-encompassing explanation, the Caddoan trend seems to be the result of gene flow between the Caddoans and the indigenous low-headed Mandan groups. The effect of this gene flow on the Mandan is as yet unknown.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4047</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5670&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4047</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5670</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-11-08T13:03:14-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9359027</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4047</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard L. Jantz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass, Fred H. Smith, John W. Philpot</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>