<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synergistic Effects of BubR1 and p53 Deficiency in Tumor Formation</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wiles</lname>
<fname>Walter</fname>
<mname>Guy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Regulation of cell proliferation within an organism is a necessary and complex process involving several proteins serving as controls at various cell cycle phases known as cell cycle checkpoints.  One of these checkpoints, the mitotic spindle checkpoint, controls the advancement from metaphase to anaphase during mitosis and monitors the proper attachment of the microtubules to the kinetochore.  The spindle checkpoint protein, BubR1 is a protein kinase that localizes to the kinetochores to monitor proper microtubule attachment.  BubR1 is able to inhibit the anaphase promoting complex (APC) and delay the onset of anaphase.  Concurrent with its role in regulating cell cycle, mutations in &lt;em&gt;BubR1&lt;/em&gt; have been observed in various human cancers.  In this work, we examine the effects of &lt;em&gt;BubR1&lt;/em&gt; deficiency at the cellular and organism level using an inbred mouse strain that is deficient for the &lt;em&gt;BubR1&lt;/em&gt; gene expression.  We showed that the complete loss of BubR1 resulted in an embryonic lethal phenotype and this phenotype could not be rescued in a &lt;em&gt;p53&lt;/em&gt; deficient background.  Additionally, mice heterozygous for BubR1 showed a decreased life expectancy and an increased incidence of tumorigenesis.  Furthermore, our data indicates that the loss of BubR1 synergizes with &lt;em&gt;p53 &lt;/em&gt;deficiency to increase the susceptibility of cancer formation in mice and alters the tumor spectrum of the &lt;em&gt;p53&lt;/em&gt; deficient mice.  Finally we show that the &lt;em&gt;BubR1&lt;/em&gt; deficiency increases cellular growth kinetics and transformation potential of MEFs derived from compound &lt;em&gt;BubR1; p53&lt;/em&gt; mutants.  This data provides insight into the importance of &lt;em&gt;BubR1&lt;/em&gt; in the prevention of tumorigensis and its role as a checkpoint protein.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1836</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3191&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1836</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3191</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-12T10:20:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4579682</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1836</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sundar Venkatachalam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly, Ana Kitazono</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>