<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>AMERICAN BLACK BEAR (&lt;i&gt;Ursus americanus&lt;/i&gt;) MOVEMENTS AND FOOD-CONDITIONING ALONG THE INTERFACE OF GREAT SMOKY MOUNTAINS NATIONAL PARK AND PRIVATE LAND</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jgiacomi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Braunstein</lname>
<fname>Jessica</fname>
<mname>Leigh-Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>black bear</keyword>
<keyword>stable isotope</keyword>
<keyword>conflict bear management</keyword>
<keyword>step selection</keyword>
<keyword>step selection function</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The American black bear, &lt;i&gt;Ursus americanus&lt;/i&gt;, is an iconic symbol of Great Smoky Mountains National Park (GRSM or park), and park officials have speculated that bears developed conflict behavior outside of the park’s boundaries. The aim of my study was to better understand black bear space use within GRSM and on surrounding private lands and identify factors resulting in advanced conflict behavior in the park. I used carbon isotopic signatures (δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C), from black bear hairs to distinguish between food-conditioned (FC) and non-food-conditioned (NFC) bears. I radio-collared FC and NFC bears and estimated annual and seasonal 95% kernel density estimation (KDE) home ranges. I then used conditional logistic regression to estimate a step selection function (SSF) to characterize movement of bears based on landscape characteristics and to determine if bears with higher mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C used the landscape differently. Based on a logistic regression model with δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C as a predictor variable, 24 bear hair samples were classified as FC (16M:8F) and 37 were classified as NFC (14M:23F). Annual 95% KDE home-ranges of female bears differed by year (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.003-0.007) but not mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.230-0.240). However, the mean proportion of development within female 95% KDE home ranges differed by mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; &lt; 0.001). Annual 95% KDE home-range sizes of male bears did not differ based on mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.132) or year (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.520). The mean proportion of development within male 95% KDE home ranges differed by mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.022), and the mean proportion of development within home ranges tended to increase as mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C increased. The top SSF model indicated that bears with higher mean δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C had higher selection for low to moderate percent canopy cover and higher selection for slopes &gt;15 degrees. The SSF model can be used to identify potential landscape modifications that could reduce the probability of bears using particular areas. Modifications could include reducing escape and canopy cover, particularly on moderate slopes. Managers will need to continue to collaborate with the communities surrounding GRSM to minimize the development of conflict behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5417</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6825&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5417</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6825</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-12T18:30:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>16528547</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5417</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph D. Clark</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William H. Stiver, Lisa Muller, John Zobel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>