<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An ethnographic future research study of Knoxville, Tennessee&#39;s empowerment zone</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Saunders</lname>
<fname>Kendra</fname>
<mname>Lorelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis examines the efficiency of Ethnographic Futures Research (EFR) in Knoxville, Tennessee&#39;s Empowerment Zone. Although EFR has rarely been used in community development, it is an intense visioning process that helps communities envision their future through three different scenarios: optimistic, pessimistic, and most likely. As a result, EFR helps prepare communities for uncertain events occurring in the future. Such research does not predict the future. Alternatively, EFR is a way to accordingly plan for the unknown using various pictures about the future. The core of this project involved interviewing a respectable individual who is knowledgeable about the area. The purpose of the interviews was to analyze the community&#39;s history and current trends in order to produce viable scenarios about Knoxville&#39;s Empowerment Zone. It was determined that the scenarios are useful and can help promote optimal growth in the area.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5990</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7623&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5990</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7623</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467652</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5990</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bruce Tonn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Planning</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>