<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Kinematic evolution of the Homestake and Slide Lake shear zones, central Colorado: Implications for mid-crustal deformation during the Mesoproterozoic</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>plee9@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Patricia Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Transpression</keyword>
<keyword>low-angle shear zones</keyword>
<keyword>microstructures</keyword>
<keyword>vorticity</keyword>
<keyword>quartz fabrics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Tectonics and Structure</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Kinematic analysis and field mapping of the Homestake shear zone (HSZ) and Slide Lake shear zone (SLSZ) in central Colorado provide new evidence for strain partitioning in the mid-crust at ~1.4 Ga. The northeast-striking, steeply dipping HSZ comprises a ~10-km-wide set of anastomosing ductile shear zones and pseudotachylyte-bearing faults. Approximately 3-km south of the HSZ, the north-northeast-striking, shallowly dipping mylonites of the SLSZ form three 1-10-m-thick shear zone splays. Both top-up-to-the-northwest and top-down-to-the-southeast shear sense are recorded in the SLSZ and HSZ. Oblique stretching lineations in both shear zones show vertical (top-down-to-the-southeast and top-up-to-the-northwest) and dextral movement occurred during mylonite development. Quartz and feldspar deformation mechanisms and quartz [c] axis lattice preferred orientation (LPO) patterns are consistent with deformation temperatures ranging from ~280-500°C in the HSZ to ~280-600°C in the SLSZ. Mean kinematic vorticity and quartz [c] axis LPOs for parts of each shear zone suggest plane and non-plane strain general shear with contributions of 47-69% pure shear and 31-53% simple shear. Based on micro- and mesoscale kinematics along with mean kinematic vorticity values and deformation temperature estimates, we propose that HSZ and SLSZ formed during strain localization and partitioning within a mid-crustal transpressional shear zone system that involved subvertical shuffling at ~1.4 Ga.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/892</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1962&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>892</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1962</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-08T11:09:45-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1858320</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/892</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Micah J. Jessup</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert D. Hatcher, Jr., William M. Dunne</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>map_and_crosssection.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>map_and_crosssection.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1962&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>