<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Personality Profiles of Pre-service Teachers: An Examination of Discipline Differences and Predictive Validity on Future Job Satisfaction</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>abeavers@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Beavers</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Teachers</keyword>
<keyword>personality</keyword>
<keyword>job satisfaction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Assessment, Evaluation, and Research</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Teacher job satisfaction has been shown to impact teacher retention,  attrition and absenteeism (Perrachione, Rosser, &amp; Peterson, 2008).  Given the significant investment of resources required to train  effective classroom teachers, retention of those teachers is important.  Research strongly supports the connection between personality traits and  occupational related outcomes such as work performance, career success,  and job satisfaction across occupational groups. Developing an  understanding of the personality profile of satisfied teachers as a  whole, as well as by teaching area, could serve to better equip teachers  for the reality of teaching, potentially having the ability to increase  job satisfaction. The purposes of this study were to investigate the  similarities and differences of personality traits within teacher  groups, as well as examine the effects of personality on job  satisfaction for teachers, through a longitudinal study using analysis  of covariance and multiple regression. When differences attributable to  gender were controlled, two groups within the teacher sample emerged.  Math, science, and physical education teachers were more resolute,  analytical and investigative, where as elementary, secondary English and  history, and special education teachers were more open-minded and  sensitive. Among the traits distinctive of the teacher occupational type  as a whole, teacher groups in this sample were generally extraverted,  warm, energetic, dutiful, and patient. Having an accurate understanding  of the personality traits that may influence teacher satisfaction could  serve to inform teacher preparation programs and best practices in  leadership for in-service teachers, potentially having the ability to  increase job satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/948</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2106&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>948</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2106</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-21T11:10:43-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2106/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1890670</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/948</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Schulyer W. Huck</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gary Skolits, John Lounsbury, Jennifer Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>