<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Does Increased Globalization Improve Citizens&#39; Quality of Life?</title>
<publication-date>2017-04-10T08:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lhirt@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hirt</lname>
<fname>Laura</fname>
<mname>E</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Econometrics</discipline>
<discipline>International Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Regional Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Countries are more open than ever to the outside world, however research is still undecided about what effects it will have on the country’s culture and way of life. In a world where many policy makers are worried about the expansion of free trade and cheaper foreign labor, we are not certain how a country’s strivings to reach this goal of more “open” economy will or will not give their citizens a better quality of life. I will attempt to gain insight into that question using the United Nation’s millennium goals; my research uses econometric techniques to tease out possible connections between economic exports and imports over GDP, “openness,” and the maximum, minimum, and average millennium development goals within a country utilizing data from 1965 until 2015. My work aims to pinpoint the factors present in a country such as political stability or population growth that are connected to the progress seen on increasing citizen’s quality of life. I hope my research will make it possible for policymakers to understand how their work to reach these millennium development goals might be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/business/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1128&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1128</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T08:02:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10002563</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/business/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>J. Scott Holladay</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-04-10T08:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>