<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Validity of the Crouter 2-Regression Model for Predicting Energy Expenditure: Transitions from Rest to Activity</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kuffel</lname>
<fname>Erin</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Crouter 2-regression model (15) is a new approach for predicting MET values. However, the Crouter 2-regression model may misclassify walking/jogging during transition periods (i.e. during the first and last minute of the activity) due to the high coefficient of variation resulting in an overestimation of MET values. &lt;strong&gt;Purpose: &lt;/strong&gt;The purpose was to examine the Crouter 2-regression model for predicting MET values during transitions from rest to activity and back to rest. It was hypothesized that starting a walking bout partway through a minute will lead to a misclassification, due to the high coefficient of variation, and therefore over-predict MET values. &lt;strong&gt;Methods:  &lt;/strong&gt;Thirty participants (age, 28.2 ± 7.7 yrs; BMI, 24.6 ± 3.6 kg&lt;sup&gt;.&lt;/sup&gt;m&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;) volunteered to perform 15 minutes of supine rest followed immediately by 8 minutes of each of the following activities: one-on-one basketball, seated rest, over-ground walking, and seated rest. An ActiGraph GT1M was positioned on the right hip and a portable metabolic unit (Cosmed K4b&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) was worn during all activities. The participants were randomly assigned to start the activity bouts at 0-s, 20-s or 40-s into the minute (according to the ActiGraph clock).  &lt;strong&gt;Results:  &lt;/strong&gt;The Crouter 2-regression model under-predicted the total energy cost of basketball compared to the Cosmed K4b&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;by an average of 12.8 MET·minutes (P &lt; 0.001) (15.9%). During walking, the Crouter 2-regression model over-predicted MET values compared to the Cosmed K4b&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;during the transitional minutes in the 20-s and 40-s conditions by an average of 2.2 METs (P &lt; 0.001). However, it accurately predicted MET values during minutes 2-7 part of the bout.  &lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:  &lt;/strong&gt;The energy cost of basketball was under-predicted by the Crouter 2-regression model. During the walk-to-rest and rest-to-walk transitions, the Crouter 2-regression model significantly over-predicted the MET values in the 20-s and 40-s conditions. This over-prediction was due to the high coefficient of variation and the oxygen deficit and debt. Despite these limitations, the Crouter 2-regression model still provided a closer estimate of MET values compared to the Cosmed K4b&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt; for basketball and walking compared to other commonly used single-regression equations for the ActiGraph. Supported by NIH Grant OIR21 CA122430-01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4449</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5947&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4449</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5947</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-31T11:49:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9955686</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4449</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edward T. Howley, Dixie L. Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>