<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Epidemiology of &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt; and a survey of other parasites in the West Indian manatee (&lt;i&gt;Trichechus manatus&lt;/i&gt;)</title>
<publication-date>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hwyrosdi@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wyrosdick</lname>
<fname>Heidi</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Toxoplasma gondii</keyword>
<keyword>toxoplasmosis</keyword>
<keyword>florida manatee</keyword>
<keyword>antillean manatee</keyword>
<keyword>cats</keyword>
<keyword>protozoa</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Preventive Medicine, Epidemiology, and Public Health</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/em&gt; is a protozoan parasite of felids reported to cause morbidity and mortality in the two subspecies of the West Indian Manatee (&lt;em&gt;Trichechus manatus&lt;/em&gt;): the Antillean manatee (&lt;em&gt;Trichechus manatus manatus&lt;/em&gt;) in Puerto Rico and the Florida manatee (&lt;em&gt;Trichechus manatus latirostris&lt;/em&gt;). Sera or plasma (n=343) were collected from live-capture &lt;em&gt;T. m. latirostris&lt;/em&gt; through the US Geological Survey (USGS) manatee health assessment program and serosanguinous fluid (n=10) were collected from necropsies conducted by the Marine Mammal Pathobiology Laboratory (MMPL). Additionally, serum or serosanguinous fluid samples (n=5) were collected from rehabilitated or necropsied &lt;em&gt;T. m. manatus&lt;/em&gt; at the Manatee Conservation Center (MCC) of Puerto Rico. Free-roaming cat (&lt;em&gt;Felis catus&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;serum samples (n=25) from Puerto Rico were collected for &lt;em&gt;T. gondii&lt;/em&gt; testing. All serum, plasma, and serosanguinous fluid samples (n=383) were screened using the Modified Agglutination Test (MAT) to determine &lt;em&gt;T. gondii &lt;/em&gt;seroprevalence in manatee and cat. All manatee samples tested on the MAT were seronegative for &lt;em&gt;T. gondii&lt;/em&gt; except for one Antillean manatee which was inconclusive. Nested PCR on the blood clot of this animal was negative. Seroprevalence of &lt;em&gt;T. gondii &lt;/em&gt;in cat sera was 16%. Fecal samples (n=79) from free-roaming cats in Florida were collected to determine the shedding prevalence of &lt;em&gt;T. gondii&lt;/em&gt; oocysts. No oocysts consistent with &lt;em&gt;T. gondii&lt;/em&gt; morphology were detected in any felid samples. This is the first attempt to connect &lt;em&gt;T. gondii&lt;/em&gt; genotypes in manatees to the hypothesized contamination source, feral cat populations. To determine manatee habitat contamination, 33 seagrass samples (&lt;em&gt;Thalassia testudinum, Syringodium filiforme, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Halodule wrightii&lt;/em&gt;) from 19 sites on the main island of Puerto Rico were collected for concentration and PCR detection of &lt;em&gt;T. gondii &lt;/em&gt;oocysts. No &lt;em&gt;T. gondii &lt;/em&gt;oocysts were detected in any of the seagrass samples. Freshly defecated fecal samples (n=24) were also collected from &lt;em&gt;T. m. latirostris&lt;/em&gt; (n=21) and&lt;em&gt; T. m. manatus&lt;/em&gt; (n=3) for parasite surveillance. Parasite ova found included: 2 &lt;em&gt;Chiorchis&lt;/em&gt; spp., &lt;em&gt;Pulmonicola cochleotrema, Moniligerum blairi, Nudacotyle undicola, &lt;/em&gt;2 &lt;em&gt;Eimeria &lt;/em&gt;spp., &lt;em&gt;Heterocheilus tunicatus, &lt;/em&gt;and several unidentified eggs, cysts, and larvae. To the author’s knowledge, this is also the first report of &lt;em&gt;Eimeria &lt;/em&gt;spp. in &lt;em&gt;T. m. manatus&lt;/em&gt; from Puerto Rico.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4274</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5480&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4274</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5480</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-20T06:50:39-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/5480/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9148489</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4274</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Debra L. Miller, Richard Gerhold</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Chunlei Su</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>