<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Physiological Evaluation and Root Morphological Differences associated with Novel Drought Tolerant Corn (&lt;i&gt;Zea mays&lt;/i&gt; L.) Hybrids</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ascott18@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>Austin</fname>
<mname>Gentry</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Drought</keyword>
<keyword>Drought tolerant corn</keyword>
<keyword>Corn</keyword>
<keyword>Water limited Corn</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Corn hybrids designated “drought tolerant” (DT) from three commercial seed companies were evaluated in order to determine the benefit of DT technology in a mid-south environment that may receive adequate but often poorly timed rainfall. Field research was conducted in 2014 and 2015 at Milan, TN where hybrid response to stress was evaluated at two planting dates and in non-irrigated and irrigated environments and greenhouse research was conducted in Jackson, TN to evaluate early season drought to plant physiology and root structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014 and 2015, the non-irrigated trials received enough rainfall to create a high yielding environment. Since the DT hybrids were only stressed for short periods of time throughout the growing season, we were unable to evaluate growth under intense stress conditions, however, it was determined that hybrids with the DT technology are quite competitive in high yield conditions, but may not be needed in areas that receive enough annual rainfall to produce a profitable corn crop. Early season root structure was not altered by exposure to extreme water deficit, but physiological properties can be changed. Stomatal conductance, biomass, and leaf temperature will change if corn is exposed to early season drought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DT corn hybrids could potentially be an option for growers producing corn in humid regions that only sustain brief periods of drought throughout the growing season. However, more research is needed to better understand these novel technologies and how they achieve their ability to tolerate drought stress.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3605</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4897&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3605</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4897</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-05T07:47:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7675064</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3605</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Angela T. McClure</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dennis R. West, Chris Boyer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>