<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Investigation of the Impact of Cutting Parameters on Surface Finish for a Discontinuous Machining Process</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Korlu</lname>
<fname>Baris</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;An investigation of the impact of cutting parameters on surface finish for a discontinuous machining process, face milling, is reported herein. While several similar studies involving continuous machining operations, primarily turning, have been conducted, few studies have addressed discontinuous machining. In addition to considering controllable parameters, cutting speed, depth of cut, and feed rate, the impact of tool temperature was also incorporated. A two-stage experiment was conducted to consider both short-term and long-term effects as cumulative wear on the cutters progressively increased. As a result of this work the following conclusions were reached: (a) no relationship was evident between the temperature of the tool and surface roughness, (b) all controlled cutting parameters have an impact on surface roughness, (c) cutter-to-cutter differences were observed, and (d) the direction of measurement with the surface analyzer is significant.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2269</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3720&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2269</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3720</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-16T11:43:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4728931</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2269</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hampton R. Liggett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert W. Lee, Dukwon Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>