<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Dialectics of Power and Dissent: A Study of the U.S. Army&#39;s Chemical Stockpile Disposal Program</title>
<publication-date>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davies</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
<mname>Griffith</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research is a study of power in contemporary American society which calls into question the assumptions of openness and permeability so cherished by the pluralists. Within a power framework, we explore the functional realities of government that illuminate why some powerful interests manage to prevail with some consistency, while the broad public is assigned to a lesser task. The context for the study is the U.S. Army&#39;s $ 11 billion dollar Chemical Stockpile Disposal Program (CSDP). The Army&#39;s decision to use on-site incineration for the destruction of the stockpile ignited a social movement in opposition. Employing participant observation and in-depth interviews, we analyze the citizen-led opposition movement that began at the Lexingtron-Bluegrass Army Depot (LBAD) in Kentucky, and the ambiguous role of the NEPA (National Environmental Policy Act) regulatory process. Using the &#39;three dimensions of power&#39; framework formulated by Steven Lukes (1974) and extended by Gaventa (1980), and Bachrach and Baratz (1974), we uncovered patterns of power (i.e., &quot;hidden faces of power&quot;) that allowed the Army to exploit some issues and suppress others while all the time urging that citizens abide by &quot;the process.&quot; This was accomplished chiefly through the &#39;mobilization of bias&#39;, and propped up by a heavily-financed public relations campaign which emanates from the Pentagon. We conclude with some recommendations for what can be done to revitalize our moribund democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2786</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4300&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2786</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4300</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-08-14T13:39:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5971184</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2786</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sherry Cable, Donald Clelland</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Gaventa, Robert Gorman, John Nolt</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>