<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Function of Ecdysone and Inhibiting Programmed Cell Death in Death Class III Neurons of Drosophila melanogaster</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-18T08:50:07-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nlikoure@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Likourentzos</lname>
<fname>Nikolas Richard</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Developmental Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The inhibition of programmed cell death is a factor believed to be responsible for the survival of cancer cells. Using Drosophila as models, factors contributing to the process of programmed cell death can be studied. Neurons die throughout Drosophila melanogaster development to allow the addition of new neurons. The groups of neurons programmed to die are Death Class I neurons, Death Class II neurons, and Death Class III neurons. Ecdysone is a hormone responsible for the timing of programmed cell death (PCD) in the Death Class neurons. Elevated levels of ecdysone are associated with the initiation of PCD of Death Class I and II neurons. In order to determine how ecdysone levels are related to PCD of Death Class III neurons, the receptor of the ecdysone hormone (ECRA) was inhibited by mutation of the gene that codes for the receptor and microRNA degradation. Results were determined by imaging ECRA mutants and control with Casor (Caspase Sensor), a gal-4 driver that codes for a peptide designed to highlight cell death under fluorescent light. Flies with ECRA inhibited showed premature cell death compared to control that had no ECRA inhibition, suggesting that ecdysone is responsible for inhibiting the PCD of Death Class III neurons.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/23</coverpage-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1265</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-18T08:09:59-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1265/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>14294668</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2019/artsscience/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Jae Park</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>