<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The synthesis and reactions of substituted perfluoroadamantanes, fluorofullerenes and norbornane carbocations</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Kenneth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Fluoro and trifluoromethyl groups are becoming increasingly popular in pharmaceuticals, as their inductive effects can be used to tailor a drug&#39;s specific interactions. Fluorous syntheses are also now becoming commonplace due to the efficient partitioning possible between fluorous and organic phases. Several new F-adamantyl derivatives were synthesized from F-Adamantyl lithium as targets for future incorporation into pharmaceuticals or for use as fluorous tags. They are: Ethyl-F-Adamantane from ethyl iodide, methyl Fadamantyl ketone and enolate from acetyl chloride, and TIPS protected F-Adamantyl ethanol from TIPS protected 2-bromoethanol. The synthesis of F-adamantyl sulfonyl halides was attempted, however, the F-adamantyl anion attacks the chlorine of sulfonyl chloride fluoride rather than the sulfur in an SNX reaction. Also, F-adamantyl sulfonyl bromide formed by the reaction ofF-Adamantyl Lithium with sulfur dioxide and bromine desulfonylated to form Fadamantyl bromide.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6311</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8263&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6311</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8263</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450416</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6311</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jamie L. Adcock</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bob Compton, Lee Magrid, David Brian</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>