<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Magneto-Optical Properties of Complex Oxides</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pchen@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Peng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>magneto optical properties</keyword>
<keyword>collective excitations</keyword>
<keyword>complex oxides</keyword>
<keyword>multiferroic</keyword>
<keyword>frustration</keyword>
<keyword>spin-orbit coupling</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Condensed Matter Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Physical Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Complex oxides give rise to rich physics and exotic cross-coupled electronic and magnetic properties. This is because of the competing interaction between charge, structure, and magnetism in the materials. In this dissertation I present a spectroscopic investigation of several model complex oxides under external stimuli of magnetic field and temperature. The compounds of interest include BiFeO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; [bismuth ferrite] nanoparticles and tetragonal film, Bi&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;Nd&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;FeO&lt;sub&gt;3 &lt;/sub&gt;[neodymium doped bismuth ferrite], α-Fe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; [hematite], Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;V&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;8 &lt;/sub&gt;[nickel vanadate], and &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;In&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;Mn&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3 &lt;/sub&gt;[manganese doped rare earth indium oxide]. These materials are attractive systems for investigating optical band gap tunability, lattice and charge dynamics, spin charge coupling, and magnetochromic effect. Systematic intensity and frequency trends in selected vibrational modes show that the paraelectric phase is &lt;em&gt;Pm-3m&lt;/em&gt; and the lowest frequency A&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; feature is the soft mode that drives the first order transition. Finite length scale effects are also evident in the electronic structure. It turns out that band gap red shifted ~0.3 eV in the nanoscale particles and blue shifted ~0.4 eV in the tetragonal film. With Nd&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; substitution, critical field of cycloid → homogenous (canted antiferromagnet) ordering transition decreases in Bi&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;Nd&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;FeO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Spiral magnetic order is quenched when x~0.2. Furthermore, we discovered that α-Fe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; appears more red in applied magnetic field, an effect that is amplified by the presence of the spin flop transition. Analysis of the exciton pattern reveals &lt;em&gt;C2&lt;/em&gt; monoclinic symmetry in the high field phase. Our measurements reveal field-induced blue shifts of the band gap in Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;V&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; that are much larger than those driven by temperature, anticipating a more greenish appearance in the fully polarized state. This change is found to emanates from charge density differences around the Ni and O centers in high field. The result on &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;In&lt;sub&gt;1-x&lt;/sub&gt;Mn&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; shows a large magnetochromic effect in TbInO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; electron excitations in DyInO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; change dramatically in the field, a result from the Zeeman effect. When doped with Mn ions, magnetic response of the material is increased, and Mn &lt;em&gt;d-d&lt;/em&gt; excitations emerge in the visible range. These findings advance our understanding of spin charge coupling and motivates fundamental research on other functional complex oxides under extreme conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2563</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3630&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2563</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3630</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-07T14:01:04-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/3630/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4677743</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2563</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Janice L. Musfeldt</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jon P. Camden, Adriana Moreo, Ziling Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>