<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a Scale Designed to Measure Interest in Verbal and Written Expression</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jgoldma4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Goldman</lname>
<fname>Jared</fname>
<mname>Ian</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>language</keyword>
<keyword>psychometrics</keyword>
<keyword>psychology</keyword>
<keyword>literature</keyword>
<keyword>survey</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research is to create a scale that measures an individual’s interest in verbal and written expression. Psychological theorists have held that individuals benefit emotionally from articulating their thoughts and feelings; these theories have found support in empirical studies that suggest the psychological benefits of certain language-based behaviors and experience in language-rich environments. Moreover, theorists and researchers have identified differences in individuals’ relationships with language. In light of this literature, this scale is an attempt to create a measure that assesses an individual’s relationship with language in a novel way. This paper consists of two studies. The first, a pilot study, develops the scale, examines its psychometric properties, and explores its relationship with theoretical correlates based on responses from online participants. The second is a replication study that aims to determine whether the pilot study’s results replicated in a different sample who filled out the questionnaire in person.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5445</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6981&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5445</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6981</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545483</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5445</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kristina Gordon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Timothy Hulsey, Jack Barlow, Heather Hirschfeld</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>