<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Lanthanide separations using rate-controlled solvent extraction</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Brooks</lname>
<fname>Angela</fname>
<mname>Denise</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, certain trivalent lanthanide ions (Nd+3, Sm+3, Eu+3, D/3, Tm+3, and Yb+3) along with Sc+3 and Y-3, were complexed with DTPA (diethylenetriaminepentaacetic acid) and extracted into a water-immiscible kerosene layer containing DEHP A ( di-2-ethylhexylphosphoric acid). Data were collected by measuring the cation content of the post-extraction aqueous phase via atomic emission. The purpose of this study was to investigate the kinetics and separation efficiencies in the extractions of binary mixtures via non-equilibrium solvent extraction and to compare these results with equilibrium results. In addition, mixture data were compared to results obtained from studies of extractions containing a single type of ion. In the single ion studies, the ions listed above were extracted in addition to Lu+ 3 and Al+ 3 • The extraction speeds were found to decrease with decreasing cation radius, except for Y-3. y+3 extracted faster than expected from eight or nine coordinate size considerations. However, if the generally accepted change in coordination number from nine to eight occurs after Sm+3 in the lanthanide series, and if Y-3 is nine-coordinate in this system, then its size would fall in line with the observed kinetic series. It was also observed that non-equilibrium extraction gives enhanced separation over equilibrium extraction in most binary mixtures. A mixing time of ten minutes seemed to give optimal separation of binary mixtures. For ions that extract at close to the same rate, a counter current non-equilibrium extraction system should require fewer stages than its equilibrium counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5198</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6606&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5198</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6606</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847030</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5198</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George Schweitzer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>