<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Integrated Internet Marketing Communications for the Global Market: An Empirical Examination</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>pboutin@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Boutin</lname>
<fname>Philip</fname>
<mname>Jean</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>global marketing</keyword>
<keyword>Internet marketing</keyword>
<keyword>online marketing</keyword>
<keyword>marketing strategy</keyword>
<keyword>marketing communications</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Marketing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Strategy formulation, strategy implementation, and performance of Internet (online) marketing communications (IOMC) by companies when they attempt to target, reach, and communicate with the global market (i.e., both domestic and foreign markets) in order to promote and sell products to the members of that market was the broad phenomenon examined. The specific focus was on the use of a globally integrated marketing communications (GIMC) approach with IOMC and the creation of the global Internet integrated marketing communications (GI-IMC) concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant theories and theoretical models were identified and leveraged to serve as the theoretical foundation for the general theoretical framework, the research program framework, and/or the hypothesized conceptual model created and/or empirically examined at least partially. They included: industrial organization theory, the resource-based view, and the strategic fit paradigm (environment-strategy coalignment). In addition, various relevant research streams and concepts were described and examined in detail. They included: IOMC, international Internet marketing, integrated marketing communications, GIMC, and Internet integrated marketing communications. The &lt;em&gt;Market Orientation&lt;/em&gt; construct was the lone independent variable or construct included in the initial four-construct model empirically examined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were three stages of data collection: (1) pre-test, (2) pilot test, and (3) main test. A convenience sample of 73 academics or industry practitioners was utilized for the pre-test in order to make modifications to the survey instrument for subsequent rounds of data collection. Samples of qualified industry practitioners were then obtained for the pilot test (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;=70) and main test (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;=400) from online respondent panels provided by third-party vendors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results included the creation of two new theoretical constructs (i.e., &lt;em&gt;Global Internet Integrated Marketing Communications &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Global Internet Marketing Communications Performance&lt;/em&gt;) and the formulation and preliminary validation of their measurement scales (though the hypothesized measurement model lacked discriminant validity, which prevented testing of the hypothesized structural model). In addition, a statistically significant positive relationship was found to exist between the &lt;em&gt;Global Internet Integrated Marketing Communications &lt;/em&gt;construct and the &lt;em&gt;Global Internet Marketing Communications Performance&lt;/em&gt; construct in a final two-construct model proposed and examined through post-hoc analysis. Implications of this research for researchers and practitioners are provided, as are future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3560</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5068&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3560</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5068</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-11-12T21:02:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7839457</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3560</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel J. Flint</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David W. Schumann, Charles H. Noble, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>