<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Predictors of Self-Reported Crashes Among Iranian Drivers: Exploratory Analysis of an Extended Driver Behavior Questionnaire</title>
<publication-date>2018-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>amohamad@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mohamadi Hezaveh</lname>
<fname>Amin</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>St. Olavs University Hospital, Norway</institution>
<lname>Nordfjærn</lname>
<fname>Trond</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran</institution>
<lname>Mamdoohi</lname>
<fname>Amir</fname>
<mname>Reza</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Nord University, Norway</institution>
<lname>Şimşekoğlu</lname>
<fname>Özlem</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Driver Behaviour Questionnaire</keyword>
<keyword>Exploratory Factor Analysis</keyword>
<keyword>self-reported crashes predictor</keyword>
<keyword>road safety</keyword>
<keyword>human factor</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;More than 16,500 people lose their lives each year due to traffic crashes in Iran, which reflects one of the highest road traffic fatality rates in the world. The aim of the present study is to investigate the factors structure of an extended Driver Behaviour Questionnaire (DBQ) and to examine the gender differences in the extracted factors among Iranian drivers. Further, the study tested the association between DBQ factors, demographic characteristics, and self-reported crashes. Based on Iranian driving culture, an extended (36 items) Internet-based version of the DBQ was distributed among Iranian drivers. The results of Exploratory Factor Analysis based on a sample of 632 Iranians identified a five-factor solution named “Speeding and Pushing Violations”, “Lapses and Errors”, “Violations Causing Inattention”, “Aggressive Violations” and “Traffic Violations” which account for 44.7 percent of the total variance. The results also revealed that females were more prone to Lapses and Errors, whereas males reported more violations than females. Logistic regression analysis identified Violations Causing Inattention, Speeding and Pushing Violations as predictors of self-reported crashes in a three-year period. The results were discussed in line with road traffic safety countermeasures suitable for the Iranian context.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_civipubs/24</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1031&amp;amp;context=utk_civipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1031</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-07-05T10:10:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Civil &amp; Environmental Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>12442772</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_civipubs/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Mohamadi Hezaveh, Amin, Trond Nordfjærn, Amir Reza Mamdoohi, and Özlem Şimşekoğlu. “Predictors of Self-Reported Crashes Among Iranian Drivers: Exploratory Analysis of an Extended Driver Behavior Questionnaire”. Promet - Traffic &amp; Transportation 30, no. 1 (2018). https://doi.org/10.7307/ptt.v30i1.2412.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.7307/ptt.v30i1.2412</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_rev" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-02-23T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Promet - Traffic &amp; Transportation</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>