<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Personal and Group Environment Factors of Water Polo Players</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sreyes1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Reyes</lname>
<fname>Shelby</fname>
<mname>Morgan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Water polo</keyword>
<keyword>team cohesion</keyword>
<keyword>team satisfaction</keyword>
<keyword>personality</keyword>
<keyword>team sports</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Personality and Social Contexts</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined to see if Division I female water polo players (n = 113) had a distinct personality profile when compared to their counterpart of other female college students (n = 170). Also, this study analyzed to see the impact personality traits and team cohesion variables had on overall athletic satisfaction in female water polo players. The measures used were as follows: for personality, the Personal Style Inventory for College Students (PSI, Lounsbury &amp; Gibson, 2008); for team cohesion, Group Environment Questionnaire (GEQ, Carron, Widmeyer, &amp; Brawley, 1985) ; and for athletic satisfaction, Athletes Satisfaction Questionnaire (ASQ, Riemer &amp; Chelladurai, 1998). The results looking at the differences between means and effect sizes in regard to the Big Five Personality traits in water polo players and other college students showed a significant difference in 3 out of the 5 traits (conscientiousness, emotional stability, and openness). Then, when looking at overall athletic satisfaction in their athletic experience a hierarchical multiple regression analysis was performed. The Big Five Personality traits only accounted for 7% of the variance (statistically insignificant change in R&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;[coefficient of determination], &lt;em&gt;p = &lt;/em&gt;.16), while the four team cohesion measures accounted for 55% (p &lt; .001) of the variance, a large effect. In particular, a part correlation showed that significant results between athletic satisfaction and &lt;em&gt;Individual attraction to the group-Task&lt;/em&gt; (ATG-T, r&lt;sub&gt;part &lt;/sub&gt;[part correlation]= .37, &lt;em&gt; p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .001) and &lt;em&gt;Group Integration-Task&lt;/em&gt; (GI-T, r&lt;sub&gt;part &lt;/sub&gt;[part correlation]= .29, &lt;em&gt; p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .001). These findings have implications to help players and coaches understand if they would be a good fit for a Division I water polo team and to understand how to best make a team successful. Future research can also be done to see if these results are generalizable to other similar team sports as well (i.e. soccer, hockey, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2638</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3581&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2638</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3581</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T07:40:55-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3581/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4691935</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2638</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jacob J. Levy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dawn M. Szymanski, John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>