<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The relationship between the susceptibility of eating disorders, self-esteem, and body image in female collegiate student-athletes</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dawkins</lname>
<fname>Stephanie</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sport studies</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research indicates athletes participating in competitive sports may be at a higher risk for developing an eating disorder than non-athletes (Costin, 2007). A variety of factors may lead to an eating disorder. This study looked at the relationship between the susceptibility to eating disorders, self-esteem, and body image and Division I, Division II, and Division III female collegiate student-athletes, and it considers whether competition level was a factor for developing an eating disorder. In this study, Division I, Division II, and Division III female athletes were asked to complete a questionnaire that included three subscales of the EDI-2, the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale, and the Body Cathexis, in order to determine the eating and exercising attitudes of female student-athletes. The study&#39;s findings showed that there was not a relationship between a student-athletes&#39; competition level and their susceptibility to eating disorders; however, there was a relationship between student-athletes&#39; self-esteem level and body image satisfaction level and their susceptibility to eating disorders. It is recommended athletic departments test their student-athletes&#39; levels of self-esteem and body image in order to set up appropriate interventions programs for athletes who may be susceptible to eating disorders due to their self-esteem levels and/or body image satisfaction levels.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5760</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7382&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5760</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7382</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467527</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5760</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robin Hardin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sports Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>