<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cerulean warbler technical group: coordinating international research and conservation</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>USGS Wildlife Research Center</institution>
<lname>Dawson</lname>
<fname>Deanna</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Council for Air and Stream Improvement, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Wigley</lname>
<fname>T.</fname>
<mname>Ben</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Keyser</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Cerulean Warbler</keyword>
<keyword>Setophaga cerulea</keyword>
<keyword>Cerulean Warbler Technical Group</keyword>
<keyword>Appalachians</keyword>
<keyword>northern
Andes</keyword>
<keyword>international conservation</keyword>
<keyword>conservation partnerships</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Effective conservation for species of concern requires interchange and collaboration among conservationists and stakeholders. The Cerulean Warbler Technical Group (CWTG) is a consortium of biologists and managers from government agencies, non-governmental organizations, academia, and industry, who are dedicated to finding pro-active, science-based solutions for conservation of the Cerulean Warbler (Setophaga cerulea). Formed in the United States in 2001, CWTG’s scope soon broadened to address the species’ ecology and conservation on both the breeding and non-breeding ranges, in partnership with biologists from South and Central America. In 2004, CWTG launched the Cerulean Warbler Conservation Initiative, a set of activities aimed at addressing information and conservation needs for the species. These include (1) studies in the core breeding range to assess Cerulean Warbler response to forest management practices and to identify mined lands that could be reforested to benefit the species, (2) ecological and demographic studies on the winter range, and (3) surveys of Cerulean Warbler distribution on the breeding and winter ranges and during migration. A rangewide conservation action plan has been completed, along with a more detailed conservation plan for the non-breeding range. CWTG and partners now move forward with on-the-ground conservation, while still addressing unmet information needs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_forepubs/20</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1025&amp;amp;context=utk_forepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>20</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-01-20T09:00:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>UT Extension publication</publication-title>
<context-key>9563358</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_forepubs/20</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>This article is in the public domain.</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Dawson, D. K., T. B. Wigley, and P. D. Keyser.  2012.  Cerulean warbler technical group: coordinating international research and conservation.  Ornitologia Neotropical, 23:275-281.</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Ornitologia Neotropical</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>