<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Control of Glyphosate Resistant Horseweed (Conyza canadensis) with Saflufenacil and Tank-Mixture Partners.</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bwaggon2@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Waggoner</lname>
<fname>Brock</fname>
<mname>Steven</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>ppo</keyword>
<keyword>burndown</keyword>
<keyword>saflufenacil</keyword>
<keyword>horseweed</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Science</discipline>
<discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Field and labratory studies were conducted to determine the efficacy of saflufenacil alone and with mixture partners for burndown. Field studies were conducted in 2009 and 2010 to evaluate saflufenacil in mixtures with glyphosate, glufosinate, or paraquat for control of glyphosate-resistant (GR) horseweed prior to planting cotton. Saflufenacil and saflufenacil mixtures were applied 7 days before planting (DBP). Saflufenacil at 25 and 50 g ai ha-1 in mixture with all three non-selective herbicides provided similar GR horseweed control when compared to the current standard of glyphosate plus dicamba. Control of GR horseweed was also not different at the 25 and 50 g ai ha-1 of saflufenacil across all mixtures from the standard of glyphosate plus dicamba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laboratory studies were initiated to determine the uptake and translocation of saflufenacil alone and when mixed with glyphosate and paraquat. It was found that glyphosate plus saflufenacil had a greater absorption of saflufenacil at 2 and 8 HAT. By 24 HAT there were not any differences between the amount of saflufenacil absorbed into GR horseweed between treatments. Translocation data also confirmed that the majority of saflufenacil stayed in the treated leaf at 72 HAT.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/840</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1897&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>840</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1897</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-11T10:58:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1639388</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/840</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence E. Steckel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas C. Mueller, Gregory R. Armel, Christopher L. Main</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>