<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Small woodland owners in Roane County, Tennessee : problem A: Characteristics of Roane County small woodland owners and their farms : problem B: Management practices of Roane County small woodland owners : problem C: Factors influencing woodland management practice adoption by Roane County small woodland owners : three related special problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1967-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Moles</lname>
<fname>Gene</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Roane County is one of five counties that was selected for an Extension State Study of Management Practices of Small Woodland Owners. Other counties involved were Rhea, Monroe, McMinn and Perry. The State Study was part of a nationwide study that took place in 1962-1963. There were eleven other states besides Tennessee participating. Roane County is located in the central part of eastern Tennessee and was established from part of Knox County in 1801. In 1880, the population was 15,237; by 1900, it had increased to 16,397. This figure was almost doubled by 1950 when the population was 31,665 (7:1). The 1960 census gives the population as 39,133. Roane County had a total of 248,300 acres. Fifty-nine point nine percent or 148,700 acres are in forest land. Thirty-one percent or 77,100 acres make up the non-forest land, and the remaining 9.1% percent or 22,500 acres is occupied by water (13:1). It is estimated that 82 percent of Roane County&#39;s forests are made up of small ownerships under 500 acres in size (7:19).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6051</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7690&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6051</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7690</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074428</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6051</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles L. Cleland, John B. Sharp, Frank Bell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1967-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>