<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Growth Policy, Annexation, and Incorporation Under Public Act 1101 of 1998: A Guide for Community Leaders</title>
<publication-date>1998-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>CTAS</organization>
</author>
<author>
<organization>MTAS</organization>
</author>
<author>
<organization>Center for Government Training</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>municipal technical advisory service</keyword>
<keyword>municipal government</keyword>
<keyword>annexation</keyword>
<keyword>incorporation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Ad Hoc Study Committee on Annexation, established by Lt. Governor Wilder and Speaker Naifeh, worked through the fall of 1997 and into the 1998 legislative session to develop a new vision for growth policy in Tennessee. Under the leadership of its co-chairs, Senator Robert Rochelle and Representative Matt Kisber, the Ad Hoc Committee vigorously pursued a solution that seeks to meet the public service demands of commercial and residential growth, while maintaining the character of Tennessee&#39;s rural areas. The general concepts embraced by the Ad Hoc Committee found substantial support in the House and Senate. Ultimately, differences between the two bodies were resolved in a conference committee, and the House and Senate approved the conference committee report by an overwhelming margin. Public Chapter 1 101 became law on May 19, 1998, with the signature of Governor Don Sundquist.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/281</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1281&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>281</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1281</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-04T07:12:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>7176972</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/281</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on Trace are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For current information, please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mtas.tennessee.edu/&quot;&gt;http://www.mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-06-04T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1998-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>