<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Efficacy of Hollow-Fiber Ultrafiltration for Microbial Sampling in Groundwater</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Knappett</lname>
<fname>Peter</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Layton</lname>
<fname>Alice</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McKay</lname>
<fname>Larry</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Mailloux</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Huq</lname>
<fname>M.R.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Alam</lname>
<fname>M.J.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Ahmed</lname>
<fname>Kazi</fname>
<mname>Matin</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Akita</lname>
<fname>Yasuyuki</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Serre</lname>
<fname>Marc</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Sayler</lname>
<fname>Gary</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>van Geen</lname>
<fname>Alexander</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this study was to test hollow-fiber ultrafiltration as a  method for concentrating in situ bacteria and viruses in groundwater  samples. Water samples from nine wells tapping a shallow sandy aquifer  in a densely populated village in Bangladesh were reduced in volume  approximately 400-fold using ultrafiltration. Culture-based assays for  total coliforms and &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli,&lt;/em&gt; as well as molecular-based assays for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bacteroides&lt;/em&gt;,  and adenovirus, were used as microbial markers before and after  ultrafiltration to evaluate performance. Ultrafiltration increased the  concentration of the microbial markers in 99% of cases. However,  concentration factors (CF = post-filtration concentration/pre-filtration  concentration) for each marker calculated from geometric means ranged  from 52 to 1018 compared to the expected value of 400. The efficiency  was difficult to quantify because concentrations of some of the markers,  especially &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; and total coliforms, in the well water (WW)  collected before ultrafiltration varied by several orders of magnitude  during the period of sampling. The potential influence of colloidal iron  oxide precipitates in the groundwater was tested by adding EDTA to the  pre-filtration water in half of the samples to prevent the formation of  precipitates. The use of EDTA had no significant effect on the  measurement of culturable or molecular markers across the 0.5 to 10 mg/L  range of dissolved Fe&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; concentrations observed in the  groundwater, indicating that colloidal iron did not hinder or enhance  recovery or detection of the microbial markers. Ultrafiltration appears  to be effective for concentrating microorganisms in environmental water  samples, but additional research is needed to quantify losses during  filtration.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eartpubs/2</coverpage-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-10T07:10:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Earth and Planetary Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1864399</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eartpubs/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-03-10T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1745-6584.2010.00712.x/abstract</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>