<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An online study of undergraduates&#39; knowledge, awareness, and attitudes of preconception care</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kcrusenb@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Crusenberry</lname>
<fname>Kelly</fname>
<mname>Jean</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>preconception care</keyword>
<keyword>online</keyword>
<keyword>undergraduates</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background: &lt;/strong&gt;The majority of pregnancies in the United States are unplanned. Health status and health-related behaviors such as poor nutrition, alcohol consumption, and/or tobacco use, occurring prior to conception, have been linked to poor obstetric outcomes for mothers and their offspring, many of which can result in lifelong challenges. Knowledge, awareness, and attitudes can be predictors of health-related behaviors, and preconception care and education may reduce risk of some of these poor obstetric outcomes. Undergraduate students are at an increased risk for many of these risky behaviors and for unplanned pregnancies, as compared to older individuals. However, little is known about undergraduates’ knowledge, awareness, and attitudes related to optimal preconception behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective: &lt;/strong&gt;To assess knowledge, awareness, and attitudes of undergraduate students related to preconception care and to explore potential differences by gender, age, sexual activity status, weight status, prior classroom exposure to pregnancy and child development, and class standing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: This was an online, cross-sectional survey, conducted among students enrolled in a basic undergraduate nutrition course, during the first week of class. The survey measured knowledge, awareness, and attitudes of pregnancy-related issues and preconception care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results/Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; Sixty-nine students completed the survey. Overall, students demonstrated low to moderate knowledge of issues related to preconception health, with an average composite knowledge score of 50%. Those reporting exposure from friends, family, and/or healthcare providers regarding preconception care demonstrated less knowledge than those who reported little exposure. It is possible that those with greater knowledge are less likely to be aware of these cues to action, or that individuals in their lives are less concerned about issues of preconception health. However, overall knowledge scores were very low, and demonstrate need for education regardless of age or perception of cues to action. Additional research is needed to identify the most effective techniques to impact preconception health-related awareness and subsequent behaviors in this population.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4006</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4901&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4006</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4901</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-07T10:23:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7689684</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4006</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Katie F. Kavanagh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Marsha L. Spence, Sarah E. Colby</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>