<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Large anaplastic spinal B-cell lymphoma in a cat</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Flatland</lname>
<fname>B</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Fry</lname>
<fname>M</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Moore</lname>
<fname>P</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>B-cell lymphoma</keyword>
<keyword>cat</keyword>
<keyword>clonality</keyword>
<keyword>cytology</keyword>
<keyword>immunohistochemistry</keyword>
<keyword>spine</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A 5-year-old female spayed domestic shorthair cat was presented for evaluation of tetraparesis. The neurologic lesion was localized to the cervical spinal segment (C1-C6). A left axillary mass was identified, and the results of fine needle aspiration cytology indicated malignant round cell neoplasia of possible histiocytic origin. The cells were large, had marked anisocytosis and anisokaryosis, occasional bi- and multinucleation, and cytoplasmic vacuolation. Euthanasia was performed due to the poor prognosis associated with severe, progressive neurologic signs and a malignant neoplasm. Postmortem examination revealed spinal cord compression and an extradural mass at the C1-C2 spinal segment, with neoplastic cells in the adjacent vertebral bodies, surrounding skeletal muscle, left axillary lymph node, and bone marrow from the right femur. The initial histologic diagnosis was anaplastic sarcoma, but immunohistochemical results indicated the cells were CD20+ and CD45R+ and CD3-, compatible with a diagnosis of B-cell lymphoma. CD79a staining was nonspecific and uninterpretable. Weak to moderate CD18 positivity and E-cadherin positivity were also observed. Clonality of the B-cell population could not be demonstrated using PCR testing for antigen receptor gene rearrangement. To the authors&#39; knowledge, this is the first reported case of a feline spinal anaplastic B-cell lymphoma exhibiting bi- and multinucleated cells. The prognostic significance of this cell morphology and immunophenotype is unknown.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/23</coverpage-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284746</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>B Flatland, M M. Fry, Shelley Newman, P F. Moore, J R. Smith, W B. Thomas, and R H. Casimir. &quot;Large anaplastic spinal B-cell lymphoma in a cat&quot; Veterinary Clinical Pathology 37.4 (2008): 389-396.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1939-165X.2008.00049.x/abstract</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Veterinary Clinical Pathology</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>