<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development and Implementation of a Successful Northern Bobwhite Translocation Program in Georgia</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:54:03-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Stations and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Terhune</lname>
<fname>Theron</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Georgia Department of Natural Resources</institution>
<lname>Thackston</lname>
<fname>Reggie</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>Florida</keyword>
<keyword>Georgia</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>National Bobwhite Conservation Initiative</keyword>
<keyword>translocation</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Gamebird translocations have been used for many years to establish or re-establish populations in North America. A long-term severe decline of northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) over much of their range has brought this issue to the forefront for this species as well. Field studies in Georgia over the last decade have documented site fidelity, high survival, reproductive success, and population response from bobwhites translocated into large blocks of well-managed habitat. The Georgia Department of Natural Resources/ Wildlife Resources Division developed an official wild quail translocation policy in 2006. Five translocation projects have been permitted and conducted since the policy was established. Extensive large scale habitat modifications were required on the recipient sites while donor sites were required to have existing high density bobwhite populations. These projects have resulted in translocation of . 800 bobwhites and the establishment of 7,480 ha of new wild quail population centers thereby contributing to the National Bobwhite Conservation Initiative (NBCI) recovery goals. Average fall densities on completed projects have increased from , 0.5 birds/ha to . 1.25 birds/ha.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/111</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1438&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>111</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_conservation_planning</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1438</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:44:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472272</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/111</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>