<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Higher Protein Kinase C ζ in Fatty Rat Liver and Its Effect on Insulin Actions in Primary Hepatocytes</title>
<publication-date>2015-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Wei</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Goff</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kuang</lname>
<fname>Heqian</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gchen6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Zucker fatty rats</keyword>
<keyword>protein kinase C</keyword>
<keyword>Zucker lean rats</keyword>
<keyword>PKCζ</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We previously showed the impairment of insulin-regulated gene expression in the primary hepatocytes from Zucker fatty (ZF) rats, and its association with alterations of hepatic glucose and lipid metabolism. However, the molecular mechanism is unknown. A preliminary experiment shows that the expression level of protein kinase C ζ (PKCζ), a member of atypical PKC family, is higher in the liver and hepatocytes of ZF rats than that of Zucker lean (ZL) rats. Herein, we intend to investigate the roles of atypical protein kinase C in the regulation of hepatic gene expression. The insulin-regulated hepatic gene expression was evaluated in ZL primary hepatocytes treated with atypical PKC recombinant adenoviruses. Recombinant adenovirus-mediated overexpression of PKCζ, or the other atypical PKC member PKCι/λ, alters the basal and impairs the insulin-regulated expressions of glucokinase, sterol regulatory element-binding protein 1c, the cytosolic form of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase, the catalytic subunit of glucose 6-phosphatase, and insulin like growth factor-binding protein 1 in ZL primary hepatocytes. PKCζ or PKCι/λ overexpression also reduces the protein level of insulin receptor substrate 1, and the insulin-induced phosphorylation of AKT at Ser473 and Thr308. Additionally, PKCι/λ overexpression impairs the insulin-induced &lt;em&gt;Prckz&lt;/em&gt; expression, indicating the crosstalk between PKCζ and PKCι/λ. We conclude that the PKCζ expression is elevated in hepatocytes of insulin resistant ZF rats. Overexpressions of aPKCs in primary hepatocytes impair insulin signal transduction, and in turn, the down-stream insulin-regulated gene expression. These data suggest that elevation of aPKC expression may contribute to the hepatic insulin resistance at gene expression level.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/39</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1042&amp;amp;context=utk_nutrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>39</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1042</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-06T08:18:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>9239040</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/39</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Chen W, Goff MR, Kuang H, Chen G (2015) Higher Protein Kinase C ζ in Fatty Rat Liver and Its Effect on Insulin Actions in Primary Hepatocytes. PLoS ONE 10(3): e0121890.
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0121890</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1371/journal.pone.0121890</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>PLOS One</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>