<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Topographical Influences on the Campaigns in Middle and West Tennessee during the First Year of the Civil War</title>
<publication-date>1953-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Scott</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Blair</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Preface: This study is an attempt to evaluate the role played by topography in the results of the campaign in West and Middle Tennessee during the first year of the War Between the States. In mid-nineteenth century America, roads were poor and communication was extremely slow. The use of the telegraph was not yet widespread; mountains and rivers still presented formidable barriers to travel, and the chief means of movement for troops was by railroad, steamboat, horseback, and on foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the main source for primary materials for this thesis I have relied on the &lt;em&gt;War of the Rebellion, A Compilation of the Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Atlas&lt;/em&gt; which accompanies these records has also been invaluable for material relating to troop movements and positions as well as for use as a source for portions of the maps included in this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hoped that the maps will aid the reader in understanding the topography of the localities with which the study is concerned. The maps are not drawn to scale but are used to show troop movements in respect to prominent relief features and political boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am deeply indebted to Doctor Stanley J. Folmsbee of the University of Tennessee History Department, who suggested the subject of this thesis and provided inspiration and guidance during its preparation. I would also like to express my appreciation to Doctor Ralph W. Haskins and Doctor H. C. Amick, whose painstaking examination and helpful comments have contributed greatly to this study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1560</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3009&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1560</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3009</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-07T09:09:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4400850</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1560</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>S. J. Folmsbee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph W. Haskins, H. C. Amick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1953-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1953-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>