<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Free Logic</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nolt</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>free logic</keyword>
<keyword>encyclopedia</keyword>
<keyword>axiom systems</keyword>
<keyword>deduction rules</keyword>
<keyword>tree rules</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Section 1 lays out the basics of free logic, explaining how it differs from classical predicate logic and how it is related to inclusive logic, which permits empty domains or “worlds.” Section 2 shows how free logic may be represented by each of three formal methods: axiom systems, natural deduction rules and tree rules. Varying conventions for calculating the truth values of atomic formulas containing empty singular terms yield three distinct species of free logic: negative, positive and neutral. These are surveyed in Section 3, along with supervaluations, which were developed to augment neutral logics. Section 4 is critical, examining three anomalies that infect most free logics. Section 5 samples applications to theories of description, logics of partial or non-strict functions, logics with Kripke semantics, logics of fiction and logics that are in a certain sense Meinongian. Section 6 takes a glance at free logic&#39;s history.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_philpubs/8</coverpage-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-30T11:29:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Philosophy</publication-title>
<context-key>1587773</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_philpubs/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>&quot;Free Logics,&quot; in &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Logic&lt;/em&gt;, ed., Dale Jacquette, (Volume 5 of the &lt;em&gt;Handbook of the
Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; under the general editorship of Dov Gabbay, Paul Thagard, and
John Woods), Elsevier 2006, pp. 1023-1060.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>&quot;Free Logics,&quot; in Philosophy of Logic, ed., Dale Jacquette, (Volume 5 of the Handbook of the Philosophy of Science under the general editorship of Dov Gabbay, Paul Thagard, and John Woods), Elsevier 2006, pp. 1023-1060.</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>