<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Communication and job satisfaction of contract security employees</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Logan</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
<mname>Thompson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine whether or not there was a relationship between communication and job satisfaction among contract security employees. In addition, this study sought to determine whether or not participants&#39; demographic characteristics impacted communication and job satisfaction. The researcher sent questionnaire packets to 306 employees who worked for a regional contract security guard company with employees in the Midwest and throughout the southeastern United States. The response rate was 47% (N = 144). The packets consisted of 2 survey instruments-the Communication Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ) developed by Downs and Hazen in 1977, and the Job Satisfaction Survey (JSS) created by Spector in 1985-plus a demographic questionnaire comprised of 8 demographic questions developed by the researcher. Results from this study indicated that there was no significant difference among the 8 demographic variables and communication satisfaction as measured by the CSQ. Regarding job satisfaction, results revealed that the demographic variable, position with company, was significant with regard to the JSS subscales of (a) pay, (b) contingent rewards, (c) coworkers, (d) nature of work, and (e) communication. Findings from this study also indicated the existence of a moderate to high relationship between communication and job satisfaction, with the best predictors of job satisfaction being personal feedback, communication climate, and general organizational perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5952</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7585&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5952</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7585</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467613</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5952</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Connie Hollingsworth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>