<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>ASSOCIATIONS BETWEEN INTIMATE PARTNER VIOLENCE VICTIMIZATION AND EMPLOYMENT OUTCOMES AMONG MALE AND FEMALE POST-9/11 VETERANS</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rmaskin@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Maskin</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>Miriam</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>gender</keyword>
<keyword>occupational functioning</keyword>
<keyword>work outcomes</keyword>
<keyword>partner abuse</keyword>
<keyword>Veterans Health Administration</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objective:&lt;/b&gt; Given high rates of intimate partner violence (IPV) victimization among veterans, along with employment-related difficulties, a better understanding of IPV’s implications for employment functioning is needed among post-911 veterans, especially male veterans. This study aimed to examine the gender-based associations between IPV victimization types (physical, psychological, and sexual) and employment outcomes (absenteeism, presenteeism, and job satisfaction).&lt;b&gt;Method:&lt;/b&gt; A national sample of male and female post-9/11 veterans completed a survey administered approximately 5.5 years after deployment including IPV victimization and employment measures. This study used data from 407 veterans (52% women) in intimate relationships to examine the associations between IPV victimization and employment outcomes by gender, using regression-based analyses.&lt;b&gt;Results:&lt;/b&gt; Sexual IPV was significantly associated with absenteeism and presenteeism for women but not men, and physical IPV was significantly associated with presenteeism for men but not women. There were also marginal associations between psychological IPV and both absenteeism and job satisfaction overall, regardless of gender.&lt;b&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/b&gt; All IPV types were linked to employment functioning for both male and female post-9/11 veterans. These findings can aid in the development of trauma-informed psychosocial intervention efforts for women and men that target employment functioning as well as IPV to help victims of partner violence achieve healthy and stable lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5447</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6855&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5447</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6855</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-12T18:30:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>16528579</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5447</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Deborah Welsh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory Stuart, Todd Moore</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>This article was previously published in Psychologist Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>