<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Resilient Micro-Power Charge Amplifier for Biomedical Applications</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hwang51@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Hanfeng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>charge amplifier</keyword>
<keyword>charge sensitive pre-amplifier</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;It is reasonable to believe, that the world of tomorrow is a surge of the cyberspace, whose interface is knitted by enormous varieties of sensor electronic systems. Biomedical sensor systems gain special interests simply because they save lives. An implanted glucose sensor system acknowledges the diabetes patient a concentration increase before symptoms. A respiratory sensor system may alert the nurse when an apnea is detected. The mass occurrences of medical conditions are uploaded to the database and statistically studied, the results of which are utilized for gross prevention basis.A sensor system as such, usually consists of a transducer that converts the information of interest to electrical energy, a front-end amplifier that buffers the energy to a voltage signal, a data converter that digitize the signal and a transmitter that pass on the information. This dissertation will exclusively discuss the front-end amplifiers. As one of the most common types, a charge-mode amplifier resolves charge amount with a RC fed-back voltage gain circuit configuration, standardly known as charge amplifiers. However, the conventional structure suffers from the tradeoff between leakage current tolerance and signal bandwidth while iterations and modifications in literature failed to address the issue efficiently.A novel approach is proposed in this dissertation that obliterates the aforementioned tradeoff and offers complementary benefits. The resiliency that this structure exhibits bolsters its feasibility to be incorporated in a wide spectrum of applications especially biomedical sensor systems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4869</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6410&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4869</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6410</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:13:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13414895</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4869</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Syed K. Islam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David M. Binkley, Benjamin J. Blalock, Joshua S. Fu</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6790-4026</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>