<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sounds of the City: The Complete Musical Story</title>
<publication-date>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jdaven20@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davenport</lname>
<fname>Julie Marie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;By using a barren urban site and reworking part of the existing fabric of downtown, this project turns part of Jackson Avenue in downtown Knoxville into a vibrant music center and a concentration of creativity. Bringing all parts of the music industry to one building, this project provides a single place for musicians to gather, learn, create, and perform in order to achieve success in the music industry. This project began with the concept of revitalizing the Jackson Avenue area and extending the downtown to increase activity in this area. Much of Knoxville revolves around music, and people will be drawn towards the city to experience the vitality music brings to a space. Organized sequentially from bottom to top in the process of creating music, the design offers all needs for success in music and emphasizes its connection to the rest of the city. In order to draw public audiences and increase overall awareness of the music industry, this project also offers music lessons, performances, and dance classes to public audiences. By bringing people downtown and exposing everyone to new kinds of music, this project encourages creativity in the city and brings an energetic vibe to a previously desolate area.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2015/architecturedesign/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1072&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1072</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-28T09:00:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>7039943</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2015/architecturedesign/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Architecture and Design</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Marleen Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>