<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Age-Specific Nesting Performance by Northern Bobwhites</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:52:29-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Miller</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Stations and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Wellendorf</lname>
<fname>Shane</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>age-specific reproduction</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>Florida</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>population dynamics</keyword>
<keyword>reproductive ecology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Greater reproductive productivity of adult versus juvenile northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) has been hypothesized as a factor for rapid population growth. Research on bobwhites in the western portions of the species’ range has not supported this hypothesis; however, no effort has been made to investigate age-specific reproduction on population dynamics in the southeast. We measured age- specific reproductive parameters between adult and juvenile bobwhites during 2000–2010. We radio-marked 1,069 females of which 308 were adults and 761 were juveniles. Nests per hens for adults (0.78 nests/hen) was slightly greater than that for juveniles (0.65 nests/hen) (P 1⁄4 0.09). Adult productivity was 1.7 times greater than for juveniles in 4 of 10 years which corresponded to years of population growth. No differences were found in initial clutch sizes or nesting success. Adult hens began incubation earlier than juveniles in all but 1 year suggesting increased nesting may be due to early recrudescence in adults. The magnitude of age-specific reproductive differences in short-lived species like bobwhites is not as great as long-lived species, but has implications for understanding bobwhite population dynamics and harvest.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/92</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1419&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>92</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_population_dynamics</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1419</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:44:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472243</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/92</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>