<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of Landscape Position and Dairy Manure Addition on Bioavailable Forms of Soil Phosphorus Using Enzyme Hydrolysis</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tstone4@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Stone</lname>
<fname>Themis Mahalia</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>enzymatic hydrolysis of soil phosphorus</keyword>
<keyword>soil phosphorus testing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Soil Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Bioavailable phosphorus (P) has traditionally been measured as inorganic orthophosphate (PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) while organic P (P&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt;) has been considered of limited relevance to short-term biological consumption. However, enzymes secreted by bacteria and fungi which serve to mineralize P&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; are ubiquitous in the environment and may contribute significant bioavailable P over time. In order to assess environmentally-relevant, potentially bioavailable P in soils with added dairy wastes, microcosms of identical soil series but differing management histories and landscape positions were incubated at 24 C° for three weeks. Subsamples were taken weekly from microcosms and analyzed by: 1) Mehlich-3 extractant, 2) NaOH-EDTA subjected to sulfuric acid total digest, and 3) NaOH-EDTA subjected to enzymatic hydrolysis by one, two or three commercially-available phosphatase enzymes. A high throughput, microplate reader method (Johnson and Hill, 2010) was adapted to quantify the enzyme-hydrolysable P. There were significant microcosm changes (&lt;em&gt;P &lt;/em&gt;&lt;0.05), with three week 24 C° incubation, in Mehlich-3 extractable P, with soils having low total P (TP) showing decreases and soils in both upland and depositional field positions increasing in Mehlich-3 extractable P. Also, over three weeks of study, low TP control soils subjected to three enzymes had a 58% increase in MRP over initial MRP in NaOH-EDTA soil extracts, whereas dairy farm upland soils had a 9% increase and depositional soils had an increase of 3%. Soils with higher levels of TP had smaller amounts of enzymatically hydrolysable P than soils containing low levels of TP. This points to limitations of this enzyme hydrolysis method for assessing potentially available P&lt;sub&gt;o&lt;/sub&gt; in soils with very high Mehlich-3 and TP (Mehlich-3 P: &gt;120 mg/kg; total P: &gt;1,200 mg/kg). In conclusion, NaOH-EDTA extracts a range of P&lt;sub&gt;o &lt;/sub&gt;species that can be transformed in the environment into P available to aquatic algae, but results from the Johnson-Hill method differ widely, even in identical series soils, possibly depending on field position and animal waste additions leading to high copper, zinc and TP.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1099</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2175&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1099</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2175</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-12T15:12:19-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2175/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2153786</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1099</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Amy M. Johnson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark Radosevich, Jennifer M. DeBruyn; Forbes Walker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental and Soil Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>