<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Tennessee Mayor-Aldermen Charter</title>
<publication-date>1970-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The title of this publication is somewhat misleading –it does not contain all of the laws available to a city incorporated under TCA 6-101 et seq. We have included only the chapters that are more or less limited to cities incorporated under this l aw (but some are applicable to all cities—for example, the annexation law in sec t ions 6 -308—6-321) . The purpose is to provide a handy reference volume with the most commonly-consulted laws for cities incorporated under the sections of the code. This publication includes chapters 1 through 8 of Title 6, Municipal Corporations, Tennessee Code Annotated, as amended through the 1970 session of the General Assembly. Chapters 9 through 37 of Title 6 have been omitted; 9 through 17 are available to all cities regardless of their legal basis of incorporation; 18 through 23 provide for the council-manager form of government; 24 through 29 deal with service agencies other than municipalities; 30 through 36 provide for the “modified” council-manager form; and 37 governs city-county consolidation (called “metropolitan government”). There are many other laws scattered throughout the Tennessee Code Annotated that are applicable to municipalities; to compile these and to extract pertinent excerpts would be no doubt useful, but the product would be voluminous—and the project is beyond our staff capabilities at the present time.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-06T12:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2638692</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1970-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>