<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Double-Edged Sword of Self-Enhancement: A Longitudinal Examination of the Effects of Self-Enhancement on Psychological and Physical Well-Being among Individuals with Multiple Sclerosis</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>eomara1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>O&#39;Mara</lname>
<fname>Erin Marie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Social Psychology</keyword>
<keyword>Self-Enhancement</keyword>
<keyword>Well-being</keyword>
<keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study prospectively examines factors that affect whether self-enhancement exerts favorable or unfavorable effects on both psychological and physical well-being in a context that is less controllable than other contexts in which self-enhancement has been examined (e.g., academic performance), an at risk population of Multiple Sclerosis (MS) patients. In particular, the present study (a) examines whether self-enhancement differentially predicts psychological and physical well-being when self-enhancement is related or unrelated to the well-being outcomes, and (b) whether self-enhancement interacts with severity of circumstances (i.e., course of MS) to predict psychological and physical well-being, as suggested by O’Mara, McNulty, &amp; Karney (2011). In addition to the baseline assessment, participants completed measures of self-enhancement (outcome-related and outcome-unrelated), and psychological and physical well-being every 30 days for 90 days, for a total of four assessments. The pattern of findings suggests that in less controllable contexts, self-enhancement is a doubled-edged sword. Outcome-related self-enhancement was trending towards a positive, cross-sectionally association with physical well-being, and a measure of prior outcome-unrelated self-enhancement (collectivistic tactical self-enhancement) was positively associated with subsequent physical well-being &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; for individuals with less severe MS. Further, prior outcome-related self-enhancement was associated with better subsequent psychological well-being but worse subsequent physical well-being, and although prior collectivistic tactical self-enhancement is associated with favorable subsequent physical well-being for individuals with less severe MS, it is also associated unfavorable psychological well-being regardless of MS severity. The discussion addresses the contributions of the present study to the literature, strengths and limitations of the present study, and directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1109</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2219&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1109</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2219</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-23T08:37:40-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2219/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2072878</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1109</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lowell Gaertner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James K. McNulty, Michael Olson, Russel Zaretski</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>