<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Talent and Trust: A Case Study Describing the Process of Designing a Global Elite World-Class University in Denmark</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bsamble@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Samble</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>Walter</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>World Class University</keyword>
<keyword>Higher Education</keyword>
<keyword>Denmark</keyword>
<keyword>Danish Higher Education</keyword>
<keyword>Global</keyword>
<keyword>Government Relations</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to describe the process of becoming a world-class university in the context of Western Europe. Aarhus University served as the case site, within the context of Denmark. One research question guided this study, “How does a higher education institution in Western Europe undergo the process to actualize its ambition to become a world-class university?” I remained in Denmark for approximately 18 days collecting data for this qualitative case study. Observations were completed in Aarhus and in Copenhagen, and documents and/or photographs were collected from university and government sources, In total 17 participants were interviewed including past and present high-level administrators, an academic administrator who also held a faculty position, and students at Aarhus University, as well as government officials serving in the Ministry of Science, Innovation, and Higher Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings indicated visionary leadership, external consultants, and a pragmatic reorganization of the university propelled Aarhus University to create academic hubs with an interdisciplinary focus, emphasize a more global focus, express a desire to obtain greater external funding and engage in greater collaboration, and develop a core focus on what Aarhus University referred to as &lt;em&gt;talent development&lt;/em&gt;. I refer to this notion similarly, as &lt;em&gt;talent capacity-building &lt;/em&gt;to accent the notion that building a growing base of talent was central to national competitiveness strategies elsewhere in Denmark in addition to Aarhus University. Trust emerged as a cultural value in Denmark and an important consideration for the university and the government. Generous government state support and autonomy enhanced Aarhus University’s resources and decision-making capacity, yet a concern for quality assurance, economic competitiveness, and academic relevancy remained.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2728</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4044&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2728</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4044</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-27T11:56:20-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4044/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5228477</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2728</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>J. Patrick Biddix</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Trena M. Paulus, David J. Houston, Dorian L. McCoy</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>