<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Innovative Event Management: Is Your Organization Thriving or Just Surviving?</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-08T12:25:46-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>chyppoli@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hyppolite</lname>
<fname>Chivonne Marie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>bjones80@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Brandon</fname>
<mname>Lamont</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Interpersonal and Small Group Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Organizational Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Innovative Event Management: Is Your Organization Thriving or Just Surviving?&quot;- All programming is not effective programming! This presentation will allow participants to critically analyze the structure and effectiveness of their organization. This presentation will address three pertinent domains of student organization function: Leadership, Event Management Strategies and Organizational Branding and offer participant’s innovative ideas to catapult their organization to the next level. The learning outcomes of this presentation will prepare the participant to utilize collaborative relationships to construct a holistic brand, develop innovative leadership strategies and effectively execute events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of your organization stems from your university and community partnerships. Innovatively leading your organization requires a team to ascend into higher realms of thinking and imagination. This creativity allows a team to create unique outlets to unify the campus and local community through collaborative leadership development and programming efforts. Thus embodying the theme of “&lt;em&gt;One Campus…One Community…Unified for One Cause.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2012/Session2/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1054&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1054</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-01-30T20:35:05-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1054/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>2480606</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2012/Session2/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Tag Words: Innovative, Leadership, Branding, Programming, Event Management, Team Building, Organizational Structure&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>