<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Biosystematic Study of &lt;em&gt;Heterotheca&lt;/em&gt; section &lt;em&gt;Pityopsis&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>1972-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bowers</lname>
<fname>Frank</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A biosystematic study of the section &lt;em&gt;Pityopsis&lt;/em&gt; of the genus &lt;em&gt;Heterotheca&lt;/em&gt; was undertaken. Cytological, morphological, chromatographic, and hybridization studies were utilized to provide a basis for taxonomic treatment of the taxa. The species were divided into two broad groups; the &lt;em&gt;Heterotheca graminifolia&lt;/em&gt; group (&lt;em&gt;H. adenolepis, H. aspera, H. graminifolia, H. microcephala &lt;/em&gt;var. &lt;em&gt;microcephala&lt;/em&gt; and var. &lt;em&gt;aequilifolia, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. oligantha&lt;/em&gt;) and the &lt;em&gt;H. pinifolia&lt;/em&gt; group (&lt;em&gt;H. falcata, H. flexuosa, H. pinifolia, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. ruthii&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;Heterotheca ruthii&lt;/em&gt; appears to be intermediate between the two groups and is closely related to &lt;em&gt;H. oligantha.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cytology indicates the diploid species (N=9) are prominent with only &lt;em&gt;H. adenolepis&lt;/em&gt; (both diploids and tetraploid), &lt;em&gt;H. graminifolia, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. oligantha&lt;/em&gt; being tetraploids (N=8). Pollen measurements were obtained showing tetraploids being significantly larger (except for &lt;em&gt;H. adenolepsis&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paper chromatographs were somewhat inconclusive but generally followed the other taxonomic evidence for the section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is thought that &lt;em&gt;H. graminifolia&lt;/em&gt; was derived via autopolyploidy from &lt;em&gt;H. microcephala. Heterotheca adenolepsis&lt;/em&gt; is thought to have been derived from an allopolyploid hybrid between &lt;em&gt;H. aspera&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;H. microcephala. Heterotheca oligantha&lt;/em&gt; has a limited range in Florida and Alabama but appears closely related to &lt;em&gt;H. graminifolia&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;H. ruthii. Heterotheca pinifolia, H. falcata, H. flexuosa, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. ruthii&lt;/em&gt; apparently were derived from one or more primitive ancestors which migrated from an Appalachian center of origin to the Coastal Plain, became geographically separated and evolved into the four entities listed above. &lt;em&gt;Heterotheca ruthii&lt;/em&gt; appears to be the most primitive of the four species. All are limited in rang with &lt;em&gt;H. ruthii&lt;/em&gt; found only in the Hiwassee Gorge of East Tennessee; &lt;em&gt;H. flexuosa&lt;/em&gt; in a few counties in Florida: &lt;em&gt;H. pinifolia&lt;/em&gt; in a few counties in the Sand Hills of Georgia and North and South Carolina, and &lt;em&gt;H. falcata&lt;/em&gt; in sand areas in five northeastern states. These four species have relatively few genetic barriers but are widely separated geographically.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2660</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4164&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2660</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4164</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-12T13:59:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5571347</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2660</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>A. Murray Evans</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank W. Woods, A. J. Sharp, H. R. DeSelm</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>