<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Suppressive Effects of 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 and Vitamin D Receptor on Brown Adipocyte Differentiation and Mitochondrial Respiration</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cricciar@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ricciardi</lname>
<fname>Carolyn</fname>
<mname>Jeanne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Vitamin D receptor</keyword>
<keyword>brown adipocyte</keyword>
<keyword>UCP1</keyword>
<keyword>mitochondrial respiration</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Molecular, Genetic, and Biochemical Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The vitamin D system plays a role in metabolism regulation. It has been reported that 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; [1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D] suppresses 3T3-L1 adipocyte differentiation. Vitamin D receptor (VDR) knockout mice showed increased energy expenditure whereas mice with adipose-specific VDR over expression showed decreased energy expenditure. Brown adipose tissue (BAT), which functions in non-shivering thermogenesis by uncoupling ATP synthesis from oxidation, plays important roles in energy expenditure. However, the effects of 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; on brown adipocyte differentiation and mitochondrial respiration have not been studied. Reported here is the mRNA expression of VDR, UCP1, and CYP27B1 (1α[alpha]- hydroxylase) in two mice models of obesity; and the down regulation of mRNA of VDR, CYP24A1 (24-hyrdoxylase), and CYP27B1 during brown adipocyte differentiation in vitro. 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; dose-dependently suppressed brown adipocyte differentiation, as revealed by oil red O (ORO) stained cell morphology, ORO absorbance, and brown adipocyte marker gene expression. Moreover, cellular bioenergetics measurements showed that 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; suppressed isoproterenol-stimulated oxygen consumption rates (OCR), maximal OCR and OCR from proton leak, but had no effects on ATP-generating OCR and spare respiration capacity in brown adipocytes. Consistently, over-expression of VDR also suppressed brown adipocyte differentiation. Furthermore, both 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and VDR over expression suppressed PPARγ[gamma] transactivation in brown preadipocytes. Taken together, the results demonstrate the suppressive effects of 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;/VDR signaling on brown adipocyte differentiation and mitochondrial respiration and suggest a role of 1,25(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;/VDR signaling in regulating BAT function for obesity treatment and prevention.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2876</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4168&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2876</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4168</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-21T13:03:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5815262</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2876</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ling Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, Guoxun Chen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>