<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Public speaking anxiety causes and correlates : new twists on an old problem</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Haun</lname>
<fname>Kristin</fname>
<mname>Nicole</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to study a well-known and well-researched topic, public speaking anxiety, in a new light. Public speaking anxiety has been researched in depth for numerous years; however, there are still a few areas that have received little research when applied to public speaking anxiety. These areas are self-perceived competency, preparation time, contagion theory, and gender differences. All of these areas may serve as correlational or causational factors for public speaking anxiety. This study was conducted using students from introductory public speaking classes at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. All students were asked to fill out two questionnaires, THE COMMUNICATION ANXIETY INVENTORY - FORM STATE and the COMMUNICATIVE COMPETENCE SCALE, before and after giving a prepared four to seven minute speech. Although more research needs to be conducted in the previously mentioned areas, this study did conclude that intuitiveness does not always mean truthfulness. Public speaking anxiety and self-perceived competency were found to decrease over time. The amount of time spent in preparation and the effects of contagion theory had no effect on the amount of public speaking anxiety felt by a student. Finally, there it was found that there were no gender differences when it comes to public speaking anxiety. In essence, dealing with public speaking anxiety and its numerous causes and correlates, can be a tricky situation. This is true because one never knows how anxiety may affect an individual or how individual differences may affect public speaking anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5931</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7564&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5931</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7564</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467588</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5931</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michelle Violanti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>