<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Predictive Validation of the Monitoring Instructional Responsiveness: Reading (MIR:R): Investigation of a Group-Administered, Comprehension-Based Tool for RTI Implementation</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kcaldwe9@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Miller</lname>
<fname>Kelli</fname>
<mname>Caldwell</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Monitoring Instructional Responsiveness: Reading (MIR:R), a group-administered measure designed to determine at-risk status for reading fluency and comprehension, was administered to 494 third-grade students to determine the relationship between MIR:R static and slope scores and student performance and non-proficiency status on the Tennessee Comprehensive Assessment Program (TCAP) Achievement Test, reading composite. Correlation coefficients defining the relationship between the total MIR:R static score (the Comprehension Rate score) and student performance and non-proficiency status on the TCAP are .60 (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .01) and .52 (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .01), respectively. When the relationships between MIR:R slope and TCAP performance and non-proficiency status were investigated, weaker correlations were obtained-- .22 (&lt;em&gt;p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .01) and .20 (&lt;em&gt;p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .01), respectively. Results from a step-wise multiple regression equation revealed that the MIR:R Comprehension Percentage component score provided moderate predictive validity for TCAP reading composite performance (9.4% age variance accounted for, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .01); the Total Words Read component score was less predictive (1.1 % age additional variance accounted for, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .05). When MIR:R component scores were entered into a logistic regression analysis, these scores predicted TCAP proficiency and non-proficiency status reasonably well; values ranged from 60% to 88% (&lt;em&gt;p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .01). Apparently, both the Comprehension Rate total static score and the Comprehension Percentage component score provide solid predictive accuracy (&lt;em&gt;p &lt;/em&gt;&lt; .01); the slope and Total Words Read component scores are less predictive. Data support the utility of the MIR:R as a promising, progress-monitoring reading screener within a Response to Intervention/problem-solving model.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2461</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2565&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2461</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2565</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-05-12T13:05:28-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2565/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2846477</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2461</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry M. Bell, Christopher H. Skinner, Amy D. Broemmel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>School Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>