<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Comparison of the Sensor Brick Concept as a Modular System Architecture to the Realtime Control System as the Operational Architecture</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Robert</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Computer Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis describes the application of modular design into an intelligent mobile robotic system. The Sensor Brick System, a mobile robotic system infused with artificial intelligence, is derived through the concept and application of modular design. Modular design drives the system’s characterization by defining, identifying and selecting the essential composite of sub-systems that form the system architecture. The principles of modular design designate grouping the technologies into modules that facilitate maintenance of the system components and allow the rapid integration of future technological developments. Developing the operational control of the system requires an examination and comprehension of the theories of intelligent control. The operational architecture of the system, an application derived from the theories of intelligent control, describes the tasks, operational units, and information flows of the system in a scope of high resolution. Generally, the application of a control structure directs the evolution of and for the intelligent systems by providing a framework for the system as it achieves increasing degrees of autonomous operations. The conceptual implementation of an operational control structure in the form of the Realtime Control System into the Sensor Brick System describes the system in a future, more developed state, and constitutes the penultimate contribution of this research. A demonstrable result of the Sensor Brick System describes the system as it is applied to an under-vehicle inspection scenario. The application of the system highlights the attributes of the system as it extracts information about the state of the vehicle using various sensor bricks.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2539</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3818&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2539</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3818</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-18T12:42:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4739766</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2539</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mongi Abidi</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Page, Seong Kong</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>