<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Functional analysis of the &lt;i&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/i&gt; gene promoter of &lt;i&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/i&gt; for caffeine- and Phenobarbital-inducibility by site-directed mutagenesis</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ohill1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hill</lname>
<fname>Olivia Nichole</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cytochrome P450</keyword>
<keyword>xenobiotic metabolism</keyword>
<keyword>gene regulation</keyword>
<keyword>cell culture</keyword>
<keyword>insecticide resistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Molecular Genetics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cytochrome P450 enzymes (CYPs), found in almost all organisms, are involved in endobiotic metabolism and detoxification of xenobiotic compounds, such as drugs, pollutants, and insecticides.  In insects, CYPs play a major role in conferring resistance to various insecticides including DDT. In &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; and other insects, DDT-resistant strains exhibit increased expression of multiple P450 genes; however, the mechanism of overexpression is unknown. Since many &lt;em&gt;CYP&lt;/em&gt; genes including &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; are induced by&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;caffeine and other xenobiotics, these chemicals are used as tools to understand the regulation of these genes.  Previously it was shown that the 0.8-kb (-1/-732) and 0.2-kb (-1/-170) upstream DNA of &lt;em&gt;Cyp6a8&lt;/em&gt; of the DDT-resistant 91-R strain support caffeine, DDT, and Phenobarbital induction in adult flies and S2 cells, the 0.2-kb DNA has many transcriptionally important sequence motifs.  In the present investigation, site-directed mutagenesis was performed on the putative TATA box and CREB/AP-1 motifs located at the -97/-101, -57/-61, -43/-47, and -6/-10 regions of the 0.2- and 0.8 DNAs to determine their cis-regulatory role in caffeine and PB induction in S2 cells using &lt;em&gt;luciferase&lt;/em&gt; reporter system. Results showed that all four deletions in 0.2- and 0.8-kb DNA decreased both basal and caffeine-induced activities, but maximum effect was seen with the -57/-61 deletion. Second, the TATA mutations greatly decreased basal activity, but they did not decrease caffeine-inducibility as much as the -57/-61 mutations. Third, the effects of other three deletions on basal activities were not as pronounced in the 0.8-kb environment as were seen in the 0.2-kb environment. Taken together these results suggest that of all four putative CREB/AP1 sites the one located at -57/-61 region is most important for both basal and caffeine-induced activities. The results also suggest that the additional 600 bases upstream of -1/-170 have distal elements that interact with the proximal promoter in the 0.2-kb DNA and boost basal transcription. A model suggesting interactions of all cis elements with the basal promoter for basal and induced transcription has been proposed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/979</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2138&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>979</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2138</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-01T08:39:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2124816</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/979</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ranjan Ganguly</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mariano Labrador, Bruce D. McKee</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>