<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Internet Use and Training in University Libraries</title>
<publication-date>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Hawaii</institution>
<lname>Neufang</lname>
<fname>Ralf</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Internet</keyword>
<keyword>university libraries</keyword>
<keyword>library instruction</keyword>
<keyword>electronic reference</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;University research libraries in the United States and Canada were surveyed to determine their use of a variety of electronic reference tools. An 85% response rate provided us with information about university library use of CD-ROM, remote online, locally loaded databases, and Internet access. The biggest change since our 1991 survey of the same libraries was in their provision of Internet access to users through the library. Follow-up interviews provided more in-depth information on how university libraries are managing Internet access, staff and user training programs, and changes in library staff attitudes or user attitudes since Internet access was introduced. In every case Internet access did not replace any other electronic reference service, but was added to existing services.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/230</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1417&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>230</label>
<document-type>conference</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1417</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-31T12:12:51-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16095461</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/230</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Carol Tenopir and Ralf Neufang. “Internet Use and Training in University Libraries.” In 16th National Online Meeting Proceedings, New York, May 2-4 1995, edited by Martha E. Williams. Medford, NJ: Learned Information, Inc., 1995. Pp. 387-396.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>16th National Online Meeting Proceedings</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>