<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Localized deformation in metallic glasses at the ambient temperature</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Song</lname>
<fname>Shuangxi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Metallic glasses have many unusual properties, such as extremely high strength and large elastic limit. However, they are also brittle, failing in a catastrophic manner, as a result of the formation of highly localized shear bands at room temperature. Such flow localization has been attributed to the influence of strain softening or local heating, or a combination of both, which leads to the local drop in viscosity and, finally, the runaway of the shear band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, a novel method was developed for in situ observation of the localized shear processes. The inhomogeneous deformation of metallic glasses at room temperature and under a slow strain rate was found to be dominated by intermittent sliding on a principal shear plane in the sample. Such sliding results in flow serration in the stress-strain curve in the plastic region, and there is one-to-one correspondence between the intermittent sliding and flow serration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using high speed camera and strain gages it was found that the displacement-time curves exhibited micron-sized bursts after the onset of yielding, apparently associated with formation of individual shear bands. Each displacement burst disclosed a three-step (acceleration, steady-state, and deceleration) process during the shear-band propagation. The viscosity of propagating shear bands was evaluated, and a detailed analysis based on free volume model indicated that shear-band propagation was mainly resulted from free volume accumulation. The propagating speed of shear band in a smaller metallic glass specimen was found to be slower, mainly because a lower accumulative strain energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of flow serration in compression at high strain rates was a result of the fact that the propagation was overshadowed when crosshead speed approaches the speed of shear-band propagation. Nanoindentation on several metallic glasses at different indentation rates indicates a much higher critical strain rate for the disappearance of flow serration. Brittle metallic glasses were found to have a higher shear-band strain rate as a result of higher shear-band energy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/635</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1704&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>635</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1704</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-24T08:27:26-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1167723</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/635</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>T.G. Nieh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>E.P. George, Y.F. Gao, D. Penumadu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>