<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rapid in vivo analysis of synthetic promoters for plant pathogen phytosensing</title>
<publication-date>2011-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>wliu2@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Wusheng</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mmazarei@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mazarei</lname>
<fname>Mira</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mrudi@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rudis</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>nealstewart@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennesseee - Knoxvile</institution>
<lname>Stewart</lname>
<fname>Neal</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aimed to engineer transgenic plants for the purpose of early detection of plant pathogen infection, which was accomplished by employing synthetic pathogen inducible promoters fused to reporter genes for altered phenotypes in response to the pathogen infection. Toward this end, a number of synthetic promoters consisting of inducible regulatory elements fused to a red fluorescent protein (RFP) reporter were constructed for use in phytosensing.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For rapid analysis, an &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium&lt;/em&gt;-mediated transient expression assay was evaluated, then utilized to assess the inducibility of each synthetic promoter construct &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;. Tobacco (&lt;em&gt;Nicotiana tabacum &lt;/em&gt;cv. Xanthi) leaves were infiltrated with &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium &lt;/em&gt;harboring the individual synthetic promoter-reporter constructs. The infiltrated tobacco leaves were re-infiltrated with biotic (bacterial pathogens) or abiotic (plant defense signal molecules salicylic acid, ethylene and methyl jasmonate) agents 24 and 48 hours after initial agroinfiltration, followed by RFP measurements at relevant time points after treatment. These analyses indicated that the synthetic promoter constructs were capable of conferring the inducibility of the RFP reporter in response to appropriate phytohormones and bacterial pathogens, accordingly.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These observations demonstrate that the &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium&lt;/em&gt;-mediated transient expression is an efficient method for &lt;em&gt;in vivo &lt;/em&gt;assays of promoter constructs in less than one week. Our results provide the opportunity to gain further insights into the versatility of the expression system as a potential tool for high-throughput &lt;em&gt;in planta &lt;/em&gt;expression screening prior to generating stably transgenic plants for pathogen phytosensing. This system could also be utilized for temporary phytosensing; e.g., not requiring stably transgenic plants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/49</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1049&amp;amp;context=utk_planpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>49</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1049</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-10T14:20:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4302726</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/49</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>BMC Biotechnology 2011, 11:108 doi:10.1186/1472-6750-11-108</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>