<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Isolated Wired and Wireless Battery Charger with Integrated Boost Converter for PHEV and EV Applications</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mchintha@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chinthavali</lname>
<fname>Madhu</fname>
<mname>Sudhan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Wireless power transfer</keyword>
<keyword>charging</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Electronics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Vehicle charging and vehicle traction drive components can be integrated for multi-functional operations, as these functions are currently operating independently. While the vehicle is parked, the hardware that is available from the traction drive can be used for charging. The only exception to this would be the dynamic vehicle-charging concept on roadways. WPT can be viewed as a revolutionary step in PEV charging because it fits the paradigm of vehicle to infrastructure (V2I) wirelessly. WPT charging is convenient and flexible not only because it has no cables and connectors that are necessary, but due more to the fact that charging becomes fully independent. This is possibly the most convenient attribute of WPT as PEV charging can be fully autonomous and may eventually eclipse conductive charging. This technology also provides an opportunity to develop an integrated charger technology that will allow for both wired and wireless charging methods. Also the integrated approach allows for higher charging power while reducing the weight and volume of the charger components in the vehicle. The main objective of this work is to design, develop, and demonstrate integrated wired and wireless chargers with boost functionality for traction drive to provide flexibility to the EV customers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3406</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4886&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3406</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4886</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-14T21:38:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7214213</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3406</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leon M. Tolbert</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Fred Wang, Rao V. Arimilli, Burak Ozpineci, Daniel J. Costinett</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>