<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Analysis of Residential Camp Site Structure !or Two Early Archaic Assemblages from Rose Island (40MR44), Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1981-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kimball</lname>
<fname>Larry</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The site structure of two Early Archaic period assemblages is defined through spatial analysis of artifact and facility distributions at the Rose Island site (40MR44) in the lower Little Tennessee River valley. These assemblages derive from well controlled excavation of deeply buried alluvial deposits attributable to LeCroy (c. 6100-6500 B.C.) and St. Albans (c. 6600-7000 B.C.) temporal units. Spatial patterning is detected using multivariate statistical analysis of formal implement, instant tool, and debitage categories. The observed spatial patterns are interpreted through a comparison with expected spatial patterns generated from an a priori model of hunter-gatherer residential camp activity structure. The results of the analysis allow the proposal of a general model of Early Archaic residential camp site structure. The model identifies activity areas based upon densities and spatial relationships of artifact categories for an assemblage. The reconstructed activity structure describes the location of the family hearth as occurring in front of the opening of the shelter. A wide range of activities are localized around the family hearth. More specialized activities, such as flintworking, hideworking, and the roasting of game, are conducted near the shelter, but apart from the family hearth.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4119</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5570&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4119</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5570</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-13T07:25:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9261931</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4119</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jefferson Chapman</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles H. Faulkner, Gerald F. Schroedl</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1981-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1981-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>