<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>House Prices and Household Behavior: Essays in Household Valuations, Price Cointegration, Residential Location Choice, and Neighborhood Resiliency</title>
<publication-date>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kkrivacs@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Krivacsy</lname>
<fname>Kevin</fname>
<mname>Russell</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>house prices</keyword>
<keyword>hedonic</keyword>
<keyword>cointegration</keyword>
<keyword>neighborhood resiliency</keyword>
<keyword>affordable housing</keyword>
<keyword>housing bust</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Residential property values have only recently recovered from the effects of the Great Recession and the housing bubble and burst. During this period, cities were not collecting as much tax revenue as predicted because of depressed housing prices and the global economy suffered greatly because of it.Economists and others have studied the causes of the instability in property values in recent years from many angles. Their research has been influential in explaining what happened to the housing market during that time. Yet, what is missing is a detailed level analysis of how the spatial structure of our cities may contribute to this instability or stability in residential property values and a better understanding of their local dynamics.While economists are likely correct in their macroeconomic focus, there is still room for research on the role that local factors may have played or will play in the determination of residential property values. Even within metropolitan areas, there may have been a difference in magnitude of property value fluctuation.Therefore, this study focuses on the extent to which the urban form may contribute to overall economic stability as seen through the stability of residential property values. This research builds on past research by 1) incorporating more detailed and accurate neighborhood measures, 2) contributing to the literature by conducting cointegration at a very local level and 3) assessing the impact that neighborhood, demographic and economic attributes at the local level may have on the long-term stability of property values in our urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5272</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6816&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5272</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6816</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-04-24T08:36:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>14342900</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5272</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Shih-Lung Shaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ronald V. Kalafsky, Hyun Kim, Wenjun Zhou</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>