<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effects of classroom seating on student attitude toward learning</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Habib</lname>
<fname>Donna</fname>
<mname>Jean</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine and reach a conclusion on the reasons behind student/teacher seating in a specific way and the effect of seating arrangement on student attitude toward learning. The study answered many questions that deal with the seating arrangements at Farragut High School in Knox County Schools. The respondents included a sample of the 1,316 students and 9 teachers enrolled in the Business/Marketing department for the full year {fall and Spring) of 2002, from Farragut High School in Knoxville, TN. Each respondent reported on his/her attitude toward seating arrangements and the reasons why teachers assigned seating in one manner versus another. Major conclusions of the study were: 1. Teachers assign seats most of the time in the Classroom. 2. Teachers have definite preference for students who sit in the front row. 3. Teachers do not want students to sit beside their friends in the classroom. 4. Male students prefer to sit beside good students and in the back rows of the classroom. They do not believe that seeing the teacher or the board affects their attitude toward leaning. 5. Male students reported that sitting in the back rows of the classroom indicates low self-esteem. 6. Female students prefer to sit in the front rows, in order to see the teacher, and the board. 7. Freshmen students believe that they pay more attention in the classroom if they sit in the front of the classroom or beside their friends. 8. Students enrolled in Basic Business courses tend to believe that (a) students pay better attention in the classroom if students are sitting in the front rows, and (b) those students who sit in the back of the classroom wish to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5929</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7562&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5929</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7562</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467586</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5929</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vickie Johnson Stout</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>