<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Localizing Ligand Binding Sites Using Overlapping Recombinant Polypeptide Sequences of Vitronectin</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Watson</lname>
<fname>Jodi</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Vitronectin is a glycoprotein involved in many cellular processes including blood coagulation, fibrinolysis, and cell/matrix binding. It interacts with a number of macromolecules including heparin, PAI-1, and the thrombin-antithrombin complex. We have studied the interaction of full-length vitronectin and the thrombin-antithrombin complex using a Far Western method. To localize the recognition site for thrombin-antithrombin binding to vitronectin, sequences for eight overlapping recombinant polypeptide sequences of vitronectin (spanning all 459 amino acids) were cloned into the pET system. Expression in BL21(DE3)pLysS &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; has been achieved for seven of the eight 100 amino acid fragments. Seven polypeptides (amino acids 1-100, 51-150, 101-200, 151-250, 201-300, 251-350, and 351-459) have been isolated and purified using metal-chelating affinity chromatography. These fragments have been tested for interaction with the thrombin-antithrombin pair using the Far Western technique. Results indicate interaction of the complex with vitronectin between amino acids 201-300 and possibly at another site near the C-terminal. Additionally, these expressed fragments have served as helpful reagents in mapping the epitopes of three monoclonal antibodies for vitronectin.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2250</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3653&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2250</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3653</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-11T13:14:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4699931</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2250</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cynthia Peterson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jeffrey Becker, Barry Bruce</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>