<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Believing Game in Mathematics: Stories in a Discipline of Doubt</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Cincinnati</institution>
<lname>Harkness</lname>
<fname>Shelly</fname>
<mname>Sheats</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Clermont College</institution>
<lname>Lane</lname>
<fname>Catherin</fname>
<mname>Pullin</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Indiana University Purdue University Fort Wayne</institution>
<lname>Mau</lname>
<fname>Sue</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Cincinnati</institution>
<lname>Brass</lname>
<fname>Amber</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Creative Writing</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>Liberal Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Many people view mathematics as a discipline of certainty and rigidity. Answers are either right or wrong, and, when they are wrong, it is easy to play the doubting game. We invite readers into our mathematics classrooms as we story our attempts to play the believing game. We provide a lens into how we suspended our own logic, assumptions, and interpretations until we first tried to &quot;unpack, &quot; understand, and honor our students&#39; logic, assumptions, and interpreta· tions. Within our individual stories, elements of tension, surprise, and wonder emerged as collective themes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jaepl/vol15/iss1/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1176&amp;amp;context=jaepl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>essay</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1176</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-20T13:12:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>The Journal of the Assembly for Expanded Perspectives on Learning</publication-title>
<context-key>4470787</context-key>
<submission-path>jaepl/vol15/iss1/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Shelly Sheats Harkness, Associate Professor, Secondary Education Mathematics, at the University of Cincinnati, was a classroom teacher for 12 years prior to earning her PhD at Indiana University. Her research interests include ethnomathematics, mathematics and social justice, and teachers’ “believing” and listening in mathematics classrooms. 

Sue Mau is Associate Professor in the Department of Mathematical Sciences, Indiana University Purdue University Fort Wayne. Her research interests include prospective teachers’ understanding of mathematics and their beliefs about teaching. 

Catherine Pullin Lane is Mathematics Instructor in the Science, Mathematics and Engineering Division at Clermont College and is a doctoral student in Curriculum and Instruction at the University of Cincinnati. Her research interests include how students develop mathematical thinking skills and how they interact with the concept of proof. 

Amber Brass is Assistant Director Academic in Middle Childhood Education at the University of Cincinnati. Prior to coming to Cincinnati, she was a middle school mathematics teacher in Iowa and Michigan. Her academic interests include the use of literature in the mathematics classroom and the content and pedagogical knowledge of preservice teachers.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>The Believing Game in Mathematics</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>