<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of a Simple DC-Balanced Encoding Method for LVDS Data Transmission Over CAT-5 Cable</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Shaoyu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, a simple dc-balanced encoding scheme was developed to reduce the bit error rate for high-speed data transmission over CAT-5 cable using Low-voltage Differential Signaling (LVDS). The dc balance encoder was implemented to make binary sequences with a spectral null at zero. A data transmission controller using the dc balanced scheme was implemented in an Altera Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA), including data generators that send data to a DS92LV1023 10-bit bus LVDS serializer, data checkers for checking the data coming from a DS92LV1224 10-bit bus LVDS deserializer, and dc balance and non-dc balance encoders. Data was transmitted over various lengths of CAT-5 cable with and without dc balance to determine the effect of the dc balance scheme on transmission errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To generalize the type of data used in the transmission tests, three different kinds were selected for the error testing: pseudo-random numbers generated by a 32-bit Linear Feedback Shift Register (LFSR) binary polynomial generator; consecutive numbers generated by a counter; and data looked-up from a Read Only Memory (ROM) implemented in an FPGA embedded memory block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data transmission controller was constructed, configured, and tested both with and without dc balance. It provides a data transmission rate of 538.8 Mbps, and is able to send the number of errors encountered during the transmission process to a PC via the PCI bus. Testing results verify that the dc balance scheme adopted in this thesis significantly improves the accuracy of the serial data transmission. Both dc-balanced and non-dc-balanced encoding proved error-free out to cable lengths of about 19.8 meters. DC-balanced encoding also extended the error-free cable length by about 1.5 meters and reduced errors by about 60% for longer cables.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2098</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3463&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2098</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3463</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T13:41:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4665183</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2098</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bruce W. Bomar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roy D. Joseph, L. Montgomery Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>