<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Understanding Zoosexuality: Prevalence, Impact, and Links to Criminal Behavior</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T13:30:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jenny.edwards@chandleredwards.org</email>
<institution>Chandler Edwards</institution>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>Jenny</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>brian.kiernan@chandleredwards.org</email>
<institution>Swedish Hospital</institution>
<lname>Kiennan</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
<suffix>MSSA, LICSW</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Keywords: bestiality, zoophilia, zoosexual, animal abuse, human-animal relations, sexual paraphilia, cross-reporting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This paper briefly discusses the historical development of zoosexualism in the United States &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;and Canada, and its significance to the fields of criminology, law, social work, and medicine. The importance of cross-reporting between veterinarians, social workers, mental healthcare providers, and law enforcement is emphasized. Preview of an ongoing study is mentioned, emphasizing a suggested link between bestiality and the sexual assault and exploitation of children. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of us, the idea of humans having sex with animals is abhorrent. The topic is seldom researched, studied, or openly discussed, yet historical and anthropological evidence suggests that such relationships have existed for millennia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoosexuality (also known as bestiality) is the sexual orientation of a human to an animal. It is considered a paraphilia, or sexual perversity, by the American Psychiatric Association and is illegal throughout most of the United States. While current and reliable statistics are lacking, some information may be gained from existing and proposed studies of sexual practices. Indications are that zoosexuals comprise between 3-8% of the general population, and are primarily single Caucasian men between 45-60. Dogs are the most common sexual partner followed by horses and livestock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year an unknown number of animals (and humans) are traumatized, injured, or killed after aggressive or repeated sexual acts. Animals are frequently solicited, traded or sold specifically for sex. They are filmed having intercourse with their own species as well as human partners, and are far too often found in pornography videos where children are involved. While there are known links between animal cruelty and human violence, few studies have been done to determine the links between bestiality and other forms of criminal behavior, such as trespass, substance abuse, or the sexual assault or exploitation of children and adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoosexuality presents practical challenges for animal welfare, legal, medical, and veterinary professionals. More research is needed to better understand causes, treatment, and intervention protocols, as well as development of practical tools and resources when investigating, examining, or treating animal or human patients. Workable mechanisms for cross-reporting between legal, healthcare, and animal welfare agencies do not currently exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study of approximately 300 litigated cases of animal sex abuse through the US and Canada between 1995 and 2012 is currently underway. Several measures are being tracked including animal victim breed and gender, type of abuse, incidence of prior or concurrent crimes, and correlation with animal or child pornography. Other measures being considered are animal disposition and outcome, frequency of multiple offenders or victims, age of offender at time of incidence, and population size where the incident occurred. The information gained will be useful in developing offender profiles as well as a taxonomy of zoosexuals. Preliminary findings suggest a link between animal and child sexual abuse. Further research could provide practical solutions for educators or healthcare professionals when presented with a suspected case of animal sexual abuse. Insights into the prevalence of zoosexuality may lead to better intervention techniques for law enforcement or animal welfare professionals as well sentencing and rehabilitation guidelines for the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/3</coverpage-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1078</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-31T17:54:06-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utvswsummit/article/1078/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3635000</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Jenny Edwards, Primary Presenter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Director of Training and Field Operations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.S., Purdue University, 1974&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate work, University of Kentucky, 1979-80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certification, Animal Control Officer, Criminal Justice Training Commission, Des Moines, WA, 2005&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certification, Legal Investigations, LMI Professional Investigations, Seattle WA, 2010&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentations and Publications:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J. and Humane Research Council, &lt;em&gt;Prevalence of child pornography in reported cases of animal sex abuse (working title)&lt;/em&gt;, study completion expected Summer, 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J. and Kiernan SSA LICSWA, Brian, &lt;em&gt;Profile of a PETophile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;©: Recognizing Animal Sex Abuse&lt;/em&gt;, Criminal Investigations Division, Puget Sound Police Departments, Mount Vernon WA, June 2012; Washington State Crime Prevention Association, Walla Walla WA, April 2012; Colorado Association of Animal Control Officers conference, Denver CO, April 2011; Texas Association of Animal Control Officers, February, 2010; Washington Animal Control Association Conference, Seattle WA, March 2009&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J., &lt;em&gt;Animal Sex Abuse: What you can do about it, &lt;/em&gt;Flying Changes Magazine, August 2011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J., &lt;em&gt;Why a National Registry for Animal Abusers is Important.&lt;/em&gt; Horsetalk of New Zealand, April, 2011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J., &lt;em&gt;Is that all there is? Why animal cruelty cases are rarely investigated and seldom prosecuted, &lt;/em&gt;Animal Justice Magazine, Fall 2010&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwards, J., &lt;em&gt;Animal Love Gone Wrong,&lt;/em&gt; Neon Magazine, Germany, April, 2008&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian A. Kiernan, MSSA, LICSW - Presenter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education/Certifications:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2011-Certificate in British Object Relations Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Center for Object Relations-Seattle, WA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2001-Case Western Reserve University-Cleveland, OH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master of Science in Social Administration (Social Work)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concentration in Mental Health and Aging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1998-Texas A&amp;M University-Corpus Christi, TX&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bachelor of Arts- major in psychology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faculty Positions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2008-Current:Clinical Teaching Associate, University of Washington School of Medicine, Family Medicine-Seattle, WA; Clinical Instructor, University of Washington School of Social Work-Seattle, WA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2006-Current:Lecturer and Instructor-Behavioural Science Faculty, Swedish Family Medicine Residency Program-Cherry Hill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Awards and Honors:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2011-Outstanding Practicum Instructor for Depth of Practice Knowledge, University of Washington-School of Social Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2009-Swedish Family Medicine Cherry Hill Clinic Mission Award, Cherry Hill Family Medicine Residency Program-Seattle, WA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2001-Dean’s Award for Academic Excellence, Mandel Scholar- Case Western Reserve University-Cleveland, OH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1997-Psi Chi (National Honour Society in Psychology) Induction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas A&amp;M University-Corpus Christi, TX&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Jenny Edwards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chandler Edwards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P O Box 2452&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woodinville WA 98072&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;425.522.3335&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T15:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CUMBERLAND ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_url" type="string">
<value>http://trace.lib.utk.edu/assets/VSW/2013/JEnnyEdwards.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Workshop: 1-hour workshop</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T13:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_file" type="string">
<value>VSW/2013/JEnnyEdwards.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_streamer" type="string">
<value>rtmp://trace.lib.utk.edu:1935/stream</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T13:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>The link between human and animal violence</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Understanding_Zoosexuality_Prevalence__Impact__and_Links_to_Criminal_Behavior.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>Understanding_Zoosexuality_Prevalence__Impact__and_Links_to_Criminal_Behavior.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1078&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>