<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Functions of Aggression and Peer Victimization in Elementary School Children: The Mediating Role of Social Preference</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>smanring@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Manring</lname>
<fname>Samantha</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Peer victimization</keyword>
<keyword>Aggression</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Child Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined the longitudinal associations among functions of aggression, social preference, and peer victimization. Participants were 492 children (249 girls, 227 boys) in grades 2-5. Proactive and reactive aggression was assessed via a self-report measure and indices of social preference and peer victimization were assessed via a peer nomination inventory. Data was collected during the fall and spring of two academic years. Results suggest that the relation between aggression, social preference, and peer victimization varied by the function of aggression and gender. For girls, reactive aggression was a significant negative predictor of social preference. Findings also revealed social preference mediated the relation between reactive aggression and peer victimization for girls. This pathway did not hold for boys. There was some evidence that proactive aggression was negatively associated with peer victimization, but only for girls. Findings from the current study suggest social preference may be a key mechanism through which reactive aggression is associated with future victimization for girls. Boys’ aggression was not related to subsequent peer victimization. Future research and intervention efforts should consider gender differences and the function of aggression when investigating children’s peer victimization experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4055</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5159&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4055</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5159</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-03-23T06:56:58-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/5159/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8368918</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4055</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence C. Elledge</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Todd Moore, Jennifer Bolden</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>