<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Habitat and Space Utilization of Black Bears in Cherokee National Forest, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1986-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Clevenger</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
<mname>Paul</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Thirty-four black bears (&lt;em&gt;Ursus americanus&lt;/em&gt;) were captured a total of 43 times in the Citico Creek area of the Cherokee National Forest (CNF) during 1982 and 1983. Seven yearlings from 3 families were immobilized and radio-collared in winter dens during February 1983 and their movements thereafter were monitored. A total of 1635 radio locations were collected from 20 bears. Data were collected during the entire study for 5 bears and continuous data were recorded for 8 bears from previous studies. The timing of family breakup occurred in 2 families between 29 May and 5 June, and 22 June and 25 June, respectively. Reassociations between mother and offspring and between siblings did occur after breakup. Summer and fall home ranges of adult males were 20 km&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;and 132 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively, and were significantly larger (P &lt; 0.002) than summer and fall ranges of adult females, which were 4 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively. The mean summer ranges of adults measured 11 km&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;, while those of yearlings averaged 4 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Fall ranges for adults were 77 km&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;and yearlings 20 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. The intra-year ranges of adult males from summer to fall increased significantly for both years (P = 0.025). Such an increase has not been reported for adult males in Great Smoky Mountains National Park. This was probably due to hunter-related activities in CNF in the fall. Intra-year ranges remained constant for adult females during the study. The intra-year seasonal ranges of yearlings increased significantly (P &lt; 0.01) from summer to fall and could be explained as pre-dispersal or exploratory movement behavior. Adult males and all yearlings shifted seasonal activity centers more than adult females. Extensive home range overlap occurred among adult males while little overlap was found among adult females. Yearlings, after separation from their mothers, became progressively independent of their mothers&#39; range. Mean distances between mothers and offspring, and between siblings after family breakup, increased each month as family bonds began to weaken and exploratory movements took place. Notably long range movements by bears did occur, mainly into the Nantahala National Forest, North Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All bears used the Mesic Hemlock and Oak-Hickory forest types, stands in the 70 and older age class more than expected, and the early succession areas less than expected. Bears used the Mature Pine and Mature Hardwood forest types more than expected. In summer, adult bears used the Oak-Hickory forest type and stands between 30 to 49 and 70 to 89 years old; yearlings preferred the Cove Hardwood forest type, Mature Pine areas, and old age stands. In fall, adults preferred the Mesic Hemlock and Oak-Hickory forest types and stands between 10 to 20 and 70 to 89 years old; yearlings were indifferent to all forest types and forest stand age classes. The Oak-Hickory forest type appeared to be the most preferred and important of all forest types throughout the year for all bears. Yearlings used lower quality habitats during summer and fall, males particularly, possibly for avoiding conflicts with adults. Yearling females remained within their mothers&#39; range and occupied sub-optimum habitats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bears in the CNF are being impacted by illegal hunting and other related activities. This situation has been promoted by the relative ease of access to many parts of the Forest and inadequate law enforcement. The Tellico Bear Refuge appears to be effective and is complemented by adjacent wilderness areas in North Carolina. By reducing road access to many areas, the suitability of the Forest for black bears will be elevated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4530</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6062&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4530</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6062</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-21T08:49:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10055423</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4530</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Darrell West, Arthur C. Echternacht</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Wildlife and Fisheries Science not listed in Subject Categories.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>