<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Benefits of dance education : the perceptions of college dance students</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Shields</lname>
<fname>Laura</fname>
<mname>Leitner</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine college dance students&#39; perceptions of the contributions of dance education to their lives. Its primary goal was to develop a picture of the benefits of dance through the thoughts and words of dancers. An open-ended dance questionnaire designed to ascertain the students&#39; thoughts on the benefits of dance education in their lives and a demographic questionnaire designed to provide information on the dancers&#39; levels of ability were administered to dance students at a major University in the Southeast United States. Eighty-six and eight tenths percent of the students enrolled in dance classes completed the questionnaire. Each of the student&#39;s responses were coded and then categorized. Similar answers were grouped into sub-categories that were then placed under larger general categories. The percentages were calculated for the advanced, intermediate, and beginner levels under each sub-category. This study answered the following research questions: I) What are the life long benefits of dance training as perceived by mature students of dance? 2) Are the perceived benefits of dance training different for dancers of different levels of ability? 3) What makes dance a valuable option for physical fitness? and 4) Has dance training influenced students to include physical fitness in their lives? The answers provided by the students fell under the three major categories of emotional, intellectual, and physical benefits. Dancers from advanced, intermediate and beginner levels reported benefits from all three categories. The differences between groups were in the degree of importance upon which they placed the emotional, intellectual, and physical benefits. This study revealed the physical benefits of dance as well as the additional emotional and intellectual benefits. The answers provided by the study&#39; s participants showed that dance provides an emotional outlet in the form of stress relief and personal expression for many dancers. The physical benefits reported by the dancers included improved physical fitness, increased body awareness, and an increased motivation to maintain a higher fitness level. Intellectual benefits included the development of time management skills, concentration skills, and self-regulation. This study concludes that the combined physical, intellectual, and emotional benefits of dance can contribute to a person&#39;s overall health and well being.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5294</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6702&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5294</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6702</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847214</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5294</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gene McCutchen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>