<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Use of the Culture Care Theory and Ethnonursing Method to Discover how Nursing Faculty Teach Culture Care</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mixer</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As the world becomes increasingly multicultural, transcultural nursing education is critical to ensuring a culturally competent workforce. This paper presents a comprehensive review of literature and results of an ethnonursing pilot study using the Culture Care Theory (CCT) to discover how nursing faculty teach culture care. The literature revealed that despite 50 years of transcultural nursing knowledge development through theory, research and practice, there remains a lack of formal, integrated culture education in nursing. The importance of faculty providing generic and professional care to nursing students and using an organizing framework to teach culture care was discovered. Additionally, care was essential for faculty health and well-being to enable faculty to teach culture care. This unique use of the theory and method demonstrates its usefulness in discovering and describing the complex nature of teaching culture care. Larger scale studies are predicted to further substantiate the CCT, building the discipline of nursing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/34</coverpage-url>
<label>34</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1034</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-23T10:54:03-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_nurspubs/article/1034/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1369421</context-key>
<withdrawn>2018-04-03</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/34</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Sandra J. Mixer. &quot;Use of the Culture Care Theory and Ethnonursing Method to Discover how Nursing Faculty Teach Culture Care&quot; &lt;em&gt;Contemporary Nurse Journal: Advances in Contemporary Transcultural Nursing&lt;/em&gt; 28.1-2 (2008): 23-36.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>