<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>WANTED: Female Corporate Directors (A Review of Professor Douglas M. Branson&#39;s No Seat at the Table)</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>corporation</keyword>
<keyword>corporate governance</keyword>
<keyword>management</keyword>
<keyword>manager</keyword>
<keyword>board</keyword>
<keyword>director</keyword>
<keyword>executive</keyword>
<keyword>CEO</keyword>
<keyword>women</keyword>
<keyword>female</keyword>
<keyword>paradigm</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Gender</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Organizational Behavior and Theory</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In his 2007 book &lt;em&gt;No Seat at the Table&lt;/em&gt;,  Professor Douglas Branson aptly describes how patterns of male  dominance inherent in the legal structures of corporate governance  reproduce themselves again and again to keep women out of executive  suites and boardrooms, and then he offers a practical way to break this  cycle of dominance-through paradigm shifting. A central value of  Professor Branson&#39;s book derives from this thesis, as well as his use of  nontraditional empirical data and  interdisciplinary literature (in  addition to more traditional decisional law and legal scholarship) to  support the positions he takes. Moreover, &lt;em&gt;No Seat at the Table&lt;/em&gt; is  an invaluable resource because it collects in one volume varied  research materials and related information at the intersection of women  and corporate boards and because it offers further support for  diversification of boards of directors as part of the overall effort to  strengthen corporate governance practices and promote more productive,  efficient, and trustworthy corporations.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This review is designed  to explore these strengths - and a few related weaknesses - in Professor  Branson&#39;s approach. Specifically, the review highlights three key  strengths of Professor Branson&#39;s work: his thorough and useful report of  2001 and 2005 proxy data from public company filings with the U.S.  Securities and Exchange Commission, his account of the effects of  tokenism in the boardroom, and his analysis of the obstacles women face  in climbing the rungs to the top of the corporate ladder. The review  then evaluates the strengths and weaknesses of his proposed paradigm  shifting as an effective way to procure female advancement to executive  ranks and board positions. Finally, the review examines the potential  shortcomings of Professor Branson&#39;s observation and suggestion that the  differences between men and women are inconsequential and should be  minimized and, further, how these statements (when taken out of context)  conflict with his efforts to keep women in the pipeline toward upper  management.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/17</coverpage-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1021</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T09:17:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035187</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod and Walters, Sarah A. , WANTED: Female Corporate Directors (A Review of Professor Douglas M. Branson&#39;s No Seat at the Table). Pace Law Review, Forthcoming; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 82. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1295366</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1295366</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>