<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Feed Restriction on Lipid Dynamics and Reproduction in Northern Bobwhites</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-24T14:20:22-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Missouri Department of Conservation</institution>
<lname>Dailey</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>V.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Missouri</institution>
<lname>Callahan</lname>
<fname>Terrance</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;High annual and prenesting mortality rates (0.46-0.95) in northern bobwhites (Colinus virginianus) compel these birds to devote extraordinary effort and resources to reproduction. Bobwhites exhibit reproductive behavior characteristic of rapid multi-clutch and ambisexual polygamous mating systems. To better understand the physiological basis of the bobwhite&#39;s high reproductive capacity, we studied effects of restricted food intake on lean mass, lipids, and egg laying. We fed 48 bobwhites 3 levels of food intake including ad libitum (100%), and 60% and 80% of ad libitum. After 15 weeks of this protocol, we switched treatments for 50% of the birds in each treatment. Lipid levels were similar for 60% and 80% groups, but significantly greater for the 100% group. Egg laying was markedly depressed and delayed in food-restricted groups. Comparing quail in the 60% and 80% groups, the latter appeared to catabolize body lipids in order to lay eggs. Egg production rates (eggs bird- 1 day- 1) were 0.7 for 100% quail, 0.18 for 80% quail, and 0.03 for 60% quail. After switching treatments, subgroups allotted ad libitum food quickly recovered. The 60% and 80% subgroups reached constant egg production (0.6-0.7 eggs bird- 1 day- 1), and with lean mass and lipid levels (9.8%-13.9% of wet body mass) within 10 days of ad libitum feeding. We discuss partitioning of endogenous reserves for reproduction and importance of exogenous energy in quail ecology.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol4/iss1/33</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1150&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>33</label>
<document-type>genetics_survival_reproduction_populationrestoration</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1150</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-24T13:24:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10470007</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol4/iss1/33</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>