<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Serotonin and the Mammalian Circadian System: I. In Vitro Phase Shifts by Serotonergic Agonists and Antagonists</title>
<publication-date>1993-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prosser</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Dean</lname>
<fname>Robin</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Edgar</lname>
<fname>Dale</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Heller</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>Craig</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Stanford University</institution>
<lname>Miller</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>circadian rhythms</keyword>
<keyword>suprachiasmatic nucleus</keyword>
<keyword>serotonin</keyword>
<keyword>5-HT1A receptors</keyword>
<keyword>oscillator</keyword>
<keyword>brain slices</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Cell Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary mammalian circadian clock, located in the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN), receives a major input from the raphe nuclei. The role of this input is largely unknown, and is the focus of this research. The SCN clock survives &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt;, where it produces a 24-hr rhythm in spontaneous neuronal activity that is sustained for at least three cycles. The sensitivity of the SCN clock to drugs can therefore be tested &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; by determining whether various compounds alter the phase of this rhythm. We have previously shown that the nonspecific serotonin (5-HT) agonist quipazine resets the SCN clock &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt;, inducing phase advances in the daytime and phase delays at night. These results suggest that the 5-HT-ergic input from the raphe nuclei can modulate the phase of the SCN circadian clock. In this study we began by using autoradiography to determine that the SCN contain abundant 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1A&lt;/sub&gt; and 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1B&lt;/sub&gt; receptors, very few 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1C&lt;/sub&gt; and 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; receptors, and no 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; receptors. Next we investigated the ability of 5-HT-ergic agonists and antagonists to reset the clock &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt;, in order to determine what type or types of 5-HT receptor(s) are functionally linked to the SCN clock. We began by providing further evidence of 5-HT-ergic effects in the SCN. We found that 5-HT mimicked the effects of quipazine, whereas the nonspecific 5-HT antagonist metergoline blocked these effects, in both the day and night. Next we found that the 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1A&lt;/sub&gt; agonist 8-OH-DPAT, and to a lesser extent the 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1A-1B&lt;/sub&gt; agonist RU 24969, mimicked the effects of quipazine during the subjective daytime, whereas the 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1A&lt;/sub&gt; antagonist NAN-190 blocked quipazine&#39;s effects. None of the other specific agonists or antagonists we tried induced similar effects. This suggests that quipazine acts on 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1A&lt;/sub&gt; receptors in the daytime to advance the SCN clock. None of the specific agents we tried were able either to mimic or to block the actions of 5-HT or quipazine at circadian time 15. Thus, we were unable to determine the type of 5-HT receptor involved in nighttime phase delays by quipazine or 5-HT. However, since the dose-response curves for quipazine during the day and night are virtually identical, we hypothesize that the nighttime 5-HT receptor is a 5-HT&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-like receptor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/31</coverpage-url>
<label>31</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1030</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-16T05:33:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1358725</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/31</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Serotonin and the Mammalian Circadian System: I. In Vitro Phase Shifts by Serotonergic Agonists and Antagonists
Prosser, Rebecca A., Dean, Robin R., Edgar, Dale M., Heller, H. Craig, Miller, Joseph D.
J Biol Rhythms, Apr 1993; vol. 8: pp. 1-16</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1993-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://jbr.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/8/1/1</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>