<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Complete Denitrification by the Non-Denitrifier &lt;i&gt;Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans&lt;/i&gt;: The Role of Coupled Biotic-Abiotic Reactions</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmerryfi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Onley</lname>
<fname>Jenny</fname>
<mname>Rae</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Anaeromyxobacter</keyword>
<keyword>nitrogen cycle</keyword>
<keyword>iron cycle</keyword>
<keyword>chemodenitrification</keyword>
<keyword>denitrification</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nitrous oxide (N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O) is a potent greenhouse gas and ozone-depleting substance produced by many different pathways in the nitrogen cycle, including nitrification, denitrification, and chemodenitrification. Abiotic sources of N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O such as the chemical reaction between nitrite (NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) and ferrous ion (Fe[II]) are generally neglected in studies of N turnover in soils. Abiotic controls containing nitrate (NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) and ferric iron (Fe[III]) fail to capture potential reactions between intermediates of N cycle pathways (e.g., NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; as an intermediate in NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; - reduction to ammonium [NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;] or nitrogen gas) or replenishment of reactants by iron cycling. Recent studies suggest that Fe(II) plays an important role in N turnover through combined biotic and abiotic reactions. &lt;em&gt;Anaeromyxobacter dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; strain 2CP-C is a common soil bacterium with a versatile metabolism, including microaerobic and anaerobic respiration. &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; reduces Fe(III) to Fe(II) and reduces NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; to NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; via respiratory ammonification. The present work investigates the mechanisms by which &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; utilizes O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and the synergistic effects of Fe(III) and NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; reduction. Evidence for respiration of 21% O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; via a low-affinity cytochrome c oxidase is presented, further expanding the respiratory versatility of &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt;. A previously unrecognized ecophysiological role is revealed in which &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; reduces NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; to approximately 50% N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and 50% NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; via coupled biotic-abiotic reactions, revealing a mechanism for denitrification in the absence of nitric oxide (NO)-forming NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; reductases. Further analysis of publicly available sequenced genomes reveal other microorganisms with the potential to couple biotic-abiotic reactions for reduction of NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; to N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the absence of NO-forming NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; reductases. Finally, the effects of sulfide and molybdenum are tested, demonstrating that &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; reduces NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; to NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; to N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O in the presence of Fe(II) and sulfide, due to the inhibition of NO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; and N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O reductases by sulfide sequestration of trace metals. Collectively, this work demonstrates an underestimated mechanism for denitrification and expands our knowledge of the role of &lt;em&gt;A. dehalogenans&lt;/em&gt; in O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; respiration and Fe and N cycling. Future efforts assessing the fate of N in agricultural soils should take into account the iron, molybdenum, and sulfide content of soils in addition to molecular information.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4705</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5590&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4705</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5590</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-07T10:40:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9243846</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4705</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank E. Löffler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Alison Buchan, Qiang He, Karen Lloyd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>