<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Insight Into the Molecular Mechanisms for Microcystin Biodegradation in Lake Erie and Lake Taihu</title>
<publication-date>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Krausfeldt</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>James Madison University, Harrisonburg</institution>
<lname>Steffen</lname>
<fname>Morgan</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Great Lakes Institute for Environmental Research, University of Windsor, Windsor, ON, Canada</institution>
<lname>McKay</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green</institution>
<lname>Bullerjahn</lname>
<fname>George</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>College of Environmental Science and Forestry, State University of New York, Syracuse,</institution>
<lname>Boyer</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilhelm</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Microcystins are potent hepatotoxins that are frequently detected in fresh water lakes plagued by toxic cyanobacteria. Microbial biodegradation has been referred to as the most important avenue for removal of microcystin from aquatic environments. The biochemical pathway most commonly associated with the degradation of microcystin is encoded by the &lt;em&gt;mlrABCD&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt;) cassette. The ecological significance of this pathway remains unclear as no studies have examined the expression of these genes in natural environments. Six metatranscriptomes were generated from microcystin-producing &lt;em&gt;Microcystis&lt;/em&gt; blooms and analyzed to assess the activity of this pathway in environmental samples. Seventy-eight samples were collected from Lake Erie, United States/Canada and Lake Tai (&lt;em&gt;Taihu&lt;/em&gt;), China, and screened for the presence of &lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt; gene transcripts. Read mapping to the &lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt;cassette indicated transcripts for these genes were absent, with only 77 of the collective 3.7 billion reads mapping to any part of the &lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt; cassette. Analysis of the assembled metatranscriptomes supported this, with only distantly related sequences identified as &lt;em&gt;mlrABC-&lt;/em&gt;like. These observations were made despite the presence of microcystin and over 500,000 reads mapping to the mcy cassette for microcystin production. Glutathione S-transferases and alkaline proteases have been previously hypothesized to be alternative pathways for microcystin biodegradation, and expression of these genes was detected across space and time in both lakes. While the activity of these alternative pathways needs to be experimentally confirmed, they may be individually or collectively more important than &lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt; genes in the natural environment. Importantly, the lack of &lt;em&gt;mlr&lt;/em&gt; expression could indicate microcystin biodegradation was not occurring in the analyzed samples. This study raises interesting questions about the ubiquity, specificity and locality of microcystin biodegradation, and highlights the need for the characterization of relevant mechanisms in natural communities to understand the fate of microcystin in the environment and risk to public health.   &lt;a id=&quot;x-x-h2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/110</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1113&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>110</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1113</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-05-26T10:48:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>17865682</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/110</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.02741</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Frontiers in Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>