<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modelling Suture Ossification: A View from the Cranial Capsule</title>
<publication-date>1992-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Matternes</lname>
<fname>Hugh</fname>
<mname>Bryson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A review of the development, anatomy, and physiology of the human cranial vault suggests that post-adolescent ossification of the suture margins is dictated by interactions between tissues of the cranial capsule and forces deriving from ectocranial, endocranial and diploid sources. A model viewing suture physiology as sensitive to changes in the cranial capsule&#39;s environment is tested to identify whether several processes stimulate connective tissue transformation in the suture area.  Correlation and factor analysis of the suture-to-suture interactions produced results indicating that when age is controlled, endocranial and ectocranial surfaces independently respond to pressures placed on the anterior and posterior portions of the cranial vault. Post-adolescent suture changes appear to be responses to age change in the structures around the cranial capsule. Modeling the suture in terms of external pressures provides a clearer understanding of how the cranial capsule is affected by age.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4192</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5655&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4192</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5655</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-11-02T11:54:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9336702</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4192</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard L. Jantz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lyle W. Konigsberg, William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1992-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>