<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Managing Black-throated Bobwhite for Sustainability in Belize: Preliminary Results of a Population Study</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:44:24-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Center for the Study of Tropical Birds, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Eitniear</lname>
<fname>Jack</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Center for the Study of Tropical Birds, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Cal</lname>
<fname>Reynold</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Center for the Study of Tropical Birds, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Martinez</lname>
<fname>Wilbur</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Florida</institution>
<lname>Fiqueroa</lname>
<fname>Omar</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas State University</institution>
<lname>Baccus</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>black-throated bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>Belize</keyword>
<keyword>Colinus nigrogularis</keyword>
<keyword>population estimate</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Black-throated Bobwhite (Colinus nigrogularis), a close relative of the Northern Bobwhite (C. virginianus), has a distinctive black throat and eye-stripes with both bounded by white. Black-throated Bobwhites occur in three distinct geographically isolated populations. Currently no limits or seasons are in place and a hunting license is the only requirement for harvesting this species in Belize. Little is known about Black-throated Bobwhite populations in Belize and data on the impact of hunting on this species is lacking. Because of its restricted distribution, it was recommended that Black-throated Bobwhites should be removed from the list of legally hunted species pending a better understanding of its population dynamics. In 2006 we initiated a long-term study of Black-throated Bobwhite biology at the 469 km2 Manatee Forest Reserve (henceforth MFR). Data collected at the end of the wet season indicated a population of 0.072-0.144 quail per hectare, which was appreciably lower than the density reported in the heneguen growing region of Yucatan, Mexico. Such densities predictably decreased throughout the dry season (breeding season).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol6/iss1/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1267&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>conservation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1267</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472013</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol6/iss1/12</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>