<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Functional Analysis of Corazonin and Its Receptor in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ksha@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Sha</lname>
<fname>Kai</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>neuropeptide</keyword>
<keyword>Corazonin</keyword>
<keyword>Corazonin receptor</keyword>
<keyword>GPCR</keyword>
<keyword>Alcohol metabolism</keyword>
<keyword>evolution</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavioral Neurobiology</discipline>
<discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Enzymes and Coenzymes</discipline>
<discipline>Genetics</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Corazonin (Crz) is an amidated undecapeptide originally isolated from the American cockroach. It has been shown to affect diverse physiological functions in a species-specific manner. However, the functionality of &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;melanogaste&lt;/em&gt;r has not yet been determined. To gain insight into the role of Crz signaling in vivo, &lt;em&gt;Crz &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; null alleles were obtained by transposable element mobilization. Flies carrying a deficiency uncovering &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pr-set7&lt;/em&gt; loci were generated via &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;-element excision, and the latter was rescued by &lt;em&gt;wild-type&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;pr-set7&lt;/em&gt; transgene. A mutation of &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; receptor (&lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt;) was generated by &lt;em&gt;Minos-&lt;/em&gt;element&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;mobilization from &lt;em&gt;GRHRII&lt;sup&gt;MB00583&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;em&gt;GRHRIIMB00583&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;allele. The mutant flies showed normal circadian rhythm and fecundity as compared with the &lt;em&gt;wild-types&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these mutants, the functions of the Crz signaling system in alcohol metabolism were investigated. Two major enzymes involved in alcohol metabolism are alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH). In this study, &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; expressing neurons and &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; were identified as important regulators of these enzymes. Flies lacking &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; neurons or &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; display significantly delayed recovery from ethanol-induced sedation, which is causally associated with fast accumulation of acetaldehyde in the &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;sup&gt;01&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;em&gt;CrzR01&lt;/em&gt;] mutant following ethanol exposure. Consistent with this, &lt;em&gt;Crz&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; were found to be required for normal ALDH activity. In addition, &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; shows a down-regulatory effect on ADH activity, which is transcriptionally initiated through the protein kinase A (PKA)-dependent pathway. Such transcriptional regulation was found to be exclusive to ADH, but not ALDH mRNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To gain the evolutionary aspect of &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CrzR&lt;/em&gt; from the Housefly, &lt;em&gt;Musca&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;domestica&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;MdCrzR&lt;/em&gt;) was cloned and characterized. MdCrzR deduced from the full-length cDNA sequence is a 655-amino acid polypeptide that contains seven &lt;em&gt;trans&lt;/em&gt;-membrane (TM) domains and other motifs that are characteristics of Class-A G-protein coupled receptors. Although the TMs and loops between the TMs are conserved in other CrzRs, &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-terminal extracellular domain is quite dissimilar. Tissue-specific RT-PCR revealed a high level of &lt;em&gt;MdCrzR &lt;/em&gt;expression in the larval salivary glands and a moderate level in the CNS. In adults, the expression was broadly observed without significant gender difference, suggesting multifunctionality of the Crz signaling system.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2480</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3094&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2480</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3094</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-21T10:11:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4250125</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2480</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jae H. Park</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bruce D. McKee, Chunlei Su, Jim Hall, Ranjan Ganguly</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry and Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>