<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Isolation of INS-1-derived Cell Lines with Robust ATP-sensitive K+ Channel-dependent and -independent Glucose-stimulated Insulin Secretion</title>
<publication-date>2000-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Hohmeier</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Mulder</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Henkel-Rieger</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Prentki</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>BetaGene, Inc.</institution>
<lname>Newgard</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The biochemical mechanisms involved in regulation of insulin secretion are not completely understood. The rat INS-1 cell line has been used to gain insight in this area because it secretes insulin in response to glucose concentrations in the physiological range. However, the magnitude of the response is far less than that seen in freshly isolated rat islets. In the current study, we have stably transfected INS-1 cells with a plasmid containing the human proinsulin gene. After antibiotic selection and clonal expansion, 67% of the resultant clones were found to be poorly responsive to glucose in terms of insulin secretion (&lt; or =2-fold stimulation by 15 mmol/l compared with 3 mmol/l glucose), 17% of the clones were moderately responsive (2- to 5-fold stimulation), and 16% were strongly responsive (5- to 13-fold stimulation). The differences in responsiveness could not be ascribed to differences in insulin content. Detailed analysis of one of the strongly responsive lines (832/13) revealed that its potent response to glucose (average of 10-fold) was stable over 66 population doublings (approximately 7.5 months of tissue culture) with half-maximal stimulation at 6 mmol/l glucose. Furthermore, in the presence of 15 mmol/l glucose, insulin secretion was potentiated significantly by 100 pmol/l isobutylmethylxanthine (320%), 1 mmol/l oleate/palmitate (77%), and 50 nmol/l glucagon-like peptide 1 (60%), whereas carbachol had no effect. Glucose-stimulated insulin secretion was also potentiated by the sulfonylurea tolbutamide (threefold at 3 mmol/l glucose and 50% at 15 mmol/l glucose) and was abolished by diazoxide, which demonstrates the operation of the ATP-sensitive K+ channel (K(ATP)) in 832/13 cells. Moreover, when the K(ATP) channel was bypassed by incubation of cells in depolarizing K+ (35 mmol/l), insulin secretion was more effectively stimulated by glucose in 832/13 cells than in parental INS-1 cells, which demonstrates the presence of a K(ATP) channel-independent pathway of glucose sensing. We conclude that clonal selection of INS-1 cells allows isolation of cell lines that exhibit markedly enhanced and stable responsiveness to glucose and several of its known potentiators. These lines may be attractive new vehicles for studies of beta-cell function.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/7</coverpage-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-08T06:45:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1386167</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>* H E Hohmeier,
    * H Mulder,
    * G Chen,
    * R Henkel-Rieger,
    * M Prentki,
    * and C B Newgard

Isolation of INS-1-derived cell lines with robust ATP-sensitive K+ channel-dependent and -independent glucose-stimulated insulin secretion. Diabetes March 2000 49:424-430; doi:10.2337/diabetes.49.3.424</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-07-08T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/content/49/3/424.abstract</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>