<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Passive Protection of Structures using Innovative Rotational Inertia Dampers and Rotational Energy Conversion Devices</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ajavidia@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Javidialesaadi</lname>
<fname>Abdollah</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Civil structures, including bridges, buildings, roads, railways, and utility networks, are vital parts of modern life; therefore, it is essential to protect these structures and systems against natural and artificial hazards. Some hazards, such as earthquake or extreme winds, can put structures in danger of damage or destruction. In some cases, even moderate amplitude vibrations decrease the serviceability of structures. Considerable research has been conducted for the purpose of reducing the effects of dynamic loads on structures due to external natural and artificial excitation. Accordingly, many different structural control technologies have been developed and utilized in civil structures in recent decades. Active, semi–active, and passive control strategies have been proposed, developed, and utilized for the purpose of protecting structures against various types of excitations and ensuring occupant safety and structural serviceability. Unlike semi-active and active control devices, passive control devices can adjust the dynamic properties of a structure and improve its energy dissipation potential without relying on a controller, sensor, and power. Because of these advantages, passive control systems are, in general, more accepted by the construction industry and have been increasingly utilized by practicing structural engineers. Significant research efforts have been made in the past and are currently ongoing to develop and improve these passive control systems including systems exploiting rotational inertial devices.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5860</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7626&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5860</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7626</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-10T23:12:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20527768</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5860</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Nicholas Edward Wierschem</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark Denavit, Brian Phillips, Eric Wade</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/Abdollah Javidialesaadi</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2021-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>