<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identifying the Spatial Distribution of Three Plethodontid Salamanders in Great Smoky Mountains National Park Using Two Habitat Modeling Methods</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mkookoge@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Kookogey</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Stephen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>salamander</keyword>
<keyword>Great Smoky Mountains</keyword>
<keyword>habitat model</keyword>
<keyword>Mahalanobis distance</keyword>
<keyword>logistic regression</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Multivariate Analysis</discipline>
<discipline>Other Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Statistical Models</discipline>
<discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main objective was to create habitat models of three plethodontid salamander species (&lt;em&gt;Desmognathus conanti&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;D. ocoee&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Plethodon jordani&lt;/em&gt;) in GSMNP. To investigate the relationships between salamanders and their habitats, I used three models—logistic regression with use-availability sampling, logistic regression with case-control sampling, and Mahalanobis distance (&lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;)—for each species to gain a robust view of the relationships. The secondary objective was to compare the different modeling methods within and across the three species. Elevation was the dominant variable for all three species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;for &lt;em&gt;D. conanti&lt;/em&gt; predicted low elevations, close proximity to streams, metasandstones, and previously disturbed areas. The use-availability model indicated habitat in low elevation, settled areas, pine understory, and flood overstory. The case-control model for&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;included only elevation and undisturbed areas. Case-control and &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;predicted presences &gt;90% correctly but absences &lt;50% correctly. Use-availability was more balanced with 75% presences and 60.5% absences correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;D. ocoee&lt;/em&gt; occurred only at the highest elevations. &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was influenced by proximity to streams, undisturbed areas, northern hardwood overstory, and frigid sandstones. Use-availability included a positive association with increasing elevation and a negative association with spruce understory. Case-control included elevation only. Use-availability did poorly at predicting presence (48.7%). Case-control predicted presences and absences at 79.5% and 89.0%, respectively. &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/em&gt;classified presences and absences at 92.3% and 78.1%, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P. jordani&lt;/em&gt; was also determined by elevation, but lower  than &lt;em&gt;D. ocoee&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;also included proximity to streams, undisturbed areas, and sandstones. Use-availability had a negative association with spruce understory. Pine understory, northern hardwood overstory, and distance to streams were negatively associated with &lt;em&gt;P. jordani&lt;/em&gt; occurrence in case-control. &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; predicted 97.1% of presences and 66.0% of absences correctly. Use-availability predicted 64.1% of presences and 91.8% of absences correctly. Case-control predicted 74.8% of presences and 89.1% of absences correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use-availability worked best for &lt;em&gt;D. conanti&lt;/em&gt;, but may have been a result of the uncertain identification of the species. For the other two species, case-control had a high classification rate for both presences and absences and a more intuitive answer for what determines habitat than &lt;em&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1176</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2305&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1176</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2305</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-19T17:36:21-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2305/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2680957</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1176</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Liem Tran</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Henri D. Grissino-Mayer, Frank T. van Manen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>