<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cloning of ribosomal ITS PCR products creates frequent, non-random chimeric sequences – a test involving heterozygotes between Gymnopus dichrous taxa I and II.</title>
<publication-date>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>khughes@utk.edu</email>
<institution>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hughes</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Morris</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Université Pierre et Marie Curie - UPMC Paris, France</institution>
<lname>Reboredo-Segovia</lname>
<fname>Ana</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>basidiomycete fungi</keyword>
<keyword>chimera</keyword>
<keyword>hybrid</keyword>
<keyword>monokaryons</keyword>
<keyword>recombination</keyword>
<keyword>ribosomal repeat</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Genetics and Genomics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gymnopus dichrous&lt;/em&gt; exists in the southern Appalachians as two distinct entities with essentially identical nuclear ribosomal ITS1 sequences but differing ITS2 and LSU sequences (for convenience, called &lt;em&gt;G. dichrous&lt;/em&gt; I and II). F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; ITS heterozygotes between the two are routinely collected from nature. Cloning of ITS PCR products from F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; heterozygotes produced sequences of both parental haplotypes but also numerous chimeric sequences (21.9%). The location of template switching was non-random leading to recovery of the same chimera several times and the chimeric region varied from 45bp to 300bp. By comparison, single-basidiospore isolates from heterozygote F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; fruitbodies showed no recombinant haplotypes within the ITS + LSU span and clones derived from P&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; homozygotes were identical to the P&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; parent. Thus, chimeric sequences are likely an artifact of the PCR-cloning process and not a consequence of natural recombination events found in nature, nor are they due to hidden existing variation within the ribosomal repeat. Chimeras and PCR-induced mutations are common in cloned PCR products and may result in incorrect sequence information in public databases&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/61</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1060&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>61</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1060</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-06-19T06:50:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>7237603</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/61</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Hughes KW, Reboredo-Segovia A, Morris SD (2015) Cloning of ribosomal ITS PCR products creates frequent, non-random chimeric sequences – a test involving a heterozygotes between Gymnopus dichrous taxa I and II. Mycokeys doi: 10.3897/mycokeys.10.5136.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>doi: 10.3897/mycokeys.10.5136</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-11-04T14:34:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>