<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Clawback Provisions: How Sharp Are the Claws? An Analysis of the Deterrence Effectiveness of Voluntary Clawback Provisions</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>abeck6@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Beck</lname>
<fname>Allison Kristina</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>clawback</keyword>
<keyword>corporate governance</keyword>
<keyword>executive compensation</keyword>
<keyword>earnings management</keyword>
<keyword>fraud</keyword>
<keyword>restatement</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Accounting</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the effectiveness of voluntary clawback provisions as a deterrent for earnings management behavior. The Dodd-Frank (DF) Bill signed into law July 21, 2010 mandates that the SEC adopt a rule requiring all U.S.-listed companies to implement clawback provisions that recapture excess compensation received by executives on the basis of a faulty financial statement filing with the SEC that later must be restated. Implicitly, the DF regulation assumes that clawbacks will successfully constrain financial misreporting and that a “one-size-fits-all” approach is best. In contrast with prior research that has investigated factors associated with a firm’s decision to adopt a clawback provision and/or various capital market consequences associated with clawback adoptions, I develop a stringency metric for analyzing clawback structures. I analyze the financial reporting consequences associated with clawback structure and mediating effects of antecedent corporate governance quality. Preliminary results indicate that, for both weak-governance and strong-governance firms adopting clawback provisions, increased clawback stringency is generally associated with lower levels of earnings management. However, the deterrent effect of clawback stringency is often attenuated for the strong-governance firms. None of the identified adopting firms had duality of the CEO and Chairman positions, thus, confirming that clawback adoptions may be conceptualized as a component of strong governance. This observation, coupled with the documented success of the clawbacks in deterring earnings management, provides support for the need for regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1267</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2514&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1267</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2514</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-28T12:15:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2707532</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1267</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bruce K. Behn</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Terry L. Neal, Joan M. Heminway, Russell Zaretzki</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>