<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Constructing Identity: Exploring Varying Degrees of Public and Private Space</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cutler</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>Jeffrey</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;While there are many ways that the individual, group, and public constructs its identity, this thesis focuses on the types of spaces that individuals, groups and the public inhabit and the specific ways that each inhabits space. It is possible to associate the individual’s construction of identity with private space and the public’s with public space. However, both public and private space and the layers between the two are important as the individual, the group, and the public construct their identity. Furthermore, the display of identity does not depend on public space, but rather can occur at various layers of shared space or even private space. This thesis asserts that it is possible to inhabit public space in a private way and also to be public within one’s own private space. Therefore, this thesis focuses on providing moments of private space, shared space, and public space but creates key moments between the two extremes of public and private.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it is necessary that each entity have a variety of spaces in which to construct and display its own identity. There is a constant shift back and forth as the individual, group, or public firsts constructs and then displays its identity. The variation of public and private spaces corresponds to the need for moments of enclosure and exposure. The individual seeks refuge at times, and this thesis gives the individual controlled access to exposure and interaction with the group or the public. However, the individual also has a desire to share with others in public space. But frequently, individuals and groups carve out their own private space within a larger public space, one example of the varying degrees of public and private space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a focus on the construction of identity, this construction is always linked to the display of identity for the individual, the group or the public. The display of specific identities is how people learn about each other. Ultimately, this thesis proposes a vision for the role of spatial inhabitation in creating a more integrated community of people who may not typically cohabitate space.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3648</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5009&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3648</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5009</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-10T11:32:39-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8125576</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3648</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Tricia Stuth</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Fox, Scott Wall</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>