<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB901-Growing Vegetables in Home Gardens</title>
<publication-date>2005-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Gardening</keyword>
<keyword>Vegetable</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Gardening can be highly rewarding, but it is not without problems and efforts. A successful garden requires a good site, careful planning, good management and considerable hard work. Insects, diseases and weeds require control measures. Acidic, infertile, poorly drained or sandy soil may have to be improved. Shade and extremes of moisture and temperature are other problems that must be overcome for a garden to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those willing to plan carefully and to perform timely gardening tasks, gardening can be very worthwhile. A vegetable garden can produce a steady supply of vegetables from spring to fall. These vegetables can be harvested at optimum maturity and eaten or preserved while fresh. Fresh vegetables may be higher in fl avor and nutritive value and lower in cost than purchased vegetables, which may have been harvested several days earlier. Vegetable production provides healthful exercise and an interesting outdoor activity for the entire family. Many gardeners feel the sense of accomplishment, self-suffi ciency and security accompanying a successful garden are other signifi cant rewards of gardening.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexgard/36</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1035&amp;amp;context=utk_agexgard&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>36</label>
<document-type>vegselect</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1035</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-15T07:20:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Home Garden, Lawn, and Landscape</publication-title>
<context-key>1275913</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexgard/36</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB901(Rev)-5M-4/05 E12-5115-00-015-05 05-0334</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>