<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Survey and Distributional Analysis of the park Coccoid Fauna of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park and Evirons</title>
<publication-date>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Watson</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Keith</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive study on the coccoids (Homoptera: Coccoidea) of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park (GSMNP) resulted in the collection of fifty-three species representing six families from which seven new collection records for Tennessee were obtained. Six species were discovered that possibly represent new species. Analysis of distribution and host relationships are provided. Keys to the families, genera, and species are provided as well as descriptions of scale covers or tests and distinguishing morphological characters of the adult females.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A higher number of species were collected at lower elevational vegetative types and decreased inversely with elevation (y = 17.104 - 8.6125e - 3x; R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.679) as did the number of infestations sampled ( y = 38.301 - 1.1970e - 2x; R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.577). One exception to this relationship was the occurrence of a slightly higher number of species recorded and number of infestations sampled on the grassy balds at higher elevations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coccoid distributions were positively correlated to host diversity. The hemlock-hardwood (HH) and the oakchestnut (OC) cover types supported more species than any other forest cover type. Many species were polyphagous and cosmopolitan, and other species had restricted hosts and a limited distribution. More species were collected in previously cutover and cultivated areas than any other type of vegetative habitat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifty-six plants in 27 families and 40 genera were recorded as coccoid hosts in the GSMNP. More species of Pinaceae and Rosaceae were recorded as hosts for coccoids and trees in the family Betulaceae supported more species than any other host family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on Shannon-Weaver diversity index values, thirty-three species were considered to be rare and only two species, &lt;em&gt;Parthenolecanium corni&lt;/em&gt; (Bouche) (European fruit lecanium) and &lt;em&gt;Abgrallaspis ithacae&lt;/em&gt; (Ferris) (hemlock scale), were considered to be abundant. &lt;em&gt;P. corni&lt;/em&gt; was collected from 25 hosts from a wide elevational range represented the greatest potential to damage host in the GSMNP.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3288</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4719&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3288</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4719</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-03-30T12:07:59-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6919428</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3288</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paris L. Lambdin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>M. L. Pan, J. F. Gant, C. D. Pless</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>