<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Faculty wisdom as teaching culture care within the indigenous context of the Southeastern United States</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>smixer@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mixer</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Presentations</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Culture Care theory</keyword>
<keyword>ethnonursing research method</keyword>
<keyword>nursing education</keyword>
<keyword>cultural competence</keyword>
<keyword>culturally congruent care</keyword>
<keyword>teaching culture care</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This poster presents an ethnonursing research study guided by the culture care theory entitled Nursing Faculty Care, Expressions, Patterns, and Practices Related to Teaching Culture Care and conducted within the environmental context of urban and rural baccalaureate nursing programs in the Southeastern United States.  The goal of the study was to discover faculty care that facilitated teaching students to provide culturally congruent and competent care.  Four universal themes with universal and diverse patterns which supported the themes were discovered.  The themes were faculty care as embedded in Christian religious values, beliefs, and practices; faculty teaching culture care without an organizing conceptual framework; faculty providing generic and professional care to nursing students; and care as essential for faculty health and well being to teach culture care.  Discoveries for nursing actions and decisions for teaching culture care and two newly discovered care constructs, care as mentoring and Christian care are presented.  This study, a unique application of the culture care theory, contributed to understanding the complex nature of teaching culture care and to the body of transcultural nursing education knowledge and the discipline of nursing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-12T13:16:15-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1145715</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>34th Annual Conference of the International Transcultural Nursing Society</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>