<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Multi-metric Conservation Assessment for the Imperiled Clinch Dace</title>
<publication-date>2018-11-28T14:20:27-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mjmhx5@mail.missouri.edu</email>
<institution>University of Missouri</institution>
<lname>Moore</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>James</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>Dorth@vt.edu</email>
<institution>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</institution>
<lname>Orth</lname>
<fname>Donald</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>ehallerm@vt.edu</email>
<institution>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</institution>
<lname>Hallerman</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Conservation planning</keyword>
<keyword>species conservation</keyword>
<keyword>imperiled species</keyword>
<keyword>aquatic habitat management</keyword>
<keyword>stakeholder assessment</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Aquaculture and Fisheries</discipline>
<discipline>Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Planning frameworks allow managers to spatially prioritize actions to promote species conservation. Traditional aquatic conservation planning frameworks are often organized at the ecological community or ecosystem level, which often neglect imperiled taxa occupying species-poor assemblages. In this study, we develop a multi-metric conservation assessment for the 15 geographically distinct candidate conservation areas (CCAs) occupied by the imperiled Clinch Dace (&lt;em&gt;Chrosomus&lt;/em&gt; sp. cf. &lt;em&gt;saylori&lt;/em&gt;). Clinch Dace habitat is threatened by anthropogenic landscape alterations, especially for coal mining and timber harvest. Our framework used four metrics to assess the conservation value of each subpopulation of Clinch Dace namely: “&lt;em&gt;habitat&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;condition&lt;/em&gt;”, “&lt;em&gt;viability&lt;/em&gt;”, conservation “&lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt;” and conservation “&lt;em&gt;feasibility&lt;/em&gt;”. Occupancy models were used to determine the most influential habitat variables to Clinch Dace presence and habitat data collected for each occupied stream were used to score habitat condition in each CCA. Clinch Dace survey data were used to assess demographic population viability to highlight areas where Clinch Dace are most likely to persist. Next, we used the metrics of opportunity and feasibility to identify opportunities for reclamation as well as landownership patterns that may be bridges or barriers to conservation action. Habitat condition and viability varied among our 15 CCAs and highlighted opportunities for specific management actions including habitat conservation in some watersheds and needs for restoration in others. The feasibility metric showed that variation exists in the average lot-parcel size along occupied stream reaches, which may affect the success of some conservation actions. We recommend that managers utilize the data summarized in this study, along with stakeholder input, in a structured-decision making approach to develop specific outreach and management plans targeted to stakeholders in individual watersheds and provide an example of such a framework.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1285&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1285</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-11T19:23:34-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1285/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10280328</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS: This research was funded through a U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service State Wildlife Grant managed through the Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries. All work was in accordance with collection permits issued by Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries and protocol 13-184 FIW, approved by the Virginia Tech Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. We particularly thank Hunter Hatcher, Skylar Wolf, and Derek Wheaton for field assistance; and Michael Pinder for advice and direction. We also thank two anonymous reviewers and the editorial staff of this journal for their helpful suggestions in improving this manuscript. We also thank S. White, C. Skelton, T. Coyner, and Z. Martin, whose work helped compile the dataset of Clinch Dace records. Support for the participation DJO and EMH in this work was provided in part by the Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station and the National Institute of Food and Agriculture, U.S. Department of Agriculture.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0x118711e0)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Conservation Assessment for Clinch Dace</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>SupplementaryTables12.xlsx</archive-name>
<upload-name>SupplementaryTables12.xlsx</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1285&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet</mime-type>
<description>Supplementary tables which include raw data and scoring criteria for viability and condition</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>