<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Contact Metamorphism of Calc-Silicate Rocks in the Belmont Contact Aureole, Central Nevada</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Plummer</lname>
<fname>Kelly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study focuses on the contact metamorphism of the Ordovician Zanzibar and Toquima Formations by the Cretaceous Belmont Pluton in central Nevada.    I mapped the distributions of tremolite and diopside to determine the location of isograds.  These isograds are the result of the reactions:  8 quartz + 5 dolomite + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O = 3 calcite + tremolite + 7 CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and tremolite + 2 quartz + 3 calcite = 5 diopside + 3 CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O.  Pressure of metamorphism is estimated at between 4 kbar and 1 kbar, but is not definite because of uncertainty in the amount of overburden at the time of metamorphism.  Temperatures of metamorphism ranged from 400 to 560 °C for the tremolite isograd and 450 to 565 °C for the diopside isograd.  Fluid compositions ranged from X(CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) = 0.25 to 0.98.    Mass balance calculations show that change in volume decreased with increasing distance from the contact (98.9 cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/kg to 5.2 cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/kg) which corresponds to loss in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.  &lt;sub&gt; &lt;/sub&gt;Toquima carbon and oxygen isotope values increase with increasing distance from the pluton which is indicative of contact metamorphism. The δ&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O (SMOW) values for both calcite and dolomite in Zanzibar samples show no pattern of decrease with increasing metamorphic grade.  Calcite values close to the pluton range from 15.7‰ to 21.2‰ and lower grade samples range from 15.0‰ to 18.6‰.  The δ&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (PDB) values are lower    (-8.9‰ to -5.2‰) in higher grade samples.  Low grade samples range from -6.6‰ to -0.8‰.    Carbon isotopic values in Zanzibar samples do not increase with increasing distance from the pluton, but these values are systematic with the extent of reaction. There is no relationship between Zanzibar δ&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;O values and change in volume or change in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.  This shows there is no correlation between Zanzibar oxygen isotopic values and metamorphic reactions resulting from the emplacement of the pluton.  The best explanation for the altered oxygen isotopic values is Tertiary volcanic activity.  This activity is thought to be responsible for the formation of gold and silver ore deposits in the area of Belmont Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1765</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3116&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1765</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3116</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-27T11:39:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4512601</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1765</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Theodore Labotka</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Claudia Mora, Kula Misra</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>