<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cell adhesion property affected by cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase: Opto-electric approach.</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-22T10:52:07-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>The University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Baek</lname>
<fname>Seung</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>cyclooxygenase</keyword>
<keyword>DICM</keyword>
<keyword>IRCM</keyword>
<keyword>Lipoxygenase</keyword>
<keyword>impedance</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Expression of cyclooxygenases (COX) and lipoxygenases (LOX) has been linked to many pathophysiological phenotypes, including cell adhesion. However, many current approaches to measure cellular changes are performed only in a fixed-time point. Since cells dynamically move in conjunction with the cell matrix, there is a pressing need for dynamic or time-dependent methods for the investigation of cell properties. In the presented study, we used stable human colorectal cancer cell lines ectopically expressing COX-1, COX-2, and 15LOX-1, to investigate whether expression of COX-1, COX-2, or 15LOX-1 would affect cell adhesion using our opto-electric methodology. In a fixed-time point experiment, only COX-1- and COX-2-expressing cells enhanced phosphorylation of focal adhesion kinase, but all the transfected cells showed invasion activity. However, in a real-time experiment using opto-electric approaches, transmitted cellular morphology was much different with tight adhesion being shown in COX-2 expressing cells, as imaged by differential interference contrast microscopy (DICM) and interference reflection contrast microscopy (IRCM). Furthermore, micro-impedance measurements showed a continued increase in both resistance and reactance of COX- and LOX-transfected cells, consistent with the imaging data. Our data indicate that both COX- and LOX-expressing cells have strong cell-to-cell and cell-to-substrate adhesions, and that cell imaging analysis with cell impedance data generates fully reliable results on cell adhesion measurement. Copyright 2009 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/10</coverpage-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1009</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284733</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Seung J. Baek. &quot;Cell adhesion property affected by cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase: Opto-electric approach.&quot; Biochem Biophys Res Commun 391.3 (2010): 1385.</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6WBK-4Y0D64J-4&amp;_user=422010&amp;_coverDate=01%2F15%2F2010&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000019958&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=422010&amp;md5=92a6bea0e6a9784f2abf8d0b6b7e05f7</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communication</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>