<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Isolation of a non-phage-like lytic virus infecting &lt;em&gt;Aureococcus anophagefferens&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Rowe</lname>
<fname>J.M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Dunlap</lname>
<fname>J.R.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Gobler</lname>
<fname>C.J.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Anderson</lname>
<fname>O.R.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Gastrich</lname>
<fname>M.D.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilhelm</lname>
<fname>S.W.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>aureococcus anophagefferens</keyword>
<keyword>phycodnaviridae</keyword>
<keyword>phytoplankton mortality</keyword>
<keyword>SEM</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We have been working to characterize viruses that infect the HAB-forming pelagophyte &lt;em&gt;Aureococcus anophagefferens&lt;/em&gt;  Hargraves et Sieburth. Field samples were collected during brown-tide events in 2002 and tested for the presence of lytic agents. Here, we describe a recently isolated, lytic virus-like particle (VLP) that is morphologically similar to particles observed in thin sections of infected &lt;em&gt;A. anophagefferens&lt;/em&gt; cells from natural samples. TEM and SEM have revealed VLPs consistent with the morphological characteristics of previously described Phycodnaviridae. Large icosahedral particles (∼140 nm) of similar shape and morphology dominate cell lysates and are accompanied by smaller phage-like particles and heterotrophic prokaryotes that appear to be incurable from our cultures. To determine which of these particles interacts with the &lt;em&gt;Aureococcus&lt;/em&gt;  cells, we preserved cultures during the early stage of infection so that SEM could be used to visualize those particles that attach to the surface of naïve cultures. SEM revealed that 63% of the large icosahedral-shaped particles attached to &lt;em&gt;A. anophagefferens&lt;/em&gt; cells after only 30 min of exposure, while no significant frequency of attachment to the alga was observed for the phage-like particles. The results of these observations are in contrast to previous studies, where phage-like particles were reported to infect cells. When considered in conjunction with field observations, the results suggest that this newly isolated virus represents the dominant virus-morphotype associated with bloom collapse and termination.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/16</coverpage-url>
<label>16</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1017</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-29T11:47:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1586177</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/16</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-29T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1529-8817.2007.00453.x/abstract</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>