<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>To Boldly Go Beyond Downloads: How are Journal Articles Shared and Used?</title>
<publication-date>2014-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Hughes</lname>
<fname>Gabriel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Lisa</lname>
<fname>Christian</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Allard</lname>
<fname>Suzie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Nicholas</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>CIBER Research Ltd.</institution>
<lname>Watkinson</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Woodward</lname>
<fname>Hazel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Shepherd</lname>
<fname>Peter</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Anderson</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>electronic publishing</keyword>
<keyword>scholarly reading</keyword>
<keyword>academic journals</keyword>
<keyword>scholarly journals</keyword>
<keyword>digital publishing</keyword>
<keyword>electronic journals</keyword>
<keyword>e-journals</keyword>
<keyword>researchers</keyword>
<keyword>research</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
<discipline>Scholarly Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Scholarly Publishing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With more scholarly journals being distributed electronically rather than in print form, we know that researchers download many articles. What is less well known is how journal articles are used after they are initially downloaded. To what extent are they saved, uploaded, tweeted, or otherwise shared? How does this reuse increase their total use and value to research and how does it influence library usage figures? University of Tennessee Chancellor’s Professor Carol Tenopir, Professor Suzie Allard, and Adjunct Professor David Nicholas are leading a team of international researchers on a the project, “Beyond Downloads,” funded by a grant from Elsevier. The project will look at how and why scholarly electronic articles are downloaded, saved, and shared by researchers. Sharing in today’s digital environment may include links posted on social media, like Twitter, and in blogs or via e‐mail. Having a realistic estimate of this secondary use will help provide a more accurate picture of the total use of scholarly articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speakers will present the objectives of the study, share the approach and avenues of exploration, and report on some preliminary findings. Furthermore, the speakers will discuss how the potential learnings could yield benefits to the library community.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/332</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1431&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>332</label>
<document-type>conference</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1431</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-07T16:22:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16134117</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/332</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Tenopir, Carol; Hughes, Gabriel; Christian, Lisa; Allard, Suzie; Nicholas, David; Watkinson, Anthony; Woodward, Hazel; Shepherd, Peter; Anderson, Robert. (2014, November 5-8, 2014). To Boldly Go Beyond Downloads: How are Journal Articles Shared and Used? Paper presented at the Charleston Conference: Issues in Book and Serial Acquisitions, Charleston, South Carolina. http://docs.lib.purdue.edu/charleston/</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Charleston Conference: Issues in Book and Serial Acquisitions</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>