<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unique Roles for ISE2 in Chloroplast RNA Metabolism and Regulation of Plasmodesmata-mediated Intercellular Trafficking</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tmccray@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McCray</lname>
<fname>Tyra</fname>
<mname>Nadine</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>RNA Editing</keyword>
<keyword>RNA Helicase</keyword>
<keyword>Pentatricopeptide Repeat Protein</keyword>
<keyword>ISE2</keyword>
<keyword>Plasmodesmata</keyword>
<keyword>Nicotiana benthamiana</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;INCREASED SIZE EXCLUSION LIMIT 2 (ISE2)&lt;/em&gt; is a nuclear gene encoding a chloroplast-localized RNA helicase that is essential for &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; embryogenesis, chloroplast RNA metabolic events and the regulation of plasmodesmal permeability. Here I report that ISE2 is essential for the editing of several chloroplast transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Emb175/PPR103&lt;/em&gt; is a nuclear gene encoding a pentatricopeptide repeat (PPR) protein that was previously reported to be required for embryogenesis in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; and for seedling survival in &lt;em&gt;Zea mays&lt;/em&gt;. EMB175/PPR103 was previously identified in our lab in a yeast-two-hybrid interaction screen with ISE2 and subsequently named ISE2 PROTEIN INTERACTOR (IPI)1. Confocal fluorescence microscopy illustrates that IPI1-YFP, similar to ISE2-YFP, localizes to chloroplasts, consistent with its predicted chloroplast N-terminal targeting sequence. In &lt;em&gt;Nicotiana benthamiana&lt;/em&gt;, silencing of &lt;em&gt;emb175/PPR103/IPI1&lt;/em&gt; in mature leaf tissue produces a chlorotic phenotype coupled to defective chloroplast structural integrity. Interestingly, virus induced gene silencing (VIGS) of&lt;em&gt; N. benthamiana emb175/PPR103/IPI1&lt;/em&gt; or&lt;em&gt; N. benthamiana ISE2&lt;/em&gt; revealed defects in the RNA editing of N. benthamiana chloroplast transcripts. However, ISE2-silenced plants displayed increased plasmodesmata-mediated intercellular trafficking, whereas no intercellular trafficking defect was observed in &lt;em&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/em&gt; plants silenced for &lt;em&gt;emb175/PPR103/IPI1&lt;/em&gt;. These results indicate that ISE2 performs unique functions in the regulation of PD permeability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively, our results identify IPI1 as an ISE2 interacting protein that localizes to the chloroplast and that participates in the proper RNA editing of select &lt;em&gt;N. benthamiana&lt;/em&gt; chloroplast transcripts. These observations add to the rapidly growing knowledge base of RNA helicase and PPR protein function in plants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4415</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5562&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4415</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5562</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-05T18:14:16-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5562/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9237375</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4415</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Tessa Burch-Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Albrecht vonArnim, Elena Shpak, Brad Binder, Barry Bruce</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>