<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&lt;i&gt;In Vitro&lt;/i&gt; Alterations of a Putative Phospholipid Translocase, &lt;i&gt;Atp10c&lt;/i&gt;, and Its Role in Glucose Metabolism</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>shurst6@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hurst</lname>
<fname>Sarah Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>type 2 diabetes</keyword>
<keyword>glucose</keyword>
<keyword>metabolism</keyword>
<keyword>siRNA</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;/ATP10C is a putative aminophospholipid translocase or “flippase” that encodes for a type 4 P-type ATPase. Based on previous research, we hypothesize that &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;/ATP10C due to its flippase nature plays a role in diet-induced obesity and type 2 diabetes as &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; heterozygous mice display this phenotype. For purposes of this dissertation, &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;/ATP10C was characterized both generally and biologically to gleam information about its molecular weight, cellular location and possible biological roles and/or functions. Multiple experiments, both &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;, were performed in order to accomplish these characterizations and are discussed at length. Essential results from this dissertation work include the validation of ATP10C’s expected molecular weight (~165 kD), the localization of ATP10C to the plasma membrane, its possible co-localization with GLUT4, and the high expression of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; in key tissues (skeletal muscle and adipose tissue) of two mice models, one a model of diet-induced obesity mice and another a genetic model (&lt;em&gt;ob/ob&lt;/em&gt;). To identify molecular and cellular targets of ATP10C, &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; expression was altered &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; in C2C12 and L6-G4myc skeletal muscle myotubes. Functional outcomes of GLUT4 translocation and glucose uptake assays were performed resulting in the significant alteration of normal GLUT4 regulation and a significant decrease in glucose uptake. Additionally, when the expression of &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt; was altered both experimentally and genetically, significant up-regulation of native and activated mitogen-activated protein kinases, p38, and ERK1/2 were observed. These results demonstrate that &lt;em&gt;Atp10c-&lt;/em&gt;silencing does affect these main mitogen-activated protein kinase proteins and in turn, glucose metabolism via both insulin-independent and insulin-dependent manners. Taken together, all these results presented in this dissertation indicate that &lt;em&gt;Atp10c&lt;/em&gt;/ATP10C has an important role in the regulation of glucose metabolism, at least in part via the mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway, and as such, plays a significant role in the development of insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1308</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2479&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1308</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2479</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-13T12:33:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2663453</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1308</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Madhu Dhar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Biggerstaff, Guoxun Chen, Carla Sommardahl</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>