<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Measurement of physical activity and energy expenditure using heart rate, motion sensors and questionnaires</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Strath</lname>
<fname>Scott</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation was designed to examine new techniques to measure physical activity (PA) and energy expenditure (EE) during lifestyle activities. The specific aims were: 1) to evaluate heart rate (HR), using percent of HR reserve in relation to percent of oxygen uptake reserve, as a method for assessing moderate intensity PA in the field setting; 2) to validate the simultaneous heart rate-motion sensor (HR+M) technique to estimate EE of selected activities; 3) to validate the simultaneous HR +M technique to predict EE over an extended time period; and 4) to use the simultaneous HR+M technique to validate selected PA questionnaires over a 7-day period. For the first aim, sixty-one males performed physical tasks in both a laboratory and field setting. HR and oxygen uptake (V0 2) were continuously measured during 15- min tasks. HR data was used to predict EE using age-predicted maximum HR and estimated maximal V0 2. The correlation between HR and measured V0 2 was r=0.68. After adjusting for age and fitness level, HR provided an accurate estimate of EE, r=0.87. Using percent HR reserve to estimate percent V02 reserve significantly improved the estimation of EE.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6445</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8419&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6445</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8419</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075121</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6445</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>