<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The suitability of five evergreen tree species for urban use in eastern Tennessee / by Vivian Orr Potter.</title>
<publication-date>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Potter</lname>
<fname>Vivian</fname>
<mname>Orr</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to determine which of five tree species was best suited for urban conditions in eastern Tennessee with respect to certain criteria. The species included eastern white pine (Pinus strobus L.), eastern hemlock [Tsuga canadensis (L.) Carr.],. Norway spruce [Picea abies (L.) Karst.], southern magnolia (Magnolia grandiflora L.), and eastern redcedar (Juniperus virginiana L.). The criteria used for comparing the species were resistance to disease, resistance to insect pests, range of soil fertility adaptability, range of soil pH adaptability, and aesthetic appeal. Questionnaires were sent to nurserymen and landscape architects in Tennessee and adjacent states to determine the importance rating of each criteria on a scale of Oto 10. Questionnaires were sent to Tennessee nurserymen and landscape architects, ornamental horticulturists, plant pathologists, entomologists, and soil scientists, to determine the rating of each species on a scale of 1 to S, with respect to all criteria except aesthetic appeal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6054</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7693&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6054</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7693</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074433</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6054</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank W. Woods</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Forestry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>