<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Benefits of Integrating Math Content into the Elementary Art Curriculum</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sigmon</lname>
<fname>Valerie</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;School accountability has become critical under the No Child Left Behind Act. As struggling schools strive to reach mandated proficiency levels, is it possible for an art teacher to contribute toward students‟ success by integrating math content into art lessons? This study attempts to show that without schedule changes, additional funding, or added training, an art teacher can support the efforts of classroom teachers as evidenced by increased scores on standardized math tests. The research used a Non-Equivalent Groups Design and examined pre-test and post-test scores for two groups of students. The population for this study is 3,800 elementary school children who attend Project GRAD schools. The experimental group which received integrated instruction is a convenience sample. It is comprised of 360 students who attend the 3rd, 4th, and 5th grades at two of the Project GRAD schools. The control group is made up of 3,440 students who did not receive the experimental instruction. The test scores were analyzed using t-test for normal distribution of scores, and a confidence level of .05 was selected. The results of this research indicate positive results from integrating math content into the elementary art curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/446</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1482&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>446</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1482</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T10:06:00-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1150575</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/446</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>E. Stephanie Cramer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patricia Davis-Wiley, Ralph Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Teacher Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/SigmonVal.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>