<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Message Quantification: The Modearing Role of Numeracy</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T19:11:04-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>iju@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Ju</lname>
<fname>Ilwoo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Advertising and Promotion Management</discipline>
<discipline>Health Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although the numerical information effects has been reported in persuasive contexts, little research has investigated how numeric information in the drug efficacy appeals may affect consumers&#39; evaluation of DTC advertising. Based on an experiment, the current study revealed that: (a) consumers reported more positive perceived message effectiveness of and attitude toward advertising toward numeric DTC advertising; (b) when consumers were lowly numerate, the persuasive effects of numeric information was stronger. When consumers were highly numerate,  however, the persuasive effects of numeric information was significantly reduced; and (c) perceived message effectiveness was found to be a valid indicator of actual DTC advertising effectiveness, by mediating between the numeric information effects and attitude toward DTC advertising. Theoretical and practical/regulatory implications of DTC advertising were discussed.  &lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/poster/10</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1051&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1051</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-14T02:55:11-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1051/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2402801</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/poster/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>