<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The High School Principal as Instructional Leader:  An Explanatory, Mixed Methods Case Study Examining Principal Leadership  within the Context of Rural Secondary Schools</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bclabo1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Clabo</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Tyler</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>instructional leadership</keyword>
<keyword>principal leadership</keyword>
<keyword>rural secondary schools</keyword>
<keyword>mixed methods research</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this explanatory, mixed methods case study was to examine instructional leadership within the context of rural secondary schools.  This investigation followed an explanatory mixed methods design of sequential quantitative and qualitative phases (QUAL→quan).  For the quantitative phase, the Principal Instructional Management Rating Scale (PIMRS) was administered to eight principals and 312 teachers in eight rural secondary schools in the southeastern United States.  Descriptive analysis of principal and teacher results found that principals were most engaged in the subscales of framing school goals, coordinating curriculum, and promoting professional development and least engaged in the subscales of maintaining high visibility, protecting instructional time, and providing teaching and learning incentives.  Independent t-tests found statistically significant differences in the instructional leadership of principals based on four contextual factors: school size, school SES, principal administrative experience, and district funding (per pupil expenditure).  Two principals and their schools were selected for participation in the qualitative phase of the study.  Interviews and observations of principals and interviews with teachers added insight to the findings of the quantitative phase. Participants characterized the principalship as a multifaceted job where secondary school principals fulfilled four leadership roles: instructional leader, district/community liaison, organizational manager, and problem solver.  Participants also identified important instructional leadership behaviors not measured by the PIMRS, such as hiring effective teachers, providing instructional resources, and sharing leadership responsibilities.  The study concludes with suggestions for future instructional leadership research and practical advice for rural secondary school principals.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/872</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2002&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>872</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-04T07:36:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1630428</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/872</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vincent A. Anfara, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gerald C. Ubben, Pamela A. Angelle, Deborah A. Wooten</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>