<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study To Enhance The B-1B Targeting Pod Integration Developmental Processes</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lane</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>Aaron</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Recent United States combat operations required weapon systems to incorporate enhanced targeting capabilities to improve their effectiveness in weapons employment. The United States Air Force B-1B heavy bomber played a key role in releasing GPS guided munitions in Operation Enduring Freedom and Operation Iraqi Freedom without enhanced targeting capabilities. Future conflicts are expected to continue to address this requirement as the battlefield evolves. These operations highlighted the need for the B-1B to incorporate an advanced targeting pod (TGP) to provide positive identification of targets and allow for more precisely planned weapon releases without the aid of additional off-board resources. During 2004-2006 a concept demonstration electro-optical and infrared TGP program was developed and tested on the B-1B to address targeting limitations. The goal of the test program was to demonstrate a limited operational capability of the TGP using minimal testing resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept demonstration highlighted areas for improvement in the final TGP implementation design. The improved alternatives were submitted as future design candidates and test procedures for the TGP development effort. The purpose of this thesis was to examine the concept demonstration test plan and planned test process and recommend improved testing processes and design enhancements for the fully integrated pod design. The planned testing included modeling and simulation of aerodynamics and structures, laboratory system functional testing, hardware development testing, ground vibration testing (GVT), electromagnetic interference compatibility testing (EMIC), crew operability testing, and flight envelope testing. Many of these elements were not planned to be thoroughly tested due to the limited demonstration constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings of this study indicate that a further evaluation of handling qualities are required, and pod related weapon separation testing should be expanded to include more release configurations and conditions. The Man Machine Interface (MMI) for the TGP future cockpit upgrade requires improvement while EMIC tests and related crew training should be increased during the final TGP System Developmental Design (SDD). No further increases in testing efforts relative to flight test instrumentation, GVT, logistics support, or aerodynamics are required.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1723</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3073&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1723</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3073</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-20T09:01:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4468833</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1723</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard Ranaudo</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>U. Peter Solies, Basil Antar</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>