<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of the In-service Education Program in the Knoxville City Schools</title>
<publication-date>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Harville</lname>
<fname>Lacy</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: One of the most challenging problems confronting educators today is that of fostering continuous professional growth. School systems throughout the country are wanting to know more about new methods and techniques of improving their in-service education programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth and development of in-service education in the United States is complicated by the influence of various factors contributing to the gradual structuring of the total educational program, of which the promotion of professional growth on the part of teachers has been only a small part. The growth and development of in-service education is further complicated by the fact that its development has not been uniform within the states. In the course of its development, in-service programs have reflected the differences in the educational programs of the forty-eight states, differences that arose from freedom of each state to shape its own educational program and from the efforts that were made by all states to meet the needs of different groups throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2911</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4343&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2911</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4343</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-06T13:06:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6209986</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2911</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John W. Gilliland</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Orin B. Graff, Howard Aldmon, Lawrence O. Haaby, E. S. Christenbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>