<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Quality of Life for Cancer Survivor Spouses</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gustafson</lname>
<fname>Meta</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In spite of increased consideration for cancer patients and their quality of life (QOL}, very little attention has been given to their spouses. The intent of this study was to gain a greater understanding of what QOL means to spouses of cancer survivors. Within this framework, this study explored QOL domains and how QOL had changed since the cancer diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A qualitative method using the grounded theory approach was used for this study. Five spouses were interviewed face-to-face about their QOL. Interviews were taped and transcribed verbatim. Responses were then analyzed by three psychology professionals using constant comparative analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results confirmed the complexity of the QOL concept; a subjective experience, influenced by numerous factors. For these subjects, QOL revolves around how their spouse was feeling, both physically and emotionally. Five categories that impact QOL emerged: personal issues, marital relationship, social support, finances, and motivation. All spouses reported changes in QOL. Findings suggest that spouses continue to live as if the survivor was still ill and undergoing treatment even though treatments had ended at least one to two years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary implications of this study include: (1) QOL for cancer survivor spouses is intimately connected to their partners&#39; health; (2) QOL has changed since the cancer diagnosis; (3) more research is needed to better understand the spouses&#39; experience; (4) increased attention must be given to the financial impact of cancer and its treatment; (5) spouses find meaning through personal belief systems that help them reframe what has happened; and (6) personal and marital issues are the most important domains for spouses when considering QOL.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4305</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6041&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4305</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6041</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-05-01T10:14:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10099859</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4305</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marla Peterson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William A. Poppen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>