<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pedogenic Relationships in a Texas Vertisol Climosequence Defined by Geochemical Mass Balance of Whole Soil and Chemistry of Iron-Manganese Nodules</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stiles</lname>
<fname>Cynthia</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Climosequence Vertisol profiles derived from the Upper Beaumont Formation in the Gulf Coastal Prairie physiographic province of Texas were examined for geochemical trends ascribed to different precipitation regimes. Mass-balance relationships were utilized for the comparisons. Compositional differences in zirconium (Zr) content between the solum and lower sub-soil precluded it use an immobile strain (volumetric change) indicator. This difference was correlated to sand weight percent (r&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.65**). Titanium (Ti) content did not shift correlatively with depth, thus making Ti the preferred strain index element for mass-balance calculations. Depths at which the Zr compositions shifted were not directly related to mean annual precipitation (MAP) regime and are considered to be functional boundaries between open-system pedogenesis and more closed system hydrogeochemical weathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mass-balance relationships of ten elements examined within the climosequence showed trends ascribed to precipitation intensity. Mass-balance relationships varied not only between locations but also between microtopographic positions within each Vertisol pedon. Basic mass-balance trends with depth in the climosequence profiles fall into four broad categories depending on the relative mobility and geochemical reactivity of the individual elements: 1) framework, 2) clay interaction, 3) leachable/biocycle, and 4) climatic/redox-sensitive. Net mass flux percentages indicate a relative steady-state of around -16% (±3%) in climosequence Vertisol pedons with MAP &gt; 900 mm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total Fe (Fe&lt;sub&gt;TOT&lt;/sub&gt;) content of pedogenic iron-manganese (Fe-Mn) nodules from Vertisol profiles correlates with mean annual precipitation (MAP, r&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 0.92***). No significant trend of Fe&lt;sub&gt;TOT&lt;/sub&gt; with depth was noted in profiles. Using the regression developed from modem Vertisol data, Feror contents of Paleozoic paleo-Vertisol Fe-Mn nodules yielded MAP regimes comparable to previously inferred paleoenvironmental interpretations. Paleoprecipitation estimates derived from Fe-Mn nodules for an uneroded, Late Mississippian paleo-Vertisol are very close to estimates made from a depth to pedogenic carbonate horizon (DCH) proxy determined from the modem Vertisol climosequence. Because the Fe-Mn nodule proxy is independent of depth, consistent paleoprecipitation estimates can be made even in eroded paleo-Vertisols and, in combination with the DCH, may be useful in determining original paleosol thickness.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4596</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6322&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4596</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6322</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-11-30T13:22:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>11178678</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4596</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven G. Driese, Claudia I. Mora</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Larry D. McKay, Sally P. Horn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>