<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of the Telemetrical Intraoperative Soft Tissue Tension Monitoring System in Total Knee Replacement with MEMS and ASIC Technologies</title>
<publication-date>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>To</lname>
<fname>Gary</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biomedical Engineering and Bioengineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The alignment of the femoral and tibial components of the Total Knee Arthoplasty (TKA) is one of the most important factors to implant survivorship. Hence, numerous ligament balancing techniques and devices have been developed in order to accurately balance the knee intra-operatively. Spacer block, tensioner and tram adapter are instruments that allow surgeons to qualitatively balance the flexion and extension gaps during TKA. However, even with these instruments, the surgical procedure still relies on the skill and experience of the surgeon. The objective of this thesis is to develop a computerized surgical instrument that can acquire intra-operative data telemetrically for surgeons and engineers. Microcantilever is chosen to be used as the strain sensing elements. Even though many high end off-the-shelf data acquisition components and integrated circuit (IC) chips exist on the market, yet multiple components are required to process the entire array of microcantilevers and achieve the desired functions. Due to the size limitation of the off-chip components, an Application Specific Integrated Circuit (ASIC) chip is designed and fabricated. Using a spacer block as a base, sensors, a data acquisition system as well as the transmitter and antenna are embedded into it. The electronics are sealed with medical grade epoxy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/231</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1263&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>231</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1263</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-10T10:34:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1139174</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/231</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mohamed R. Mahfouz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard D. Komistek, William Hamel</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biomedical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/ToGary.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>