<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Repeatable, Visual Survey of Three Rare &lt;em&gt;Percina&lt;/em&gt; (Osteichthyes: Percidae) Fish in Little River, Blount County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Heacock</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A recent apparent decline of the darter species in Little River, Blount County, Tennessee, suggested a deterioration on habitat quality was taking place. The objective of this study was to establish a baseline of the abundance and distribution of three large and easily recognized darter species (&lt;em&gt;Percina aurantiaca, P. burtoni, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;P. macrocephala&lt;/em&gt;) believed to be very pollution intolerant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study area included 27 river miles with 20 accessible sites which were determined by an area reconnaissance. Each site has been described, including diagrams and photographs, and was surveyed six times between July and October 1993. A review of published accounts of the darters&#39; habitats are presented along with observations of the unique type of stream habitat utilized by each darter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This visual study was set up to be repeatable, using site and habitat descriptions, for future monitoring of the fish populations. The baseline of abundance included adults and young-of-the-year of the three species. The number of fish sightings was compiled from the 120 observations conducted during the 6 surveys at each site. Additional information included sightings of fish observed in areas adjacent to the survey sites. Finally, a comparison was made between the 1993 study and a survey following a historical flood in 1994.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3261</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4689&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3261</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4689</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-03-19T10:01:59-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6866018</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3261</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Etnier</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dewey Bunting, J. Larry Wilson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>