<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Antioxidant Properties of Some Edible Fungi in The Genus &lt;i&gt;Pleurotus&lt;/i&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jean-Philippe</lname>
<fname>Sharon</fname>
<mname>Rose</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Antioxidant activity, of several species within the Genus &lt;em&gt;Pleurotus &lt;/em&gt;was studied. Sequencing of the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region of the ribosomal genes ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 confirmed species identification. Free radical scavenging ability of several &lt;em&gt;Pleurotus &lt;/em&gt;species was demonstrated by the DPPH assay. Two lipid model systems were used to test for oxidation of stripped corn oil; the first was an oil-in-water emulsion method which measured a primary product formed from lipid peroxidation, hydroperoxides. The second method was thiobarbituric acid (TBARS) which measured one of the secondary breakdown products of lipid peroxidation, malonaldehyde (MDA). Phenol, protein, and carbohydrate content were measured to elucidate relationships these compounds might have with antioxidant activity. In general all species sampled showed ability to scavenge free radicals. In particular &lt;em&gt;P. drynius&lt;/em&gt;, had high scavenging ability (71-75%). Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to test if there was any significant relationship between levels of protein, phenol, or polysaccharide with respect to antioxidant activity. The ability of &lt;em&gt;Pleurotus &lt;/em&gt;species to inhibit lipid oxidation using the thiobarbaturic acid assay was significant (PPleurotus.Protein and polysaccharide were significantly correlated with antioxidant activity measured by the TBAR assay (PPleurotusspecies (P&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2093</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3445&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2093</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3445</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T10:14:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4663239</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2093</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Karen Hughes</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Beth Mullin, Jay Whelan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>