<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An analysis of some characteristics of Ruffed Grouse (Bonasa Umbellus) drumming sites and logs in Middle Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1976-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Taylor</lname>
<fname>Daryl</fname>
<mname>Aycock</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Determining those factors which render a log as an acceptable site for ruffed grouse drumming and determining the difference between drumming and non-drumming logs was investigated. The study was conducted in the Blue Ridge Region and Great Valley of Eastern Tennessee are part of the Southern Appalachians. All three regions the oak hickory and oak-pine forest types are dominant in the areas studied. A total of 129 drumming logs and 37 non-drumming logs were located from February through May of 1974. Fifty-eight drumming and 37 non-drumming logs were found in the Great Valley, 46 drumming logs were found on the Cumberland Plateau, and 25 drumming logs in the Blue Ridge Region. A number of characteristics were measured on each log. Of these, 10 were analyzed by factor analysis, discriminant function and multiple regression. Factor analysis revealed that physical appearance and physical dimensions account for 80.7 percent of the variance within the population of drumming logs. Discriminant function analysis determined that there was a difference between drumming and non-drumming logs. When weighted with discriminant function scores, it was possible to place logs in a drumming or non-drumming log category with an accuracy of 85-90 percent. Within the confines of availability, drumming site preference is discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5823</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7501&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5823</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7501</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359305</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5823</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1976-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>