<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Report of Nutrition Field Observation and Experiences in the State of Arkansas</title>
<publication-date>1966-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nelson</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
<mname>Virginia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: This report is a presentation of the student&#39;s observations and experiences during seven weeks of field training with the Nutrition Service of the Arkansas State Department of Health. During this period the student was under the direct supervision of the Senior Nutrition Consultant responsible for training and orientation programs of the Nutrition Service. Much information was obtained concerning state and local nutrition services, but the information presented in this report will be restricted since it is impossible to comprehend the full extent of the program within this limited amount of time. The student will describe the nutrition program as it appeared during the field experience. It is hoped that this report will reflect the progressiveness and effectiveness of the nutrition program in the Arkansas State Department of Health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this field experience was to supplement the student&#39;s academic training in Public Health Nutrition at the University of Tennessee. It was felt that actual observation of and participation in the Nutrition Service programs would provide the student with knowledge of how the nutrition staff functions to meet the particular needs of the community in which it works. Another objective was to become familiar with the public health programs on state and local levels and to develop appreciation of the place of nutrition services in these total health programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the student had had no background in public health work, another objective of the field experience was to develop some ability to function as a nutritionist in a health agency. This would include ability to plan, organize, and carry on the services that make nutrition an integral part of the public health program Skills in working effectively with individuals, families, and groups needed to be developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help the student accomplish these objectives, a varied program was planned. Some time was spent with each member of the nutrition staff since they each had different types of responsibilities and programs. Conferences with the Assistant State Health Officer and with the directors of various divisions of the Arkansas State Department of Health and other related agencies helped to present a picture of the total health program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the majority of time was spent in observation of the work carried on by the nutrition staff members, the student did participate in some phases of the program. During the seven weeks, the student recorded daily the information gained through observations, meetings, conferences, and actual participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information gained during the field experience is summarized in the following four chapters. In Chapter II, some of the cultural, geographical, economical, educational, and health characteristics of the state are presented since these factors directly influence the health problems and programs of the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter III briefly describes the history, organization, and bureaus and divisions of the Arkansas State Department of Health. The administrative placement of the Nutrition Service in relation to the total health department program is also discussed in this chapter. In Chapter IV, the history, staff organization, and functions of the Nutrition Service are presented. A summary and evaluation of the field experience as related to the objectives as stated in the introduction are given in the last chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3861</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5341&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3861</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5341</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-16T12:15:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8984574</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3861</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harold H. Walker, John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1966-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1966-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>