<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Organizational Commitment, Perceived Supervisor Support, and Performance: A Field Study</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Soulen</lname>
<fname>Sarah</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined the relationships among supervisor support, organizational commitment, and job performance in a work environment. Specifically, differential relationships between supervisor support, affective commitment, and continuance commitment were explored. The relationship between commitment dimensions and job performance in the presence of supervisor support was also investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sample of 96 social workers completed measures of affective commitment, continuance commitment, and perceived supervisor support. Participants’ supervisors provided ratings of job performance and withdrawal behaviors. Results indicated that affective commitment is positively related to supervisor support (r = .42, p&lt;.01) and performance (r = .18, p&lt;.05). Continuance commitment was unrelated to any measured variable. When added to the model, affective commitment did not predict performance (β= .11, SE= .17, p&gt;.05), but perceived supervisor support did significantly predict performance (β = .38, SE= .16, p&lt;.05).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results support past research and extend current knowledge on the relationship between organizational commitment, supervisor support, and job performance. Findings from this study also highlight the importance of supportive treatment by a supervisor on employees’ commitment and job performance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2209</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3616&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2209</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3616</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T12:40:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4693626</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2209</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eric Sundstrom</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Lounsbury, Rich Saudargas</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>