<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>More Myself: Exploring Students&#39; Perceptions of Self-Authorship Development</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bstubbs@uwf.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stubbs</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>student development</keyword>
<keyword>higher education</keyword>
<keyword>purpose</keyword>
<keyword>independence</keyword>
<keyword>developmental experiences</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Assessment, Evaluation, and Research</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the challenges of modern adult life include the responsibility for ambiguous tasks, the need to work as a team with diverse others and the expectation to make important decisions in the face of competing interests. Research suggests that individuals able to meet these challenges demonstrate self-authorship, a way of knowing that allows them to exert control over their lives. Existing research provides insight into college students’ self-authorship and the influence of situational, environmental and personal factors on self-authorship development. However, the literature has yet to explore students’ own understanding of their self-authorship development. The purpose of this study was to explore the ways students make meaning of their self-authorship and self-authorship development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study utilized a qualitative approach and a narrative inquiry design to collect data from recent college graduates. Eleven graduates from a public, comprehensive university in the southeast participated in the study. Participants represented a variety of ethnic backgrounds, ages, and academic disciplines. Each participated in two in-depth, semi-structured interviews. The study utilized a constant comparative approach to analysis, and open, axial, and selective coding, to identify themes that would inform the findings of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings of the study include the following: (1) nine of the eleven participants demonstrated self-authored perspectives and processes, (2) participants viewed their self-authorship development not as a series of developmental experiences or transitions, but as a singular experience of continuous development, (3) participants made meaning of their self-authorship in the context of their independence and purpose, and (4) participants’ understanding of their development provided new insight into self-authorship and its development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2863</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4113&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2863</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4113</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-31T07:52:46-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4113/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5413474</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2863</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Norma T. Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dorian L. McCoy, Tricia McClam, J. Patrick Biddix</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>