<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a Bacteriophage Based Bioluminescent Bioreporter System for the Detection of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; K12 and O157:H7</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Courtney</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Detection of pathogenic bacteria in the environment and food products is of increasing importance especially in light of recent outbreaks of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7. I describe here a bacteriophage based bioluminescent bioreporter method for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 detection that combines the specificity bacteriophage have for their host, quorum sensing, and &lt;em&gt;lux&lt;/em&gt; based bioluminescence from &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fischeri&lt;/em&gt;. This new method for detection of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; utilizes the &lt;em&gt;luxI/luxR&lt;/em&gt; quorum sensing present in &lt;em&gt;V. fischeri&lt;/em&gt; which uses &lt;em&gt;N-&lt;/em&gt;(3-oxohexanoyl)-L-homoserine lactone (OHHL) as an autoinducer (Miller &amp; Bassler 2001). Once the concentration of OHHL is high enough it binds the LuxR protein initiating transcription of &lt;em&gt;luxCDABE&lt;/em&gt; and additional &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt;, leading to the production of light. This bioluminescent bacteriophage bioreporter method uses 2 components, first, the bioreporter cell called &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; OHHLux which carries the complete &lt;em&gt;lux&lt;/em&gt; cassette (luxCDABE) along with the transcriptional regulator &lt;em&gt;luxR&lt;/em&gt; (Ripp et al. 2006). The OHHLux (lambda phage resistant) detects the diffusible OHHL produced by the second component, the &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; engineered phage which when infecting target &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; cells produces autoinducer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial feasibility of the phage based reporter assay was tested using the well characterized lambda phage and &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; K12 model (Ripp et al. 2006). Once the initial feasibility of this bacteriophage based bioluminescent bioreporter system was confirmed, an &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 specific phage, PP01, was constructed with a &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; insert. This PP01- &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; phage was used in conjunction with &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; OHHLux to test for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 in pure culture, apple juice, ground beef, tap water, and spinach rinsates. This method has the potential to be a sensitive, rapid, and non-invasive method of screening for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 contamination. The system provided rapid and sensitive detection with results in well under 24 h even at &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 concentrations as low as 1 CFU/ml (Brigati et al. 2007, Ripp Submitted 2007). Our system is self-sufficient and could be adapted to be fully-automated and capable of high throughput screening in a production line setting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/388</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1420&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>388</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1420</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T09:54:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1147739</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/388</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gary Sayler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Steve Ripp, Todd Reynolds, David Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/JohnsonCourtney.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>