<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Student and faculty perceptions and attitudes about the master&#39;s thesis in social work</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Cherry</lname>
<fname>Donna</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The general aim of this study was to examine student and faculty perceptions of barriers to pursuing the thesis. This was in response to the relatively limited knowledge base, research, and literature addressing the thesis/capstone option for the master&#39;s program in social work, and lack of theses successfully completed at the University of Tennessee College of Social Work. Specifically, the study investigated the background characteristics, curriculum choices, and attitudes of a sample of current and former students enrolled in the MSSW program at the University of Tennessee as well as current faculty at the same institution. The data were obtained from a purposive sample of 364 current and former MSSW students and 25 current faculty from the three campuses of University of Tennessee College of Social Work located in Knoxville, Memphis, and Nashville. The data were collected in October and November 2002 through the use of a survey questionnaire that included a quantitative and qualitative design. Findings revealed that students feel positively about research and writing, which are the main components of a thesis, and appreciate the value of the thesis and research for both personal and professional growth. Statistically significant findings utilizing Pearson&#39;s Chi Square Test of Independence were realized. Significant relationships were found between undergraduate majors and writing ability (Chi-square(l 2) = 27.221, p&lt;.05), between undergraduate majors and the perception of writing skills required for a thesis (Chi-square(l2) = 24.370, p&lt;.05), and between undergraduate majors and interest in research (Chi-square(12) = 22.447, p&lt;.05). Both students and faculty expressed that the lack of time and the lack of support from the College of Social Work were significant barriers to pursuing or supporting the thesis option. The implications for social work education and future research are discussed in relation to this study. There is a need to reconsider how to support the thesis option. In addition, there is a substantive level of expressed student interest in an alternative capstone option that would realize the essence of a thesis but be tailored to accommodate time constraints and the need for a formal structure. Therefore, there is a need to consider how to support the thesis option or alternate capstone for students who are interested in pursuing it and for faculty who are interested in supporting it.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5202</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6610&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5202</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6610</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847035</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5202</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stan Bowie</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>