<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Microcomputer Software for In-House Databases... Four Top Packages Under $2000</title>
<publication-date>1985-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>library software</keyword>
<keyword>databases</keyword>
<keyword>database software</keyword>
<keyword>microcomputer systems</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the growing power and storage capacity of microcomputer systems, the prospect of developing an in-house database is becoming more attractive for many. Software for the design and creation of in-house databases, for information retrieval is now available to meet the requirements of a wide range of applications. The quality of recent software is much improved over that available a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article we will examine four information retrieval packages which run on small single user microcomputers: CAIRS, INMAGIC, Sci-Mate, and SIRE. All of the packages are available for the IBM PC and other MS-DOS systems, and are also available for other systems as well--in some cases ranging up to large multi-user minicomputer systems. All use variable length fields and records, and all sell for under $2000. These four packages are the best we have seen that meet these criteria. Additional packages were discussed in earlier article.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/246</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1401&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>246</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1401</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-12-29T13:37:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16090047</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/246</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;pp. 30-38&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Online</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>