<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Empowerment and occupational stress of International Society for Performance Improvement members</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Marshall</lname>
<fname>Vivian</fname>
<mname>Gregory</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine whether or not there are correlations between empowerment behaviors, and occupational stress, as measured by occupational role adjustment, psychological strain, and the availability of personal coping resources. In addition, this study sought to determine whether or not there are significant differences in occupational stress, as measured by occupational role adjustment, psychological strain, and the availability of personal coping resources based on demographic variables of age, race, marital status, work schedule, education, seniority, work hours, gender, and job title. Four hundred questionnaire packets were mailed to members of the International Society for Performance Improvement (ISPI). The return response rate was 40% (N = 160). Thirty-three (33) packets also were returned marked &quot;unknown at this address.&quot; The research packets consisted of two survey instruments: (a) the Occupational Stress Inventory-Revised (OSI-R) developed by Osipow (1998) and (b) the Management Empowerment Assessment Direct Report (MEADR) developed by Briggs (1999). In addition, the packets contained a demographic sheet comprised of eight demographic questions. Also enclosed was a cover letter, which described the study and contained a plea for help, and a small token incentive of one dollar.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6268</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8220&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6268</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8220</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450365</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6268</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty, Randal Pierce, Julia Malia</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>