<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>I Know I Can Learn: The Experiences of NCAA Division I – FBS Student-Athletes with Learning Disabilities and/or ADHD in Higher Education</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sstokows@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Stokowski</lname>
<fname>Sarah Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>ADHD</keyword>
<keyword>experience</keyword>
<keyword>football</keyword>
<keyword>learning disabilities</keyword>
<keyword>stereotype threat</keyword>
<keyword>student-athletes</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the evolvement of the NCAA’s initial and continuing eligibility practices throughout the past two decades, interest in studying the experience of student-athletes has increased (Gayles, 2009). Student-athletes have long been stereotyped as “dumb jocks” (Harrison et al., 2009; Sack &amp; Staurowsky, 1988). Campus groups such as faculty members and students suspect that student-athletes lack intelligence (King &amp; Springwood, 2001; Sailes, 1998), and put forth far less motivation in the classroom than they do on the playing field (Baucom &amp; Lantz, 2001; Burke, 1993; Watt &amp; Moore, 2001).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Student-athletes, especially those with learning disabilities can potentially face harsh scrutiny due to being labeled as not only a student-athlete, but as a person with a learning disability (Clark &amp; Parette, 2002). When an individual is aware of the negative stereotype surrounding his or her social group, depending on the situation that the individual is in, there is a possibility of stereotype threat (Steele &amp; Aronson, 1995). Despite the countless studies that have utilized stereotype threat, studies that use the theory pertaining to student-athletes, as well as literature involving those with learning disabilities are scarce (Aguino, 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although research has focused on educational experiences in regards to the general student-athlete population, little is known about the experiences of student-athletes with diagnosed learning disabilities and/or ADHD. The purpose of this study was to examine the experiences of NCAA Division I FBS football student-athletes who have been diagnosed with a learning disability and/or ADHD. Nine football student-athletes at an NCAA Division-I FBS institution were interviewed. Three major themes appeared throughout the data: the impact of football, learning competence, and stereotypes. The results of this study will allow those working with this particular population of student-athletes to develop a greater understand of their experience, and can ultimately assist in eliminating stereotype threat, which will lead to an increase in the academic performance of student-athletes with learning disabilities and/or ADHD (Cohen, Purdie-Vaughns, &amp; Garcia, 2012; Clark &amp; Parette, 2002).&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1780</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2916&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1780</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2916</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-01T15:53:08-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2916/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3820713</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1780</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robin Hardin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry Mee Bell, Leslee Fisher, Steven Waller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>