<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Some Hematological and Serum Biochemical Parameters of European Wild Hogs (&lt;em&gt;Sus scrofa&lt;/em&gt;)</title>
<publication-date>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Williamson</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>John</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Blood samples were obtained from 70 European wild hogs (&lt;em&gt;Sus scrofa&lt;/em&gt;), of which 33 were live-trapped in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park and 37 were reared in captivity on farms which were geographically proximal to the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anticoagulated blood was analyzed for erythrocyte sedimentation rate, red blood cell count, white blood cell count (total and differential), pack cell volume, hemoglobin concentration and platelet count. The values for mean corpuscular volume and mean corpuscular hemoglobin were calculated. Sera were analyzed for chloride, potassium, sodium, glucose, blood urea nitrogen, total serum protein, albumin, alpha, beta and gamma globulins. The albumin/globulin ration was calculated. Statistical analyses in the form of analysis of variance (P &lt; 0.05) were performed on the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of serum sodium, significant sex differences were not found. Subadult free-roaming hogs were higher than adults for red blood cell count, white blood cell counts, packed cell volumes, hemoglobins and platelet counts. The ratios of white blood cells in the differential counts were the same, though subadults had slightly fewer neutrophils and slightly more lymphocytes. Among the pen-reared animals, values for the different categories (i.e., age or sex) were more similar to one another with females having slightly higher sedimentation rates, white blood cell counts and platelet counts than males, and adults having somewhat higher values than subadults for all hematological parameters except percentage of neutrophils, mean corpuscular volume and mean corpuscular hemoglobin. Serum biochemical values for male, free-roaming hogs were slightly higher than females with the exception of glucose. Among adult and subadult, free-roaming hogs, only the total serum protein was significantly higher in the adults. Serum values of male and female pen-reared hogs were similar though the females had somewhat higher levels of total serum protein and albumin. Adult, pen-reared hogs had slightly higher levels of potassium, sodium and beta globulins and significantly higher levels of total serum protein than subadults. Analysis of variance of data indicated that location (i.e., free-roaming versus pen-reared) had a significant influence on platelet counts, neutrophil and lymphocyte counts, potassium, sodium, glucose, blood urea nitrogen, total serum protein, alpha, beta and gamma globulins. The influence of sex was significant only on sodium levels. Age apparently exerted a significant influence on platelet counts, chloride, sodium, total serum protein, albumin and the gamma globulins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is postulated that the differences mentioned above may be largely accounted for by differences in hematopoietic development, differences in reaction to stress and excitement, and differences in locational milieu.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1435</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2774&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1435</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2774</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-01T13:27:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4094634</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1435</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George M. Merriman, R. L. Murphee</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>