<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Experimental Investigation of Stresses in Gusset Plates</title>
<publication-date>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Whitmore</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Formerly, it was common practice to design and build trusses with pin connected joints. However, at present this practice has been virtually discontinued, owing to the increasing popularity of riveted connections. It is a reasonable assumption that rivets (or bolts) are used in 90% of all connections in present structural practice. The advantages of the riveted joint are due largely to the inherent strength, stiffness, and rigidity of this type of construction. This eliminates much vibration and wear, resulting in a more durable structure. At present, the usual practice is to rivet or bolt all the members meeting at a joint to a plate (or plates). These plates, commonly called &quot;gusset plates&quot; are subjected to a multiplicity of stresses which fact makes the analytical stress determination quite difficult, if not impossible. The gusset plate must transmit the direct stress in each member (or difference in stress for a member which continues through the joint) by direct, bending and shearing stresses. If there is any bending twist (torque), in the members, the gusset plate must also resist these moments, setting up a more complex pattern of stress. Modern practice is to make the size of the gusset plate, in the plane of the truss, as large as necessary so that all required rivets may be placed properly, and then to select a thickness in accordance with average values used for similar trusses. The stresses are then analyzed as carefully as possible to make sure that the plates are adequate and economical. This analysis generally requires passing various sections through the plate and analyzing for direct, bending and sharing stresses, all of which necessitates making certain questionable assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5770</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7447&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5770</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7447</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-14T04:24:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23341901</context-key>
<withdrawn>2021-06-22</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5770</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Armow Granger</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1950-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>