<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Impact of Matrix Metallopeptidase-9 Supplementation During In Vitro Maturation of Bovine Oocytes</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mgoodwi5@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Goodwin</lname>
<fname>Megan</fname>
<mname>Rene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>oocyte</keyword>
<keyword>heat stress</keyword>
<keyword>MMP9</keyword>
<keyword>oocyte maturation</keyword>
<keyword>progesterone</keyword>
<keyword>matrix metallopeptidase-9</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Dairy Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Heat-induced decreases in bovine blastocyst development have been related to reductions in latent matrix metallopeptidase-9 (proMMP9) production from maturing cumulus-oocyte complexes. Elevated intrafollicular proMMP9 levels at the time of oocyte retrieval have been positively related to pregnancy following human IVF. Thus, we hypothesized that heat-induced reductions in proMMP9 levels during oocyte maturation may be responsible for decreased blastocyst development. As a first step towards testing this hypothesis, bovine cumulus-oocyte complexes were matured at 38.5°C for 24 h with 0 or 300 ng/mL recombinant human proMMP9 (rhMMP9) added at 0 h of in vitro maturation (hIVM). No differences were found in ability of oocytes to cleave or form blastocyst-stage embryos after IVF. In a second study, cumulus-oocyte complexes were matured at 38.5 or 41.0°C (first 12 h only, then transferred to 38.5°C). At 12 hIVM, 0 or 300 ng/mL of rhMMP9 was added. Heat stress exposure decreased 24 hIVM proMMP9 levels in 0 (P = 0.006) but not 300 ng/mL groups and elevated progesterone levels most when 300 ng/mL rhMMP9 was added (P = 0.0002). Heat stress exposure did not affect ability of oocytes to cleave but reduced blastocyst development (P = 0.006). Independent of maturation temperature, addition of rhMMP9 decreased cleavage (P = 0.02) and blastocyst development (P = 0.08). In a third study, 0, 30 or 300 ng/mL rhMMP9 was added at 18 hIVM to cumulus-oocyte complexes matured at 38.5 or 41.0°C (first 12 h only, then transferred to 38.5°C). Heat stress exposure decreased 24 hIVM proMMP9 levels in 0 (P = 0.007) and 30 (P = 0.04) but not 300 ng/mL groups and increased progesterone levels in 0 and 300 but not 30 ng/mL rhMMP9 groups (P = 0.039). Heat stress exposure decreased cleavage (P &lt; 0.0001) and blastocyst development (P &lt; 0.0001). Independent of maturation temperature, addition of rhMMP9 did not alter cleavage but decreased blastocyst development (P = 0.02). In summary, addition of rhMMP9 at evaluated doses and times during IVM did not restore development of heat-stressed oocytes. Addition of 30 or 300 ng/mL rhMMP9 after 12 hIVM, regardless of maturation temperature, was detrimental to development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2818</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4156&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2818</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4156</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-07T12:21:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5756607</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2818</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>J. Lannett Edwards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>F. Neal Schrick, Louisa A. Rispoli, James D. Godkin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>