<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>From Tomato Fields to Tourists: Hilton Head Island and Beaufort County, South Carolina, 1950-1983</title>
<publication-date>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Shannon</lname>
<fname>Margaret</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Between 1950 and 1983, Hilton Head Island was transformed from a sleepy rural barrier island to a humming urban tourist destination. In the process, Hilton Head&#39;s native black population which had originally dominated the island was ultimately both politically and economically marginalized. This study seeks to answer two questions: first, what are the ways in which blacks sought to retain political power in the face of massive demographic and economic change? and second, how successful were they? I examined three issues through which blacks at Hilton Head sought political empowerment. They are the question of land acquisition and use, the controversy over the location of a potentially polluting industry just upstream of Hilton Head, and the final incorporation of the town of Hilton Head Island itself. I concluded that although blacks were informed and active participants in the island&#39;s political and economic life, the dramatic influx of whites with different economic profiles ultimately overwhelmed blacks through sheer numerical superiority.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5187</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6595&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5187</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6595</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-17T07:59:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13496124</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5187</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James C. Cobb</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>W. Bruce Wheeler, Charles Johnson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>