<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Beyond Black and White: Visualizing Cultural Identity Amidst Racial Anxiety and Nativism in American Modernist Novels</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ekrick@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Harrison</lname>
<fname>Emily</fname>
<mname>Moore</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>race</keyword>
<keyword>identity</keyword>
<keyword>Modernism</keyword>
<keyword>The Professor&#39;s House</keyword>
<keyword>The Great Gatsby</keyword>
<keyword>Quicksand</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Walter Benn Michaels’ &lt;em&gt;Our America: Nativism, Modernism, and Pluralism&lt;/em&gt; highlights that the search for identity is a mutual project of both nativism and Modernism and reveals how relevant racial identity is in American Modernism. While this is an important relationship in American Modernism, I argue that many recent studies following Michaels’ legacy of scholarship on race and nativism in modern American literature reduce individual authors’ projects, too often interpreting them all to have similar anxieties and desires for American racial identity and citing the presence of racial tropes as evidence of the authors’ own social and political arguments. Michaels set a precedent of overlooking the aesthetic in critical examinations of racial identity in American modernist texts, but I argue that aesthetic spaces are often the spaces where authors work through issues of race and identity and that aesthetics are crucial to understanding identity formation in many American modernist novels. Modernism is a movement that explores the idea that identity is not one-dimensional or whole, and I wish to illustrate a more kaleidoscopic view of racial aesthetics in American Modernism, exploring the complexity and variations of race presented by a variety of authors. Various American authors come to both Modernism and race in different ways and have unique projects and perspectives about racial identity. I wish to broaden the scope of conversation surrounding American Modernism and race, and I hope to illuminate the significance of examining the various and unique aesthetic elements at play in individual works of modern American fiction. I will examine works by Willa Cather, F. Scott Fitzgerald, and Nella Larsen to argue that race and Modernism have a more complicated relationship than much scholarship acknowledges and that the nativist and racial language and themes presented by many American modernist writers can be read more richly according to the various narrative perspectives and projects of the writers using them.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4744</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5769&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4744</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5769</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-22T07:45:56-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9728755</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4744</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisi Schoenbach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas F. Haddox, Martin Griffin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>