<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Gender Differences in the Preferred Methods of Training, Needs and Interests, and Hindrances and Motivators for Sexual Harassment Training</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Whaley</lname>
<fname>Heather</fname>
<mname>Monique</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this descriptive study was to assess employees’ preferences regarding sexual harassment prevention training (SHPT), compared by gender. A convenience sample of city/county governmental employees from a mid-size metropolitan city in the southeast representing multiple occupational groups consisted of 1387 employees. A response rate of 12% represented 169 respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modified Sexual Experiences Questionnaire - Department of Defense (SEQ- DoD) and the SHPT Preferences Climate Survey were completed. Frequency counts, descriptive statistics, principal component analysis, factor analysis, MANOVA tests, ANOVA tests, and a Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel (CMH) test allowed for hypotheses testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No statistical differences between genders exist in SHPT interests, design and intent, perceived usefulness of approaches of learning, or training attendance hindrances. Gender differences do exist in SHPT attendance motivators, identification of behaviors as sexual harassment compared between coworkers and supervisors, and factor scores of knowledge level and interest level of topics related to SHPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender is irrelevant in SHPT design. Training should focus on reducing gender- difference of attendance motivators and identification of behaviors as sexual harassment. Areas of future research include: (a) a longitudinal study to investigate the incidence rate to reveal whether reports decreased once more people were familiar with specific behaviors that constitute sexual harassment; (b) differences related to race; and (c) outcomes of training programs focused on needed areas of training, as indicated by employees.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2059</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3495&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2059</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3495</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-26T09:51:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4633097</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2059</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Lane Morris</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sharon Jeffcoat Bartley, Priscilla Blanton, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Business Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>