<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using Video Viewing to Evoke Hispanic Children&#39;s Narrative Samples</title>
<publication-date>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nradford@uthsc.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Health Science Center</institution>
<lname>Radford</lname>
<fname>Nola</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Cannon-Smith</lname>
<fname>Gerri</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Saenz</lname>
<fname>Adelaida</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Narrative Assessment</keyword>
<keyword>Narrative Sampling</keyword>
<keyword>Language Sampling</keyword>
<keyword>Language Development in Children</keyword>
<keyword>Bilingual Language Development</keyword>
<keyword>Hispanic Children’s Language Development</keyword>
<keyword>Multicultural Issues</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background. Discourse or narrative sampling is used routinely to examine children’s language skills. Conclusions differ as a function of elicitation procedures. Some investigators suggest using multimedia with reconstruction tasks as a choice method. This study was a preliminary examination of the video, Frankenweenie, for narrative sampling to examine the language abilities of English-Spanish speaking and English-speaking children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Method &amp; Procedure. Participants were four normally developing 6 to 9-year-old Hispanic males (Mexican-American). After each narrative elicitation, subjects completed an attitudinal survey about the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions. All 4 children produced lower-level narratives in response to the video. Revision of the protocol is planned to determine the influence of different cues to increase use of episode elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clinical Implications. The case studies were a first step for developing a video protocol for Frankenweenie as an alternative to The Frog Story and to examine the discourse skills of Hispanic children in the Rio Grande Valley of Texas.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_audipubs/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_audipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-02-19T09:03:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Audiology and Speech Pathology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>11587218</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_audipubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>ECHO Journal of the National Black Association for Speech-Language and Hearing</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>