<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Temperature effects on emergence time, proportion of males, and diapause in three species of Nasonia (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae)</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Grinnan</lname>
<fname>Anne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Temperature has been demonstrated to induce phenotypic plasticity in numerous insects for numerous traits. An organism of a specific genotype is said to exhibit phenotypic plasticity if it shows variation in a trait or traits that is dependant on changes in the external environment. A reaction norm is the function that relates the environments to which a particular genotype is exposed and the phenotypes that can be produced by that genotype. Genotype-by-environment interactions measure how genotypes vary in their· reaction norms. Trait responses to temperature can be examined with analyses that test for G by E interactions and display norms of reaction; thus telling us if different genotypes behave differently in different temperature environments. In the genus Nasonia, females produce large numbers of virtually identical offspring in a single clutch, making them ideal for a study of reaction norms. Nasonia vitripennis, N. giraulti and N. /ongicomis are parasitic wasps that parasitize various species of blow flies. I tested two strains of each of the three species for differences in emergence time, proportion of males and tendency to diapause due to different temperature environments. I also tested for genetic differences among the strains and any G by E interactions that might occur. I found that emergence time was the same for all species and all strains tested; as temperature increased the emergence time decreased. The proportion of males per clutch tended to have less of a plastic response, but there is evidence of a genetic response, with strains of the same species behaving differently. Diapause showed more genetic than temperature variation. In general, the G by E responses were modest.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5232</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6640&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5232</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6640</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847083</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5232</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Christine Boake</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>