<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a Real-time Ultra-wideband See Through Wall Imaging Radar System</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Yunqiang</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Ultra-Wideband (UWB) See-Through-Wall (STW) technology has emerged as a musthave enabling technology by both the military and commercial sectors. As a pioneer in this area, we have led the research in addressing many of the fundamental STW questions. This dissertation is to investigate and resolve a few hurdles in advancing this technology, and produce a realizable high performance STW platform system, which will aid the STW community to find the ultimate answer through experimental and theoretical work. The architectures of a realizable STW imaging system are thoroughly examined and studied. We present both a conceptual system based on RF instruments and a standalone real-time system based on custom design, which utilize reconfigurable design architecture and allows scaling down/up to a desired UWB operating frequency with little difficulty. The systems will serve as a high performance platform for STW study and other related UWB applications. Along the way to a complete STW system, we have developed a simplified transmission line model for wall characteristic prediction; we have developed a scalable synthetic aperture array including both the RF part and the switch control/synchronization part; we have proposed a cost-effective and efficient UWB data acquisition method for real-time STW application based on equivalent-time sampling method. The measurement results reported here include static image formation and tracking moveable targets behind the wall. Even though digital signal processing to generate radar images is not the focus of this research, simple methods for image formation have been implemented and results are very encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/432</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1493&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>432</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1493</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T10:59:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1150919</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/432</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Aly E. Fathy</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Marshall O. Pace, Paul B. Crilly, Mohamed R. Mafouz, Thomas T. Meek, Samir El-Ghazaly</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/YangYunqiang.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>