<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;None of us will ever be the same again:&quot; Reactions of American midlife women to 9/11</title>
<publication-date>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sthomas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Refereed Journal Articles</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>terrorism</keyword>
<keyword>psychosocial factors</keyword>
<keyword>women</keyword>
<keyword>stress</keyword>
<keyword>descriptive research</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;According to terror management theory (TMT), an event that heightens awareness of death produces the need to defend against existential anxiety. The horrifying events of September 11, 2001 (9/11), created an unparalleled opportunity to apply TMT beyond the laboratory. This study examined post-9/11 stress (via perceived stress scale [PSS] scores) and interview responses of a diverse community sample of American midlife women (ages 35-60). Previous studies showed that many women have high stress during midlife, suggesting that 9/11 could have a unique impact on this segment of the U.S. population. Education of the sample ranged from 12 to 23 years. Seventy-five percent had children and 70.6% were married. Data analysis showed that 4 to 6 months after 9/11, 61% of the women were still distressed, exhibiting symptoms of fear, sadness, anger, powerlessness, distrust, and vigilance. Highly stressed women (upper 25% on PSS) differed in several respects from low-stress women (lower 25% on PSS). As predicted by TMT, core values central to a woman&#39;s world view were activated by 9/11. Patriotism and altruism increased, but bigotry intensified as well. Major changes (e.g., marriage, moving) were undertaken only by a small percentage (18%), but all expressed the view, &quot;None of us will ever be the same again.&quot; Women who had experienced previous trauma felt that their background actually helped them cope.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/108</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1123&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>108</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1123</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-11T09:46:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1473203</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/108</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Thomas, S.P. (2003).  “None of us will ever be the same again:” Reactions of American midlife women to 9/11.  &lt;em&gt;Health Care for Women International&lt;/em&gt;, 24, 853-867.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Health Care for Women International</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>