<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Black Narrative</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:36:42-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kjone169@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Karmen Alexia</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Arts and Humanities</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Through art and literature, we are able to create our own of narratives of any cultural experience. In this scenario, the African American experience can be exemplified through methods of reiterating or recreating. Artists can choose to reiterate or repeat a narrative that meets the status quo of stereotypes that have already been established through social, civil, economic traditions of teaching, or an artist can recreate and bring light to a new aspect to the complexity of the humanisation and emotional journeys of Black people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this discussion is to highlight the purposes within each selected work or individual’s attributes, along with whether or not these narratives help or hurt the African American community’s representation within and outside or our community. These narratives include the sectors of visual, musical, and other forms of entertainment that have been created by Black artists. The conclusion will be a reflection of what we do as individuals to protect our truths for the good of the next generation of black creators and educators.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/2</coverpage-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1220</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-11T14:01:19-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1220/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13611106</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>