<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>STEMM-Humanities Co-Teaching and the Humusities Turn</title>
<publication-date>2020-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hrcohen2@stkate.edu</email>
<institution>St. Catherine University</institution>
<lname>Cohen</lname>
<fname>Hella</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Humusities</keyword>
<keyword>STEMM</keyword>
<keyword>Humanities</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Creative Writing</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>Liberal Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Donna Haraway calls for a new Humanities that attends to the role of this traditionally anthropocentric field on a damaged planet. The Humusities, she offers, empower us to teach at the intersections of observation, speculation, and affective reasoning. This article considers co-teaching and interdisciplinary teaching structures as part of the Humusities model. Drawing from interviews and pedagogical materials of professors who have co-taught STEMM-Humanities classes, student feedback from these sections, and current research on interdisciplinary education, I theorize the possibilities and limitations of the interdisciplinary Humusities at the undergraduate level. The article explores how we translate the tenets of Haraway into a co-taught curriculum, while considering the objectives, benefits, and drawbacks of doing so. Several pedagogical and procedural issues are discussed: “norming” student performance in courses where two or more instructors are likely using different assessment modalities; navigating STEMM-Humanities co-teaching within current university budget structures; considering how university size and collegial climate affects implementation; and revealing roadblocks that exist relating to Registrar policy, enrollments, student majors, and hiring practices. I also speculate how the Humusities turn can redistribute university wealth and mitigate educational threats at the state and federal levels. Like science fiction in Haraway’s Staying with the Trouble, co-teaching across the Humusities engages in “storytelling and fact telling; it is the patterning of possible worlds and possible times, material-semiotic worlds, gone, here, and yet to come” (31). With this sentiment in mind, I explore what is entailed in the process of humanizing STEMM and composting the humanities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jaepl/vol25/iss1/15</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1361&amp;amp;context=jaepl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>15</label>
<document-type>essay</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1361</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-09-16T13:59:59-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>The Journal of the Assembly for Expanded Perspectives on Learning</publication-title>
<context-key>19426574</context-key>
<submission-path>jaepl/vol25/iss1/15</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>