<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Caught in (or on) the Web: A Review of Course Management Systems for Legal Education</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>legal education</keyword>
<keyword>teaching</keyword>
<keyword>technology</keyword>
<keyword>course management system</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Education</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Like  other teaching innovations, course management software has been somewhat  slow to take hold in legal education. Yet, as law teachers, we cannot  deny that our current students are children of a technological age that  centers on electronic communication. Although there is a lack of  empirical evidence strongly supporting the pedagogic case for the use of  technology in law teaching, some of us in the law academy have ventured  forth with the use of teaching technologies on the theory that the  current demographics of the law student population demand our  interaction with students on this basis. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Course management  systems are an easy way to bridge the technological gap between law  teachers and law students without forcing law teachers to irrevocably  alter the material they teach and the way in which they teach it. In  that spirit, this article describes the way in which I have implemented  Web-based course management in my law school course offerings and sets  forth my perspectives on that experience. The article adds to existing  literature by offering primary experiential observations that should be  useful to others in law teaching - especially those who may not be  familiar with course management systems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/31</coverpage-url>
<label>31</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1029</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-01T11:42:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2041883</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/31</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Caught in (or on) the Web: A Review of Course Management Systems for Legal Education (October 24, 2005). Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=842105</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=842105</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>