<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Field Experience with the Section of Nutrition, Division  of Health, Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services</title>
<publication-date>1970-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rowland</lname>
<fname>Ann</fname>
<mname>Miller</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis describes and analyzes the author&#39;s eight-weeks of field observations and experiences with the Section of Nutrition in the Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services. The purpose of the field experience was to augment the academic program with practical experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience was planned to strengthen the author&#39;s philosophy and understanding of the principles of public health. The author observed and participated in nutrition programs within the health agency at various levels as well as with professional groups and community agencies. The author was provided the opportunity to develop her professional skills and competencies through practical application of established nutritional programs in a health agency and in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience made the author aware of the necessity of a planned nutrition program to adequately meet the nutritional needs of a population. The author&#39;s previous work experience in a Children and Youth Project and observing in two such projects provided a basis for comparing different approaches to planning programs for similar services in different geographic areas. Moreover, the field experience strengthened the author&#39;s professional skills and competencies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3970</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5464&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3970</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5464</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T10:37:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9124954</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3970</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Rose Gram, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1970-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1970-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>