<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Utilizing Animal-Assisted Therapy to Treat Children with Mulitple Traumas</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cmharm@uga.edu</email>
<institution>University of Georgia</institution>
<lname>Harm</lname>
<fname>Catherine</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Social Workers&#39; knowledge of trauma among children is increasing significantly through research and practice. One of the most complex areas of research is determining what interventions are effective with children who have suffered multiple traumas. Each day, practioners are challenged to find evidence based practices that can aid children suffering from emotional turmoil caused by trauma. One such practice is Animal-Assisted Therapy which is rapidly becoming an accepted practice. This presentation will illustrate how Animal-Assisted Therapy is linked to Attachment Theory and provide an overview of the current research. In addition, common Animal-Assisted Therapy techniques will be demostrated by the presenter and one of her certified therapy dogs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/24</coverpage-url>
<label>24</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1031</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-10-22T18:05:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3416515</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/24</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Primary Presentator: Catherine Harm is a Doctoral Student with the University of Georgia&#39;s School of Social Work. In addition, she is a Licensed Master Social Worker who specializes in providing Animal-Assisted Therapy through a private agency with one of her three certified therapy dogs to children who have experienced multiple traumas. Ms. Harm has over 10 years of experience in working with children who have experienced abuse and neglect with 8 of those years spent directly in the child welfare field. In addition, Ms. Harm is forensically trained to interview abuse and neglect victims. In their free time, Ms. Harm and her dogs participate in canine sports.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Catherine Harm, 678-333-4409, 716 Moonlite Trace, Winder, GA 30680&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T18:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Workshop: 1-hour workshop</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T17:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>