<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effects of changing forest dynamics in the northern Cumberland Plateau on the Indiana bat (Myotis sodalis)</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>French</lname>
<fname>Amelia</fname>
<mname>Clayton</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Forestry</keyword>
<keyword>Myotis sodalis</keyword>
<keyword>Forest dynamics</keyword>
<keyword>Ecosystem management</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Northern Cumberland Plateau contains both extensive stretches of hardwood forests and remarkable biodiversity. The presences of unique and threatened wildlife species, including the Indiana bat (Myotis sodalis), have made the Plateau an area of concern. Future changes in forest conditions, ranging from declining timber markets to drastic increases in timber harvests, could prove to have significant impacts on M. sodalis. A study of M. sodalis occupancy on the Plateau indicated that although the species was difficult to detect and may not be very common on the Plateau, it could potentially be very sensitive to human disturbance. Although only a reduction in the probability of detection resulted from increased human activity, prolonged disturbance could also reduce occurrence of the species. In order to better understand a larger area of concern for the species, a map was created to designate areas with high potential for M. sodalis maternity roosts. Based on expert opinions, the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) was utilized to compare and rank habitat characteristics. Upland and riparian hardwood stands were determined to be the most important for the species&#39; maternity roosts, while developed and agricultural areas were determined to be the least important. Several areas across Tennessee&#39;s Northern Cumberland Plateau were defined as having high potential for M. sodalis maternity roosts. Both the presence and potential for the species in the Plateau, combined with the changing forest dynamics in the Plateau, have made the area a special concern for forest, ecosystem and M. sodalis management.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5716</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7338&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5716</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7338</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467467</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5716</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Donald G. Hodges</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Forestry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>