<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mississippian Architecture: Temporal, Technological, and Spatial Patterning of Structures at the Toqua Site (40M R6)</title>
<publication-date>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Polhemus</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The description and analysis of 130 Native American structures from the Toqua site (40MR6) provide an architectural typology for determining age, form, and function of Mississippian and historic Cherokee structural remains in East Tennessee. The Toqua structure, ranging in age from circa A.D. 1200 to circa A.D. 1780, are examined for temporal, technological, and spatial patterning and are compared with 469 structures from 58 Mississippian archaeological sites in the interior Southeastern United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superimposed structures and radiocarbon determinations provided a temporal sequence of structure types. Closely controlled excavations, botanical analysis of construction materials, and technological studies of building materials provided insight into two successive construction techniques. An earlier flexed form of building construction had continuous elements making up both walls and roof. A later rigid form of building construction use separate components for walls, roof, and roof support system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study of structure size, form, proportion, elaboration, content, and location provided information concerning structure function and the relationship of contemporary structures to each other. Insight concerning the temporal, technological, and spatial patterning of Mississippian structures was obtained.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3320</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4762&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3320</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4762</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-15T12:43:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6989064</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3320</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles H. Faulkner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gerald F. Schroedl, Jefferson Chapman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>