<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Interrelationships Between Sulfate Metabolism and Tocopherols in the Weanling Rat</title>
<publication-date>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chin</lname>
<fname>Young</fname>
<mname>Ping</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;There have been numerous investigations in which reported observations point toward the existence of metabolic interrelationships between tocopherols, the sulfur-containing amino acids, and inorganic sulfur.  In previous work, this laboratory has used mixtures partially composed of oxidized casein and casein to produce a protein source having a low methionine content and lending variation with respect to inorganic sulfate.  Alpha protein, a purified soybean protein, is characteristically similar to oxidized casein in that both substances have a low sulfur amino acid content.  Due to the expenses involved in the laboratory use of oxidized casein, the present investigation was undertaken to determine if alpha protein rather than a casein-oxidized casein mixture could be used advantageously in studying the interrelationships of sulfur-containing amino acids, tocopherols, and sulfate.  In addition, it would be of interest to study growth effects of young animals receiving diets containing varied amounts and forms of sulfur both with and without sufficient vitamin E.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four groups of diets were used.  Although two diets were basically the same with regard to level of sulfur, there was some variation in the ratio of inorganic: organic sulfur.  Eight matched groups of five rats each were maintained on the experimental diets for 70 days, with each group receiving diets containing sufficient amounts of vitamin E while the corresponding littermates consumed the same diet which had been depleted with respect to alpha-tocopherol.  Food consumption for each group was determined and recorded daily.  Weekly recordings of weights were made to observe growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the rats attained the weight normally observed for ninety-day-old rats in this colony.  In contrast, eight of the animals on the vitamin-E deficient diets died.  Supplementation of the diets with both vitamin E and methionine resulted in improved growth and greater food efficiency.  Supplementation with cysteine and vitamin E did not affect improved growth or food efficiency.  A sex difference was observed in the effect of vitamin E. supplementation on weight change in all diets showing any weight gain.  The female rats responded most favorably to vitamin E supplementation.  The data obtained from this investigation confirm a previous proposal that sufficient dietary vitamin E is essential for optimal utilization of sulfur-containing amino acids.  In addition, alpha protein does not appear to be a satisfactory protein source, low in sulfur-containing amino acids, for investigational purposes when weanling rats are employed in studying interrelationships between sulfur metabolism and vitamin E.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3946</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5428&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3946</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5428</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-09T10:25:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9097213</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3946</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Florence L. MacLeod, Ruth Buckley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>