<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Investigation into potential cross-resistance of Enterococcus faecalis OG1RF induced by adaptation to NaCl and subsequent SDS challenge</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>vsingh4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Singh</lname>
<fname>Vidisha</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>efozo@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fozo</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>E. faecalis</keyword>
<keyword>cross-resistance</keyword>
<keyword>SDS Challenge</keyword>
<keyword>salt stress</keyword>
<keyword>bile</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Pathogenic Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gram-positive, non-spore forming bacteria &lt;em&gt;Enterococcus faecalis &lt;/em&gt;has been the interest of numerous stress studies due to its ability to survive a range of harsh environments. Its highly adapted membrane replete with specialized proteins enable &lt;em&gt;E. faecalis &lt;/em&gt;to maintain homeostasis in such conditions as bile salts, low pH, and low oxygen encountered in the human gastrointestinal tract (12). Bile is a bacteriostatic agent because of its amphipathic nature and toxic amino acid moiety when in its conjugated bile acid form. Similarly, the detergent SDS (sodium dodecyl sulfate) exhibits toxic effects on the bacterial membrane of &lt;em&gt;E. faecalis&lt;/em&gt; and for this reason is a comparable stressor to bile (4). Previous studies have explored the existence of cross-protection by exposure of bile salts stress to test growth in subsequent stress challenges such as heat, bile salts, SDS, and varied pH (9). We predicted that growth in NaCl may confer similar resistance to &lt;em&gt;E. faecalis &lt;/em&gt;OG1RF when challenged to low concentrations of SDS in rich growth media. To examine the effects of such cross-protection by NaCl, OG1RF was grown with varying concentrations (%w/v) of NaCl then subjected to 0.01% SDS. Dilutions plated at various time points of the challenge revealed that rather than providing cross-protection, growth in salt only served to prolong the death of cells in the SDS challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/18</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1019&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1019</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-11T07:40:25-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_micrpubs/article/1019/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3574854</context-key>
<withdrawn>2013-11-18</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>1. Fisher, Katie and Phillips, Carol. (2009) The ecology, epidemiology and virulence of Enterococcus. Microbiology 155: 1749–1757.
2. Flahaut, S., Benachour, A., Giard, JC, Boutibonnes, P., Auffray, Y. (1996) Defense against lethal treatments and de novo protein synthesis induced by NaCl in Enterococcus faecalis ATCC 19433. Arch Microbiol.165: 317-324. 
3. Flahaut, S, Hartke, A, Giard, JC, Benachour, A, Boutibonnes, P, Auffray, Y. (1996) Relationship between stress response towards bile salts, acid and heat treatment in Enterococcus faecalis. FEMS Microbiology Letters 138: 49-54
4. Flahaut, S., Frere, J., Boutibonnes, P., Auffray, Y. (1996) Comparison of the Bile Salts and Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate Stress Responses in Enterococcus faecalis. Applied and Environmental Microbiology 62: 2416-2420.  
5. Hofmann, AF and Eckmann L. (2006) How bile acids confer gut mucosal protection against bacteria. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 103: 4333- 4334.
6. Kunin CM, Rudy J (1991) Effect of NaCl-induced osmotic stress on intracellular concentrations of glycine betaine and potassium in Escherichia coli, Enterococcus 	faecalis and staphylococci. J Lab Clin Med 118:217–224 
7. Maddalo, G, Chovanec, P, et.al. (2011) A reference map of the membrane proteome of Enterococcus faecalis. Proteomics 11: 3935-3941. 
8. Merrit, ME and Donaldson, JR. (2009) Effect of bile salts on the DNA and membrane
	integrity of enteric bacteria. Journal of Medical Microbiology 58: 1533–154. 
9. Rigottier-Gois L, Alberti A, Houel A, Taly J-F, Palcy P, et al. (2011) Large-Scale Screening of a Targeted Enterococcus faecalis Mutant Library Identifies Envelope Fitness Factors. PLoS ONE 6(12): e29023. Doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0029023 
10. Rincé, A, Breton, YL, Verneuil, N, et. al. (2003) Physiological and molecular aspects of bile salt response in Enterococcus faecalis. International Journal of Food Microbiology 88: 207– 213.
11. Shimada, K, Bricknell, KS, et. al. (1969) Deconjugation of Bile Acids by Intestinal Bacteria: Review of Literature and Additional Studies. The Journal of Infectious Diseases 119: 273-281. 
12. Solheim, M, et. al. (2007) Transcriptional responses of Enterococcus faecalis V583 towards bovine bile and SDS. Applied Environmental Microbiology 73(18): 5767-74.
13. Hoffman, Tamara, et. al. (2012) Synthesis, Release, and Recapture of Compatible Solute Proline by Osmotically Stressed Bacillus subtilis Cells.  Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 78: 5753-5762. 
14. Lee, JY, et. al. (2012) Proteomic and Transcriptional Analysis of Lactobacillus johnsonii PF01 during Bile Salt Exposure by iTRAQ Shotgun Proteomics and Quantitative RT-PCR. Journal of Proteome Research.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-11-04T13:57:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>