<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A New Lean Model:  Improving Race Team Performance through Team-Driver Communication Efficacy</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jstainback@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stainback IV</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Ruric</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Communications Model</keyword>
<keyword>Lean</keyword>
<keyword>NASCAR</keyword>
<keyword>Speech Recognition</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Industrial Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In some organizational settings and in the field of competitive automobile racing, certain situations and rules place an emphasis on and sometimes escalate the need for effective team communications.  This dissertation hypothesizes that effective and dense communications contributes directly to team performance.  Supported by organizational behavioral and lean six sigma theory, communications is declared a form of waste within the context of Industrial Engineering subject to data collection, measurements, and real-time, value-added metrics.   Measuring and reporting trends in communications provides a basis for a new and unique model called a Communications Productivity Model (CPM) with an associated Communications Density Report (CDR).  Industrial Engineering productivity, statistics, linguistic and text analysis tools were combined to develop a unique Dynamic Productivity Index (DPI) enhancing the CDR as a means to rapidly provide meaningful and value-added feedback on recent and future performance.  Data was collected on actual automobile racing teams to validate the new communications model, report on the results using the CDR and introduce the DPI.   Future research is also proposed in this dissertation to enhance the new communications model whereby speech recognition technologies are evaluated and tested.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/752</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1761&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>752</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1761</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-13T18:54:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1273828</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/752</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rapinder S. Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Xueping Li, Charles H. Aikens, Joseph H. Wilck, IV, David K. Irick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>