<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Four Women’s Experiences in Agriculture Education Across Generations</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Baxter</lname>
<fname>Linda</fname>
<mname>Sue</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this phenomenological study was to discover the perceptions and barriers for female agriculture educators across three generations in a non-traditional field of agriculture. The United States Department of Labor (2006) defined a non-traditional job as any occupation where one gender comprises 25% or less of the total employment. Camp, Broyles, and Skelton (2002) revealed secondary female agriculture teachers comprise 22% of the agriculture education field. However, there is a 35% female student membership in high school FFA (National FFA, 2000) so why is there a discrepancy in the number of high school females taking agriculture and the low number females in the teaching field? There are several perceptions of why this is occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four female agriculture teachers were interviewed with the open-ended question: “What are your experiences in teaching agriculture education in a predominately male field?” The teachers selected were from three generations: early Baby Boomer, late Baby Boomer, Generation Xer, and Millennial. Each participant has a Bachelor‟s degree in agricultural education and ethnicity was not taken into account when selecting participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four women&#39;s experience in teaching agriculture education across generations revealed many statements with similar content. The barriers included, but not exclusively, &lt;em&gt;qualification to teach agriculture education&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;challenges in teaching agriculture education&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;stress in teaching agriculture education&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;stereotyping of agriculture teachers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/17</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1045&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1045</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-14T09:48:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1110804</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carrie Ann Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barbara Thayer-Bacon, Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>