<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The synthesis and characterization of building block-based titanosilicates and their activity toward alcohol dehydration/dehydrogenation reactions</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Mayes</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>Thomas</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Chemistry</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Catalysis, in general, plays an integral part to many aspects of everyday life. Next-generation heterogeneous catalysts need well defined site structures to correlate with activity in order to maximize selectivity and activity. The building block methodology is a widely-applicable route to synthesizing single-site catalysts that are atomically dispersed. The building block methodology has been used to synthesize a series of titanosilicates with different site structures that mimic the potential sites in current titanosilicates. These catalysts have been characterized via EXAFS and gravimetric analysis. The EXAFS suggest single-site nature for the embedded (TiO₄) and surface (ClTiO₃) titanosilicate and suggest composite structure for the two intermediate titanosilicates ClTiO₃ and Cl₂TiO₂. An embedded tripodal titanosilicate ([superscript i]PrO)TiO₃ was synthesized as well to mimic the tripodal sites without the presence of chloride ligands. Alcohol dehydration/dehydrogenation reactions have been used to characterize the acidity and basicity of heterogeneous catalysts. Isopropanol and ethanol were used to characterize the embedded TiO₄ and embedded tripodal ([superscript i]PrO)TiO₃ building block titanosilicates as well as the embedded building block vanadium(V)-silicate and vanadium(IV)-silicate. The catalysts were highly selective toward isopropanol dehydration with the post-calcination catalysts exhibiting higher conversion at lower temperatures than the pre-calcination catalysts. The titanosilicates exhibited no selectivity toward ethanol decomposition reactions while the vanadium-silicates were more selective toward ethylene production. The differences in reactivity and selectivity illustrate the differences in the type of site and metal used.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5977</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7910&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5977</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7910</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467586</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5977</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Craig E. Barnes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>