<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>AN ANALYSIS OF THE VALUES AND SPIRITUALITY PROFILES OF COLLEGE AND UNIVERSITY PRESIDENTS BY CARNEGIE CLASSIFICATION</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hballard@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Ballard</lname>
<fname>Harold Wayne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>president</keyword>
<keyword>values</keyword>
<keyword>spirituality</keyword>
<keyword>rokeach values survey</keyword>
<keyword>Ballard &amp; Bogue Spirituality Assessment</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Higher Education Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to ascertain whether there are significant differences in the spirituality and value profiles of the presidents of institutions with differing Carnegie Classification: Associates Institutions, Arts &amp; Sciences Plus Professions four year colleges and universities, and Research universities. This study extends the scope of the growing, but limited research conducted in the past twenty years on spirituality and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study employed the use of three survey instruments, the Rokeach Value Survey, the Ballard &amp; Bogue Spirituality Assessment, and a demographic questionnaire in an online survey. Three hundred and seventy seven presidents of American colleges and universities were asked to participate in this survey. Sixty presidents completed the survey. Data were compared and studied by gender, type of institution, years of service, academic discipline, private versus public, geographic region, and religious affiliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research determined there is little difference in the concept of values and spirituality between presidents of all three major types of institutions studied. The Research university presidents did, however, differ in order of preference on some values.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1507</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2711&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1507</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2711</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-09-25T08:53:17-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2711/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3348775</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1507</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>E. Grady Bogue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Norma T. Mertz, Robert Cunningham, Charles H. Reynolds</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>