<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Patriarchy and Women: A Study of Charlotte Perkins Gilman&#39;s &#39;The Yellow Wallpaper&#39;&quot;</title>
<publication-date>1990-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Delashmit</lname>
<fname>Margaret</fname>
<mname>Victoria</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Charlotte Perkins Gilman reached within her own gothic world for the inspiration for &quot;The Yellow Wallpaper,&quot; and in doing so, she created a gothic heroine to whom women of her own and succeeding generations could relate. This study examines the elements in Gilman&#39;s life that helped her to create this story; but unlike many other studies, it treats &quot;The Yellow Wallpaper&quot; as a work of art apart from its author as much as possible. This study interprets the story as an example of the female gothic and examines Gilman&#39;s philosophy of literature and her skill in employing the narrative voice to depict her heroine as a grotesque within the context of nineteenth-century Victorian more and medical practices. It also analyzes her unique treatment of the female doppelganger by comparing and contrasting her use of this device with that of Dostoevsky&#39;s in &lt;em&gt;The Double&lt;/em&gt;. A different type of doubling, that of the beloved Other, is also discussed in an effort to understand the sexual relationship between Gilman&#39;s narrator and her physician husband John. The early history of the story then precedes an annotated bibliography of Gilman criticism in chronological order beginning with Carl Degler&#39;s 1956 article and including dissertations and published criticism through 1989.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2662</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4160&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2662</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4160</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-12T09:55:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5570111</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2662</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William H. Shurr</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allison Ensor, Mary Papke, Susan Becker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1990-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1990-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>