<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Northern bobwhite (Colinus virginianus) population ecology on reclaimed mined lands</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>etanner2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Tanner</lname>
<fname>Evan Philip</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>reclaimed mined lands</keyword>
<keyword>population ecology</keyword>
<keyword>survival</keyword>
<keyword>nest survival</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The northern bobwhite (&lt;em&gt;Colinus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) has experienced range-wide population declines for the past half century. The primary cause has been large-scale habitat loss and fragmentation. Through auspices of the Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977 (SMCRA), large tracts of early successional vegetation have been created throughout much of the bobwhite’s range that may be managed to increase usable space. Peabody WMA is a reclaimed coal mine in Western Kentucky where bobwhite have been present in the past. To better understand the dynamics of this population and how habitat on Peabody WMA influences these dynamics, my two objectives were to (1) document survival, cause-specific mortality, and assess multi-scale habitat effects on survival of bobwhite, and (2) estimate nest survival, reproductive efforts, and gauge the effects of habitat composition on these parameters across multiple scales. In relation to bobwhite survival, there was not evidence of multi-scale habitat influence (Part II). Survival increased as the amount of forest vegetation increased within a home range. This was likely related to the availability of woody escape cover associated with forest vegetation on our study site. Pooled seasonal survival rates differed between Ken (S = 0.316, SE = 0.027) and Sinclair (S = 0.141, SE = 0.022) sites. This may have been attributed to differences in habitat suitability or predator abundance. Nest survival rate was low relative to other research (S = 0.317, SE = 0.081; Part III). Nest age was the most influential factor relative to nest survival on our study site and had a positive relationship. Evidence of micro-habitat effects on nest survival existed, though these effects were minimal. Nest survival increased as distance to bare ground increased. This is likely related to the importance of nest concealment on our study site. Our results show that reclaimed mined lands can provide usable space to support bobwhite populations. Management efforts should focus on increasing woody cover within reclaimed vegetation blocks to increase bobwhite survival while increasing the amount of native warm-season grasses for nesting vegetation and litter cover to support reproductive efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1257</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2312&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1257</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2312</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-21T11:45:06-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2312/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2688431</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1257</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Patrick Keyser</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Craig Harper, David Buehler, Arnold Saxton, John Morgan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>