<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Magnetic Field Dependent Electroluminescence and Charge Transport in Organic Semiconductors</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mshao2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Shao</lname>
<fname>Ming</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>magnetic field effects</keyword>
<keyword>electroluminescence</keyword>
<keyword>organic semiconductor</keyword>
<keyword>magnetoresistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;It has been found that a small magnetic field (&lt;300 mT) can substantial change the electroluminescence, photoluminescence, photocurrent, electrical injection current in nonmagnetic organic semiconductors. It is generally believed that these magnetic field effects (MFE) are related to the spin dependent processes in organic semiconductor. However, the origin of MFE is still not well understood. In this dissertation, we investigate the underlying mechanism for magnetic field effects on electroluminescence (MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt;) and magnetoresistance (MR) and demonstrate the complete tuning of MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; and MR based on our theoretical understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consider MFE arising from magnetic field sensitive intersystem crossing (ISC) and triplet charge reaction. Magnetic field can increase the singlet ratios through ISC, accounting for positive MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL. &lt;/sub&gt;Magnetic field modulated ISC strongly depends on the electron-hole pair separation distance. MFE can be enhanced by increasing the electron hole pair distance through material mixing and interplaying the electric dipole-dipole interaction. Meanwhile, two possible mechanisms corresponding for negative MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt;: triplet-triplet annihilation and triplet charge reaction are also discussed. The negative MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; is achieved through adjusting triplet density charge confinement and exciton/charge ratio, which indicates that triplet charge reaction is a dominate process accountable for negative MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significant MR and MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL &lt;/sub&gt;are observed in strong spin orbital coupling iridium complex based OLED device after introducing the non-magnetic insulating blocking PVA layer. A possible mechanism for this new interface induced MR and MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; is proposed based on magnetic field perturbed spin-spin interaction at short capture distance of inter-charge carriers. The comparative study of two strong spin orbital coupling materials Ir(ppy)&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and Ir(ppy)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(acac) with different electrical dipole moments indicate the electric dipole-dipole interaction can change  MR and MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; from short distance capture based regime  to long distance intersystem-crossing regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At last, we demonstrate the fully tuning sign of magnetic field effect on the fluorescence (MFE&lt;sub&gt;FEL&lt;/sub&gt;) and phosphorescence (MFE&lt;sub&gt;PEL&lt;/sub&gt;) by using the ISC, energy transfer and spin-spin interaction. In addition, we demonstrate a giant MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; (400%) in electrochemical cells and attribute this giant MFE&lt;sub&gt;EL&lt;/sub&gt; to Lorentz force driven ion transport and Lorentz force dependent diffusion layer thickness through convection.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1124</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2237&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1124</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2237</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-07-06T15:20:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2089431</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1124</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bin Hu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roberto S. Benson, Syed Islam, Shanfeng Wang, Ilia N. Ivanov</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>