<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Test of the Classical Model for Predicting Endurance Running Performance</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McLaughlin</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Purpose: The purpose of this investigation was to compare the &quot;classic&quot; physiological predictors of endurance performance (V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;,%V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;at LT, and RE) with a treadmill performance test (PTV) to see which best predicts performance in a simulated 16 km time trial. A secondary purpose was to identify physiological factors related to PTV. &lt;strong&gt;Methods: &lt;/strong&gt;Seventeen healthy, well-trained distance runners (10 males, 7 females) underwent laboratory testing to determine maximal oxygen uptake (V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;), running economy (RE), percentage of maximal oxygen uptake at the lactate threshold (%V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; at LT); running velocity at the lactate threshold (LT) and peak treadmill running velocity (PTV) for predicting performance in a 16 km time trial. &lt;strong&gt;Results: &lt;/strong&gt;Regression analysis revealed that V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;, PTV, and RE were highly correlated with the distance running performance and together explained 92.5% of the variation in run time. Stepwise analysis showed that 92% of the total variance in 16 km run time was accounted for by V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;and RE. When the calculated variable velocity at V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;(vV̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;) was added to the model the R&lt;sup&gt;2 &lt;/sup&gt;increased to 0.954 and Stepwise analysis identified vV̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;as the best single predictor accounting for 94.4% of the total variance in 16 km run time. &lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; Among well-trained subjects heterogeneous in V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;and running performance, velocity at V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;is the best predictor of running performance because it integrates both maximal aerobic power and the economy of running, while %V̇O&lt;sub&gt;2max &lt;/sub&gt;at LT contributes little to the prediction model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Words: &lt;/strong&gt;endurance performance, distance running, oxygen uptake, running economy, lactate threshold, peak treadmill velocity&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4286</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5984&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4286</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5984</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-07T06:56:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9988684</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4286</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward T. Howley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr., Dixie L. Thompson, Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>