<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1616-Plant Nutrition and Fertilizers for Greenhouse Production</title>
<publication-date>1999-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Greenhouse</keyword>
<keyword>Plant Nutrition</keyword>
<keyword>Fertilizer</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Horticulture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This publication is one of three in a series that covers the basics of developing a nutritional program for producing container-grown plants in greenhouses. A complete nutrition program encompasses the fertilizers, media and water used. The first section in &lt;strong&gt;Plant Nutrition and Fertilizers for Greenhouse Production&lt;/strong&gt; develops background information about plant nutrition that growers need to understand before discussing which fertilizers to use. The second section covers the range of fertilizers that growers can choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second publication in the series, &lt;strong&gt;Irrigation Water Quality for Greenhouse Production&lt;/strong&gt; (PB 1617), examines the effect of water quality on a greenhouse nutritional program. The third publication, &lt;strong&gt;Growing Media for Greenhouse Production&lt;/strong&gt; (PB 1618), describes the important physical and chemical properties of growing media, media testing procedures and interpretation of test results. The objective of this series of publications is to provide basic information that will allow greenhouse operators to develop a nutritional program for their specific business.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexcomhort/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;amp;context=utk_agexcomhort&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>greenhouseproduction</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-10T11:01:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Commercial Horticulture</publication-title>
<context-key>1213306</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexcomhort/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1616-1M-2/99 E12-2015-00-104-99</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-10T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1999-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>