<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Air Stripping of Volatile Organic Compounds from Groundwater: An Evaluation of a Centrifugal Vapor-Liquid Contactor</title>
<publication-date>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Singh</lname>
<fname>Surinder</fname>
<mname>Paul</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The performance of a centrifugal vapor-liquid contactor equipped with high specific surface area packing (&gt;2000 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;) was evaluated for air stripping of jet fuel components from groundwater. Hydraulic test data indicated that the Sherwood flooding correlation which has been proposed for use in designing centrifugal vapor-liquid contactors overestimates the rotational speeds at which flooding occurs. For the mass transfer of performance, a concept of area of a transfer unit (ATU) was introduced to account for the change in fluid loading with radius of the packing torus. The ATU was found to be a strong function of the specific surface area of the packing and to a lesser extent a function of rotor speed and liquid flow rate. A correlation based on the specific surface area of the packing is proposed for predicting the ATU. A simple empirical model is also proposed for determining the power consumed in turning the packing torus at various operating conditions. Previous claims in the literature that centrifugal vapor-liquid contactor is resistant to fouling because of high shear force were found not to be valid for groundwater with high iron content.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1621</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3046&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1621</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3046</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-12T13:58:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4218845</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1621</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory D. Reed</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. M. Counce, W. T. Davis, R. B. Robinson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1989-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>