<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Response of Small and Large Rib and Round Beef Roasts of Two Degrees of Finish to Two Rates of Heat Application</title>
<publication-date>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bayne</lname>
<fname>Barbara</fname>
<mname>Hammer</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Eighty roasts consisting of paired small and large, bone-in rib and boneless top-round cuts from five low-finish and five high-finish Hereford steers were studied. One cut from each pair was roasted at 200&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F and the other at 300&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F to end points of 152&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; and 158&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F respectively, according to a balanced-lattice design. Tenderness, juiciness, and flavor were evaluated by a trained taste panel. An objective measurement of tenderness was obtained with the Warner-Bratzler Shear. Cooking loss and cooking time were determined also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuts roasted at 200&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F had lower total cooking losses, longer cooking times per pound, and were more tender than those roasted at 300&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F. The 200&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;F heat treatment afforded relatively more increase in tenderness of round cuts than of rib cuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rib roasts scored higher in tenderness, flavor, and juiciness and had lower total cooking losses and shorter cooking times per pound than round roasts. Cooking times per pound were longer and total cooking losses higher for small than large roasts. Small rounds scored and sheared more tender than large rounds but tenderness of rib cuts was not affected by size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only flavor scores were affected by degree of finish, being higher for high-finish than for low-finish cuts.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3979</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5451&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3979</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5451</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-15T07:11:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9123433</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3979</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bernadine Meyer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Grayce E. Goertz, John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>