<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The role of a glycosyltransferase, ST6Gal I in regulating viral specific T and B cell responses</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jzeng@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Zeng</lname>
<fname>Junwei</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Glycosyltransferase</keyword>
<keyword>ST6Gal I</keyword>
<keyword>B cell</keyword>
<keyword>T cell</keyword>
<keyword>IgA</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Immunity</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Glycosylation is one of the most abundant post-translational modifications of proteins. Glycoproteins participate in virtually all aspects of cellular functions. ST6Gal I is a glycosyltransferase highly expressed by B and T cells. Here, we interrogated the role of ST6Gal I in viral specific B and T cell immune responses, as well as examined how loss of this enzyme impacted viral pathogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, to understand how loss of ST6Gal I expression impacted viral specific humoral responses, we infected ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice with influenza virus. We discovered that loss of ST6Gal I expression results in both reduced influenza specific antibodies levels and decreased viral-specific antibody secreting cells numbers. Following influenza infection, mice that received ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; B cells showed reduced influenza-specific IgM responses compared to mice that received wild-type B cells. These experiments demonstrated that the expression of ST6Gal I by B cells is required for optimal viral-specific humoral response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We further examined how loss of ST6Gal I expression impacted the anti-influenza IgA response. We observed that immune ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice displayed higher viral specific IgA levels and altered sialylation of IgG and IgA, which have been implicated in a human disease, IgA nephropathy. Moreover, ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice exhibited increased immunoglobulin deposition in kidney glomeruli following influenza infection. These data suggest that ST6Gal I deficiency, together with influenza infection, may result in the initiation of a kidney disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we examined how ST6Gal I expression regulated CD8 T cell responses. We discovered that ST6Gal I is differentially expressed during CD8 T cell activation. To understand its relevance, we infected ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; mice and demonstrated that the early expansion of effector T cells was impaired in a cell intrinsic manner. Moreover, in the absence of ST6Gal I, the differentiation of CD8 T cells skewed towards memory precursor cells, whereas terminal effector cell expansion was impaired. Mechanistically, we identified delayed surface expression of IL-2Ralpha on ST6Gal I&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CD8 T cells due to impaired IL-2/IL-2R signaling. These studies implicate that ST6Gal I expression enhances early proliferation of terminal effector CD8 T cells by promoting the rapid surface expression of IL2Ralpha during acute viral infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;﻿&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1244</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2301&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1244</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2301</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-08T12:12:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2139281</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1244</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thandi M. Onami</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barry T. Rouse, Mark Y. Sangster, Tim E. Sparer, Chunlei Su</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>