<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dating, Friendship, Courtship: Developing Healthy Relationships (Women Only)</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:37:28-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>regkam2@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Jenkins</lname>
<fname>Reggie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Gender, Race, Sexuality, and Ethnicity in Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Dating, Friendship, Courtship: Developing Healthy Relationships&quot; is a powerpoint presentation that is designed for young adult women. It defines the difference between courtship, dating, and friendship. It goes into detail regarding what dating really entails and what questions to ask when going out on dates. It also explains how dating and friendships are really about self-discovery. It explains what personalities to avoid while dating and steps to take toward self-empowerment. The purpose of this presentation is an attempt to prevent future trauma and abuse within the Black community. Its also an attempt to empower young ladies by providing a thorough understanding of dating, courtship and healthy friendships with their male counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/15</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1207&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>15</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1207</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-07T18:57:47-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1207/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13581338</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/15</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;My purpose of having this discussion with young ladies to provide a perspective that many attendees may not have heard. I&#39;ve spoken to hundreds of young ladies ages 11 to 20 from various events in the past 10 years. I believe my experience as an educator and child&#39;s advocate will benefit those attending. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>