<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A statistical investigation of normal regional intra-subject heterogeneity of brain metabolism and perfusion by F-18 FDG and O-15 H2O PET imaging</title>
<publication-date>2006-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Wong</lname>
<fname>Ching-yee</fname>
<mname>O.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jathie@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Medical Center</institution>
<lname>Thie</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Gaskill</lname>
<fname>Marianne</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Ponto</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Hill</lname>
<fname>Jack</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Tian</lname>
<fname>Hai-yan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Balon</lname>
<fname>Helena</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Wu</lname>
<fname>Dafang</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Fink-Bennett</lname>
<fname>Darlene</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>William Beaumont Hospital</institution>
<lname>Nagle</lname>
<fname>Conrad</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definite evaluation of the regional cerebral heterogeneity using perfusion and metabolism by a single modality of PET imaging has not been well addressed. Thus a statistical analysis of voxel variables from identical brain regions on metabolic and perfusion PET images was carried out to determine characteristics of the regional heterogeneity of F-18 FDG and O-15 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O cerebral uptake in normal subjects.  &lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourteen normal subjects with normal CT and/or MRI and physical examination including MMSE were scanned by both F-18 FDG and O-15 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O PET within same day with head-holder and facemask. The images were co-registered and each individual voxel counts (Q) were normalized by the gloabl maximal voxel counts (M) as R = Q/M. The voxel counts were also converted to z-score map by z = (Q - mean)/SD. Twelve pairs of ROIs (24 total) were systematically placed on the z-score map at cortical locations 15-degree apart and identically for metabolism and perfusion. Inter- and intra-subject correlation coefficients (r) were computed, both globally and hemispherically, from metabolism and perfusion: between regions for the same tracer and between tracers for the same region. Moments of means and histograms were computed globally along with asymmetric indices as their hemispherical differences.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical investigations verified with data showed that, for a given scan, correlation analyses are expectedly alike regardless of variables (Q, R, z) used. The varieties of correlation (r&#39;s) of normal subjects, showing symmetry, were mostly around 0.8 and with coefficient of variations near 10%. Analyses of histograms showed non-Gaussian behavior (skew = -0.3 and kurtosis = 0.4) of metabolism on average, in contrast to near Gaussian perfusion.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The co-registered cerebral metabolism and perfusion z maps demonstrated regional heterogeneity but with attractively low coefficient of variations in the correlation markers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biolpubs/12</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1011&amp;amp;context=utk_biolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>12</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-11T11:49:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- General Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4306066</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biolpubs/12</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>BMC Nuclear Medicine 2006, 6:4 doi:10.1186/1471-2385-6-4</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-07-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>