<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Long Range Interdiction: Effects Based Justification of the B-1B Lancer Aircraft</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Stanley</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to evaluate the B-1B aircraft for the land-based, long-range, ground attack mission and to use that evaluation to support my belief that the B-1B aircraft provides a better platform than U.S. Naval fighter aircraft for the same, based on the effects that each aircraft delivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One flight totaling 6.5 hours was flown by the author in the B-1B aircraft during daylight visual meteorological conditions (VMC) and included low level flight, aerial refueling, low altitude weapons delivery, threat simulation at an Electronic warfare range, and terminal area operations. This flight was used to evaluate the B-1B aircraft in a test environment and concentrated mainly on aircraft flying qualities. Additionally, thirty-three F/A-18 flights were flown by the author during actual combat operations from the flight deck of the USS John C. Stennis, in support of actual combat operations in Afghanistan during Operation Enduring Freedom. The contrast in effects based capabilities between the F/A-18 and the B-1B form the basis of this thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the U.S. Navy’s approach to long range interdiction was revolutionary, compared to how the U.S. Navy traditionally conducts flight operations, it was lacking in the effectiveness afforded through the use of the B-1B aircraft, primarily due to the B-1B’s superior range, endurance, and payload. Quantitative and qualitative findings regarding the flying qualities, weapons systems, and overall aircraft performance of the B-1B support the continued development of the B-1B aircraft and its inclusion as a critical weapons platform in future conflict planning and execution.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2088</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3453&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2088</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3453</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T11:10:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4663683</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2088</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank G. Collins, Charles T. N. Paludan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>