<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Regulatory Perspective on Nuclear Cyber Security: The Fundamental Issues</title>
<publication-date>2020-07-06T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>arinzeuchechukwu@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Information and Communication Technology (ICT) Unit, Department of Radiological Safety, Nigerian Nuclear Regulatory Authority, Abuja.</institution>
<lname>Arinze</lname>
<fname>Uchechukwu</fname>
<mname>Christian</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>olumide.longe@aun.edu.ng</email>
<institution>Department of Information Systems, School of IT &amp; Computing, American University of Nigeria, Yola.</institution>
<lname>Longe</lname>
<fname>Olumide</fname>
<mname>Babatope</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>agozie.eneh@unn.edu.ng</email>
<institution>Computer Science Department, University of Nigeria, Nsukka</institution>
<lname>Eneh</lname>
<fname>Agozie</fname>
<mname>Hyacinth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Cyber security</keyword>
<keyword>nuclear security</keyword>
<keyword>nuclear power plants</keyword>
<keyword>critical digital assets</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are living in a digital and information-driven age; hence need to retain information on virtually every aspect of our lives, nuclear information inclusive. Security in computer systems is strongly related to the notion of dependability. For such system to be reliable and secure in a nuclear facility, unauthorized logic changes must be prevented - confidentiality, field device inputs and outputs must remain immutable throughout their usable lifetime - integrity, and everything should remain in an operable state - availability. The dynamic and complex nature of cyber threats has made it a serious challenge to secure computer systems in nuclear facilities. Despite the adoption of varied cyber security services, policies, mechanisms, strategies and regulatory frameworks like confidentiality, integrity, availability, non-repudiation, encipherment, defence-in-depth, design basis threat, IAEA technical guidance documents such as: GS-R-1, GS-R-2, NSS13, NSS17, NST036, NST045, and NST047, IEEE standard 7-4.3.2-2010, NIST SP 800-53, NIST SP 800-82, NEI 08-09 and country-specific requirements such as: 10 CFR 73.54, 10 CFR 73.1, RG 5.71 (USNRC), KINS/RG-N08.22 (South Korea) respectively, the threats remain persistent. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;This paper is aimed at providing a regulatory perspective on nuclear cyber security, its relationship to nuclear safety and security, regulatory requirements and cyber security global best practice recommendations and strategies to prevent its occurrence. This is imperative as Nigeria prepares to join the league of countries with operational nuclear power plants and reactors by its approval and adoption of the nuclear power programme roadmap in 2007.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/ijns/vol6/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1096&amp;amp;context=ijns&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1096</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-11-29T05:36:16-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ijns/article/1096/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>International Journal of Nuclear Security</publication-title>
<context-key>11167135</context-key>
<submission-path>ijns/vol6/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Special thanks to the Management of the Nigerian Nuclear Regulatory Authority, under the leadership of Professor Lawrence Anikwe Dim, for his support and encouragement to embark on this research.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.7290/ijns060103</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xdeaaab0)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-07-06T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Regulatory Perspective on Nuclear Cyber Security: The Fundamental Issues</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>