<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A toxicity study of low-dose rate half-body irradiation and chemotherapy in dogs with lymphoma</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mfry@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fry</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Dog</keyword>
<keyword>lymphoma</keyword>
<keyword>radiotherapy</keyword>
<keyword>toxicity</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Thirteen dogs with previously untreated multicentric lymphoma were enrolled in a prospective study investigating the effects of low-dose rate total body irradiation (TBI) and chemotherapy. Dogs received either 6 or 8 Gy TBI in half-body fractions, 2 weeks apart. Toxicity consisted of mild to moderate haematological and gastrointestinal (GI) signs. One dog died from treatment complications. Anorexia was noted independent of dose. Haematological toxicity was more common and more severe after 8 Gy treatment. GI toxicity was more likely postcaudal half-body irradiation with 8 Gy. Other than leukotrichia, late effects from radiation were not observed. Results indicated that haematological and nonhaematological toxicity was dose dependent. However, the protocol was well tolerated and treatment intensification using a 2-week inter-radiation interval was possible in all dogs treated with 6 Gy. Preliminary survival data for these dogs were very encouraging, providing a strong rationale to analyse the efficacy of low-dose rate irradiation (LDRI) in canine lymphoma.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/45</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>45</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1044</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T07:18:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2323230</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/45</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Veterinary and Comparative Oncology</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>