<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Inclusive Access: A multi-institutional study of academic outcomes from a statewide community college automatic billing eTextbook pilot</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>spica@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Spica</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Textbook costs</keyword>
<keyword>college textbooks</keyword>
<keyword>Inclusive Access</keyword>
<keyword>community college affordability</keyword>
<keyword>course material costs</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Technology</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In response to issues related to the high cost of textbooks and other course materials, Inclusive Access programs allow the cost of a discounted eTextbook and/or courseware to be automatically added to a student’s tuition bill at the time of course registration (McKenzie, 2017). Touted for their ability to lower costs and provide students with access to materials on or before the first day of class, automatic billing programs have become increasingly prolific across the higher education landscape. At the same time, research into many aspects of the program’s impact and efficacy remains lacking. This study examined academic outcomes from an Inclusive Access pilot launched fall 2019 by Tennessee’s largest system of public higher education. Results from across 13 community colleges, 41 course areas, and 141 courses indicated no significant differences in either overall or population-specific academic outcomes between the Inclusive Access pilot semester and the two prior falls in which the courses were taught. The findings demonstrate that benefits accrued from relative cost-savings and/or Day One Access were insufficient to produce significant improvements in academic outcomes, with no significant differences in outcomes also evidenced for non-White, federal Pell grant award recipients, and/or non-traditional students over the age of 25. These results suggest that measures beyond cost-savings and Day One access, such as hidden costs, the need for perpetual access, and the ultimate repercussions of deferred costs to student debt, should also be considered when evaluating ways to provide students with affordable course materials that enable high-quality, equitable learning experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_edleadpubs/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_edleadpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-10T15:08:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Educational Leadership and Policy Studies Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>22422134</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_edleadpubs/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This preprint article has been accepted for publication in Community College Journal of Research and Practice, published by Taylor &amp; Francis. The final authenticated version will be available online, at which time this document will be updated with the DOI, official citation, and a direct link to the official version of record.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Spica, E. (in press). Inclusive Access: A multi-institutional study of academic outcomes from a statewide community college automatic billing eTextbook pilot. Community College Journal of Research and Practice. https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.23965.03044</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.23965.03044</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2021-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Community College Journal of Research and Practice</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Pre-print</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>