<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Validating Geospatial Analysis with Community Risk Perception Survey in Big Island, Hawaii</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-08T11:53:16-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dayers3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ayers</lname>
<fname>Darcy Ann</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geographic Information Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Human Geography</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Cultural Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Military vehicle-generated particulate matter released into the atmosphere are possible concerns for human health. The author’s prior geospatial research has been to identify, using GIS analysis, the local populations surrounding a military installation in Hawaii that are most at-risk from the vehicle-generated particulate matter. A continuation of the past research, this project aims to assess the perceived impact of the identified dust pollution among local residents by conducting a survey through both qualitative and quantitative methods. The survey of health and public perception is then used to validate the model developed in the previous GIS analysis. This research is a contribution to the ongoing pursuit of achieving solutions to social problems through geospatial applications. Socially just environmental sustainability can begin with an identification of a problem, but must be pursued by community awareness and education. This project uses geospatial statistical analysis as a means to progress from an identified and quantified environmental problem to an assessment of the societal perception of its impact, which in turn presents an opportunity in which a community can arrive at a cooperative, sustainable solution to their environmental concerns.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/artsandsciences/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1134&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1134</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-16T11:28:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>10025762</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/artsandsciences/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Raja Swamy</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>