<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tungsten Alkyl Alkylidyne and Bis(Alkylidene) Complexes. Their Unusual Inter-Conversion and Reactions with Phosphines, Dioxygen and Water</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Morton</lname>
<fname>Laurel</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation focuses on the unique chemistry of &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;0 alkylidyne and bis &lt;em&gt;(alkylidene) complexes with β-silicon atoms. The goals of this dissertation &lt;/em&gt;research were to prepare and characterize these new &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;0 transition metal complexes, to study their reactivities including thermodynamics and kinetics of the inter-conversion between the alkylidyne and &lt;em&gt;bis&lt;/em&gt;(alkylidene) complexes, and to explore the mechanism of the reactions of O2 or water with &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;0 alkylidyne complexes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A summary of the research in this dissertation is provided in Chapter 1.Chapter 2 reports the study of an unusual exchange between new alkyl alkylidyne and &lt;em&gt;bis&lt;/em&gt;(alkylidene) complexes promoted by phosphine coordination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A novel &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;0 tungsten alkylidyne complex (Me3SiCH2)3W(≡CSiMe3)(PMe3) (&lt;strong&gt;3a&lt;/strong&gt;) was prepared from (Me3SiCH2)3W≡CSiMe3 (&lt;strong&gt;4a&lt;/strong&gt;) and PMe3, and found to undergo a rare exchange with its &lt;em&gt;bis&lt;/em&gt;(alkylidene) tautomer (Me3SiCH2)2W(=CHSiMe3)2(PMe3) (&lt;strong&gt;3b&lt;/strong&gt;). The thermodynamics of this equilibrium were investigated by variable-temperature31P NMR to give the thermodynamic parameters Δ&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;o and Δ&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;o of the exchange. Kinetic studies show that the α-hydrogen exchange between &lt;strong&gt;3a &lt;/strong&gt;and &lt;strong&gt;3b &lt;/strong&gt;follows first-order reversible kinetics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activation parameters Δ&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;≠ and Δ&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;≠ for the forward (&lt;strong&gt;3a &lt;/strong&gt;→ &lt;strong&gt;3b&lt;/strong&gt;) and reverse reactions (&lt;strong&gt;3b &lt;/strong&gt;→ &lt;strong&gt;3a&lt;/strong&gt;) are reported. Reaction of &lt;strong&gt;4a &lt;/strong&gt;with PMe2Ph to give alkylalkylidyne &lt;strong&gt;5a &lt;/strong&gt;and &lt;em&gt;bis&lt;/em&gt;(alkylidene) &lt;strong&gt;5b &lt;/strong&gt;tautomeric mixture has also been studied, and the exchange here is compared with that involving &lt;strong&gt;3a &lt;/strong&gt;and &lt;strong&gt;3b&lt;/strong&gt;. Preparation and characterization of two new alkyl alkylidene alkylidyne complexes, and kinetic studies of their formation are presented in Chapter 3. The &lt;strong&gt;3a &lt;/strong&gt;º &lt;strong&gt;3b &lt;/strong&gt;equilibrium mixture under heating in the presence of excess PMe3 was found to undergo α-hydrogen abstraction and convert to (Me3SiCH2)(Me3SiCH=)W(≡CSiMe3)(PMe3)2 (&lt;strong&gt;8a-b&lt;/strong&gt;). This reaction follows second-order kinetics – first order with respect to &lt;strong&gt;3 &lt;/strong&gt;and PMe3. In the presence of excess PMe3, pseudo first-order kinetics was observed to give the activation parameters Δ&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;≠ and Δ&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;≠ for the reaction. Preparation of(Me3SiCH2)(Me3SiCH=)W(≡CSiMe3)(PMe2Ph)2 (&lt;strong&gt;9a-b&lt;/strong&gt;) is also reported and compared with the formation of &lt;strong&gt;8a-b&lt;/strong&gt;. Chapter 4 describes the synthesis of (Me3SiCH2)3(Me3SiC≡)W←O=PMe3(&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;) and its reaction with O2 to yield an unusual oxo-siloxy complex O=W(OSiMe3)(CH2SiMe3)3 (&lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt;). Unexpected –SiMe3 migration from an alkylidyne to an oxo ligand occurs in the reaction. In the absence of O=PMe3, the reaction of (Me3SiCH2)3W≡CSiMe3 (&lt;strong&gt;4a&lt;/strong&gt;) and O2 did not yield &lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;12 &lt;/strong&gt;was isolated as (Me3SiCH2)3(Me3SiC≡)W←O=W(OSiMe3)(CH2SiMe3)3 (&lt;strong&gt;13&lt;/strong&gt;), an adduct with (Me3SiCH2)3W≡CSiMe3 (&lt;strong&gt;4a&lt;/strong&gt;). Studies with 18O-labelled 18O2 have been conducted to determine whether the oxygen atoms in &lt;strong&gt;12 &lt;/strong&gt;come from 18O2. Highresolution mass spectrometry (HRMS) was used to analyze the products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5 reports the study of the reaction of (Me3SiCH2)3W≡CSiMe3 (&lt;strong&gt;4a&lt;/strong&gt;) with H2O and the unexpected formation of CH4 and &lt;strong&gt;12 &lt;/strong&gt;in this reaction. The reaction of &lt;strong&gt;4a &lt;/strong&gt;with D2O showed α-hydrogen scrambling during the reaction and formation of methane isotopomers, which were studied by HRMS. Reactions of (Me3SiCH2)3(Me3SiC≡)W←O=PMe3 (&lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;) with H2O were also studied, and found to yield the oxo complex &lt;strong&gt;12 &lt;/strong&gt;as well.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2258</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3767&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2258</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3767</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-11T13:02:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4699915</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2258</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ziling (Ben) Xue</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Craig E. Barnes, Charles D. Feigerle, X. Peter Zhang, John R. Collier</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>