<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The nuclear envelope localization of DYT1 dystonia torsinA-ΔE requires the SUN1 LINC complex component</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-31T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mjungwir@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jungwirth</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dkumar1@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kumar</lname>
<fname>Dhivya</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>yjeong3@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jeong</lname>
<fname>Danielle</fname>
<mname>Y.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>groodchi@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Goodchild</lname>
<fname>Rose</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>torsinA</keyword>
<keyword>LINC complex</keyword>
<keyword>AAA+ protein</keyword>
<keyword>Nuclear Envelope</keyword>
<keyword>SUN1</keyword>
<keyword>DYT1 dystonia</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Cell and Developmental Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DYT1 dystonia is an autosomal dominant neurological condition caused by a mutation that removes a single glutamic acid residue (ΔE) from the torsinA (torA) AAA+ protein. TorA appears to possess a nuclear envelope (NE) localized activity that requires Lamina-Associated-Polypeptide 1 (LAP1), which is an inner nuclear membrane localized torA-binding partner. Although hypoactive, the DYT1 dystonia torA-ΔE isoform often concentrates in the NE, suggesting that torA-ΔE also interacts with an NE-localized binding partner.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We confirm that NE-localized torA-ΔE does not co-immunoprecipitate with LAP1, and find that torA-ΔE continues to concentrate in the NE of cells that lack LAP1. Instead, we find that variability in torA-ΔE localization correlates with the presence of the SUN-domain and Nesprin proteins that assemble into the LINC complex. We also find that siRNA depletion of SUN1, but not other LINC complex components, removes torA-ΔE from the NE. In contrast, the LAP1-dependent NE-accumulation of an ATP-locked torA mutant is unaffected by loss of LINC complex proteins. This SUN1 dependent torA-ΔE localization requires the torA membrane association domain, as well as a putative substrate-interaction residue, Y147, neither of which are required for torA interaction with LAP1. We also find that mutation of these motifs, or depletion of SUN1, decreases the amount of torA-WT that colocalizes with NE markers, indicating that each also underlies a normal NE-localized torA binding interaction.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These data suggest that the disease causing ΔE mutation promotes an association between torA and SUN1 that is distinct to the interaction between LAP1 and ATP-bound torA. This evidence for two NE-localized binding partners suggests that torA may act on multiple substrates and/or possesses regulatory co-factor partners. In addition, finding that the DYT1 mutation causes abnormal association with SUN1 implicates LINC complex dysfunction in DYT1 dystonia pathogenesis, and suggests a gain-of-function activity contributes to this dominantly inherited disease.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/71</coverpage-url>
<label>71</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1069</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-11T10:54:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4305816</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/71</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>BMC Cell Biology 2011, 12:24 doi:10.1186/1471-2121-12-24</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>