<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Website Analysis of the University of Tennessee’s Peer Institutions to Assess their Support of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender People</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The Commission for Lesbian, Gay Bisexual and Transgender People at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>LGBT</keyword>
<keyword>Lesbian</keyword>
<keyword>Gay</keyword>
<keyword>Bisexual</keyword>
<keyword>and Transgender</keyword>
<keyword>Equity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Gender and Sexuality</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report is based upon activities of the Research Committee, UTK’s Commission for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) People, conducted during spring 2007. The objectives of the report include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assess the support provided to LGBT people at the University of Tennessee’s (UT) peer institutions (based on website analysis).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To develop a methodology to quantitatively and qualitatively analyze the support provided to LGBT people at UT’s peer institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a checklist that provides a quantitative comparison of the support provided to LGBT people at UT’s peer institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide a detailed qualitative analysis of the support provided to LGBT people at UT’s peer institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To generate an initial assessment of the UT’s support of LGBT people as compared to its peer institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future applications as follow-up to this report will include a detailed assessment of UT’s performance in terms of its support of LGBT people based on comparison to its peer institutions (e.g., the Research Committee plans to develop and conduct a quantitative survey assessing and evaluating the UT’s campus climate for LGBT people). Findings in this report are based solely on information found on the websites of UT’s peer institutions. Follow-up research will involve establishing contacts with students, faculty, and staff at UT’s peer institutions to verify the accuracy, currency, and coverage extent of information presented on the websites of the select institutions. Suggestions for interventions and concrete strategies in support of LGBT people at UTK will be made to insure that UT does not stray far behind its peer institutions in terms of its support of LGBT people.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lgbtrepo/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;amp;context=utk_lgbtrepo&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-07-16T11:17:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Commission for LGBT - Reports, Minutes, Events and Other Documents</publication-title>
<context-key>901139</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lgbtrepo/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2009-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>