<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rejection Enhanced Off-Lattice Kinetic Monte Carlo</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hruzayqa@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Ruzayqat</lname>
<fname>Hamza</fname>
<mname>Mahmoud</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>kmc</keyword>
<keyword>off-lattice kmc</keyword>
<keyword>rejection</keyword>
<keyword>atomic simulation</keyword>
<keyword>lattice</keyword>
<keyword>kinetic monte carlo</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;We introduce a new kinetic Monte Carlo (KMC) algorithm for off-lattice simulation. In off-lattice KMC one needs to calculate the rates for all possible moves from the current state by searching the energy landscape for index-1 saddle points surrounding the current basin of attraction. We introduce a rejection scheme where the true rates are replaced by rate estimates. This is done by first associating each saddle point with a key atom defined to be the atom that moves the most or that corresponds to the largest energy change if the transition were to take a place, then constructing an estimate for the total rate associated with each atom by using a nearest-neighbor bond count. These estimates allow one to select a set of possible transitions, one of which is accepted or rejected based on a localized saddle point search focused on a particular atom. In principle, this allows a performance boost that scales with the number of particles in the system. We test the method on a growing two-species nanocluster with an emerging core-shell structure bound by Lennard-Jones potential. In addition to that, we give a detailed review for the dimer method used in this study to locate index-1 saddle points on the potential energy surface.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5385</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6921&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5385</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6921</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545398</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5385</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Tim Schulze</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ohannes Karakashian, Steven Wise, Haixuan Xu</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6394-0695</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>