<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Development of APCI Mass Spectrometry Based Systems for Quantitative Real-Time Monitoring of Process-Scale Homogenous and Heterogeneous Reactions</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>zzhu4@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Zhu</lname>
<fname>Zhenqian</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>FIA</keyword>
<keyword>APCI-MS</keyword>
<keyword>industrial process control</keyword>
<keyword>quantitative real-time reaction monitoring</keyword>
<keyword>batch slurry reaction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Analytical Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The dissertation presents solutions to monitor industrial chemical processes quantitatively in real time by mass spectrometry. Chapter 1 presents the background of atmospheric pressure chemical ionization mass spectrometry (APCI-MS). Chapters 2-6 present methods developed based on flow injection analysis coupled to atmospheric pressure chemical ionization mass spectrometry (FIA/APCI-MS) for quantitative real-time monitoring of homogeneous and heterogeneous reactions conducted at molar concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2 introduces auto-sampling FIA/APCI-MS with the ability to overcome potential sample overloading when molar concentration samples were analyzed without sample pretreatment procedures. A homogenous Michael-addition reaction between phenethylamine and acrylonitrile was conducted at room temperature and monitored quantitatively in real time at 1.63 M (molar) level. In chapter 3, auto-sampling FIA/APCI-MS was adapted for the quantitative real-time monitoring of a transesterification reaction, methanolysis of glycerol trioctanoate, which proceeded as a homogenous liquid system and a heterogeneous bi-phasic liquid-liquid system at an alcohol-to-oil molar ratio of 30:1 and 6:1, respectively. Simultaneous quantification of major compounds including two intermediates was achieved using calibrations based on the analysis of simulated reaction mixtures of standards and validated by parallel off-line reaction monitoring with HPLC/APCI-MS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4 introduces slurry FIA/APCI-MS with the ability to overcome potential instrumental clogging and sample overloading in quantitative real-time monitoring of a heterogeneous solid-liquid system, i.e. a batch slurry reaction. Slurry samples up to 30% (w/w) were successfully quantified. Chapter 5 describes an alternative slurry FIA/APCI-MS setup to accommodate a different mass spectrometer, aiming to prepare the slurry FIA/APCI-MS method to be used in quantitative real-time monitoring of a model batch slurry reaction at DuPont Crop Protection where a similar mass spectrometer was to be used. In Chapter 6, slurry FIA/APCI-MS was adapted for the quantitative real-time monitoring of a heterogeneous-catalyzed Pechmann condensation reaction using 50 g/L silica supported perchloric acid as catalyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7 presents a study on the differentiation of underivatized monosaccharides from their stereoisomers using APCI quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry (QTOF-MS). Identities of ions were assigned after accurate mass measurement by QTOF-MS. Distinctive fragmentation patterns were used to distinguish isomers of hexoses, methyl D-glucopyranosides, hexosamins and &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-acetylhexosamines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 8 presents the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2782</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4025&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2782</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4025</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-26T08:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5215382</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2782</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John E. Bartmess</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jon P. Camden, Robert N. Compton, Stephen J. Paddison</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>