<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Contributions of Translocation to Northern Bobwhite Population Recovery</title>
<publication-date>2017-11-08T08:27:04-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>clay@pinelandplantation.com</email>
<institution>Albany Quail Project &amp; Dixie Plantation Research, Albany, GA</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>tterhune@talltimbers.org</email>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Terhune</lname>
<fname>Theron</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
<suffix>II</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>bpalmer@talltimbers.org</email>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Palmer</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>thackstonwildlife@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Tall Timbers Research Station and Land Conservancy</institution>
<lname>Thackston</lname>
<fname>Reggie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>Florida</keyword>
<keyword>Georgia</keyword>
<keyword>habitat</keyword>
<keyword>translocation</keyword>
<keyword>NBCI</keyword>
<keyword>National Bobwhite Conservation Initiative</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Natural Resources and Conservation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The National Bobwhite Conservation Initiative (NBCI 2.0) is a range-wide plan for recovering northern bobwhites (&lt;em&gt;Colinus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;; hereafter, bobwhite[s]). Using geospatial analysis informed by expertise from practitioners, the plan categorizes landscapes into restoration potential by weighing biological constraints and opportunities such that targeted habitat management will produce bobwhite population growth. A fundamental assumption of the NBCI 2.0 for achieving recovery goals is that bobwhite source populations currently exist on the landscape at densities necessary to (re)colonize newly established or improved habitat. However, we have found that these source populations can be very low or non-existent, especially in northern tiers of the bobwhite distribution. In 1997, we initiated research to evaluate bobwhite population response following translocation using birds from high density populations to newly developed habitats with low bobwhite numbers (ha). We worked collaboratively with the Georgia Department of Natural Resources in 2006 to develop and implement a wild bobwhite translocation policy based on key findings from that research. Since that time 3,866 wild bobwhites have been trapped and translocated from properties in the Albany and Greater Red Hills region of Florida and Georgia to 13 recipient sites in 6 states (AL, GA, MD, NC, NJ, and SC) on 29,780 ha. A typical translocation was conducted for 2 – 3 years in March by capturing, tagging and transporting birds overnight for release at an average rate of 1 bird per 7 ha per property. Prior to translocation, each recipient property underwent extensive habitat restoration and agreed to conduct a monitoring program including spring whistle counts and fall covey counts before, during, and after translocation. Bobwhite populations increased on recipient sites from an average of 0.38 (CI: 0.13 – 0.63) birds per hectare to 2.2 (CI: 1.45 – 2.95) birds per hectare resulting in the establishment of huntable wild bobwhite populations adding approximately 42,714 bobwhites to the landscape. The value of these wild bobwhites was determined to average $736 per translocated bird bringing the total value of birds donated from the Albany and Greater Red Hills region for translocation to $2,844,564. The establishment of population hubs through translocation contributes to population recovery efforts outlined in the NBCI 2.0, especially where source populations are limited.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol8/iss1/46</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1518&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>46</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_translocation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1518</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-10-31T07:13:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10974431</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol8/iss1/46</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Contributions of Translocation to Northern Bobwhite Population Recovery</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Sisson.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>Sisson.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1518&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
<description>Powerpoint presentation</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>