<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Prevalence of Copper Resistance among Foliar Bacterial Pathogens of Tomato in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmixon5@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Mixon</lname>
<fname>Jonathon</fname>
<mname>Thomas</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Bacteria</keyword>
<keyword>Copper</keyword>
<keyword>Tomato</keyword>
<keyword>Resistance</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Plant Pathology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Foliar bacterial diseases are among the most important diseases of tomato. Bacterial spot is caused by four species: &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas euvesicatoria&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;X. vesicatoria&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;X. perforans&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;X. gardneri&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;hereafter referred to as&lt;em&gt; Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt; spp. Bacterial speck is caused by &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas syringae &lt;/em&gt;pv.&lt;em&gt; tomato &lt;/em&gt;and bacterial canker is caused by &lt;em&gt;Clavibacter michiganensis &lt;/em&gt;subsp.&lt;em&gt; michiganensis&lt;/em&gt;. Fixed copper products are relied upon extensively for control, due to a lack of effective and economical alternatives.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Copper resistance in bacterial spot and speck pathogens has been reported worldwide. Copper resistance quite likely exists in Tennessee, but the extent has never been determined. The objectives of this study were to (i) optimize the conditions for in-vitro determinations of the level of copper sensitivity in &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt; spp., &lt;em&gt;P. syringae&lt;/em&gt; pv. &lt;em&gt;tomato&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;C. michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; subsp. &lt;em&gt;michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; cultures in a protocol that would be practical for processing large sample numbers, and validation with bioassays; (ii) determine the incidence and distribution of copper resistance in Tennessee populations of these pathogens. Parameters selected for &lt;em&gt;in-vitro&lt;/em&gt; copper resistance testing were sucrose peptone agar adjusted to pH 6.8 (&lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas &lt;/em&gt;spp. and&lt;em&gt; C. michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; subsp. &lt;em&gt;michiganensis&lt;/em&gt;) or 6.2 (&lt;em&gt;P. syringae&lt;/em&gt; pv. &lt;em&gt;tomato&lt;/em&gt;), amended with 2-(&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid (20 mM) and CuSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·5H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O (200 µ[micro]g/ml), and amended with 200 µ[micro]g/ml CuSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·5H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O. After solidifying, media were promptly streaked with cells produced on solid agar, and incubated for three days. Bacterial growth was visually assessed on a 0 to 10 scale. For rapid identification, a multiplex PCR protocol was developed and used successfully to detect the three pathogens&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;from symptomatic plants. When plants were co-inoculated with &lt;em&gt;P. syringae &lt;/em&gt;pv. &lt;em&gt;tomato&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;C. michiganensis &lt;/em&gt;subsp.&lt;em&gt; michiganensis&lt;/em&gt;, the latter could not be detected. As a result, alternative methods of pathogen identification were employed in the field survey. A survey of 19 fields representing 195 acres in six Tennessee counties during the 2010 and 2011 growing seasons, 162 were identified as &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt; spp., none as &lt;em&gt;P.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;syringae&lt;/em&gt; pv. &lt;em&gt;tomato&lt;/em&gt;, and four as &lt;em&gt;C.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; subsp. m&lt;em&gt;ichiganensis.&lt;/em&gt; Copper resistance was detected in 95.1% of &lt;em&gt;Xanthomonas&lt;/em&gt; spp. isolates and 4.9% were sensitive. All &lt;em&gt;C. michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; subsp. &lt;em&gt;michiganensis&lt;/em&gt; isolates were sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1187</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2243&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1187</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2243</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-12T07:46:30-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2243/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2397732</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1187</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven C. Bost</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bonnie Ownley, Carl Sams, Kimberly Gwinn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Entomology and Plant Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>