<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Studies Towards &lt;em&gt;Anti&lt;/em&gt;-Bredt Ring Systems of Natural Products</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Peters</lname>
<fname>Ulf</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Different ways for the synthesis of &lt;em&gt;anti&lt;/em&gt;-Bredt ring systems of natural products have been explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An intended Favorskii rearrangement-divinylcyclopropane rearrangement to lead to the bicyclo[4.3.1] decadiene ring system was not accomplished. An envisioned tandem cyclopropanation-divinycyclopropane rearrangement of 2,3-divinyhex-2-enol did not furnish the desired bicyclo[4.4.1]undecadiene system, either, because cyclopropane occurred on the exocyclic double bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of cyclopropanation studies on various cyclohexenols, an α-silyl-α-diazoethyl acetate was employed as tether. It could be removed by protodesilylation or oxidative cleavage to give a 1-(carboxylic ester)-cyclopropane or a 1-(carboxylic easter)-1-hydroxy cyclopropane derivative, respectively. Cyclopropanation general occurred on the less substituted more electron rich double bond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epoxidation of 2,3-divinylhex-2-enol with subsequent Cope rearrangement furnished the &lt;em&gt;anti&lt;/em&gt;-Bredt oxabicyclo[4.4.1]undecadiene system that could be transformed into its regioisomer by Ireland-Claisen rearrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies of the ring-closing metathesis of a cobalt carbonyl complexed ynediene to give a 10- or 11-membered ring failed. Ring-closing metathesis of a vinylsilane furnished an eight-membered ring.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1443</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2784&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1443</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2784</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-06T11:33:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4109787</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1443</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David G. young</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Baker, John Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science in Landscape Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>