<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>HUDSON HEALTH CORRIDOR: REDEFINING THE WORKFORCE HOUSING COMMUNITY</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bburdy@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Burdy</lname>
<fname>Brianne</fname>
<mname>Michelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>housing</keyword>
<keyword>architecture</keyword>
<keyword>urbanism</keyword>
<keyword>planning</keyword>
<keyword>affordability</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Neighborhoods slated for redevelopment and revitalization within urban centers are often overtaken by luxury development due to the incentives and benefits related to return on investment in these relatively ignored areas. Developers tend to create housing that will attract higher incomes in order to gain higher returns, resulting in the creation of an exclusive area marketed to particular groups within a certain income bracket. These areas then grow in popularity, continuing to attract upper class residents, and increasing the income level of the area. The result of this type of development displaces those who previously occupied these areas because they are no longer able to afford the various options and become priced out of their homes. Those with an income below the target market in these neighborhoods are never able to occupy them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis aims to counter the problem. Instead of beginning revitalization with living options exclusive to higher incomes, these communities can instead be anchored by affordable housing options. This involves developing affordable housing marketed to the working class at the initial phase of redevelopment. By combining workforce housing with a health platform, flexible and adaptive spaces can be produced to fit a variety of family types, balance community, and maintain economic sustainability for the future. Through this approach, it is possible for different residents to find housing situations that fit their family with adaptable units for a variety of income levels. A community focus in design becomes an economic driver to produce revenue as well as an attractor of neighborhood residents to help break down barriers and perceptions commonly associated with workforce housing. Architecture has the potential to change the way in which society views and treats workforce housing and its residents. By challenging the current development process, a new approach can be created where residents feel valued and community engagement becomes the forefront of workforce housing design.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4860</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5944&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4860</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5944</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-31T08:14:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9954066</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4860</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marleen Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John McRae, Avigail Sachs</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>