<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Problems of Supervision of Principals in Knox County Elementary Schools</title>
<publication-date>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davis</lname>
<fname>Mack</fname>
<mname>Parker</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statement of the Problem: The purpose of this thesis is to make a study of the problems and practices in the supervision of instruction by Knox County Elementary School principals. Therefore it has been entitled, THE STUDY OF PROBLEMS IN THE SUPERVISION OF INSTRUCTION BY KNOX COUNTY ELEMENTARY SCHOOL PRINCIPALS. First hand information in regard to these problems was obtained by means of a questionnaire designed to gain facts and suggestions relative to average supervisory situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer is an average principal of a typical Knox County elementary school. He has his share of supervisory difficulties because he has six teachers for eight grades under his guidance. The enrollment is large and the conditions are over-crowded. He is face with the multiplicity of problems which are discussed throughout this thesis. Besides teaching during the greater part of the school day, he is burdened with office work, clerical work, welfare work, church and community activity, teachers&#39; league affiliation, and many other worthwhile activities. He realizes his inadequacy to supervise properly under such handicaps. Furthermore, he realizes that the majority of his colleagues are likewise handicapped. Therefore, one of the prime purposes of this thesis is to suggest procedures by which a principal in the average situation can more effectively supervise instruction in any particular school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter II tells how the survey and study were made. It presents the technique in successfully gaining the desired information and explains how the data yielded by a comprehensive questionnaire were organized and treated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third chapter briefly gives the results of the survey according to an appropriate classified form. No critical or interpretive statements are therein inserted. The facts are presented so that a critical analysis is facilitated for presentation in the succeeding chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter IV is an interpretation of the results based upon the responses given to the questions used in the survey, the writer&#39;s experience as a principal of one of these schools, and the experience and suggestions of eminent educational authorities. An attempt is made to suggest how principals may solve their most difficult problems in supervision. Recommendations for the improvement of the average situation are subsequently made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last chapter will suggest studies and surveys which could and should be made in the interest of improving instruction and the supervision of instruction in the elementary schools of Knox County.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2978</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4353&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2978</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4353</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-02T11:44:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6411546</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2978</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mildred A. Dawson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Florence V. Essery, S. L. Jonsten Lund</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>