<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>W089-Discharge Events</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-20T12:10:48-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Livestock</keyword>
<keyword>Waste Management</keyword>
<keyword>Conservation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;All wastewater discharges from a CAFO to waters of the state of Tennessee are prohibited. For existing CAFOs, new dairy CAFOs and new cattle CAFOs, an exception will be made when either chronic or catastrophic rainfall events cause an overflow from a facility properly designed, constructed, maintained and operated to contain all process wastewater from the operation (such as wash water, parlor water, watering system overflow, etc.), plus all runoff from a 25-year, 24-hour rainfall event. For new swine and poultry CAFOs, the exception will be made if the facility was properly designed, constructed, maintained and operated to contain all process wastewater from the operation, plus all runoff from a 100- year, 24-hour rainfall event, and chronic or catastrophic rainfall events cause an overflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If for any reason, there is a discharge to waters of the state, the producer must make oral notification to the TDEC within 24 hours, and notify the TDEC in writing within five working days of the discharge from the facility. In addition, the producer must keep a copy of the notification submitted to the TDEC together with the Nutrient Management Plan.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexani/58</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1057&amp;amp;context=utk_agexani&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>58</label>
<document-type>factsheet</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1057</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-20T12:10:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Animals/Livestock</publication-title>
<context-key>1281413</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexani/58</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-20T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>