<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spatial Distribution of Water Quality Parameters Using Kayak-Mounted Sensor</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-27T10:49:50-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hjordan3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jordan</lname>
<fname>Hayden</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the Biosystems Engineering and Soil Sciences Department of the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, water quality testing was conducted at the confluence of the New River and Clear Fork in the Big South Fork National River and Recreation Area on July 22, 2015. This testing aimed to determine the feasibility of using a kayak-mounted water quality collection system to measure the spatial distribution of water quality parameters (i.e. temperature, conductivity, pH, turbidity, and dissolved oxygen) in a given body of water. In addition to the water quality data collected by the spatial water quality analyzer, GPS and depth were collected, and the gathered data was thematically mapped in ArcGIS. Results revealed a 25-second offset between the time it took for the collection system to draw water from the river and the time it took for the system to record the water quality of that spatial point within the river. USGS Real- Time water data, as well as measurements taken in a lab setting, confirmed that the 25-second offset was a valid conclusion taken from the collected data. As a result, this study indicated that the kayak-mounted spatial water quality analyzer provides a practical means of collecting spatial water quality parameters representative of a given stretch of river.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol7/iss1/15</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1316&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>15</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1316</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-27T10:03:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>8529509</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol7/iss1/15</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>