<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Examining the Influence of Knowledge and Experience on Attitudes Toward Disability</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Giecek</lname>
<fname>Nicholas</fname>
<mname>Antoni</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>attitudes</keyword>
<keyword>adaptive sport</keyword>
<keyword>integration</keyword>
<keyword>contact theory</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined how attitudes of able-bodied individuals towards disability can be influenced by individuals with disabilities’ participation in an adaptive sport program. The &lt;i&gt;Scale of Attitudes Toward Disabled Persons&lt;/i&gt; (SADP) was used to determine if adaptive sport participation, as well as knowledge and experience on disability can create an attitudinal change regarding disability in society. The theories of the contact theory, social constructionism, and identity negotiation are all used to offer insight into if and why sport can be utilized as an effective tool in generating intrapersonal and interpersonal change. Inclusion for people with disabilities in all settings can be viewed as a benefit to society, but when paired with sport can have a higher likelihood of acceptance due to the reputation of value that most cultures combine with sport (Modell, 2007). Sport has often been a driving force in relation to equality within societies, specifically in the case of women and ethnic minorities (Harada, Siperstein, Parker, &amp; Lenox, 2011). In the same way, sport has the potential to expedite the process of gaining equal opportunity and societal acceptance in all facets of life for people with disabilities (Harada et al., 2011).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5401</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6809&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5401</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6809</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-12T18:30:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>16528527</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5401</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jason Scott</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Steven Waller, Angela Wozencroft</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>