<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Studies of High Temperature Hydrogen Related Damage in  Welded Carbon Steel Components used in  Refineries</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mbharadw@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bharadwaj</lname>
<fname>Maneel</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>HTHA</keyword>
<keyword>Hydrogen</keyword>
<keyword>API RP 941</keyword>
<keyword>Welded Flange-Pipe</keyword>
<keyword>Methane Cavities</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Metallurgy</discipline>
<discipline>Structural Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Five materials encompassing various grades of carbon steel were received from retired and ex-service petroleum refinery equipment for root-cause evaluation of High Temperature Hydrogen Attack (HTHA) damage at UTK. These materials were submitted by three contributors: Irving Oil Refinery (IOR #1110-2), Valero (#67 &amp; #1252134), and Phillips 66 (#555-S1 &amp; #555-S2) on behalf of American Petroleum Institute (API). These materials originated from various flange-to-pipe welded components that were exposed in hydrogen pressure environment at elevated temperatures (&gt; 640°F and &gt;70 psia).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A singular crack originating at the flange inside surface just outside of the visible HAZ was observed in IOR #1110-2 and Valero #67, respectively. Cracking in IOR #1110-2 was 1/4” long in the circumferential direction and ~3/8” deep (3/4 of the flange wall) in the sample received at UTK. A singular crack 5/8” long in the flange circumferential direction and 3/4 deep was found only in one quadrant in the flange base metal just outside of the visible HAZ. However, the cracks in these components (IOR #1110-2 and Valero #67) were different from traditionally accepted HTHA morphology, i.e. no decarburization, no residual methane, and no evidence of cavitation were observed adjacent to crack areas. Cracking in these two components showed a mixture of intergranular and transgranular cracking morphology. No evidence of cracking or microstructural damage was observed in Valero #1252134.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Phillips 66 component, #555-S1 showed the evidence of the beginning stage of HTHA damage with grain boundary microfissures in the flange base metal just outside of the visible heat-affected zone (HAZ); no apparent decarburization was observed adjacent to microfissures. The presence of methane cavities were observed along pearlite/ferrite and ferrite/ferrite boundaries. A residual methane content of 28 ppm was measured in the damaged region of P66 #555-S1 (from the most damaged area). No evidence of fissuring or decarburization was observed in the second component received from P66 #555-S2. The results showed two of the components exhibited nontraditional form of HTHA damage, two components did not exhibit any damage, and one component from Phillips 66 exhibited traditional HTHA damage.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3330</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4575&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3330</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4575</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-21T11:43:53-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6701930</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3330</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carl D. Lundin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carl J. McHargue, Hahn Choo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>