<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Beats that Commute: Algebraic and Kinesthetic Models for Math-Rock Grooves</title>
<publication-date>2012-01-18T10:52:57-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>trace@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Osborn</lname>
<fname>Brad</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Music</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Math rock’s most salient compositional facet is its cyclical repetition of grooves featuring changing and odd-cardinality meter. These unconventional grooves deform the conventional rhythmic structures of rock, such as backbeat and steady pulse, in such a way that a listener’s sense of metric organization is initially thwarted. Using transcriptions from math-rock artists such as Radiohead, The Mars Volta, and The Chariot, the author demonstrates a new analytical apparatus aimed at making sense of the ways listeners and performers process these changing pulse levels: the pivot pulse. The pivot pulse is defined as the slowest temporal level preserved in a given meter change. The author suggests that the preservation or disruption of the primary pulse level (that is, the temporal level at which a listener’s or performer’s primary kinesthetic involvement happens, such as dancing or foot-tapping) is of paramount importance. For example, a change from 4/4 to 3/4, which preserves the quarter-note pulse, will be less disruptive to a listener’s metric entrainment than a change from 4/4 to 7/8 or 7/8 to 15/16, both of which split the primary pulse in half. In order to formalize pivot-pulse methodology, the author presents an algebraic model based on the commutative operations greatest common denominator and lowest common multiple. Pivot-pulse methodology is also applied metaphorically to the kinesthetic interpretations of performers and listeners to better understand the complex movements incited by math-rock grooves.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol3/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1041&amp;amp;context=gamut&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1041</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-01-17T11:17:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Gamut: Online Journal of the Music Theory Society of the Mid-Atlantic</publication-title>
<context-key>2451564</context-key>
<submission-path>gamut/vol3/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-17T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Beats that Commute</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>