<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Family Presence During Resuscitation in the Emergency Room</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-12T09:23:28-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lspenc12@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Spence</lname>
<fname>Laura Rachel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gwz118@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Hooker</lname>
<fname>Sierra</fname>
<mname>Rachel</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>xyz979@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Erinn</fname>
<mname>Margaret</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>twatso24@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Watson</lname>
<fname>Taylor</fname>
<mname>Nicole</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Effects of Family Presence During Resuscitation in the Emergency Room&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laura Spence, Taylor Watson, Erinn Wright, Sierra Hooker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Tennessee, Knoxville&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effects of Family Presence During Resuscitation in the Emergency Room &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem statement and background:&lt;/em&gt; The role of family members during resuscitation in the emergency room has not been universally addressed by all hospitals in the United States. Some facilities have a specific family presence during resuscitation (FPDR) policy in place while others do not. To determine the effects of FPDR during emergency resuscitation it is important to examine the results in hospitals with a policy; health care provider and family experiences; and patient outcomes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Purpose and research questions&lt;/em&gt;: The purpose of this project is to review the literature addressing the effects of existing policies; health care provider and family experiences; and patient outcomes to make recommendations for best practice as it relates to FPDR .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Design:&lt;/em&gt; A review of literature related to FPDR in the emergency department was performed. The review of literature was categorized under four subtitles: &lt;em&gt;Family Presence During Resuscitation Policies&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Health Care Provider Experience, &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Support of Family Presence During Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Patient and Family Outcomes. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Results:&lt;/em&gt; The findings demonstrated growing support by the general public of FPDR to improve the emotional experience of patient’s families. Family members with prior exposure to FPDR reported positive experiences. Support of FPDR was highest when individuals were asked to be present should their child require cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR). Health care providers often lacked FPDR experience or education. There was not substantial evidence to support FPDR improves patient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions: &lt;/em&gt;To safely and consistently implement FPDR, each hospital should adopt a universal FPDR policy that incorporates staff education and protocols. A universal FPDR policy will increase the competency of ED staff to incorporate FPDR and improve the emotional well-being of family members. Further research is recommended to determine the effects of existing FPDR policies on patient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2016/nursing/2</coverpage-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1106</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-11T10:43:00-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>8459696</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2016/nursing/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Nursing</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Undergraduate Nursing</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Kathleen Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>