<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>NCAA Division I Athletic Trainers&#39; Perceptions and Use of Psychological Skills during Injury Rehabilitation</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mmccaul2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Estepp</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Kathleen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Psychological Skills</keyword>
<keyword>Athletic Trainers</keyword>
<keyword>Injury Rehabilitation</keyword>
<keyword>Sport Psyhchology</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Applied sport psychology research suggests that the use of psychological skills (e.g., positive self-talk, goal-setting, relaxation) during the rehabilitation process increase recovery rates, increase adherence to rehabilitation, and decrease anxiety and stress (Heaney, 2006). Certified athletic trainers (ATCs) hold a critical role within injury rehabilitation as the primary health care professional who interacts with injured athletes. Therefore, properly trained, ATCs have been identified as the ideal professional to implement psychological skills during injury rehabilitation (Larson, Starkey, &amp; Zaichkowsky, 1996). The purpose of this study was to explore National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) Division I (D-I) ATCs use of psychological skills and perceptions of qualifications to implement psychological skills with athletes during rehabilitation. Results revealed that participants reported using goal-setting, communication, and time management most frequently with athletes. Results of a stepwise multiple regression analysis revealed that participants confidence in their ability to effectively demonstrate psychological skills significantly predicted their use of psychological skills, along with perceptions of the effectiveness of psychological skills and previous level of training in sport psychology. Lastly, participants perceived psychologists to be the most qualified professional to implement psychological skills with injured athletes. Implications for ATCs and sport psychology professionals are education. This includes ATCs educational requirements to be more detailed and clear for athletic training students as well as education by sport psychology consultants to help other professional better understand their role in the overall sport team.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1614</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2719&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1614</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2719</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-05T08:36:57-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2719/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3998388</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1614</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rebecca A. Zakrajsek</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Leslee A. Fisher, Jeffery T. Fairbrother</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>