<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Parent-Reared Bobwhite Survival in the Texas Rolling Plains</title>
<publication-date>2017-11-08T08:27:22-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>txquailguy@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Texas Tech University</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Mark</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>brad.dabbert@ttu.edu</email>
<institution>Texas Tech University</institution>
<lname>Dabbert</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>Brad</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>anti-predator behavior</keyword>
<keyword>colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>parent-reared</keyword>
<keyword>population augmentation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Natural Resources and Conservation</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Considerable research has been accomplished over the past 6 decades on the possible reasons for decline in the northern bobwhite (&lt;em&gt;Colinus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;), henceforth known as the bobwhite. Restoring or restocking bobwhite populations by augmentation in areas that once held significant numbers has been a focus for many wildlife agencies and managers. Three main methods for augmentation of bobwhites currently exist: release of pen-raised birds, release of juvenile birds reared by Surrogator&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;, and translocation of wild bobwhites from one area to another. Of these 3 methods, only translocation has accomplished the goal of reestablishing bobwhite populations. Recently a new model developed by Tall Timbers Research Station in Tallahassee, Florida, USA, has successfully produced parent-reared bobwhite chicks from wild strain, which are raised by a surrogate parent in a simulated wild habitat environment. These birds have been released into the southeastern United States and successfully established new bobwhite population in areas of restored habitat. We designed a study to determine the viability of this rearing and release method for restoring depleted bobwhite populations in the semiarid, Rolling Plains of Texas. One hundred fifty nine radiomarked, parent-reared bobwhites were released in 2013–2014 on 8 ranches. One hundred five radiomarked, parent-reared bobwhites were released in 2014–2015 on 6 ranches. The survival rates were low for both years of the study with only 4 radiomarked birds surviving the first year and no birds surviving the second year. An apparent lack of predator-avoidance skills appears to be responsible for the high mortality rates that we estimated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol8/iss1/50</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1522&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>50</label>
<document-type>bobwhite_translocation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1522</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-10-31T07:37:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10974682</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol8/iss1/50</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Parent-Reared Bobwhite Survival in the Texas Rolling Plains</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Thomas.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>Thomas.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1522&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
<description>Powerpoint presentation</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>