<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1544 Comparing the Cost of Broadcasting Versus Injecting Nitrogen in No-Tillage Corn</title>
<publication-date>1995-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Corn</keyword>
<keyword>Crops</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agronomy and Crop Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;No-tillage has become a popular production option with many Tennessee farmers in the past 20 years. In 1993, no-tillage production systems were used on 290,000 acres of corn in Tennessee, or 44 percent of the total corn acreage planted in the state (TDA). Many farmers see no-tillage as a way to reduce the cost of growing corn. Others have chosen no-tillage as a way to comply with governmental regulations covering the farming of highly-erodible soils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Input levels and prices are important to consider in any production system. A major expense in corn production is nitrogen (N) fertilizer. No-tillage budgets published by The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service include N (ammonium nitrate) application rates as high as 125 pounds per acre, at a cost of $31.25 per acre (Gerloff). In this publication, the costs of five fertilization methods are compared and break-even prices to land, management and risk are calculated. The methods studied are: 1) broadcasting urea; 2) broadcasting ammonium nitrate (AN); 3) broadcasting urea-ammonium nitrate (UAN-B, 32 percent solution); 4) injecting urea-ammonium nitrate (UAN-I, 32 percent solution); and 5) injecting anhydrous ammonia (AA).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexcrop/50</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1049&amp;amp;context=utk_agexcrop&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>50</label>
<document-type>croproduction</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1049</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-30T11:58:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Field &amp; Commercial Crops</publication-title>
<context-key>1253993</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexcrop/50</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1544-2.5M-7/95
E12-2015-00-002-96</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1995-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>