<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Combination of &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt;-specific RNA Interference with lmatinib Treatment in the K-562 Cell Line</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Baker</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Eugene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;RNA interference (RNAi) involves the specific repression of the translation of a gene through mRNA degradation. Its application has been extended to a variety of studies both &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; translocation is the cytogenetic marker for chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) and has been studied extensively. The K-562 cell line possesses the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; fusion gene and has been established as a model for RNAi. Imatinib mesylate (Gleeved) is a proven specific inhibitor of the Bcr-Abl tyrosine kinase. The aim of this study was to combine K-562 cells primes with short interfering RNA (siRNA) targeting the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; fusion site with treatment with Gleevec. Two different preperations of siRNA: homogenous-synthetic &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; and heterogeneous-transcribed-digested &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; were used to silence the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; fusion gene. The synthetic siRNA consisted of a homogenous mixture of 21nt long double stranded RNA duplexes specific for the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; fusion site. The transcribed-digested &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; siRNA were generated using an in vitro transcription method producing a 450 bp cloned fragment with the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; fusion site in the center of the cloned region. This cloned fragment was further digested with RNAse III to produce a heterogeneous mizture of &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; 19-21nt siRNA duplexes. We demonstrated a 70% down-regulation of the &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; mRNA through real time PCR and RT-PCR as well as a 75% down-regulation of the Bcl-Abl and Bcl-&lt;sub&gt;XL&lt;/sub&gt; proteins in K-562 cells transfected with synthetic &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; siRNA. The IC&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt; of Gleevec alone in the K-562 subline F&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; was lowered from 0.2μM to 0.06μM in cells transfected with both preparations of &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; siRNA, while no effect was observed in an irrelevant siRNA control. This suggests an additive relationship between Gleevec and &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt;-specific-siRNA treated cells. An increase in apoptosis was also seen in K-562 cells primes with &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; siRNA and treated with Gleevec indicating the additive relationship between Gleevec and &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl&lt;/em&gt; siRNA. These results indicate that priming K-562 cells with &lt;em&gt;Bcr-Abl &lt;/em&gt;siRNA correlate with a decrease in the effective dose of Gleevec required to inhibit the Bcr-Abl protein.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4657</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6248&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4657</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6248</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-02T09:51:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10531234</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4657</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Albert T. Ichiki</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert L. Donnell, Daniel P. Kestler, Karla J. Matteson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>