<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>5 Minutes</title>
<publication-date>2006-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parakramaweera</lname>
<fname>Hasitha</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Nejad</lname>
<fname>Ali</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>the studio</keyword>
<keyword>video contest</keyword>
<keyword>free range</keyword>
<keyword>perspectives</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Description: Life&#39;s too short to hold a grudge against those you love. Credits Running Time: 8:52 Additional Information You all probably won&#39;t watch these movies more than once so I&#39;ll point out some things that people probably won&#39;t catch after one viewing. These things are important to the story and they&#39;re kind of hidden. The story is about a husband and a wife who have a fight and the next day the husband learns that life&#39;s too short to be mad at someone you love. The main idea is that your life can change in five minutes. Time is illustrated throughout the movie: keep an eye on the clocks. Five minute intervals occur quite a bit. To explain what happens to the husband at the end of the movie, he actually had a revelation. This is pointed out in the office, where his coworker quotes Revelations 1:3 from the Bible in order to point out that the husband is late for work. &quot;Something funny&quot; is handled by the husband actually seeing the words &quot;something funny&quot; in the newspaper at the breakfast table. The discovery happens twice. First he discovers his wife&#39;s dead body. The real discovery is actually where he learns through his revelation that life&#39;s too short to hold grudges. &quot;Lead character goes back to sleep&quot; is handled metaphorically. You see him wake up at the beginning of the movie, but technically, he slips back into a subconscious state during his whole revelation, which is when he goes &quot;back to sleep&quot;. Winner, Second Place &amp; Audience Award&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_studfr06/20</coverpage-url>
<label>20</label>
<document-type>audiovideo</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-30T11:19:34-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>2006 Freerange Video Contest</publication-title>
<context-key>1485746</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_studfr06/20</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_url" type="string">
<value>//trace.lib.utk.edu/assets/studfr06/40.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_file" type="string">
<value>studfr06/40.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_streamer" type="string">
<value>rtmp://trace.lib.utk.edu:1935/stream</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>https://trace.lib.utk.edu/embed/stream.php?file=studfr06/40.mp4&amp;w=480&amp;h=360</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>