<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Acronym Usage in Groups: The Relationship of Socialization and Identification</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-04T08:48:12-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dcarneyn@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carney-Nedelman</lname>
<fname>Dara</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Acronym</keyword>
<keyword>Group Communication</keyword>
<keyword>Socialization</keyword>
<keyword>Identification</keyword>
<keyword>language</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Interpersonal and Small Group Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Organizational Communication</discipline>
<discipline>Social Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study analyzed the relationship between knowledge of acronym meaning and group member’s socialization and identification. It examined the understudied relationship between knowledge of acronym meaning for group members and their socialization and identification in the group. Research has concluded that when assimilated into a group the group members contribute more, and overall have greater satisfaction (Riddle, Anderson, &amp; Martin, 2000). This assimilation can be separated into two variables, socialization and identification of group members. Research on the relationship for knowledge of acronym meaning and assimilation has been understudied; therefore, this project explored how the terms we use in groups impacts our connection within the group.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol10/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1406&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1406</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-04-03T21:28:53-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/pursuit/article/1406/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>17209465</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol10/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>I would like to express my thanks to those who have assisted me through the creation of my Undergraduate Honors Thesis and have guided me to find my passion for research.  Firstly, to my Thesis Advisor, Dr. Paskewitz, for her patient guidance, constant encouragement, and bountiful knowledge of methods and group communication.  I would also like to thank my advisor Dr. Wright for her direction of the honors program, and for pushing me to realize my ‘self-efficacy.’  I will always be indebted to my Mother who has encouraged me to think critically, and even at a moment’s notice is willing to help me polish my work.  Finally, to my institution for supporting undergraduate research and establishing programs to allow young scholars to develop their research interest. This research from this thesis placed in the Global Undergraduate Awards highly commended Psychology division. It was also, recognized with a silver award during the University of Tennessee’s 23rd Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement (EURēCA), and placed first at EURēCA for the College of Communication and Information in 2019.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0x1291a080)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>AUIGTROSAI</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>A_Model_of_Group_Socialization_.png</archive-name>
<upload-name>A_Model_of_Group_Socialization_.png</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1406&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>image/png</mime-type>
<description>Figure one was described on page of four of my document, and included in my text on page 5. It provides a visual representation of the socialization process.</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>