<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relationships Among Orthographic Measures and Reading Achievement</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wood</lname>
<fname>Margaret</fname>
<mname>Scruggs</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As participants in an after school tutoring program, 29 second through fifth graders were administered subtests designed to measure visual processing and memory skills: &lt;em&gt;Orthography, Visual Discrimination, Sound Symbol Learning, Letter Memory: Visual, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Rapid Symbol Naming &lt;/em&gt;from the &lt;em&gt;Test of Dyslexia &lt;/em&gt;(McCallum &amp; Bell, 2001); and &lt;em&gt;Picture Recognition &lt;/em&gt;and&lt;em&gt; Visual-Auditory Learning &lt;/em&gt;from the &lt;em&gt;Woodcock-Johnson III-Cognitive Battery &lt;/em&gt;(WJIII; Woodcock, McGrew &amp; Mather, 2001).  Subtest scores were obtained from administration of achievement measures:  &lt;em&gt;Letter-Word Calling, Fluency, Passage Comprehension, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Spelling (Test of Dyslexia); Letter-Word Identification, Reading Fluency, Comprehension, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Spelling (WJIII-Achievement Battery)&lt;/em&gt;; and the &lt;em&gt;Test of Silent Word Reading Fluency &lt;/em&gt;(Mather, Hamill, Allen &amp; Roberts, 2004).  Zero-order correlational analyses were employed to demonstrate the relationships among the orthographic and achievement variables.  &lt;em&gt;Orthography, Letter Memory: Visual&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Rapid Symbol Naming &lt;/em&gt;from the &lt;em&gt;Test of Dyslexia &lt;/em&gt;had mildly positive correlational relationships with achievement measures.  In addition, stepwise multiple regressions were conducted to measure the extent to which the orthographic variables predict criterion achievement variables.  &lt;em&gt;TOD Rapid Symbol Naming &lt;/em&gt;was found to have predictive capabilities to all four achievement constructs:  Sight word identification, fluency, comprehension, and spelling.  &lt;em&gt;WJIII Reading Fluency &lt;/em&gt;had three predictors: &lt;em&gt;Orthography, Letter Memory: Visual&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Rapid Symbol Naming &lt;/em&gt;from the &lt;em&gt;Test of Dyslexia.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4824</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6331&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4824</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6331</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-28T12:59:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10670615</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4824</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sherry Mee Bell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum, Michael Hannum</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Teacher Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>