<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Strangers with Benefits: Ovulation and Attraction to Outgroup Men</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jsalvato@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Salvatore</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Frederick</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Evolution</keyword>
<keyword>Ovulation</keyword>
<keyword>Intersexual selection</keyword>
<keyword>Intergroup relations</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The tendency for humans to behaviorally and attitudinally favor ingroups over outgroups is robust and pancultural. An evolutionary framework, however, provides reason to expect a systematic tendency toward outgroup-favoritism in a particular context. Ancestral females may have mated furtively with outgroup-males and returned to their cuckolded ingroup-male partner for child rearing, as a means of both maximizing genetic variability and promoting the long-term welfare of an offspring. The footprint of such a process may evidence in human females via increased physical attraction to outgroup (but not ingroup) males as ovulation approaches (conception-risk increases). Two studies of normally ovulating women tested this hypothesis. I procured via pilot testing photographs of ambiguously-Hispanic men, which enabled me to randomly assign the presumed race (Caucasian/Hispanic) of those men. In Study 1, Caucasian females rated the attractiveness of the photographed men, with each photograph randomly assigned the label &quot;Caucasian&quot; or &quot;Hispanic.&quot; A Conception-Risk x Group-Membership interaction indicated women deemed outgroup (but not ingroup) males to be increasingly attractive as conception-risk increased. Study 2 replicated the interaction using different social groupings (In-state, Out-of-state student). These data provide rare (but theoretically derived) evidence of outgroup attraction and imply an evolved psychology resulting from plausibly furtive ancestral outgroup-mating.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1201</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2313&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1201</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2313</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-21T11:59:00-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2313/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2688495</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1201</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lowell Gaertner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gordon Burghardt, Jim McNulty, Michael Olson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>