<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>FCC minority broadcast ownership policies-- a critical race theory analysis of judicial assumptions in court decisions : the convergence of race and law</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Washington</lname>
<fname>Kadesha</fname>
<mname>DeFrance</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation used critical race theory as a basis to probe legal and regulatory transitions in the area of minority ownership and their implications for marketplace diversity and public interest. Through the examination of judicial decisions involving minority broadcast ownership this dissertation analyzed the expressed or implied assumptions of the judiciary in reaching those decisions, provided a critical analysis of those assumptions, discussed the implications and results of those assumptions on minority broadcast ownership, and suggested approaches to promote diversity and minority ownership in a deregulated media environment. Both primary and secondary authorities were integral to this research. Overall, analysis took place in three parts. First, there was a collection of United States district court, appellate court, and Supreme Court cases in the area of minority ownership and minority ownership policies promoted by the FCC. Second, analysis of cases consisted of reviewing majority and dissenting opinions. Placing majority and dissenting opinions in the framework of critical race theory, the study continued with determining the judicial rationales and arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6460</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8434&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6460</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8434</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075141</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6460</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Benjamin Bates</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>