<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The &quot;Ruins of the Future&quot;: Counter-Narratives to Terrorism in the 9/11 Literature of Don DeLillo, Jonathan Safran Foer, and Ian McEwan</title>
<publication-date>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carlini</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Francis</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the days after 9/11, Don DeLillo asserted that the narrative of the future ended in the aftermath of the terrorist attacks, and &quot;it is left to us to create the counter-narrative&quot; (34). In this thesis project, I illustrate how Jonathan Safran Foer and Ian McEwan take up DeLillo‘s call to construct a counter-narrative to empty futurism and the backwards-oriented narrative of terrorism. Through my comparative analysis of &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Falling Man&lt;/em&gt; in Chapter One, I illustrate how DeLillo argues for the renewed importance of the place of memory in the world following the attacks of 9/11. &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolis&lt;/em&gt;’ world of constant motion illustrates a pre-9/11 mindset of the persistent &quot;white-hot future&quot; that eviscerates the space of memory in society. However, in &lt;em&gt;Falling Man&lt;/em&gt;, following the attacks of 9/11, the characters highlight the utility and importance of productively engaging with the past in order to move forward into the future. After setting up the renewed importance of memory after 9/11, I turn to an analysis of how the increased importance of memory structures the 9/11 writings of Jonathan Safran Foer and Ian McEwan as they extend DeLillo‘s literary counter-narrative to terrorism. Chapter Two‘s discussion of Foer‘s &lt;em&gt;Extremely Loud and Incredibly Close&lt;/em&gt; highlights how the narrative itself serves as a site of memory that speaks to the power of a productive engagement with the past to illuminate the future. An engagement with his grandfather‘s past allows Oskar Schell to look back and provide a witness to the traumatic past of his grandparents at Dresden in order to transition beyond the trauma of losing his father on 9/11. Finally, Chapter Three concerns Ian McEwan‘s &lt;em&gt;Saturday&lt;/em&gt;, specifically how Henry Perowne and his family struggle with the vicarious traumatization that they experience living in an anxious post-9/11 geopolitical moment. Ultimately, these novels construct a forward-looking counter-narrative to the backwards-looking narrative of terrorism that productively engages with the past in order to transition into the future, at the same time that they speak to the trauma of the present.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/28</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1056&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>28</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1056</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-15T07:44:26-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1111883</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/28</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Amy J. Elias</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary E. Papke, Margaret Lazarus Dean</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>