<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Comparison of Clonal Relatedness and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of fecal Escherichia coli from healthy dogs and their owners</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bartges</lname>
<fname>Joe</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: To determine prevalence of within-household sharing of fecal Escherichia coli between dogs and their owners on the basis of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE), compare antimicrobial susceptibility between isolates from dogs and their owners, and evaluate epidemiologic features of cross-species sharing by use of a questionnaire. SAMPLE POPULATION: 61 healthy dog-owner pairs and 30 healthy control humans. PROCEDURES: 3 fecal E coli colonies were isolated from each participant; PFGE profiles were used to establish relatedness among bacterial isolates. Susceptibility to 17 antimicrobials was determined via disk diffusion. A questionnaire was used to evaluate signalment, previous antimicrobial therapy, hygiene, and relationship with dog. RESULTS: A wide array of PFGE profiles was observed in E coli isolates from all participants. Within-household sharing occurred with 9.8% prevalence, and across-household sharing occurred with 0.3% prevalence. No behaviors were associated with increased clonal sharing between dog and owner. No differences were found in susceptibility results between dog-owner pairs. Control isolates were more likely than canine isolates to be resistant to ampicillin and trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole. Owners and control humans carried more multdrug-resistant E coli than did dogs. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL RELEVANCE: Within-household sharing of E coli was detected more commonly than across-household sharing, but both direct contact and environmental reservoirs may be routes of cross-species sharing of bacteria and genes for resistance. Cross-species bacterial sharing is a potential public health concern, and good hygiene is recommended.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_smalpubs/4</coverpage-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1003</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T11:30:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Small Animal Clinical Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1284871</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_smalpubs/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>K A. Stenske, D A. Bemis, B E. Gillespie, D H. DiSouza, S P. Oliver, F A. Draughton, K J. Matteson, and Joe Bartges. &quot;Comparison of Clonal Relatedness and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of fecal Escherichia coli from healthy dogs and their owners&quot; &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Veterinary Research&lt;/em&gt; 70.9 (2009): 1108-1116.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19719426</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>American Journal of Veterinary Research</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>