<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dissident Peace Movements Inside the German Democratic Republic: The Search for Reform, Freedom, and Toleration 1979-1986</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thompson</lname>
<fname>Abby</fname>
<mname>DeMaris</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis explored the role of the independent peace movements in the German Democratic Republic in the early 1980s. It specifically examined three leaders of these movements: Rainer Eppelmann, Frank Eigenfeld, and Vera Wollenberger. Their work helped create the much larger dissident actions of 1989 by increasing the level of “free space” provided in various Lutheran parishes in East Germany. This expansion occurred in spite of the formation of the GDR Peace Council, which the state used in an attempt to quell opposition by politicizing peace. Their efforts were examined by looking at English translations of GDR Peace Council works, which often exaggerated their goals, actions, and the level of participation. The thesis also discussed the role of &lt;em&gt;Ostpolitik&lt;/em&gt; and the early 1980s arms race between the Soviet Union and the United States. The latter was the initial inspiration for the independent peace movements, even as it demonstrated that the German Democratic Republic often did not strive for peace, especially when its allies were a factor in state diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of the early 1980s independent peace movements has been largely absent from the historiography of the German Democratic Republic. The activities of 1989 have overshadowed the important precursors, such as the independent peace movements. Many of the leaders of these movements later became influential figures in the actions of 1989. The independence peace movements taught them important skills that they transferred from leading small groups in 1979-1983 to larger groups in 1989. The independent peace movements provided East German citizens with a public forum where they discussed their concerns and wished. Their main goals were peace and the internal reform of the German Democratic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4814</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6321&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4814</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6321</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-23T13:28:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10650248</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4814</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vejas Liulevicius</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Bohstedt, Ernest Freeberg</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>