<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Guide to Technical Services Available to State and Local Agencies in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1948-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>Division of University Extension, University of Tennessee</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>municipal technical advisory service</keyword>
<keyword>university of tennessee</keyword>
<keyword>UT</keyword>
<keyword>extension</keyword>
<keyword>public administration</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This handbook is one of the products of a cooperative program of study of government in the South. For several years the Universities of Alabama, Kentucky, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia, along with the Tennessee Valley Authority, have been working together in an effort to obtain more information about governn1ent in the southern states, and to 1nake that inforn1ation available to public officials and other interested individuals. The General Education Board, a philanthropic foundation, has helped finance this progran1, and those who have participated in the enterprise greatly appreciate &#39;its assistance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtashist/30</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1029&amp;amp;context=utk_mtashist&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>30</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1029</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-29T08:37:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS History</publication-title>
<context-key>6580870</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtashist/30</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on Trace are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For current information, please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mtas.tennessee.edu/&quot;&gt;http://www.mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-01-29T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1948-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>