<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The career satisfaction, future plans, and personal characteristics of Tennessee public school science and mathematics teachers in 2001</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Dismukes</lname>
<fname>Delisa</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The effect of state mandates on the supply and demand of science and mathematics teachers in Tennessee is dependent upon the composition of the population of science and mathematics teachers. The purpose of this study was to replicate a study conducted in 1985 by Smith which determined the demographic profile of the general population of secondary school science and mathematics teachers in Tennessee; their general level of job satisfaction; their future plans; and their perceptions of the extent to which they possess job-related skills and abilities, the extent to which they value job-related variables, and the extent to which they have achieved in the teaching profession. Like the previous study, this study also was designed to determine if any relationships existed between the variables. The population of this study consisted of licensed secondary science and mathematics teachers employed in Tennessee during 2001. A survey questionnaire was mailed to a sample of 320 science teachers and 325 mathematics teachers in order to obtain the information described above. Findings of this study included: 1) The typical teacher has over a decade of teaching experience and holds a graduate degree, 2) The highest rated ability for both subgroups was &quot;Cooperating with a team.&quot; The highest rated value and extent of achievement for both groups was &quot;An inner sense of knowing you are doing well,&quot; 3) The typical science and mathematics teacher can us computers and educational technology to a moderate or large extent, 4) The typical science and mathematics teacher indicated they were very satisfied with their current employment and their personal growth in their career, and would be extremely likely to choose an education career again, 5) Approximately one-half of the science and mathematics teachers indicated that they plan to leave the public school classroom in five years, and 6) Science teachers related job satisfaction with recognition from supervisors, obtaining professional growth, a chance to contribute to decisions, and using technology in the classroom. Mathematics teachers related job satisfaction with knowing that you are doing well, high salary, recognition by students, and having a chance to contribute to decisions. Recommendations for further research included investigating the gender ratio to identify factors that determine a career choice in education versus a career in other mathematical fields, since the number of female mathematics teachers is twice the number of males.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5125</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6669&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5125</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6669</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-11T12:24:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13799675</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5125</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Jane Connelly</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Teacher Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>