<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Investigation of the Big Five and Narrow Personality Traits in Relation to Academic Performance</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rogers</lname>
<fname>Craig</fname>
<mname>Lancer</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study investigated the relationship between the Big Five personality traits (&lt;em&gt;agreeableness, conscientiousness, emotional stability, extroversion, &lt;/em&gt;and&lt;em&gt; openness&lt;/em&gt;), as well as the relationship of more narrow personality traits, with academic performance. The issue of narrow traits adding incremental validity to the Big Five in predicting academic performance was investigated, using archival data collected from 552 university students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from a correlation analysis indicated that &lt;em&gt;openness, conscientiousness, agreeableness,&lt;/em&gt; and&lt;em&gt; emotional stability&lt;/em&gt; were all significantly related to GPA (college grade-point average), while extroversion was not related. Due to a significant gender difference in college GPA, gender interaction terms with each of the Big Five factors were employed for regression analyses. The regression analyses indicated that GPA was related to &lt;em&gt;openness, emotional stability&lt;/em&gt;, and&lt;em&gt; agreeableness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bivariate correlation analyses showed that, of the five narrow traits, &lt;em&gt;aggression, self-directed learning, optimism&lt;/em&gt;, and&lt;em&gt; work drive&lt;/em&gt; were related to GPA. Regression analysis indicated that &lt;em&gt;aggression, self-directed learning, tough-mindedness&lt;/em&gt;, and&lt;em&gt; work drive&lt;/em&gt; accounted for partial effects in GPA. Significant interactions were noted between gender and &lt;em&gt;optimism&lt;/em&gt; and gender and &lt;em&gt;self-directed learning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a sequential multiple regression revealed that the following narrow traits added incremental validity to the Big Five in explaining variance in college GPA: &lt;em&gt;conscientiousness&lt;/em&gt; from the Big Five, and the narrow traits of &lt;em&gt;self-directed learning, aggression, tough-mindedness, &lt;/em&gt;and&lt;em&gt; work drive&lt;/em&gt;. Significant interactions were noted between gender and &lt;em&gt;optimism&lt;/em&gt; and gender and &lt;em&gt;self-directed learning&lt;/em&gt;. These findings were interpreted as supporting the usefulness of both broad and narrow personality traits to predict real-world outcomes. Furthermore, these findings illuminate the relationship between personality and academic performance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2329</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3853&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2329</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3853</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-17T12:48:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4733943</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2329</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Saudargas, Debra Baldwin, Mary Sue Younger</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>