<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Relationship Between the Student Teachers&#39; Self-reflection of Performance and the Student Teachers&#39; Performance Evaluation as Viewed by their Evaluation Team</title>
<publication-date>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Eder</lname>
<fname>Bonnie</fname>
<mname>Peterson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this correlational study was to explore the relationship between the student teachers&#39; self-reflection of performance and the student teachers&#39; performance evaluation as viewed by their evaluation team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study involved the use of a &quot;Student Teaching Evaluation&quot; instrument based on the &lt;em&gt;Framework for Evaluation and Professional Growth&lt;/em&gt; that has been adopted by the Tennessee State Department of Education as the procedure through which K-12 public school teachers are evaluated. This study focused on the student teachers&#39; self-reflection as measured against their on-site evaluation team&#39;s appraisal. The subjects of the study were 108 student teachers in elementary and secondary education in attendance at the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga, during the Spring Semester of 1999, who were assigned to a Professional Development School (PDS) II to complete their student teaching and the student teachers&#39; evaluation teams (teams of cooperating teachers employed by the Hamilton County Public Schools).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Student Teaching Evaluation&quot; instrument focused on six areas: (1) planning, which included nine descriptors, six in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level. (2) teaching strategies, which included thirteen descriptors, six in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level. (3) assessment and evaluation, which included eleven descriptors, four in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level. (4) learning environment, which included eight descriptors, five in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level. (5) professional growth, which included nine descriptors, eight in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level. (6) communication, which included six descriptors, three in which correlations were statistically significant at the .05 level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the correlations on the majority of the descriptors indicated a statistically significant relationship between the student teachers&#39; self-reflection of performance and the student teachers&#39; performance evaluation as viewed by their evaluation team, the practical significance of that relationship, as defined by Hinkle et al (1994), indicated a rather low practical correlation on each descriptor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3642</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5386&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3642</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5386</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-27T10:38:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8776719</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3642</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>C. Glennon Rowell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Tanner, Cynthia Gettys, Dan Quarles, Lloyd Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2000-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>