<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A CAPACITY MODEL FOR RESEARCH BASED GOVERNMENT MANUFACTURING SYSTEMS</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Tomcy</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>manufacturing systems</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing systems take longer than necessary to be designed and implemented, hence the greater developmental cost. A class of manufacturing systems exist which would benefit from the concepts of reverse engineering, to reduce lead times for establishing critical manufacturing capabilities essential to national safety and security. There is a need to reverse engineer these manufacturing systems as no current system and/or body of knowledge exists. Manufacturing systems vary in their ability to deliver products in an efficient and reliable manner and hence the variability in national readiness. Presently the design of manufacturing systems for some critical operations ranges from an educated trial and error process to duplicating from documentation and professional expertise. The literature search highlights the non-existence of a current systematic operational reverse engineering model that could be the standard for designing manufacturing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main constraints in the manufacturing is that the time for production is limited and denoted by time available (TA). The time to finish (TF) is the time needed to complete the manufacturing operations in a facility so that the entire quantity demanded is produced, from start to end, in the production line. If the TF is less than the TA there is sufficient capacity to meet the demand. Literature search indicates that no study has been conducted to compute the TF. Further, it also indicates that no study has been carried out focusing on the vi impact of variations and disruptions at the design stage, even though these topics are covered in analysis of existing operational systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithms and mathematical model were developed. The model will compute the exact TF taking into account variation, disruption and flow issues. The equation for TF was developed. The model to be designed is validated using information from a government manufacturing system.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5940</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7726&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5940</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7726</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-24T14:18:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>21246591</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5940</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rapinder S. Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John E. Kobza, Hamparsum Bozdogan, Harry Lee Martin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>