<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Determination of Ceftiofur and its Metabolites in Plasma Using Reverse Phase Liquid Chromatography</title>
<publication-date>2016-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>Sherry</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>White</lname>
<fname>Molly</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gordon</lname>
<fname>Kristen</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bailey</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A high performance liquid chromatography procedure for the determination of ceftiofur and all its desfuroylceftiofur metabolites in plasma has been developed and validated using reverse phase liquid chromatography. Following a derivatization method that converts ceftiofur and all desfuroylceftiofur metabolites to desfuroylceftiofur acetamide, separation was attained on a Symmetry C18 column and quantification occurred using UV detection at 265 nm. The mobile phase was a mixture of (A) 0.1% trifluroracetic acid (TFA) in water and (B) 0.1% TFA in acetonitrile. The mixture was pumped at a starting gradient of 90% A and 10% B and was adjusted to 75% A and 25% B over 25 min, and back to initial conditions over 3 min. with a flow-rate of 1.0 ml/min. The procedure produced a linear curve over the concentration range of 0.1 – 100 μg/mL with a lower limit of quantification of 0.1 μg/mL. Intra-assay variability ranged from 0.7 to 4.5% and inter-assay variability ranged from 3.6 to 8.8% for desfuroylceftiofur acetamide, respectively, and the average recovery was 99%. This method could be useful to those investigators dealing with small sample volumes, particularly when conducting pharmacokinetics studies which require multiple sampling from the same animal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/152</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1151&amp;amp;context=utk_compmedpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>152</label>
<document-type>poster</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1151</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-04-24T07:39:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>17511889</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/152</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>ACS Conference</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>