<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Composition Dependence of the Flory-Huggins Interaction Parameter in Polymer Blends: Structural and Thermodynamic Calculations</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>trusse18@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Russell</lname>
<fname>Travis</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>polymer</keyword>
<keyword>interaction</keyword>
<keyword>thermodynamic</keyword>
<keyword>composition</keyword>
<keyword>dependence</keyword>
<keyword>parameter</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Polymer Science</discipline>
<discipline>Statistical, Nonlinear, and Soft Matter Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Flory-Huggins Theory has been the basis for understanding polymer solvent and blended polymer thermodynamics for much of the last 60 years. Within this theory, a parameter (&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;) [chi] was included to quantify the enthalpic energy of dispersion between distinct components. Thin film self-assembly of polymer melts and block copolymers depends critically on this parameter, and in application, &lt;em&gt;χ &lt;/em&gt;has generally been assumed to be independent of the concentrations of the individual components of the system. However, Small-Angle Neutron Scattering data on isotopic polymer blends, such as polyethylene and deuterated polyethylene, have shown a roughly parabolic concentration dependency for &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, an investigation of this concentration dependency was undertaken from both thermodynamic (&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt;) [chi T] and structural (&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt;) [chi S] theories. Thermodynamic information was obtained through thermodynamic integration with &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; defined using the original Flory-Huggins theory, and structural calculations for &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt; were based on the Random Phase Approximation of de Gennes. Comparison of the two theories revealed that &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt; possess unique composition dependencies; however, via an expression developed within the Random Phase Approximation involving the second derivative of the Gibbs free energy function with respect to composition, &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; can be transformed into &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt; while sacrificing some information related to system specificity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having investigated the composition dependencies of &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt;, simulations were then performed to address the effects of wavenumber selection and chain length on the observed composition dependencies of &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; and &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&lt;/sub&gt;. Lastly, simulations on a polymer melt and its corresponding diblock copolymer were completed to investigate the differences in the characteristics of their interaction parameter composition dependencies. This study was inspired due to a desire to extend the original Flory-Huggins Theory to include a composition dependency for &lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;, thereby producing more accurate morphological data for polymeric systems, and develop more precise methods for calculation of the interaction parameter in polymer systems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2853</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4109&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2853</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4109</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-03-28T11:06:17-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4109/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5407638</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2853</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brian Edwards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bamin Khomami, Robert Counce, Dibyendu Mukherjee</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>