<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Novel Rapid Molecular Detection and Processing Approaches for the Control of Salmonella enterica Serovars in the Food Environment</title>
<publication-date>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ctechath@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Techathuvanan</lname>
<fname>Chayapa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Salmonella</keyword>
<keyword>molecular</keyword>
<keyword>detection</keyword>
<keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
<keyword>inactivation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The increase in &lt;em&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/em&gt; outbreaks calls for an urgent need to rapidly detect and control &lt;em&gt;Salmonella-&lt;/em&gt;associated contamination. Loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) assay is a novel method that can be completed within 90 min in a simple waterbath. Detection is by simple turbidity, fluorescence, or gel electrophoresis and is more specific than PCR. Reverse-transcriptase LAMP (RT-LAMP) targeting mRNA for the potential detection of live infectious &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; or recent contamination was used in this study and detection sensitivity to culture-based detection and RT-PCR assays was compared in pure culture, food products, and food processing environments. Our results showed detection limits of 10&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and 10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; CFU/ml for &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. Typhimurium and 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; and 10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; CFU/ml for &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. Enteritidis by RT-PCR and RT-LAMP assays, respectively. Both assays targeted the specific &lt;em&gt;Salmonella invA&lt;/em&gt; gene. Enrichment of 10 h was required for equivalent detection to culture-based methods for &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. Typhimurium in pork products and 16 h for &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. Enteritidis in liquid whole egg (LWE).  For natural LWE and pork samples, 4-h non-selective enrichment followed by 16-h selective enrichment is recommended to ensure sensitive detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective inactivation/control measures for foodborne pathogens include high intensity ultrasound (HIU, an attractive non-thermal microbial inactivation process). HIU is gaining popularity due to its low cost that also maintains product sensory and functionality attributes. The efficiency of HIU (20 kHz) for &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; inactivation alone or in combination with nisin (a broad range bacteriocin), in a food model (liquid whole egg, LWE) was studied. Significant &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;. Enteritidis reduction of 3.6 log CFU/ml in pure culture and 1.4 log CFU/25 ml in LWE were obtained after HIU treatment alone for 10 min (&lt;em&gt;P&lt;0.05&lt;/em&gt;). Scanning electron micrographs revealed microbial structural damage after 5-min HIU. After 10-min HIU, LWE color became visually and instrumentally lighter along with a lower measured viscosity. However, no additional or synergistic antimicrobial effect was observed with nisin (100 and 1000 IU/ml) in combination with HIU. HIU shows great promise as an alternative non-thermal inactivation process for liquid foods. For use in hurdle approaches, further research on HIU combinations with other natural or generally recognized as safe antimicrobials is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1357</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2494&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1357</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2494</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-21T12:05:46-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2494/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2688502</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1357</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Doris H. D&#39;Souza</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frances A. Draughon, P. Michael Davidson, Alan G. Mathew, Gina M. Pighetti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>