<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Genetic and Ecological Characterization of Indigoidine Production by Phaeobacter sp. strain Y4I</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>wcude@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Cude</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Nathan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>microbiology</keyword>
<keyword>ecology</keyword>
<keyword>antimicrobial</keyword>
<keyword>bacteria</keyword>
<keyword>ocean</keyword>
<keyword>roseobacter</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Microbiology and Microbial Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Roseobacter&lt;/em&gt; clade is a widely distributed, abundant, and biogeochemically active lineage of marine alpha-proteobacteria. Members of the &lt;em&gt;Roseobacter&lt;/em&gt; lineage are prolific surface colonizers in marine coastal environments, and antimicrobial secondary metabolite production has been hypothesized to provide a competitive advantage in colonization. In this work, &lt;em&gt;Phaeobacter&lt;/em&gt; sp. strain Y4I was found to produce the water soluble, blue pigment indigoidine via a nonribosomal peptide synthase-based biosynthetic pathway encoded by a novel series of genetically linked genes, termed &lt;em&gt;igiBCDFE&lt;/em&gt;. Comparison of wildtype, non-pigmented, and hyper-pigmented Y4I insertional mutants demonstrated a perfect correlation between indigoidine production and the inhibition of &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fischeri&lt;/em&gt; on agar plates, revealing a previously unrecognized bioactivity of this molecule. Competitive co-cultures of &lt;em&gt;V. fischeri&lt;/em&gt; and Y4I showed that the production of indigoidine by Y4I significantly inhibits surface colonization of &lt;em&gt;V. fischeri&lt;/em&gt;. Subsequent experiments identified a role for quorum sensing in the production of this secondary metabolite. Y4I has two independent quorum sensing systems, termed &lt;em&gt;pgaIR &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;phaIR. &lt;/em&gt;Transposon insertions in each of the &lt;em&gt;phaIR &lt;/em&gt;genes resulted in defects in indigoidine production. A transposon insertion in &lt;em&gt;pgaR&lt;/em&gt; confers a null indigoidine phenotype. All of these quorum sensing mutants are unable to inhibit the growth of &lt;em&gt;V. fischeri&lt;/em&gt; in competition experiments. These strains also have altered biofilm and motility phenotypes suggesting a role for the quorum sensing systems in regulation of these activities.&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Identification of the &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-acyl homoserine lactone signaling molecules that are produced by Y4I was achieved using a combination of (AHL) bioreporters and mass spectrometry analyses. The two dominant AHLs were found to be &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-octanoyl homoserine lactone (C8-HSL) and a putative monounsaturated &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-3-hydroxydodecanoyl homoserine lactone (3OHC12:1-HSL) when the strain is grown on a complex medium. Evidence is provided that AHL production is not wholly cell-density dependent in this strain. Finally, a comprehensive analysis of the &lt;em&gt;luxRI&lt;/em&gt;-type quorum sensing systems in sequenced roseobacter genomes provide evidence that these genetic systems are closely related among lineage members and likely share a common ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2413</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2955&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2413</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2955</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-03T10:21:22-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2955/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3989487</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2413</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alison Buchan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jeffrey M. Becker, Shawn R. Campagna, Todd B. Reynolds, John P. Biggerstaff</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>