<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Seasonal, Altitudinal, and Vegetational Incidence of Black Bear Scats in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park</title>
<publication-date>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Matthews</lname>
<fname>Susie</fname>
<mname>Jo Kelly</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A study was conducted in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park to determine the variability of incidence of black bear scats as a reliable index to the population density. A total of 6085.7 km were hiked along six different routes, each hiked biweekly, from June-October, 1970-1975, resulting in the collection of 697 scats. The overall incidence of scats was 0.11 scats/km. The Elkmont-Bent Arm yielded 0.21 scats/km, Sugarlands Index Route 0.18 scats/km, Tremont-Derrick Knob Index Route 0.07 scats/km, Gregory-Hannah Mountain Index Route 0.06 scats/km, and Spence-Russell Index Route 0.03 scats/km. Variability in the scats/km over the nine hiking periods was partially attributed to the behavioral activities of breeding. Other factors such as the relative scarcity and abundance of summer and fall foods, climatic conditions, and pre-hibernation activities may have also influenced variability. The number of scats/km collected prior to and after the June-October time period was less, in both cases, except for the Spence-Russell Index Route. Factors possibly causing less evidence of bear presence along this route were the high degree of hiker use (40 percent higher than the next most popular trail) and the large number of horseback riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bears preferred higher elevations in the Park during the June-October period. The highest values of scats/km occurred between elevations of 1219-1371 m. Specific vegetation types in the higher elevations were also preferred over those same types in the lower elevations. Since certain abundant and available berry crops occur only in the higher elevations, it is assumed that this accounts for the apparent preference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the number of scats/km were analyzed in conjunction with a combination factor of altitude-vegetation, it was found that altitude had as least a 95 percent probability of influencing the location of scats along all routes except the Spence-Russell Index Route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous factors such as fluctuation in temperature, variations in precipitation, behavioral aspects of bears, etc., may influence the incidence of scats. Taking this into consideration when attempting to establish an independent index to monitor population fluctuations, it was found that certain statistical assumptions concerning factors that influence the variability of scats incidence would need to be made if the index was to be statistically valid. As these assumptions could not be made, a less sensitive but still effective equation was determined. Used in conjunction with the number of scats collected annually, the equation can be used as a check on population fluctuations.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2580</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3898&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2580</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3898</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-13T12:07:48-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4923287</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2580</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Boyd L. Dearden, Ralph W. Dimmick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>