<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unbound by Theory and Naming: Survival Feminism and the Women of the South African Victoria Mxenge Housing and Development Association</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jacobs@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Jacobs</lname>
<fname>Becky</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>South Africa</keyword>
<keyword>feminism</keyword>
<keyword>gender</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The emergence of a uniquely African formulation of feminism is one of the most energizing developments in feminist theory and discourse in recent history. As African women confront unprecedented economic and political challenges, they also are questioning, and, in some instances, redefining, individual and societal orthodoxies of gender and family roles. This Article will examine the discourse on African feminism and will consider the practical utility of feminist theory in the context of one extraordinary group of South African women, the members of the Victoria Mxenge Housing and Development Association. The discussion will review the historical context in which the Association evolved, will reflect upon a few of the impediments that its members confronted, and will contemplate the challenges and possibilities that these women continue to encounter.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/87</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1090&amp;amp;context=utk_lawpubl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>87</label>
<document-type>publication</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1090</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-15T10:50:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>13626831</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/87</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Jacobs, Becky L., Unbound by Theory and Naming: Survival Feminism and the Women of the South African Victoria Mxenge Housing and Development Association (December 1, 2009). Berkeley Journal of Gender, Law &amp; Justice, Vol. 26, No. 19, 2011; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 151. Available at SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=1816575 or http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1816575</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Berkeley Journal of Gender, Law &amp; Justice</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>