<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Encapsulating History of Place</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>alenenti@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Lenentine</lname>
<fname>Ashley</fname>
<mname>Linn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Responsive</keyword>
<keyword>Architecture</keyword>
<keyword>Ruins</keyword>
<keyword>Place-making</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Archaeological Anthropology</discipline>
<discipline>Cognition and Perception</discipline>
<discipline>Historic Preservation and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Landscape Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Architecture has the ability to reveal the culture and history of a place, to support the community and educate society. The design becomes the vessel that retains the history of the place and increases cultural appreciation throughout society. This thesis looks to reinterpret how design responds to a historic context and incorporates culture and memory into the method for new design. A place is an accumulation of layers that tell a story of the past and overlay conditions of the present that enhance the experience of the place. The site, context, history, and culture can be identified as various layers that drive time-responsive architecture. The stratification of the site creates a complex ground from which to develop a program to inform society and respond to the culture of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site that was chosen for investigation through this thesis is located in Cherokee territory. The site is situated along a hiking trail in the mountains of Northern Georgia, and is within a protected archaeological zone. The architecture emerges through careful interpretation and revelation of the traces of the site. The traditions and culture of the Cherokee are significant as well as the culture and traditions uncovered from the remains excavated on the site. The architecture protects the sacred conditions of the history and educates the public through experiential interpretation. The history and culture of the place is perceived through passage across the terraces revealing the strata that stitch together an authentic understanding of place.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1639</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2739&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1639</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2739</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-15T19:00:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4033402</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1639</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brian M. Ambroziak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Katherine A. Ambroziak, Michael A. Olson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>