<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Content validation of a model for organizational cultural competence of health-related post-secondary academic departments or units</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Krause</lname>
<fname>Diane</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: Health-related academic units need to be culturally competent to meet workforce needs for culturally competent personnel and to establish effective academic-practice linkages. This study was designed to test the content validity of a model, developed from a literature review, for organizational cultural competence of health-related academic units. METHODS: An expert panel convened as a virtual team to provide input on domains and criteria statements that are important and relevant for academia. An iterative process was used as a series of large and small group telephone conferences and e-mail comment period. RESULTS: Over a 4-month period, the expert panel revised, deleted, and added domains and criteria statements. Twelve domains with 73 criteria statements were identified and categorized as: Organization &amp; Administration; Personnel; Community &amp; Environment; Curriculum &amp; Experiential Practice; Research; and Technical Skills &amp; Consultation. CONCLUSION: A model for organizational cultural competence of health-related academic units is proposed. Although further validation is needed, this research begins to establish content validity for the evolving model and establishes the beginning of a foundation to develop an organizational self-assessment tool for academic units to assess and enhance their cultural competence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5738</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7360&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5738</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7360</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467500</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5738</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Betsy Haughton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>