<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>(Re)Discovering Civitas: The L.A.gora</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dnewby@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Newby</lname>
<fname>Douglas</fname>
<mname>Russ</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Architecture</keyword>
<keyword>Civitas</keyword>
<keyword>Los Angeles</keyword>
<keyword>Polycentrism</keyword>
<keyword>Urban Design</keyword>
<keyword>Agora</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was the development of an architectural methodology capable of re-establishing polycentric civitas in the City of Los Angeles. To establish a new civic design framework for the city of Los Angeles, research and analysis was conducted in many fields using several different methods. A review of literature pertaining to the historic establishment of civitas serves an analysis of the different forms of public space in Western civilization. An analysis of urbanism in Los Angeles was conducted using existing literature related to the topic, while an analysis of the neighborhood chosen as the site for the “execution” of the methodology was performed through first-hand research and field study. This information was then synthesized, producing a building program customized to the Miracle Mile in Los Angeles. The final stage of the study was the design of this new civic core. In the context of the Miracle Mile—defined by the presence of the Los Angeles County Museum of Art—the proposed civic core took the form of an artist commune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study concludes that the re-establishment of polycentrism in Los Angeles, as a means for (re)discovering civitas, requires the development of several new alternative civic cores, dispersed throughout the urban fabric of the Los Angeles Basin. In order to effectively operate as sites of critical civic engagement, however, each core must be developed independently of the other, responding to specific micro-cultures. This study advocates choosing sites based on the presence of existing civic potentials. In this way, the alienating effects of tabula rasa city planning are avoided. The architectural project presented at the end of this study, should therefore be understood, not as an architectural prototype to be universally replicated across the city, but as a prototype for an architectural research method. In order to (re)discover civitas in Los Angeles, architects and urban planners must recognize the limitations of universal models and accept that the architectural spaces that define the civic realm must reflect the needs of the specific societies who will ultimately activate them.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/735</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1726&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>735</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1726</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-28T00:43:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1335237</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/735</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edgar Stach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barbara Klinkhammer, Avigail Sachs, Mark Schimmenti</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>