<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Geology of the Blockhouse Quadrangle, Blount County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ricketts</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Preface: It is the purpose of this report to describe the major geologic and geographic conditions of the Blockhouse Quadrangle, Blount County, Tennessee, based upon field studies of the writer. This area, a relatively small portion of the Tennessee Section of the Valley and Ridge Provence, is typical of the East Tennessee Valley and the adjacent Blue Ridge Province. Since field study constituted a large part of the work, much of the written information was taken from field notes. Maps, charts, and photographs are interspersed throughout the text thus aiding in a better understanding of the subject at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the creation of the Tennessee Valley Authority in 1933 there has been careful mapping of much of the territory included in the development program. The maps, by quadrangles, have been masterpieces of workmanship and represent the first intensive program of remapping done in the area since the turn of the century. The Blockhouse Quadrangle, chosen as a research project, was contoured and the map brought up to date by the Authority in 1941.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1468</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2833&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1468</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2833</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-05T08:29:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4199735</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1468</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paris B. Stockdale</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>H. C. Amick, R. Lee Collins, J. S. Walls</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1942-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>