<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Modal Tonicization in Rock: The Special Case of the Lydian Scale</title>
<publication-date>2013-10-17T14:32:40-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Ball State University</institution>
<lname>Clement</lname>
<fname>Brett</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Music Theory</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This article reexamines modal techniques in rock music, using the “problematic” Lydian mode as a test case. I argue that the Lydian scale plays a larger role in rock music than has been previously acknowledged, particularly in songs of the 1970s and ’80s. First, I outline a hierarchy of pitches and chords in the scale, which will aid in recognition of Lydian patterns in rock. Then, I address existing controversies surrounding Lydian interpretations of chord progressions, which will be viewed in light of three “tonal stability rules” necessary for convincing Lydian centricity. This will lead to a general theory of “modal tonicization” in rock music, also relevant to the remaining diatonic modes. Finally, I offer a series of analyses of songs by Todd Rundgren, Tears for Fears, and Steely Dan, which will demonstrate some of the musical and expressive potential of Lydian tonality.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol6/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1081&amp;amp;context=gamut&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1081</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-17T13:13:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Gamut: Online Journal of the Music Theory Society of the Mid-Atlantic</publication-title>
<context-key>4734129</context-key>
<submission-path>gamut/vol6/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Modal Tonicization in Rock</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>