<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Comparison of Three Transfer of Training Strategies in Inservice Adult Teacher Training</title>
<publication-date>1988-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jahenschke@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Lindenwood University</institution>
<lname>Henschke</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
<suffix>EdD</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Community College Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Leadership</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
<discipline>Online and Distance Education</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Student Counseling and Personnel Services</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The need for effective inservice education for teachers in great. Often, inservice programs teach new knowledge and skills, but there is little carry over into teaching practice. The purpose of this study was to develop an effective inservice program in methods of teaching specific subject matter and to compare the effectiveness of four difference follow-up strategies: consultant coaching, team coaching, group meeting, and no follow-up. The major hypotheses tested were: teachers receiving training will demonstrate a significant increase in mean scores on a knowledge test and on a skill performance instrument when compared with a group of teachers not receiving the same training; there will be significant differences in performance of skills between trained subjects exposed to follow-up treatment and trained subjects receiving no follow-up treatment; and, there will be no significant differences in skill performance among treated groups receiving the four levels of follow-up. Data were analyzed using two-factor analysis of covariance. The covariates were age, years of schooling, and years of teaching experience. A significant difference was found between trained and untrained subjects on the knowledge criterion. No other significant interactions were found, however, subjects receiving follow-up made positive changes on the two performance measures. Subjects in the consultant coaching and group meeting treatments improved more than subjects in the team coaching and no follow-up groups.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_IACE-browseall/454</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1459&amp;amp;context=utk_IACE-browseall&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>454</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1459</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-07-16T13:35:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>IACE Hall of Fame Repository</publication-title>
<context-key>7336863</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_IACE-browseall/454</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="class_year" type="date">
<value>1998-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1988-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>