<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Perceptions of NCAA Time Restrictions on Female Student-Athletes and Women&#39;s Intercollegiate Athletics at The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</title>
<publication-date>1992-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Donna</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Leisure Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Intercollegiate athletics are a part of every day life for millions of people. Americans are involved in sport in a variety of aspects; fans, participants, coaches and administrators to name a few. At times, intercollegiate athletics have seemed to be outside the realm of the role of higher education. In an attempt to make the collegiate athlete indistinguishable from the general student body, the National Collegiate Athletic Association, through the leadership of the Presidents Commission, has begun an effort to reform sport programs. A part of this reform movement is the restriction of playing and practice seasons and time commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the purpose of this study to determine the perceptions of the effect of those NCAA time restrictions on female student-athletes and women&#39;s intercollegiate athletics at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. Sub-problems included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Determining the effect of NCAA time limitations on athletic and academic tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Determining the change, if any, in the level of academic performance as indicated by a comparison of grade point averages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Determining the reaction of coaches and administrators to the NCAA time limitation legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the study, participants completed the same questionnaire used by the , American Institutes of Research in a 1987 national survey of intercollegiate athletes. This questionnaire was administered before the time limitation legislation took effect and after the rule had been in effect for a semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal interviews were conducted with the coaching and administrative staff members. Female student-athletes who were freshmen, sophomores or juniors in the spring of 1990 participated in the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of this study did not indicate that there was a significant difference in the amount of time student-athletes spend on sport related activities. There was no significant difference in the grade point averages when comparing Fall 1990 and Fall 1991 semesters. Student-athletes did not appear to become more active in the general student body. Coaches and administrators indicated that the intent of the rule was good, but had some minor problems with the specifics involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this study indicated that student-athletes did not think they had better access to academic counseling or course progress reports despite the athletic department position of Academic Advisor. Student-athletes think they manage their time well, but would like more assistance in the area of time management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for further research include replication of this study after the rule has been in effect for a longer period of time and the use of a more precise instrument. It is also recommended that the NCAA research the possibility of making the rule sport specific so that the out of season needs of individual sport teams may be better accommodated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2684</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4086&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2684</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4086</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-08T11:34:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5562106</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2684</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Dale Blanton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patricia A. Beitel, Nancy E. Lay, Dru Hancock</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Leisure Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1992-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>