<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Antimicrobial activity of aqueous Yerba Mate extracts</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kparks2@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Burris</lname>
<fname>Kellie</fname>
<mname>Parks</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Yerba Mate</keyword>
<keyword>Ilex paraguariensis</keyword>
<keyword>antimicrobial activity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ilex paraguariensis&lt;/em&gt;, is used in the preparation of a widely popular tea beverage (Yerba Mate) mainly produced and consumed in the countries of Uruguay, Paraguay, Argentina and Brazil.  Dialyzed aqueous extracts were screened for antimicrobial activity against &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7, &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt;, methicillin-resistant &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas syringae &lt;/em&gt;pv. tomato.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a concentrated extract, &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; was found to be the more sensitive to extracts than &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7.  Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was defined as the lowest concentration of extract tested that did not allow bacterial growth (inhibition) above the original inoculums of approximately 5.0-6.0 log CFU/ml after 24 hr.  The minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) was defined as the lowest concentration tested where bacterial death (inactivation) was observed after 24 hr.  MBCs were determined to be ca. 0.150- 0.800 mg protein equivalent/ml and 0.025-0.050 mg protein equivalent/ml against &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 and &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a lyophilized extract, MICs were determined to be 5 mg/ml for two strains of &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 and MBCs 5 mg/ml for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 strain ATCC 43894 and 10 mg/ml for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 strain ‘Cider’ in microbiological media.  An approximately &gt;4.5 log reduction was observed for &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;O157:H7 treated with 40 mg/ml extract in modified apple juice, which approximate to the requirements of the United States Code of Federal Regulations (21 CFR part 120).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated antimicrobial effectiveness of aqueous extracts after 24 hr at 1 and 2 mg/ml against all strains of methicillin-resistant &lt;em&gt;S. pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; and of &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; tested respectively.  An approximately &gt;5 log reduction was observed in all strains at all concentrations after 24 hr.  Methicllin-resistant &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; (MRSA) strains appeared more susceptible to the extract than methicillin-resistant &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus pseudintermedius&lt;/em&gt; (MSRP) strains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was concluded that aqueous extracts of Yerba Mate demonstrated broad activity against foodborne, human, animal and plant pathogenic bacteria, including strains demonstrating resistance to certain antibiotics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/954</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2089&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>954</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2089</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-03-04T10:59:45-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2089/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1847710</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/954</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Federico M. Harte</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>C. Neal Stewart Jr., Philip M. Davidson, Svetlana Zivanovic</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>