<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Mammalian Circadian Clock in the Suprachiasmatic Nuclei is Reset In Vitro by cAMP</title>
<publication-date>1989-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prosser</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</institution>
<lname>Gillette</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
<mname>U.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Cell Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A circadian clock located in the suprachiasmatic nuclei (SCN) of the  hypothalamus controls the daily behavioral and physiological rhythms of  mammals. While the mammalian circadian system has been the focus of  research for many years, very little work has been directed at understanding its underlying biochemical mechanisms. In these experiments we used the hypothalamic brain slice technique to investigate these  mechanisms, focusing specifically on the intrinsic resetting properties of the circadian clock of the rat. We monitored a primary expression of the  clock or pacemaker, the circadian rhythm of electrical activity of SCN  neurons. This rhythm continues the oscillatory pattern seen in vivo for up to 60 hr in vitro, with an activity peak near midday that shows very little variation among SCN from different rats. The stability of the rhythm in  vitro enabled us to use the time of peak activity to monitor the phase of the underlying pacemaker. Bath application of membrane-soluble cAMP analogs in 1 hr pulses induced robust advances in the phase of the rhythm that  remained stable for 2 cycles. This effect depended on the phase of the  pacemaker at the time of treatment: the peak was maximally advanced (4-6  hr) by treatments during the middle of the subjective day (projected from the donor&#39;s cycle); treatments during most of the subjective night and  early subjective day induced no phase changes. Half-maximal phase resetting was induced at 1 x 10(-10) M concentrations of active cAMP analog.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/27</coverpage-url>
<label>27</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1026</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-11T08:04:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>1353983</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/27</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>RA Prosser, and MU Gillette
    The mammalian circadian clock in the suprachiasmatic nuclei is reset in vitro by cAMP
    J. Neurosci. 9: 1073-1081; doi:</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1989-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.jneurosci.org/cgi/content/abstract/9/3/1073</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>