<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Phylogenetic analysis of the Nearctic Blepharicera Macquart (Diptera: Blephariceridae) with an emphasis on the eastern Blepharicera tenuipes group Hogue</title>
<publication-date>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ajacobs7@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jacobson</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>Jane</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>net-winged midges</keyword>
<keyword>United States</keyword>
<keyword>new species</keyword>
<keyword>lotic</keyword>
<keyword>phylogeny</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Entomology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The eastern Nearctic fauna of Blepharicera Macquart (Diptera: Blephariceridae) is revised to include twenty-three species, six of which are new to science.  Descriptions of the larvae, pupae, and adults of B. amnicula n. sp., B. conifera n. sp., B. crista n. sp., B. enoristera n. sp., B. hillabee n. sp., and B. opistera n. sp. are presented.  Keys to instar IV larvae, pupae, and adults of all eastern Blepharicera (except B. caudata Courtney) are provided.  Phylogenetic studies were conducted to determine the relationships between eastern and western Nearctic Blepharicera and among species within these groups.  Larvae, pupae, and adults were available for all known Nearctic species except B. caudata and B. micheneri Alexander.  Molecular data acquired from two genes and morphological data for 44 characters were used to test previous phylogenetic hypotheses on the historical relationships and biogeography of Nearctic Blepharicera.  Analyses using maximum parsimony, maximum likelihood, and Bayesian inference were conducted.  Resulting phylogenies support monophyly of the B. tenuipes and B. micheneri groups and suggest that multiple species complexes may exist within the B. tenuipes group.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/889</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2009&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>889</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2009</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-11T14:46:31-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1639836</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/889</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John K. Moulton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ernest C. Bernard, Juan Luis Jurat-Fuentes, Randall L. Small</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plants, Soils, and Insects</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>