<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Self-Directed Learning:  A Potential Predictor for Technology Integration among K-12 Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jvolk@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Kirk</lname>
<fname>Julia Marie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>self-directed learning</keyword>
<keyword>teaching innovation</keyword>
<keyword>technology integration</keyword>
<keyword>self-directed learning readiness</keyword>
<keyword>technology</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Adult and Continuing Education and Teaching</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate the relationship between technology integration and self-directed learning readiness among K-12 teachers in one large southeastern school district. The intent was to determine the extent to which self-directed learning might predict the level of technology integration. In this study, the &lt;em&gt;Levels of Teaching Innovation (LoTi) &lt;/em&gt;(Moersch, 2010) instrument was utilized to measure the level of technology integration (Technology Integration), current instructional practices (CIP), and personal computer use (PCU) of K-12 teachers. Additionally, the &lt;em&gt;Self-Directed Learning Readiness Scale &lt;/em&gt;(SDLRS)&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;(Guglielmino, 1977) was employed to measure self-directed learning readiness in K-12 teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conduct this study, one large, southeastern K-12 school district was chosen as the population. Of this population, 15 schools agreed to participate, 10 elementary schools, four middle schools, and one high school. Of these 15 schools, 722 teachers were contacted and 135 responded. Analysis was conducted to investigate the relationships between the major variables of self-directed learning readiness, levels of technology integration, current instructional practices, and personal computer use. Demographic variables of age, experience, grade level, and subject area also were examined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study revealed that self-directed learning readiness has both a significant relationship with and is a predictor of levels of technology integration and current instructional practices, two of the three factors of teaching innovation. Additionally the study showed that elementary teachers have higher levels of current instructional practices, which means they are more likely to utilize student-centered learning activities, than their secondary counterparts. Finally, the results of the study showed that personal computer use had no significant relationship with other variables, indicating that the age of the user and the comfort level of the user have no bearing on their level of self-direction in using technology. Thus, the major significance of this study is that self-directed learning is a predictor, though a weak model, of teaching innovation and therefore professional development in schools should focus more on self-directed learning when trying to integrate technology.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1534</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2699&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1534</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2699</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-08-17T05:56:00-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2699/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3227414</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1534</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Ziegler, Gary Skolits, Jean Derco</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>