<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Arabidopsis thaliana NIP2;1 , a lactic acid transporter, is essential for plant survival during hypoxic stress</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:53:01-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>smcintir@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McIntire</lname>
<fname>Samantha Jean</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemistry, Biophysics, and Structural Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NIP&lt;/em&gt;s are nodulin-intrinsic proteins that are specific to plants and involved in transport of water and other uncharged solutes. &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana &lt;/em&gt;consists of nine &lt;em&gt;NIP&lt;/em&gt;genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the current study, attention has been focused on &lt;em&gt;NIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;NIP&lt;/em&gt;subgroup I), one of the representative Arabidopsis &lt;em&gt;NIP&lt;/em&gt;s, in accordance with its cellular and subcellular localization, tissue, transport activity, and biological roles in Arabidopsis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been shown in experiments that &lt;em&gt;AtNIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;is especially responsive to hypoxia-induced stress. Hypoxia is a condition in which most of the oxygen has been removed from an environment. In hypoxic environments, plants construct a specific mechanism to cooperate with hypoxic conditions, such as increasing glycolytic flux to provide ATP, increase of fermentation metabolism, and induction of morphological and developmental changes. A functional analysis of &lt;em&gt;AtNIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;has shown that &lt;em&gt;AtNIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;transports lactic acid, and may play a role in adaptation to fermentation of lactic acid under anaerobic stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, it is shown that &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;NIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;AtNIP2;1)&lt;/em&gt;expression is explicitly stimulated through hypoxia. It is shown that knockout of &lt;em&gt;NIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;genes are susceptible to hypoxic treatment. In the survival assay experiment, &lt;em&gt;NIP2;1&lt;/em&gt;knockout plants had a significantly lower survival rate than the wild type plants. A metabolic analysis was performed on both the wild type and knockout lines after hypoxia.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1193&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1193</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-23T19:37:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>12010810</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Daniel Roberts</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>