<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Perceived stress in HIV-infected individuals: Phsyiological and psychological correlates</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Hand</lname>
<fname>G.A.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Phillips</lname>
<fname>K.D.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Dudgeion</lname>
<fname>W.D.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>HIV</keyword>
<keyword>perceived stress</keyword>
<keyword>depression</keyword>
<keyword>anxiety</keyword>
<keyword>disease</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine the correlation of perceived stress with selected physiological and psychological factors in an HIV-infected, predominantly African American population and to assess the multivariable effects on perceived stress. The variables that correlated significantly with perceived stress were entered into a backward stepwise regression model. Pearson’s r analysis showed significant correlations between perceived stress and state and trait anxiety, depression, HIV-related symptoms, sleep quality, daytime sleepiness and fatigue. State and trait anxiety, depression and fatigue retained significance (p&lt;0.1) in the final regression model. These factors explained approximately 80% of the variance in perceived stress. The significant interactions of multiple physiological and psychological correlates suggest that perceived stress is a complex outcome with a multifactorial etiology. Further, the model suggests that psychological factors may contribute to perceived stress in this population more than physiological factors such as HIV-related symptomatology or stage of disease.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/47</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1047&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>47</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1047</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-15T08:25:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1395935</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/47</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Hand, G. A., Phillips, K. D., *Dudgeon, W. D. (2006). Perceived stress in HIV-infected individuals: Physiological and psychological correlates. &lt;em&gt;AIDS Care&lt;/em&gt;, 18(8), 1011-1017.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>