<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Developmental evolution of flowering plant pollen tube cell walls: callose synthase (&lt;em&gt;CalS&lt;/em&gt;) gene expression patterns</title>
<publication-date>2011-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jabercro@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Abercrombie</lname>
<fname>Jason</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>bomeara@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>O&#39;Meara</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>amoffat2@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Moffatt</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>joewill@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of innovations underlie the origin of rapid reproductive cycles in angiosperms. A critical early step involved the modification of an ancestrally short and slow-growing pollen tube for faster and longer distance transport of sperm to egg. Associated with this shift are the predominantly callose (1,3-β-glucan) walls and septae (callose plugs) of angiosperm pollen tubes. Callose synthesis is mediated by callose synthase (CalS). Of 12 &lt;em&gt;CalS &lt;/em&gt;gene family members in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt;, only one (&lt;em&gt;CalS5&lt;/em&gt;) has been directly linked to pollen tube callose. &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;orthologues are present in several monocot and eudicot genomes, but little is known about the evolutionary origin of &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;or what its ancestral function may have been.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigated expression of &lt;em&gt;CalS &lt;/em&gt;in pollen and pollen tubes of selected non-flowering seed plants (gymnosperms) and angiosperms within lineages that diverged below the monocot/eudicot node. First, we determined the nearly full length coding sequence of a &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;orthologue from &lt;em&gt;Cabomba caroliniana &lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;CcCalS5&lt;/em&gt;) (Nymphaeales). Semi-quantitative RT-PCR demonstrated low &lt;em&gt;CcCalS5 &lt;/em&gt;expression within several vegetative tissues, but strong expression in mature pollen. &lt;em&gt;CalS &lt;/em&gt;transcripts were detected in pollen tubes of several species within Nymphaeales and Austrobaileyales, and comparative analyses with a phylogenetically diverse group of sequenced genomes indicated homology to &lt;em&gt;CalS5&lt;/em&gt;. We also report &lt;em&gt;in silico &lt;/em&gt;evidence of a putative &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;orthologue from &lt;em&gt;Amborella&lt;/em&gt;. Among gymnosperms, &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;transcripts were recovered from germinating pollen of &lt;em&gt;Gnetum &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Ginkgo&lt;/em&gt;, but a novel &lt;em&gt;CalS &lt;/em&gt;paralog was instead amplified from germinating pollen of &lt;em&gt;Pinus taeda&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finding that CalS5 is the predominant callose synthase in pollen tubes of both early-diverging and model system angiosperms is an indicator of the homology of their novel callosic pollen tube walls and callose plugs. The data suggest that &lt;em&gt;CalS5 &lt;/em&gt;had transient expression and pollen-specific functions in early seed plants and was then recruited to novel expression patterns and functions within pollen tube walls in an ancestor of extant angiosperms.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_ecolpubs/23</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1022&amp;amp;context=utk_ecolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-11T11:14:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4305905</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_ecolpubs/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>EvoDevo 2011, 2:14 doi:10.1186/2041-9139-2-14</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>