<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Quality of the 1998 Skillathon and Premier Exhibitor Program as Perceived by Participants, Facilitators, 4-H Agents, and FFA Advisors</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ingram</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural and Resource Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study primarily focused on the skillathon&#39;s ability to meet educational objectives as well as an evaluation of the award recognition for participants. The specific objectives of the study were to: (1) Characterize the participants of the 1998 Beef and Sheep skillathons; (2) Characterize the present and past skillathon facilitators; (3) Characterize the 4-H agents and FFA advisors of past and present skillathon participants; (4) To determine the participants’ perceptions of how the individual skillathon stations in Tennessee help increase their knowledge of a specific animal industry; (5) Determine the level of which the following skillathon goals are met: a)To provide a learning laboratory that enhances knowledge of a specific animal industry; b) To develop critical thinking and problem-solving skills; c)To help members gain self-confidence and skill in interpersonal communication; d) To increase the comfort of youth in communicating with an adult; e) To develop greater responsibility for completing a project; f) To provide additional opportunities to recognize youth for their accomplishments; (6) Determine the appropriateness of recognition provided for award recipients; and (7) Describe the differences of perceptions regarding skillathon goals between facilitators, 4-H agents and FFA Advisors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2008</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3368&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2008</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3368</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T13:12:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4641210</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2008</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roy R. Lessly, H. Dwight Loveday</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>