<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Occurrence of proximal droplets in performance-tested beef bulls</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Bartenslager</lname>
<fname>Zachariah</fname>
<mname>Johnson</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>proximal droplet</keyword>
<keyword>bulls</keyword>
<keyword>fertility</keyword>
<keyword>scrotal circumference</keyword>
<keyword>breeding soundness examination</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;To determine the occurrence of proximal droplets in performance-tested bulls, parameters related to breeding soundness examination (BSE) classification were evaluated. Bulls (542 Angus bulls) were classified as satisfactory (BSE guidelines; Society for Theriogenology) or deferred. On-test risk factors were identified, associated with increased probability for bulls to be deferred due to proximal droplets. On-test weight (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.019), on-test scrotal circumference (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.018) and the covariate of age (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.007) were all associated with the probability for a bull to be deferred on test due to proximal droplets. Accounting for the covariate of age and the effect of on-test SC, bulls in weight category 5 (&gt;500 kg on-test weight) had 12.5 times the odds of deferral due to proximal droplets compared to bulls in weight category 2 (350 – 400 kg) (OR: 12.5, 95% adj. CI: 1.47, 111.11; adj. &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.017). Accounting for the covariate of age and the effect of on-test weight, bulls that were categorized as SC on-test 1 (&lt; 30 cm) had 7.9 times the odds for deferral due to proximal droplets compared to bulls categorized as SC 3 (33 – 36 cm; OR: 7.9, 95% CI: 1.4, 44.4; &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.012). Additionally, bulls that were categorized as SC 2 (30 – 33 cm) had 4.7 times the odds for deferral due to proximal droplets compared to bulls categorized 3 (33 – 36 cm; 95% CI: 1.1, 20.0; &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.03). After accounting for age and bull on-test weight, bulls that were categorized as SC growth 3 (&gt; 6.2 cm growth) had 3.7 times the odds for deferral due to proximal droplets compared to bulls categorized 2 (3.4 to 6.2 cm growth; OR: 3.7, 95% CI: 1.69, 8.26; &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; = 0.001. In summary, bull on-test weight, on-test scrotal circumference, scrotal circumference growth and age are important factors associated with unsatisfactory classification due to proximal droplets. Occurrence of proximal droplets have been previously associated with bull maturity; however the cause of its relationship to on-test weight, on-test scrotal circumference and rapid scrotal circumference growth in performance-tested bulls remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5038</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6445&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5038</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6445</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:06:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414710</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5038</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Frank Neal Schrick</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. Lannett Edwards, Ky G. Pohler, Lewrell G. Strickland</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>