<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Merry Death Collector</title>
<publication-date>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bmurph16@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Murphy</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Wade</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Broadcast and Video Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Film Production</discipline>
<discipline>Journalism Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Documentary filmmaking puts life on lens and who knows what the outcome will be. The creative team chose Arnie Meredith to be the subject of the short documentary The Merry Death Collector. The oddball LaFollette, Tennessee resident collects and sells antique items from estate sales and recently purchased two buildings to house and run his business. The story follows Arnie’s struggle to open and maintain a small-town business. He attends a convention in Knoxville, Tennessee to raise funds, and even attempts to hang a biplane in one of his buildings. With his projected opening date around the corner, an exhausted Arnie finds himself two weeks behind schedule. The journey to his opening was a late one but one of true community support. The Merry Death Collector will make its official World Premiere at the Nashville Film Festival in late April. This Academy-Award qualifying film festival is the oldest running festival in the South and accepts only 6% of its over 3500 entrees.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2015/communicationinformation/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1063&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1063</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-28T07:50:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>7039553</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2015/communicationinformation/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Journalism/Electronic Media + Cinema Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>