<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Longevity and Fecundity of &lt;em&gt;Edovum puttleri&lt;/em&gt; Grissell, with Notes on Its Effectiveness as a Biocontrol Agent in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Elkassabany</lname>
<fname>Nader</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Entomology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the laboratory, fecundity and longevity of &lt;em&gt;Edovum puttleri&lt;/em&gt; Grissell (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) were determined. Longevity was tested at two temperatures and with three different diets. The tested groups were mated females, virgin females, and males. Mean longevity was 17.9 ± 2.2 days, and parasite survival rate was highest under a combination of 24±1&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C and 50% water: 50% honey diet. Mean fecundity for each female was 1.9±0.2 eggs/24 hr and 40.8±4.8 eggs in 21 days. In the summer of 1986, field releases were made in Knoxville and Crossville to determine the effectiveness of the parasite as a biocontrol agent. Counts of &lt;em&gt;Leptinotarsa decemlineata&lt;/em&gt;(Say), Colorado potato beetle (CPB) (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), percent parasitized eggs and potato yields were the factors used to determine the effectiveness of the field treatments. At the rate of 12 female parasites/1 female CPB, there was no significant difference between the mass release treatment and the control. The parasite did not suppress the population of the CPB, while applying Ambush 112.5 g ai/ ha as a chemical treatment was effective.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4419</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5923&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4419</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5923</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-15T11:54:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9861280</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4419</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paris L. Lambdin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Reid R. Gerhardt, Charles D. Pless</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Entomology and Plant Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>