<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Politics of Representations: &lt;em&gt;Snow Man&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Bait&lt;/em&gt; by David Albahari</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mraovic</lname>
<fname>Damjana</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thesis analyzes stereotypes about the Balkans in two novels, &lt;em&gt;Snow Man &lt;/em&gt;(1995) and &lt;em&gt;Bait &lt;/em&gt;(1996), by contemporary Serbian writer David Albahari (b. 1948), and how these assumptions, mostly imposed by the West and its tradition of reading the East/the Balkans, are internalized or problematized in these works. This thesis also includes a new, original interview with Albahari conducted by the thesis author. The thesis addresses a change in Albahari’s poetics from metafiction typical for the 1970s and 1980s, to epic forms, which encapsulate the totality of historical experience, in the 1990s. Ultimately, the thesis points out a paradox in Albahari’s works. Although he and his characters adamantly claim that they want to escape from history and the limitations it imposes on an individual, they are defined by a specific historical context (war) and cultural context (the Balkans). The novels suggest that it is not only impossible to overcome a dominant negative discourse about the Balkans, but also that identity is always defined by a historical and cultural context of which an individual is a part. In addition, Snow Man is based on visual metaphors while Bait is based on aual Albahari claims that intercultural understanding is unattainable because it is rooted in stereotypes, although, paradoxically, he allows a possibility that stereotypes represent a provisional identity form.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1746</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3096&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1746</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3096</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-08-22T14:05:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4486000</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1746</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Amy Elias</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allen Dunn, Lisi M. Schoenbach</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>