<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Space / Anti-Space: Revisiting a Relationship of Opposites</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cook</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>Dayne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the article “Space and Anti-Space” Steven Kent Peterson states that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;…our objective (as architects) is an elaborate condition of spaces, a collision of inventions; not a neutral ground of anti-space but a plasma of spatial fields promoting multiple interactions, choices and opportunities.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article focuses on the separation of the two and promotes the exclusion of anti-space in favor of space. Therefore, it is the contention of this thesis that architects can, in fact, fuse the aspects of space and anti-space in order to create more meaningful places than either can do alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vehicle chosen to explore this issue in contemporary Architecture is the Tony Sudekum low income housing development in Nashville, TN. The Sudekum development is a victim of an overabundance of anti-space and little or no discernible space, which detracts from the area’s spatial layering and texture. This study will overlay the principles of space and anti-space in an effort to analyze the aspect of place making in America’s Housing and Urban Development program, specifically the Hope VI Housing Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mario Botta’s Residential Development in Turin will serve as an example of how the fusion of space and anti-space can serve to promote and enrich the spatial qualities needed in place making in contrast to space and anti-space alone. Proctor and Matthew’s Abode Housing Development in Newhall, Harlow, Essex, (England) will serve as a precedent that also combines space and antispace that is illustrative of what the Sudekum Development in Nashville could potentially be.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/270</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1303&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>270</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1303</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-11T07:30:39-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1140575</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/270</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>T.K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mark Schimmenti, William Martella</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/CookDavidDayne.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>