<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Determinant attributes used by the elderly for making grocery store choices</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lewis</lname>
<fname>Angela</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the determinant attributes used by the rapidly increasing elderly (aged 65 and older) consumer segment when choosing among the various retailers for grocery purchases. This study also sought to examine the importance of these determinant attributes and how these determinant attributes affect grocery store patronage decisions. Finally, this study explored the impact that primary store choice, age, self-reported healthiness, activity and mobility have on the importance placed on grocery store attributes. Data were gathered via a mail questionnaire. A determinant attribute . model based on the basic multi-attribute model formed the theoretical framework for this study. This model offered a defined structure that allowed the investigation of the influence of belief strength and importance weights on consumer attitudes and decisions. A determinance score was determined for each store attribute. The higher the determinance score for the store attribute, the more the determinant the attribute was in the store patronage decision. Data results are based on the responses of 366 elderly respondents aged 65 and older. The store attributes that were most important to elderly consumers related to the quality/price relationship and finding satisfactory products. The store attributes dealing with physical aspects were rated relatively low in importance. Eight determinant attributes were identified. Four of the most determinant attributes related to the quality/price relationship. The elderly also sought in-store services and convenience. It was hypothesized that differences would exist in determinant attributes based on the elderly consumer&#39;s primary store choice, age, activity level, mobility, and self-reported healthiness. Multiple Discriminant Analysis was used to provide a test of difference across these independent variables. MDA was performed on both the determinant and nondeterminant attributes. Although, all of the hypotheses were rejected, a few differences were found for the determinant attributes. Easy to read signs/price stickers showed the most difference across the independent variables for determinant attributes. Significant differences were found for the nondeterminant attribute wide aisles; but, overall, the nondeterminant attributes did not vary across the independent variables. Recommendations for grocery retailers and marketers are provided as well as recommendations for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5150</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6694&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5150</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6694</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-11T12:24:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13799771</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5150</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ann Fairhurst</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>