<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Relationship Between Vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;, Folate, Ascorbic Acid, and Mercury Metabolism</title>
<publication-date>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Zorn</lname>
<fname>Nancy</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The effect of megadoses of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;, folate, and vitamin C on the &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; vivo methylation of mercuric chloride was studied in guinea pigs. The incorporation of high levels of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;, folate, and vitamin C resulted in a decrease in both inorganic mercury and methylmercury concentrations in all tissues except the lung and heart compared to controls. However, percent methylmercury levels tended to increase with vitamin treatments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The addition of megadoses of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; fed either singularly or in combination with the other vitamins resulted in increased methylmercury concentrations in the liver, spleen, and kidney tissues of the guinea pig. Moreover, percent methylmercury levels increased with B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; treatment in the liver, heart, and kidney. Incorporation of high levels of folate into the dietary regime also affected the mercury methylation process particularly in the liver, heart, kidney and hair tissues. However, this effect was observed most often in animals fed both B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; and folate. Vitamin C appears to play a synergistic role with vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; and/or folate in the methylation of mercury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auditory brainstem responses (ABR) produced results which supported the theory that vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt; treatment can potentiate the mercury effect in the auditory pathways of the guinea pig. Wave latencies were longer and threshold values were higher in animals fed megadoses of B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;. Interpeak latency means were also longer in animals treated with vitamins and mercury compared to untreated controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rats fed diets supplemented with either methionine or cysteine exhibited differences in methylmercury levels. Both methionine and cysteine supplementation resulted in a significant increase in percent methylmercury levels in the liver and kidney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These data indicate that megadoses of vitamin B&lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;, folate, and/or vitamin C may alter the methylation process of mercury &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt;. In addition, methionine or cysteine supplementation can effect the metabolism of mercuric chloride possibly via transmethylation processes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3864</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5348&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3864</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5348</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-17T09:52:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8988653</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3864</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Betsy Haughton, Michael H. Sims, Roy Beauchene</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1988-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>