<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rethinking Childhood Subjectivity: The Psycho-Politics of Socialization, Private-Language Formation, and the Case of Bosnian Youth</title>
<publication-date>2010-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>utktrace@gmail.com</email>
<institution>York University, Canada</institution>
<lname>Selimovic</lname>
<fname>Adnan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>International Education</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Childhood Subjectivity</keyword>
<keyword>Socialization</keyword>
<keyword>Private-Language</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Under the guise of socialization, the child-subject born into the modern society is subjugated by a familial childhood trauma that appropriates the infantile psychosis caused by the incommunicability of early childhood. This appropriation, put to instrumental ends, results in a psychology of commodified object relations. In fact, there is a close relationship between the historical narrative of a culture and the trauma to which children are subjected as they become members of the social organization. The psycho-politics of the human condition are thus revealed in the realm of the progressive political discourse under which socialization occurs. This project concerns the psycho-political reading of trauma and socialization of children amidst the radical social transition in Bosnia and Herzegovina during the 1990s. The psycho-social situation of the youth raises questions about the social construction of identity, political subjectivity and the possibility of a democratic polity. I experiment with new concepts of political psychology to understand the relationship between the historical society and its infant citizens. Furthermore, I imagine ways of reconstituting theories of war trauma and memory to rediscover a democratic empowerment through a social education that pushes the notion of empowerment beyond its present scope.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol39/iss2/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1172&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1172</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-26T08:00:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>1409169</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol39/iss2/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Rethinking Childhood Subjectivity</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>