<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of L-asparaginase on tumor burden in cats with lymphoma</title>
<publication-date>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>LeBlanc</lname>
<fname>A</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Kirk</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>amino acids</keyword>
<keyword>feline cancer</keyword>
<keyword>L-Asparaginase</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: L-Asparaginase (Elspar(a)), is an Escherichia coli-derived enzyme that depletes lymphoma cells of asparagine, inhibiting protein synthesis and resulting in cell death. The single agent response rate in cats with lymphoma and impact of L-asparaginase on plasma amino acid concentrations is unknown. HYPOTHESES: L-Asparaginase significantly reduces plasma asparagine concentrations and has demonstrable efficacy against untreated lymphoma in cats. ANIMALS: Thirteen cats with confirmed lymphoma (LSA) of any anatomic site were given 1 dose 400 IU/kg IM) of L-asparaginase for initial LSA treatment. METHODS: Plasma collected at 0, 2, and 7 days after L-asparaginase therapy was assayed for ammonia, asparagine, aspartic acid, glutamine, and glutamic acid concentrations. Cats were restaged 7 days later to assess tumor response. RESULTS: Eight cats had T-cell LSA, 4 cats had B-cell LSA, and 1 cat&#39;s immunophenotype was unknown. Two complete and 2 partial responses to L-asparaginase were seen. Four cats had stable disease, and 5 cats had progressive disease. Ammonia and aspartic acid concentrations were increased from baseline at 2 and 7 days posttreatment. Asparagine concentrations were decreased from baseline at 2 days but not 7 days posttreatment. Glutamic acid concentrations were increased at day 2 compared to day 7 posttreatment but not compared to baseline. Glutamine concentrations were unchanged. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL IMPORTANCE: L-asparaginase significantly reduced asparagine concentrations within 2 days of treatment, but this effect was lost within 7 days. The apparent overall response rate of feline LSA to L-asparaginase in this study was 30%.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/28</coverpage-url>
<label>28</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1027</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284751</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/28</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>A LeBlanc, S Cox, C Kirk, Shelley Newman, J Bartges, and A Legendre. &quot;Effects of L-asparaginase on tunor burden in cats with lymphoma&quot; Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine 21.4 (2007): 760-763.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1939-1676.2007.tb03018.x/abstract</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>