<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>(Un)Packing Your Backpack: Educational Philosophy, Positionality, and Pedagogical Praxis</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>yfrankli@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Franklin</lname>
<fname>Yvette</fname>
<mname>Prinsloo</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>philosophy of education</keyword>
<keyword>positionality</keyword>
<keyword>pedagogy</keyword>
<keyword>inclusion</keyword>
<keyword>diversity</keyword>
<keyword>teacher preparation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Bilingual, Multilingual, and Multicultural Education</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Philosophical Foundations of Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this philosophical research project, the author examines the question: &lt;em&gt;How can the case be made that there is an imperative need to change the trajectory of current efforts to reduce “achievement gaps” in the United States and (re)vision a transformation of our school settings through conscious-raising sensitivity regarding issues of equity towards equality amongst educators that harnesses the work of philosophy of education scholars?&lt;/em&gt; She engages the reader in a theoretical hike through a philosophical argument for attending to philosophical theories of education, extending the work of Jane Roland Martin regarding sensitivity and drawing heavily on the scholarship of Barbara Thayer-Bacon regarding relational “(e)pistemologies,” constructed thinking, and democratic community. Contending that there is a tandem need to address issues of diversity as they pertain to equity and work towards inclusion of dominant community and marginalized groups to establish a new equality of dominant and marginalized groups working together, the author explores guiding graduate level education students to personal preparation for conscious-raising regarding issues of sensitivity to diversity for equity with the imperative of inclusion for equality. The case is made, through theory infused with illustrative narrative, that a critical philosophically positional approach can raise consciousness regarding diversity for equity and inclusion to advance toward an ideal of equality, resulting in pedagogical praxis in educational practitioners which the author claims will help advance the vital aim of reducing “achievement gaps” in schools in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1415</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2583&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1415</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2583</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-06-01T19:42:11-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2583/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2930305</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1415</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Barbara J. Thayer-Bacon</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allison D. Anders, Katherine H. Greenberg, Scott Ellison</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>