<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Comparison of a human portable blood glucose monitor, a veterinary portable blood glucose monitor and an automated chemistry analyzer for measuring canine blood glucose concentration</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mfry@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fry</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Peer-reviewed journal articles</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Glucometer</keyword>
<keyword>dog</keyword>
<keyword>method comparison</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Veterinary Pathology and Pathobiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: To compare blood glucose concentrations measured with 2 portable blood glucose meters (PBGMs) validated for use in dogs (PBGM-D) and humans (PBGM-H) and an automated chemistry analyzer. DESIGN: Validation study. SAMPLE POPULATION: 92 samples of fresh whole blood and plasma from 83 dogs with various diseases. PROCEDURES: Each PBGM was used to measure whole blood glucose concentration, and the automated analyzer was used to measure plasma glucose concentration. Passing-Bablok linear regression and Bland-Altman plots were used to determine correlations and bias between the PBGMs and the automated analyzer. Calculated acceptability limits based on combined inherent instrument imprecision were used with Bland-Altman plots to determine agreement. Clinical relevance was assessed via error grid analysis. RESULTS: Although correlation between results of both PBGMs and the standard analyzer was &gt; 0.90, disagreement was greater than could be explained by instrument imprecision alone. Mean difference between PBGM-H and chemistry-analyzer values was -15.8 mg/dL. Mean difference between PBGM-D and chemistry-analyzer values was 2.4 mg/dL. Linear regression analysis revealed proportional bias of PBGM-H (greater disagreement at higher glucose concentrations); no proportional bias was detected for PBGM-D. No constant bias was detected for either PBGM. Error grid analysis revealed all measurements from both PBGMs were within zones without an anticipated effect on clinical outcome. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL RELEVANCE: Neither PBGM had exact agreement with the automated analyzer; however, the disagreement detected did not have serious clinical consequences. Our findings stressed the importance of using the same device for monitoring trends in dogs and using instrument-specific reference ranges.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>1309</fpage>
<lpage>1313</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_pathobiopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-16T11:29:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1231334</context-key>
<withdrawn>2010-04-22</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>