<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Discussion and Modern Edition of Some Works from Walter Porter&#39;s &lt;em&gt; Madrigales and Ayres &lt;/em&gt; (1632)</title>
<publication-date>1970-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Linda</fname>
<mname>Dobbs</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Music</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Walter Porter (1588 or 1595-1659) was an important composer as the dawn of the Baroque broke over England. A small amount of scholarly work concerning his life and music has already been done. Five pieces from Porter&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Madrigales and Ayres&lt;/em&gt; (1632) have been published in modern transcriptions. The supplement to this thesis contains modern transcriptions of three additional works from &lt;em&gt;Madrigales and Ayres. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this thesis is to discuss at length and in detail some of the works in &lt;em&gt;Madrigales and Ayres.&lt;/em&gt; Five selections--the three in the thesis supplement and two edited by Ian Spink--provide a broad representative base for such a detailed study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter I gives a biographical sketch of Porter, discusses general characteristics of, and Italian influence in, his works, and discusses Baroque performance practice apropos to &lt;em&gt;Porter&#39;s Madrigales and Ayres. &lt;/em&gt;Chapter II gives a detailed stylistic analysis concerning these aspects of the five selections:  relationship of text to music, form, harmony, melody, rhythm, instrumentation, and basso continuo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions revealed in the thesis point out innovative Baroque characteristics, characteristics adopted by numerous followers of Porter in England, such as Henry Purcell (1659-1695).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4331</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5751&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4331</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5751</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-14T11:49:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9687205</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4331</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stephen E. Young</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George F. DeVine</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Music</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1970-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1970-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>