<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Role of Molecular Weight in Controlling the Structure and Properties of High-Speed Melt Spun Nylon-6 Filaments</title>
<publication-date>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Suryadevara</lname>
<fname>Jogendra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive study of the structure development during high speed melt spinning of nylon-6 was performed. The major emphasis of the research was on the effect of molecular weight in the structure development of high speed melt spun nylon-6 filaments. The various measurements done on the filaments to determine their morphology included diameter, tensions in spin-line, density as well as x-ray diffraction and birefringence measurements. The effects of mass throughputs were also studied. Tensile properties of conditioned fibers were measured and related to the spinning variables and molecular weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spin-line stresses measured increased rapidly with take-up velocity and molecular weight. The increase with molecular weight was more rapid at higher take-up velocities than at lower take-up velocities. The wide angle x-ray diffraction pattern indicated a significant level of crystallinity, and a high y-phase content at high take-up velocities in low molecular weight samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chain axis crystalline orientation function increased rapidly at the beginning with take-up velocity and then started to level off after reaching an attainable maximum at higher take-up velocities. Increase in spin-line stresses increased crystalline orientation but not independent of molecular weight. Increased molecular weights resulted in increased crystalline orientation functions at low take-up speeds and they decreased at higher take-up speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birefringence measurements showed increases with take-up speeds and molecular weights and decreases with increased mass throughputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensile strength and modulus of the conditioned filaments increased, but the elongation at break decreased with increasing take-up velocity and spin-line stress. Modulus and tensile strength increased with molecular weight. The increase in modulus with molecular weight was rapid at high take-up speeds, producing very high modulus fibers at high speeds and high molecular weight. The tensile properties correlated with spin-line stress and birefringence, but not independent of mass throughput and molecular weight.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3211</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4533&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3211</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4533</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-09T10:40:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6627062</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3211</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph E. Spruiell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edward S. Clark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Polymer Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>