<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Martha Stewart and the Forbidden Fruit: A New Story of Eve</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Insider Trading</keyword>
<keyword>Securities Regulation</keyword>
<keyword>Martha Stewart</keyword>
<keyword>Bible</keyword>
<keyword>Eve</keyword>
<keyword>Law And Literature</keyword>
<keyword>Narrative</keyword>
<keyword>Teaching</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Gender</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Education</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  paper narrates a biblical story - Eve’s ingestion of the forbidden fruit  - and analogizes it to a recent business law story that I explore in my  scholarship and use in my teaching - Martha Stewart’s sale of ImClone  stock as alleged insider trading. The analogy, while imperfect, helps  expose interesting questions about the descriptive and normative content  of U.S. insider trading law and related legal process issues. Although  many of the points made in the paper (and the related details and  examples presented) can be and have been explored or used in other ways,  I contend that the juxtaposition of Eve’s story with Martha’s has  utility in illustrating desirable and undesirable attributes of U.S.  insider trading regulation, in motivating related scholarship, and in  teaching insider trading theory, doctrine, and enforcement under Section  10(b) and Rule 10b-5.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/22</coverpage-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1016</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T07:12:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035018</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Martha Stewart and the Forbidden Fruit: A New Story of Eve (2009). Michigan State Law Review, Vol. 2009, p. 1017, Winter 2009; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 126. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1692173</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1692173</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>