<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Evaluation of Forage Management</title>
<publication-date>1961-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Knight</lname>
<fname>Felix</fname>
<mname>Eugene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Summary&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to analyze two beef farms and two dairy farms, in order to compare the following: (1) the per cent of TDN supplied from pasture, roughage, and concentrates; (2) cow acre days pastured; (3) TDN per acre pastured; and (4) the pounds of concentrates and roughages fed to produce beef and milk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimated yield of pasture per acre in terms of TDN&#39;s was 1,472 pounds on beef farm 1; 1,652 pounds on beef farm 2; 717 pounds on dairy farm 1; and 876 pounds on dairy farm 2. This indicates beef cattle receive more TDN&#39;s from pasture than dairy cattle and that dairy cattle receive more TDN&#39;s from harvested forages and concentrates than beef cattle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this study beef farm 1 derived 112.5 cow days of grazing per acre; beef farm 2, 105.7; dairy farm 1, 73.7; and dairy farm 2, 79.2. This indicates beef cattle received more cow acre days per acre pastured than dairy cattle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cattle on beef farm 1 was fed 269.7 pounds of concentrates and 541 pounds of hay to produce 100 pounds of beef, while the cattle on beef farm 2 was fed 201.1 pounds of concentrates and 907 pounds of hay to produce 100 pounds of beef. Beef farm 1 produced an estimated 304.6 pounds of beef per animal unit, while beef farm 2 produced 258.6 pounds of beef per animal unit. This indicates the farmer on beef farm 1 was a more efficient producer of beef. It also indicates that it was profitable for the farmer on beef farm 1 to wean his calves and keep them four to five months and sell them as feeder calves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cattle on dairy farm 1 was fed 36 pounds of concentrates, 35 pounds of hay, and 104 pounds of silage per 100 pounds of milk produced. The cattle on dairy farm 2 was fed 32 pounds of concentrates, 16 pounds of hay, and 82 pounds of silage per 100 pounds of milk produced. The value of milk produced per cow on farm 1 was $378.26, while the corresponding value for dairy farm 2 was $373.86. This indicates the Holstein cows on dairy farm 1 were eating more feed than the smaller Jerseys, Guernseys, and crossbreeds on dairy farm 2. The Holsteins were producing more milk, but the smaller cows on dairy farm 2 were eating less feed and producing milk with a higher per cent of butterfat. This indicates the net income from milk was as great, if not greater, from dairy farm 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the cost and yield assumption used for this study in Table XII, pasture forage is the cheapest source of TDN&#39;s both in terms of cash cost of production and total cost. This indicates it would be profitable for dairy farmers and beef farmers to make more efficient use of their pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many problems in evaluating a study of this nature, but the author feels that more studies should be made under farm conditions in order to learn more about the farmers&#39; operations and what can be done to help them.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4341</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5783&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4341</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5783</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-23T10:31:48-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9737942</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4341</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Luther H. Keller</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lewis H. Dickenson, Horace C. Smith, Summer Griffin, Harold J. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>