<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mandala and Charisma: The Federalist Potentials in Traditional Indonesian Political Culture</title>
<publication-date>2014-06-25T17:31:45-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>yh.wensea@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Beijing Normal University – Hong Kong Baptist University United International College</institution>
<lname>Wen</lname>
<fname>Yuhao</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Indonesia</keyword>
<keyword>Tradition</keyword>
<keyword>Political Culture</keyword>
<keyword>Mandala</keyword>
<keyword>Charisma</keyword>
<keyword>Federalist</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Asian History</discipline>
<discipline>Asian Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Cultural History</discipline>
<discipline>Models and Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Political History</discipline>
<discipline>South and Southeast Asian Languages and Societies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research explores the federalist elements in the &lt;em&gt;mandala&lt;/em&gt; (a graphic art pattern in Southeast Asia) and political charisma to discuss their constructive roles as traditional Indonesian political culture in federalizing Indonesia. Since August 17, 1945 when Sukarno declared the independence of the country in Jakarta, the newly–born Indonesia was also finalized as a centralized presidential republic. However, till today, societal diversities in Indonesian society are continuously increasing, the tendency of federalization, therefore, has never entirely faded away. Both the &lt;em&gt;mandala&lt;/em&gt; and political charisma &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; have spontaneously generated their own initiatives for federalization since ancient times. Upon illustration of these initiatives, this paper emphasizes the significances of traditional political culture in shaping modern Indonesia’s political regime.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol5/iss1/17</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1170&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1170</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-11-27T01:32:24-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/pursuit/article/1170/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>4858474</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol5/iss1/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>First of all, I would like to show my deepest gratitude to my advisor, Dr. Victor Rodriguez, a respectable and resourceful scholar of History and Southeast Asian Studies, who has provided me with valuable guidance in the preparing and writing of this article. I shall extend my thanks to Mr. Brock Erdahl, Teaching Assistant at UIC English Language Centre, for all his help, patience and kindness.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-11-27T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xeadde68)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Mandala and Charisma</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>