<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of Using and Reusing Melt-Blown, Microwavable Materials to Heat Frozen Fish Filets: Objective and Sensory Perspectives</title>
<publication-date>1990-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cochrane</lname>
<fname>Patricia</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Frozen fish filets were heated in the microwave oven on polyester and polypropylene melt-blown materials. Paper towels were used as the control. After heating, all filets were analyzed for fat and moisture retention. Materials were stored under refrigeration temperatures (18&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C) or freezing temperatures (0&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C) and reused. Polypropylene melt-blown materials used once absorbed significantly more fat than polyester melt-blown materials used once. Neither absorbed more fat than paper towels. Total cooking losses, evaporative losses, and moisture retention of fish filets were not significantly different among the melt-blown materials or paper towels. Reused melt-blown materials absorbed significantly more fat than first use melt-blown materials. Total cooking losses and evaporative losses also were significantly greater for fish filets heated on reused melt-blown materials. Moisture retention for fish filets was not affected. Refrigerated melt-blown materials absorbed significantly more fat from frozen fish filets than paper towels but did not affect total cooking or evaporative losses or moisture retention of the fish filets. Frozen polypropylene melt-blown materials did not affect fat absorption or moisture retention of the fish filets but significantly increased total cooking and evaporative losses when compared to paper towels. Panelists evaluated the fish filets after being heated on the melt-blown materials one time. Greasiness to the touch was perceived as significantly less for fish filets heated on paper towels when compared to polypropylene melt-blown materials but not polyester melt-blown materials. Mouth-feel, tenderness, moistness, and flavor were not significantly different. The results of this study indicated that refrigerated melt-blown materials exhibited greater fat absorption without increasing total cooking and evaporative losses or decreasing the moisture remaining in the heated fish filets.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3923</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5401&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3923</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5401</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-31T07:43:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9055619</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3923</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carol A. Costello</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Betsy Haughton, Michael L. Keene</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1990-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1990-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>