<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Design Methodology for Composite Structures Consisting of Reinforced Hollow Brick Walls and Concrete Beams Connected at a Joint With Flashing and Subject to In-Plane Bending</title>
<publication-date>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McCall</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Kennedy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Due to waterproofing requirements, a flashing joint is generally used at the base of a brick wall to facilitate transport of moisture from the back of a brick wall to the outside of the building. The flashing results in a loss of bond and reduced friction between the reinforced brick wall and the supporting structure. This loss of strength is of little consequence to veneer; however, it may impact wall behavior for reinforced hollow brick. This research, which uses hollow Suprking bricks as manufactured by the General Shale Co., develops data to assess the in-plane shear behavior of the flashing joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research scope includes: (a) testing wall components, shear joints with flashing, and small scale walls; (b) developing numerical models and comparing test results and analysis based on numerical models; (c) developing design details and methods; and (d) demonstrating the use of the methods developed with several design examples. Strength design methods were found applicable to design of composite structures consisting of reinforced brick walls and concrete beams connected at a joint with flashing and subject to in-plane bending. Several specific construction details were found necessary to assure performance including (a) the use of #4 or smaller reinforcing steel bars, (b) grouting of cells in the first two courses of brick adjacent to cells with reinforcing, (c) use of bond beam brick elements on each side of reinforcing steel, and (d) minimum spacing of reinforcing steel of twenty inches.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2655</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4148&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2655</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4148</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-30T14:09:54-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5539850</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2655</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard M. Bennett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>L. W. Tompson, Edwin G. Burdette, Jack W. Wasserman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>