<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Practicality of the &lt;em&gt;Abhidhammattha-Sangaha&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bass</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>Wayne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study centers on a close analysis of the &lt;em&gt;Abhidhammattha-Sangaha-- &lt;/em&gt;a compendium of Abhidhamma philosophy written by a Sri Lankan monk named Acariya Anuruddha Mahathera sometime between the eighth and twelfth centuries. Through a detailed comparison of the &lt;em&gt;Abhidhammattha-Sangaha &lt;/em&gt;to its sources, I am able to demonstrate that the text represents an important innovation in the Abhidhamma tradition. First of all, in the &lt;em&gt;Sangaha, &lt;/em&gt;the building blocks of its primary source are rearranged by degrees of meditative attainment. We will see that the &lt;em&gt;Sangaha&#39;s&lt;/em&gt; author systematized the prior material into a clearly stratified map of meditative states. Also, in his compendium Anuruddha included sections of Buddhaghosa&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Visuddhimagga, &lt;/em&gt;a text that is not part of the canonical or commentarial corpus of Abhidhamma literature. Anuruddha chose this source precisely because it complimented his conception of Abhidhamma as a guide to the practice of Theravada meditation. In the second half of my study, I examine the influence that Anuruddha&#39;s innovations had on future representations of both the Abhidhamma tradition and Theravada in general. Several Abhidhamma specialists characterize Abhidhamma activity in ancient India as an effort to construct a guide for the practice of meditation. I challenge these characterizations, arguing that they are the result of Anuruddha&#39;s far reaching influence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4476</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5983&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4476</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5983</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T09:06:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10003485</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4476</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rachelle Scott</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James Fitzgerald, Johanna Stiebert</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>