<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Impact of Egg Nutrient Composition and Its Consumption on Cholesterol Homeostasis</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kuang</lname>
<fname>Heqian</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Chinese Medicine, Wuhan</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Fang</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Tiannan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gchen6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nutrient deficiencies and excess are involved in many aspects of human health. As a source of essential nutrients, eggs have been used worldwide to support the nutritional needs of human societies. On the other hand, eggs also contain a significant amount of cholesterol, a lipid molecule that has been associated with the development of cardiovascular diseases. Whether the increase of egg consumption will lead to elevated cholesterol absorption and disruption of cholesterol homeostasis has been a concern of debate for a while. Cholesterol homeostasis is regulated through its dietary intake, endogenous biosynthesis, utilization, and excretion. Recently, some research interests have been paid to the effects of egg consumption on cholesterol homeostasis through the intestinal cholesterol absorption. Nutrient components in eggs such as phospholipids may contribute to this process. The goals of this review are to summarize the recent progress in this area and to discuss some potential benefits of egg consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/40</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;amp;context=utk_nutrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>40</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1044</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-07-21T14:04:31-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>14966629</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/40</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heqian Kuang, Fang Yang, Yan Zhang, Tiannan Wang, and Guoxun Chen, “The Impact of Egg Nutrient Composition and Its Consumption on Cholesterol Homeostasis,” Cholesterol, vol. 2018, Article ID 6303810, 22 pages, 2018. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/6303810.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1155/2018/6303810</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Cholesterol</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>