<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Experimental Investigation of the Differential Effects of Hypnotic, Post-Hypnotic and Waking Suggestion on Learning, With Tasks Varied in Complexity</title>
<publication-date>1960-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Salzberg</lname>
<fname>Herman</fname>
<mname>Carl</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Introduction: This study was designed to test, first of all, whether there were any differential learning effects following hypnotic, post-hypnotic, and waking suggestion. Secondly, the investigation was designed to test whether learning following suggestion increased or decreased differentially when learning tasks varied in complexity. Finally, the study was set up to find out whether there was a difference between the quality and quantity of learning following suggestion. A large number of the features of previous experiments in the area of hypnosis and learning were combined. As past experimenters found contradictory results, no hypotheses were forwarded regarding the outcome of this investigation. Several features not found in past experiments were included in the design of this investigation. These features are mentioned following the review of the literature in this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2960</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4445&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2960</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4445</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-21T10:47:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6262587</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2960</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>W. O. Jenkins</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harold D. Holloway, K. R. Newton, M. E. Keister, C. Pascal</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1960-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1960-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>