<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Case Study of Mediated Learning, Delayed Auditory Feedback, and Motor Repatterning to Reduce Stuttering</title>
<publication-date>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nradford@uthsc.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Health Science Center</institution>
<lname>Radford</lname>
<fname>Nola</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Tanguma</lname>
<fname>Jesus</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Gonzalez</lname>
<fname>Marcia</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Nerriccio</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Denis</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A case study of DW, an 11-yr. old monolingual, English-speaking boy who exhibits stuttering, language delay, and ADHD is presented. DW experienced only limited improvement during stuttering therapy received in public schools, according to parents and the public school clinician. The purpose of this case study was to assess whether fluency treatment which incorporated Mediated Learning, Delayed Auditory Feedback, and Speech Motor Repatterning would enhance progress. Therapy was delivered in two treatments, with each treatment being 5 wk. of intense therapy, separated by one year. Treatment 1 of combined Medjated Learning and Delayed Auditory Feedback yielded improvement in fluency, judged by parents and the teacher to be clinically significant. The improved fluency was maintained for one year when DW was pretested for participation in Treatment 2, which combined Mediated Learning, Delayed Auditory Feedback, and Speech Motor Repatterning Exercises. As no conclusions are possible, further study is needed&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_audipubs/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;amp;context=utk_audipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1005</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-03-26T11:20:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Audiology and Speech Pathology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>11848284</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_audipubs/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Nola T. Radford, Jesus Tanguma, Marcia Gonzalez, Mary Anne Nericcio, and Denis G. Newman. &quot;A Case Study of Mediated Learning, Delayed Auditory Feedback, and Motor Repatterning to Reduce Stuttering.&quot; Perceptual and Motor Skills, 2005, 101, 63-71.</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Perceptual and Motor Skills</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>