<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular Barcoding of Eupatorieae of Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:54:01-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mpoindex@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Poindexter</lname>
<fname>Magen R</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Molecular analysis has become a popular method used to characterize the complex biodiversity of our world. In this project, we have been able to add to the understanding of the native species of Tennessee by analyzing particular regions of DNA. We obtained DNA sequences for a standard barcode marker from each of about 30 species belonging to the Eupatorieae tribe found in the state. This process of molecular barcoding has produced a catalog of the state’s diversity of these plants. With this, we are better able to identify unknown samples and aid in the conservation of rare plants such as &lt;em&gt;Eupatorium leucolepis&lt;/em&gt;. This plant, also known as justiceweed, is a flowering plant currently listed as endangered in the state of Tennessee. While commonly found in the coastal plain region, justiceweed is also native to one county in Tennessee. Isolated by hundreds of miles from any other of its species, the populations of this plant found in Tennessee have raised some questions. Is this truly the same plant that grows along the eastern coast of North America? If so how did it come to occupy this land locked state? So far, we have been unable to find a characteristic to distinguish Tennessee’s justiceweed from that of coastal plain populations. However, molecular data have determined that the plants in Tennessee previously identified as &lt;em&gt;E. leucolepis&lt;/em&gt; differ significantly from those found in the coastal plain region, and instead are hybrids of &lt;em&gt;E. leucolepis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;E. semiserratum&lt;/em&gt;, a species more commonly found in Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/16</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1178&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>16</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1178</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-17T16:28:56-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1178/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11979364</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/16</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ed Schilling</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>