<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of High Temperature Cyclic Aging on a Fully-Formulated Lean NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; Trap Catalyst</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ottinger</lname>
<fname>Nathan</fname>
<mname>Andrew</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mechanical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The thermal deactivation mechanisms of a lean NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; trap (LNT) are analyzed in this study. Accelerated lean/rich aging experiments are performed with a bench-flow reactor, and high temperature exotherms are achieved with pulses of reductants. Reduction in steady state NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; conversion as a result of aging is evaluated at a range of temperatures using the same bench-flow reactor. The results of these evaluations are used to show that NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; conversion in this study is a function of evaluating temperature, aging temperature, and number of aging cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surface characterization studies are used to determine changes in washcoat morphology. Electron probe microanalysis line scans and elemental maps show that migration or agglomeration of washcoat components (excluding PGM) does not occur. Substantial PGM growth as a result of aging is seen using scanning transmission electron microscopy/scanning electron microscopy/energy dispersive spectroscopy (STEM/SEM/EDS) and powder X-ray diffraction (P-XRD), but this growth, at least initially, has little effect on NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; conversion. P-XRD is also used to study phase transitions of Ba and Al&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. All BaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; peaks quickly disappear after aging, and there is no subsequent growth of any BaAl&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; peaks. The disappearance of crystalline BaCO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; does not appear to have a large effect on NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; storage or conversion. The Al&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; peaks are stable, but large surface area reductions are measured with Brunauer, Emmett, and Teller (BET) surface area measurements. Both reductions in surface area and PGM particle size growth are shown to correlate well with reductions in NOx conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3678</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5036&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3678</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5036</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-11T11:42:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8132918</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3678</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ke Nguyen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bruce G. Bunting, Todd J. Toops, J. Roger Parsons</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>