<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Controversy in the Coalfields: Evaluation of Media and Audience Frames in the Print Coverage of Mountain Justice Summer</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Womac</lname>
<fname>Amanda</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to evaluate the media and audience frames used in print media coverage of Mountain Justice Summer and mountaintop removal. The study synthesizes aspects of framing theory of media effects as described by other media scholars in an attempt to create a working model to evaluate media and audience frames. As this study will show, the media use an overall negative frame in the coverage of Mountain Justice Summer, but also have an overall negative frame in the coverage of mountaintop removal. Based on these findings, the study suggest activists with Mountain Justice Summer helped to frame the issue of mountaintop removal by staying on message, and the overall source for negative perception of activists came from industry representatives or community members. Evaluation of audience frames shows an overall positive perception of Mountain Justice Summer activists and opposition to mountaintop removal. This finding suggests a weak connection between media frames and audience frames, but also allows for further evaluation of the framing theory of media effects.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/442</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1478&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>442</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1478</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T09:59:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1150431</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/442</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Littmann</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edward Caudill, Dorothy Bowles</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication and Information</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/WomacAmanda.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>