<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Validation of the ParvoMedics TrueOne® 2400 Metabolic Measurement System for measuring resting metabolic rate in a heterogeneous adult population</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Weinheimer</lname>
<fname>Tracie</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to validate and compare the accuracy of the ParvoMedics TrueOne® 2400 Metabolic Measurement System in measuring resting VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; against the criterion Douglas bag method, and secondarily to compare the Douglas bag measures of VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; to those from the ParvoMedics TrueMax® 2400 Metabolic Measurement System, which has been previously validated up to near maximal metabolic rates (3).  Resting metabolic rate (RMR) is determined by measuring the oxygen consumption (VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) of the subject lying in the supine position in the early morning following an overnight fast.  The TrueOne® system uses a “flow-through” methodology, with the subject under a plexiglass canopy; the TrueMax® system measures gas exchange in a conventional manner.  Seven males and thirteen females underwent a 30-minute RMR test on each machine; test order was randomly assigned.  In addition, expired air was collected into either a Douglas bag or a non-diffusing gas collection bag from the back of the mixing chamber of each system.  This allowed a simultaneous measurement of the resting VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; to compare the systems to the criterion method.  Expired gas volume was determined using a Collins 120 liter gasometer, and O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; fractions were determined using calibrated gas analyzers.  The TrueOne® 2400 systematically underestimated VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; compared to the external Douglas bag method by approximately 22% (0.18 L/min and 0.24 L/min, respectively).  The TrueMax® 2400 yielded VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; values nearly identical to the criterion Douglas bag method (VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.24 L/min and 0.23 L/min, respectively).  The systematic underestimation of resting VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; by the ParvoMedics TrueOne® 2400 Metabolic Measurement System indicates it is not an accurate device for measuring resting VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.  The ParvoMedics TrueMax® 2400 is capable of accurately measuring resting VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4512</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6036&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4512</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6036</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-17T07:50:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10027216</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4512</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward T. Howley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr., Eugene Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>