<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>College choice and retention of international students in the United States</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Washam</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
<mname>Anne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>College Student Personnel</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The global transformation of the world has not precluded international education, as international students are increasing in number on many college campuses today. This quantitative study investigates factors influencing the choice and retention of international students at institutions of higher education in the United States. To date, very little research has been conducted in this area. International F-1 undergraduate students from two large, public research I universities were surveyed to examine what factors influence college choice and retention. Descriptive statistics yielded findings that suggest that preparation for the future, academic quality/reputation of the institution, and strength of the academic program influence college choice, while retention influences included personal motivation, good grades, and good knowledge of the English language. Correlations suggested that students who consider academic factors in college choice believe that academic factors are critical to one&#39;s success in retention, while those influenced by social factors in college choice believe social factors are critical in retention. Findings have implications for international student advisors, admissions recruiters, and professors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5695</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7317&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5695</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7317</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467443</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5695</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Terrell L. Strayhorn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>College Student Personnel</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>