<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Advocacy Among Counseling Leaders: A Constructivist Grounded Theory</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ihartman@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Farrell</lname>
<fname>Isabel</fname>
<mname>Cecilia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Legislative professional advocacy</keyword>
<keyword>professional counselors</keyword>
<keyword>professional organizations</keyword>
<keyword>leaders</keyword>
<keyword>counselor education</keyword>
<keyword>constructivist grounded theory</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Social/political or legislative professional advocacy is vital for growth of the counseling profession. However, knowledge regarding social/political professional advocacy is limited by a lack of empirical evidence. The purpose of this constructivist grounded theory study was to explain the process of social/political professional advocacy for counseling leaders. The research question guiding this study was &lt;i&gt;what is the process of social/political professional advocacy for counseling leaders?&lt;/i&gt; Constructivist grounded theory (Charmaz, 2014) was used to analyze fifteen semi-structured interviews with professional counselors who engaged in leadership related to social/political professional advocacy. During analysis, four major themes emerged, &lt;i&gt;Connection to Personal and Professional Identity, Use of Personal and Professional Community, Making it your Own,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Picking your Battles&lt;/i&gt;. Findings suggested that the legislative professional advocacy process involved three tiers &lt;i&gt;Advocacy Catalyst, Advocacy Action, and Advocacy Training&lt;/i&gt;. The &lt;i&gt;Advocacy Catalyst&lt;/i&gt; provided connection to the advocacy need. &lt;i&gt;Advocacy Action&lt;/i&gt;, involved ways that advocates acted upon advocacy by picking battles and making it their own. &lt;i&gt;Advocacy Training&lt;/i&gt; provided participants with support and knowledge to apply to their &lt;i&gt;Advocacy Action&lt;/i&gt;. In addition, using an aggregate of the participants’ own perspective and experience, a definition of legislative professional advocacy was proposed. Based on these findings, implications for counselor education programs and professional organizations and recommendations for future research were provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4884</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6425&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4884</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6425</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:13:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13414943</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4884</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Casey A. Barrio Minton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patrick R. Grzanka, Misunori Misawa, Shawn L. Spurgeon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Counselor Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>