<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The University of Tennessee Libraries Newfound Press Scholarly Publishing Demonstration</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-17T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>llphillips@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Phillips</lname>
<fname>Linda</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>University library digital publishing</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>newfound press</keyword>
<keyword>library publishing</keyword>
<keyword>Digital Commons platform</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2005, the University of Tennessee Newfound Press demonstrates open access; ensures quality through peer review; encourages innovative approaches to the creation and dissemination of scholarly and specialized work; seeks content with narrow focus or innovative format unlikely to be published by a market-driven press; helps authors of specialized content disseminate their work; and experiments with new forms of publication. This presentation describes the reasons for starting Newfound Press; offers highlights from the business plan; and discusses the convergence of Newfound Press with other campus publishing, including the digital showcase and archive, Trace (operates on the bepress Digital Commons platform), and the University of Tennessee Press.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfpubs/23</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1022&amp;amp;context=utk_libfpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-21T16:35:30-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_libfpubs/article/1022/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Other Library Publications and Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1140490</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libfpubs/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-17T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>The Library As Publisher: Increasing Library Relevance through Institutional Repository Services, a program sponsored by the Berkeley Electronic Press at the Midwinter Meeting of the American Library Association, Boston, MA, January 17, 2010.</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>