<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extrovertive mysticism and the inner unity of opposites : An examination of two philosophical ideas in the early poetry of James Dickey</title>
<publication-date>1983-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Beasley</lname>
<fname>Wallace</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Certain critics have alluded to the mysticism of James Dickey&#39;s early poetry, but little critical work has been done on this aspect of Dickey&#39;s work. The purpose of this study was to examine certain philosophical ideas in Dickey&#39;s early work, as these ideas inform the poet&#39;s underlying, mystical vision. The idea of extrovertive mysticism and the idea of the inner unity of opposites were two philosophical ideas which seemed to operate in many of Dickey&#39;s early poems. In extrovertive mysticism the mystic intensifies and explores his sensory experience of the world as a means of establishing a sense of personal connection with the underlying unity of external reality. The inner unity of opposites is the idea that in every system of dualistic opposition, there exists a middle ground of implicit unity/ Oppositions such as life and death, self and other, being and not being, are viewed as the conceptually extreme ends of a common core of related experience.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5773</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7451&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5773</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7451</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359244</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5773</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>H. Philips Hamlin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1983-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>