<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterizing the Morphology of Solvent Annealed PCBM/P3HT Bilayers using GIXRD and Raman Spectroscopy</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tmcpher5@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McPherson</lname>
<fname>Tyler</fname>
<mname>Evan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>OPVs</keyword>
<keyword>Raman</keyword>
<keyword>NEXAFS</keyword>
<keyword>thin polymer films</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A growing demand for new forms of renewable energy has been at the forefront of scientific research. Organic photovoltaics (OPVs) provide a promising alternative to the expensive inorganic solar cells used today. Poly(3-hexylthiophene) (P3HT) and [6,6]-phenyl C61-butyric acid methyl ester (PCBM) are common donor and acceptor materials used in the active layer of an OPV device. These systems have reached power conversion efficiencies of approximately 12 %. However, little is known about the actual morphology. A better understanding of the morphology would allow researchers to optimize device fabrication to increase the device performance. As-cast devices are limited by the processing conditions which they were casted. Post-annealing allows us to alter these samples. Unlike thermal annealing, solvent annealing provides a slow, selective way to alter the samples. We looked to explore how solvent annealing affects a P3HT:PCBM bilayer. By increasing the loading of PCBM, we are able to investigate different morphologies based on the miscibility of the system. Grazing Incidence X-ray Diffraction (GIXRD), Raman spectroscopy, and Near-Edge X-ray Absorption of Fine Structure (NEXAFS) were used to explore the morphology of these systems.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2735</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3976&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2735</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3976</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-27T12:21:49-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3976/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5230849</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2735</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark D. Dadmun</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Alexei Sokolov, Jon Camden</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>