<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An examination of doctoral training from the students&#39; perspective</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Tanzer</lname>
<fname>Adam</fname>
<mname>Mendel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined doctoral training from the students&#39; perspective. Several different aspects of the involved experience of doctoral training were investigated, including higher education, political and psychological concerns. Eight Ph.D. students enrolled in the social sciences were interviewed. A qualitative methodological approach was used for the data gathering and analysis. A variety of findings were reported. Two of the main findings were (1) the importance of social relationships (with mentors and colleagues) for the students; and (2) the bi-directional aspect of the mentor relationship. Several changes were suggested for the improvement of the Ph.D. training. One conclusion emphasized the importance of departments and universities having established policies to increase the likelihood that mentor-mentee and peer relationships will be formed. An additional suggestion for the improvement of Ph.D. training includes providing training for professors and students involved in mentor relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6398</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8372&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6398</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8372</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:39:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24074673</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6398</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Schuyler Huck</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>