<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1594-Insect and Mite Management in Greenhouses</title>
<publication-date>2007-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Pests</keyword>
<keyword>Greenhouses</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Horticulture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Pest Management (PM) is a term that refers to the use of various strategies to manage greenhouse insect and mite pests. The focus of PM is to use a variety of management strategies to deal with existing pest problems, rather than relying solely on pest control materials such as insecticides and/or miticides. PM involves the use of cultural, physical, biological and/or chemical management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PM programs typically require growers to be proactive rather than reactive. An effective PM program begins by regularly scouting the greenhouse for insect and mite pests. A PM program may include establishing action thresholds for specific insect and/or mite pests and then implementing a pest management strategy once a threshold has been reached. Greenhouse producers who have successfully implemented PM programs indicated that they have reduced costs and increased worker safety. As a result, employees often respond to PM programs with increased enthusiasm. The objective of this publication is to assist greenhouse producers in starting a PM program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexcomhort/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1002&amp;amp;context=utk_agexcomhort&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>greenhouseproduction</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-10T10:57:22-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Commercial Horticulture</publication-title>
<context-key>1213292</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexcomhort/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1594-500-9/07(Rev) E12-4615-00-004-08 08-0033</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-10T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>