<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Academic Librarians and Research Data Services: Preparation and Attitudes</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Sandusky</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Allard</lname>
<fname>Suzie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Birch</lname>
<fname>Ben</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>academic libraries</keyword>
<keyword>research data services</keyword>
<keyword>data management</keyword>
<keyword>digital curation</keyword>
<keyword>metadata</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research funding bodies recognize the importance of infrastructure and services to organize and preserve research data, and academic research libraries have been identified as locations in which to base these research data services (RDS). Research data services include data management planning, digital curation (selection, preservation, maintenance, and archiving), and metadata creation and conversion. We report the results of an empirical investigation into the RDS practices of librarians in US and Canadian academic research libraries, establishing a baseline of the engagement of librarians at this early stage of widespread service development. Specifically, this paper examines the opinions of the surveyed librarians regarding their preparedness to provide RDS (background, skills, and education), their attitudes regarding the importance of RDS for their libraries and institutions, and the factors that contribute to or inhibit librarian engagement in RDS.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/365</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1432&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>365</label>
<document-type>conference</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1432</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-01-08T18:08:46-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>16145790</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/365</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Tenopir, Carol, Sandusky, Robert, Allard, Suzie, and Birch, Ben. “Academic Librarians and Research Data Services: Preparation and Attitudes,” Proceedings of the International Federation of Library and Information Associations (IFLA), August 2012.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Proceedings of the International Federation of Library and Information Associations (IFLA)</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>