<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dickens and his intrusive first-person &quot;authors&quot;</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Rogers</lname>
<fname>Arthur</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study explores the intrusive authorial presence of the fictive autobiographer in Charles Dickens&#39;s David Copperfield, Bleak House, and Great Expectations and traces the biographical implications in these three thinly veiled &quot;rewritings&quot; of Dickens&#39;s own life&#39;s story, the story of the abandoned, neglected child. After defining &quot;intrusive authorial presence&quot; more precisely according to the Structuralist conception of &quot;narrative discourse,&quot; the discourse tendencies in Dickens&#39;s third-person fiction are examined for context and comparison, and then the discourse tendencies establishing David Copperfield, Esther Swnmerson, and Philip Pirrip as unique &quot;writers&quot; and fictive personalities are explored in depth. Almost certainly more than Dickens intended, David Copperfield&#39;s narrative discourse suggests that he emerges from his traumatic childhood with enduring scars or minor character flaws that belonged to Dickens as well: defensiveness, insecurity, irrational guilt, class snobbery, lingering self-pity, and an inability to escape the past that impinges so vividly upon the &quot;narrating present.&quot; In the Esther Summerson revealed in her discourse lies Dickens&#39;s deeper exploration of the more debilitating consequences of abandonment and neglect in childhood: most evidently, the denial of painful emotions that reveal themselves despite their intended suppression, a compulsive need for praise and admiration that cannot be satisfied, and grossly distorted feelings of guilt and worthlessness.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6297</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8249&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6297</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8249</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450398</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6297</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Don Richard Cox</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Kelly, David Goslee, Natalia Pervukhin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>