<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Seroprevalence of hantavirus in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lewis</lname>
<fname>Shawn</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2000 and 2001 we conducted a hantavirus survey in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park to gather preliminary information on the general distribution of hantavirus in this park. We tested 142 small mammals for antibodies against Sin Nombre Virus, a highly pathogenic strain of hantavirus. Peromyscus spp. were the only animals that were seropositive. Antibodypo_sitive Peromyscus spp. were found in 6 of the 13 sites sampled. Of the 96 Peromyscus spp. tested, 16.7% of 42 P. manicu/atis (deer mice) and 3.7% of 54 P. leucopus (white-footed mice) had antibodies reactive to Sin Nombre Virus. Although no human hantavirus cases have been reported in or originating from the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, reservoir populations in the park are infected with a pathogenic strain of hantavirus. The potential for human-rodent contact and subsequent human infection does exist in many areas of the park.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5951</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7584&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5951</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7584</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467612</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5951</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John C. New Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stephen A. Kania, Dorcas O&#39;Rourke, Robert L. Donnell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Comparative and Experimental Medicine</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>