<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mappings of ANR&#39;s Whose Images are ANR&#39;s</title>
<publication-date>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Choi</lname>
<fname>Jung-In</fname>
<mname>Kang</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mathematics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Recently, R.J. Daverman and J.J. Walsh modified an example due to J. Taylor to obtain an example of a cell-like map from a compactum with non-trivial shape onto the Hilbert cube Q such that the non-degeneracy set is contained in the countable union of finite dimensional closed subsets of Q. Previously, G. Kozlowski proved that a cell-like map f: X&#39; → X from a compact ANR X&#39; onto a metric space X is a hereditary shape equivalence if there exists a sequence {B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;}∞&lt;sub&gt;n=1&lt;/sub&gt; of finite dimensional closed subsets of X such that the non-degeneracy set is contained in ∞U&lt;sub&gt;n=1&lt;/sub&gt; B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; and {f&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; (B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;)}∞&lt;sub&gt;n=1&lt;/sub&gt; forms a pairwise disjoint null-sequence. Here we raise two questions, which we show are equivalent. First: Is a cell-like map f: X&#39; → X a hereditary shape equivalence if there exists a sequence {B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;}∞&lt;sub&gt;n=1&lt;/sub&gt; of finite dimensional closed subsets of X such that U&lt;sub&gt;n≠m&lt;/sub&gt; (B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; ∩ B&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;) has a strong transfinite dimension and the non-degeneracy set is contained in ∞U&lt;sub&gt;n=1&lt;/sub&gt; B&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; ? Even though we are not able to answer these questions, we give affirmative answers to the questions for special cases, and , furthermore, we are able to extend the aforementioned result of Kozlowski&#39;s. Also, we attempt to extend certain analyses of cell-like maps, which are proper by definition, to (non-proper) UV∞-maps. We prove that for a UV∞-map f: X&#39; → X from an ANR X&#39; to a metric space X the following are equivalent: (1) X is an ANR; (2) f is a hereditary homotopy equivalence; (3) f is a hereditary shape equivalence; (4) f is a fine homotopy equivalence. Since UV∞-maps are generally not onto, the notion of a &quot;hereditary shape equivalence&quot; is a variation of that for cell-like maps, though it agrees with, say, Kozlowski&#39;s for cell-like maps.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2996</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4498&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2996</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4498</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-30T09:37:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6308525</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2996</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John J. Walsh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert J. Daverman, Kwangh Jeon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>