<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of the Thermal Inactivation Kinetics of Surrogate Vegetative Bacteria</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>arenix@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Renix</lname>
<fname>Amber Lynne</fname>
<mname>Parham</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Surrogates Thermal Inactivation Vegetative Bacteria</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Microbiology</discipline>
<discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Microbial surrogates are defined as non-pathogenic organisms with behavioral and/or survival characteristics correlating to those of specific pathogens. The purpose of this study was to determine the thermal inactivation kinetics (D and z-values) of&lt;em&gt; Lactobacillus bulgaricus &lt;/em&gt;ATCC 11842&lt;em&gt;, Lactobacillus fructivorans &lt;/em&gt;ATCC 8288&lt;em&gt;, Lactobacillus plantarum&lt;/em&gt; ATCC 4008&lt;em&gt;, Listeria innocua &lt;/em&gt;ATCC 33091, ATCC 51742, and 11/97, and&lt;em&gt; Staphylococcus carnosus&lt;/em&gt; CS-299&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;as potential surrogates for hepatitis A virus (HAV; D&lt;sub&gt;72°C &lt;/sub&gt;= 0.9 min). Additionally, the effect of sub-lethal heat on increasing the thermotolerance of &lt;em&gt;L. bulgaricus&lt;/em&gt; was investigated. All strains were tested in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) as a preliminary step and, contingent upon the survival characteristics, further tested in ultra-high temperature (UHT) 2% fat milk and chopped spinach. Thermal inactivation experiments in PBS, UHT milk, and chopped spinach were performed at a temperature range of 58-70°C for 0-60 min. For sub-lethal heating, &lt;em&gt;L. bulgaricus &lt;/em&gt;was subjected to 45 or 50°C for 30 min prior to inoculation of milk and subsequent heating at 70°C. &lt;em&gt;L. fructivorans, L. plantarum, &lt;/em&gt;and all &lt;em&gt;L. innocua&lt;/em&gt; strains had insufficient thermal resistance to be used for HAV surrogates. In contrast, D-values for &lt;em&gt;L. bulgaricus&lt;/em&gt; in UHT milk were 9.98, 2.68, and 0.45 min, at 65, 67, and 70˚C, respectively, with a z-value of 3.7°C. When subjected to sub-lethal heating, the D&lt;sub&gt;70˚C&lt;/sub&gt; values for the 45 or 50˚C treatment were 0.34 or 0.48 min, respectively. Thus sub-lethal heating did not increase thermal resistance. D-values for &lt;em&gt;L. bulgaricus&lt;/em&gt; in spinach were 43.29, 10.13, 3.20, 0.91 min for 63, 65, 67, 70°C. &lt;em&gt;S. carnosus&lt;/em&gt; had D-values in PBS of 3.46, 1.27, and 0.47 min at 65, 67, and 70°C, respectively, and a z-value of 5.84°C. In milk &lt;em&gt;S. carnosus&lt;/em&gt; D-values were 4.60, 1.94, and 0.46 min at 65, 67, and 70°C, respectively and in spinach D-values of 4.61, 2.42, 0.73 min were found at 65, 67, and 70°C, respectively. While D-values of &lt;em&gt;L. bulgaricus &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;S. carnosus&lt;/em&gt; were lower than that of HAV, they may have potential value at high cell concentrations in validation studies for inactivation of HAV.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3503</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4779&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3503</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4779</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-05-01T13:46:35-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4779/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7057780</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3503</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>P. Michael Davidson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Golden, Doris D&#39;Souza</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>