<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development of a Mobile Teaching and Learning Module for VM893 (Field Services) with</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bwhitloc@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Whitlock</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Mobile Teaching and Learning</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>Veterinary</keyword>
<keyword>Mobile</keyword>
<keyword>Teaching</keyword>
<keyword>Learning</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to develop a teaching and learning module with interactive comprehension assessments that can be used in a mobile (truck) or stationary (classroom) environment. A considerable portion of the Field Services clinical rotation is spent with students driving from the UT Veterinary Medical Center and from farm to farm in a large four-door truck. During these trips a consistent set of relevant topics will be delivered to students by discussing clinical cases. The format will be interactive and students will be equipped with technology allowing an assessment of their comprehension. Students will have day-to-day access to data collected during their assessments. Easy access to evaluations during the course could improve comprehension of the material. Moreover, the quality of teaching may improve as faculty can more easily determine if the materials they are delivering are understood, allowing adjustments to be made when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_animpubs/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;amp;context=utk_animpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>other</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1007</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-07-26T20:01:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Animal Science Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>3763264</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_animpubs/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>