<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Quiet “Purge” of Jews and Jewish Thinking in American Social Science</title>
<publication-date>2018-03-14T08:42:13-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>brooks.duncan@yahoo.com</email>
<institution>Independent Scholar</institution>
<lname>Duncan</lname>
<fname>Brooks</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This article uses the method of ethnic stratification analysis and participant observation to raise questions about what appears to be one of the hidden ethnic transformations that has occurred in the disciplines of anthropology and sociology in the past two decades; the replacement of Jews. Jews, who were among the founders of and became “over-represented” in these disciplines, have now been replaced with other minorities through a process of selection based on “representation”. Along with the use of these disciplines for overall university quota filling, in order to promote statistics for hiring of underrepresented groups, has come the loss of the empirical “scientific” approach of Jewish scholars and the idea of application of “universal” principles for social progress. These two phenomena appear to be related, raising questions about the actual social justice and social progress impacts of what was claimed as “diversity”. Under the veneer of apparent diversity, the costs to social science and actual social justice may outweigh the benefits. In today’s political environment, there seems to be an unwillingness to pursue and raise these questions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol8/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1104&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1104</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-03-14T07:33:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>11771746</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol8/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-03-14T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>