<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Quality of Turkey as Affected by Ovens of Varying Energy Costs</title>
<publication-date>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McNeil</lname>
<fname>Marsha</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Energy conserving cooking procedures have been of recent interest to the consumer and the researcher. The introduction of convection and microwave ovens for consumers has been credited with potential energy savings. Therefore, an investigation was designed to compare the energy consumption of conventional, convection, and microwave ovens as boneless turkey roasts were cooked. Turkey was chosen because its consumption is increasing and it is a time and energy demanding muscle food to cook. The quality of the cooked roasts was evaluated by objective tests, an experienced sensory panel, and a consumer sensory panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The microwave oven cooked significantly faster (P &lt; 0.05) than the other ovens. The convection oven consumed the most energy (P &lt; 0.05) but had the most cooking power (P &lt; 0.05) when compared to the other ovens. The relative efficiency of the convection and microwave ovens was greater (P &lt; 0.05) than that of the conventional oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evaporative and total cooking losses did not differ among treatments. The microwave roasts had the greatest (P &lt; 0.05) drip loss. The conventional and convection roasts had lower (P &lt; 0.05) percentages of fat-free dry weight than did the microwaved roasts. The expressible moisture index did not differ among treatments. The shear values of the convection roasts were lower than shear values of the microwave roasts but did not differ from those of the conventional roasts. The conventional and microwave roasts were similar in tenderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riboflavin content of the cooked roasts, on a wet basis and dry basis did not differ. On a wet basis the conventional and on both a wet and dry basis the microwaved roasts did not differ from the raw samples with respect to riboflavin content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9-member, experienced sensory panel found no differences in doneness, appearance, juiciness, flavor, and overall acceptability but did find a difference in tenderness of the roasts cooked in the three ovens. The microwave-heated roasts were found to be tougher than the other roasts. A 72-member, consumer sensory panel also did not find any differences among the roasts in paired comparison tests for acceptability.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3845</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5321&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3845</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5321</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-11T07:58:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8962054</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3845</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marjorie P. Penfield</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frances A. Draughon, Jean D. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>