<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessment of Cognitive Abilities in Children with a Pervasive Developmental Disorder Using the Universal Nonverbal Intelligence Test</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Burton</lname>
<fname>Bobbie</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study was designed to examine the utility of the Universal Nonverbal Intelligence Test (UNIT; Bracken &amp; McCallum, 1998) for use with children who have been diagnosed with a pervasive developmental disorder (e.g., autistic disorder, asperger’s disorder, pervasive developmental disorder-not otherwise specified). The goal was to determine whether distinct cognitive profiles on the UNIT exist within this population and between those with and without a pervasive developmental disorder: a) Do children with a pervasive developmental disorder earn significantly lower mean scores than a demographically matched control group on the UNIT Full Scale Intelligence quotient? b) Do children with a pervasive developmental disorder earn a significantly higher mean score on the UNIT Nonsymbolic quotient versus the Symbolic quotient? c) Do children with a pervasive developmental disorder earn significantly different mean scores on the UNIT Reasoning and Memory quotients?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examiners administered the UNIT to 43 children with a pervasive developmental disorder. Data from 31 children who received raw scores of at least 1 on every subtest were used for statistical analyses. Data from an additional 31 children who participated in the UNIT standardization process were also included as the control group. The group with a pervasive developmental disorder had significantly lower scores (p&lt;.001) on every quotient of the UNIT when compared to the control group. When the mean Full Scale Intelligence quotients were compared, the difference of approximately 22 points was significant, t(26) = 4.46, p = .000. Within the group with a pervasive developmental disorder, the mean score of the Nonsymbolic quotient was approximately 4 points higher than the Symbolic quotient; this difference was not significant, t(30) = 1.59, p &gt; .05 (onetailed). When the Memory and Reasoning quotients were compared, the mean difference of .19 was not significant, t(30) = .068, p = .947. Based on mean difference analysis of this sample, there does not seem to be a unique cognitive profile for this population on the UNIT.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/415</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1476&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>415</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1476</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T10:02:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1150505</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/415</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sherry Bain, Joel Diambra, John Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/BurtonBobbie.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>