<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>U.S. history textbook comprehensiveness : a study of how current textbooks meet the standards of Tennessee, California, Texas, New York, and Georgia</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lovorn</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Glen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to quantitatively analyze the extent to which each of the four basal 2001-2002 editions of secondary school U.S. History textbooks addresses the U.S. History standards approved by the State of Tennessee Board of Education and then to draw qualitative comparisons between those analyses and the secondary social studies curriculum standards of Georgia, Texas, New York and California. This study revealed that the four basal U.S. History textbooks on the Tennessee adoption list for the 2002 approval cycle were all found by means of line counts to be comprehensive in their coverage of the performance indicators. outlined in the Tennessee Social Studies Curriculum Standards for secondary U.S. History. The study also revealed that textbook publishers rely heavily on the standards of California, New York, and Texas for the format of their products. Recommendations ate made for further research on teaching practices of secondary school U.S. History teachers in the State of Tennessee as they apply to the use of textbooks as the primary source of curricular informational transfer within the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5152</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6696&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5152</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6696</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-11T12:24:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13799777</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5152</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas N. Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>