<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Self-Directed Learning: A Potential Predictor of Technology Integration Confidence among Preservice Teachers</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jbeard8@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee -  Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Beard</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>preservice teacher</keyword>
<keyword>teacher education</keyword>
<keyword>technology integration confidence</keyword>
<keyword>self-directed learning</keyword>
<keyword>adult learning</keyword>
<keyword>NETST</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship between self-directed learning (SDL) and the confidence to integrate technology into the classroom among preservice K-12 teachers enrolled at a large southeastern university. The intent was to determine the extent to which SDL is related to technology integration confidence and, further, to what extent SDL predicts technology integration confidence. In this study, the Personal Responsibility Orientation—Self-Directed Learning Scale (PRO-SDLS) (Stockdale, 2003; Stockdale &amp; Brockett, 2010) was used to measure levels of learner self-direction. Additionally, the Technology Integration Confidence Scale (TICS) (Browne, 2009) was revised (TICS-R) and was used to measure the confidence to integrate technology into the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conduct this study, a teacher education program at one large, southeastern university was chosen as the population. Of this population, coordinators for two courses offered in the teacher education program gave permission to survey their students. Of these two courses, 143 preservice teachers were contacted, 115 responded, and 102 fully participated. Analysis was conducted to investigate the relationships between the factors of SDL and technology integration confidence. Demographic variables of age, gender, ethnicity, teacher education program, GPA, and whether or not they had completed the teacher education technology course at this university were also examined, but were primarily intended to provide a profile of the sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study revealed that SDL has both a significant relationship with and is a predictor of technology integration confidence. Significant relationships were found among the factors of the PRO-SDLS and the subscales of the TICS-R. The strongest relationship was between self-efficacy and technology integration confidence. Self-directed learning was found to predict technology integration confidence at a statistically significant level. The reliability of the PRO-SDLS was found to be consistent with previous research, and the TICS-R was found to be highly reliable, giving promise to future use and further development. Based on these results, this study includes implications for preservice teacher education, as well as recommendations for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3677</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5232&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3677</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5232</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-03-04T10:03:16-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5232/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8265832</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3677</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Morrow, Blanche O&#39;Bannon, Karee Dunn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>