<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Report to the National Science Foundation</title>
<publication-date>1980-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Norris</lname>
<fname>Donald</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This Report presents a description of the programs and activities of the Tennessee Innovation Group during its first seventeen months of operation. The report is presented in three sections. The first section discusses the processes employed in the establishment and operation of the Tennessee Innovation Group. Particular attention is given to: (1) the committee structure of the Innovation Group; (2) methods employed to identify priority needs among small and medium size Tennessee cities; (3) criteria employed in selection of projects to be undertaken by the Tennessee Innovation Group; (4) the &quot;demonstration project&quot; approach to local government innovation employed by the Tennessee Innovation Group; and (5) the relationship of the Tennessee Innovation Group to Municipal Technical Advisory Service and the Tennessee Municipal League. The second section of the report discusses specific projects undertaken by the Innovation Group. Each project is presented in terms of the identified problem, technology selected for demonstration, site selection, and methodology of application employed in the demonstration. Particular attention is paid to the success, or lack thereof, of the demonstration project in each selected site including a brief discussion of the major factors affecting the demonstration. In section three of the report, a description of the technologies selected by the Tennessee Innovation Group for demonstration during the next phase of the project is presented. This phase is expected to include most of calendar year 1980. In addition, a brief discussion is presented concerning the transfer of technologies which were developed during the first 17 months of the project. An Appendix, following the body of the report, presents the Tennessee Innovation Group&#39;s initial technology needs list and preliminary designs for the Group&#39;s first year projects.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/17</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1016&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1016</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-06T12:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2638704</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1980-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>