<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The revised leadership scale for strength and conditioning</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Gearity</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to establish reliability scores for the Revised Leadership Scale for Strength and Conditioning (RLSSC). Modifications were made to the Revised Leadership Scale for Sport (RLSS) (Zhang et al., 1996) to make it specific to strength and conditioning. Sixty-one Division I athletes from a large public southeastern university responded to the scale. Fifty-three scales were deemed usable and analyzed to assess a reliability score. Reliability scores, determined by Cronbach&#39;s alpha, ranges from: &#39;social support&#39;, .75; &#39;situational consideration&#39;; .76, &#39;training and instruction&#39;, .90; &#39;democratic behavior&#39;, .83, &#39;autocratic behavior&#39;, .64; and &#39;personal feedback&#39;, .84. Reliability scores revealed were within acceptable limits. Validity for the RLSSC can be inferred through the already established reliability and validity scores of the RLSS. The RLSSC is a reliable and valid instrument to assess leadership preference of athletes. _ Recommendation for use of the RLSSC include assessing athlete&#39;s perception of leadership, strength and conditioning coaches perception of their own leadership, and a qualitative study to provide a thick, detailed description of leadership between strength and conditioning coaches and athletes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5227</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6635&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5227</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6635</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847074</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5227</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dennie Kelley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>