<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Public Career of William B. Bate</title>
<publication-date>1951-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chesney</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>N</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;PREFACE&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;William B. Bate, soldier, governor, and United States Senator, had a long and active public career, lasting from 1846 to 1905. When one considers the important and far-reaching events that transpired within this period, it can readily be seen that a work of this length cannot tell a complete story. Consequently I have tried to deal with Bate mainly in his relationship to the history of Tennessee.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Having been interested in the history of Tennessee and of the South since I was a child, I chose Bate as the subject of this thesis. My interest was also increased by the fact that my paternal grandfather took part in the Battle of Chickamauga, and many times my father has told me how Grandfather described the battle and spoke of the part that Bate&#39;s brigade had in it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The writer is greatly indebted to Dr. S. J. Folmsbee, under whose supervision this work has been done, for his suggestions, assistance, and criticism. Acknowledgment is also due to Dr. Ruth Stevens and Dr. Leroy P. Graf who read the manuscript and offered valuable suggestions. Lastly, acknowledgments are due to the staffs of the University of Tennessee Library and the Lawson-McGhee Library, as well as to Mr. Robert A. Quarles, Custodian of the State Archives at Nashville, who made available for me the correspondence of the governors and the Nashville &lt;em&gt;Daily Gazette&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. N. C.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/849</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1950&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>849</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1950</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-02-25T11:29:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1821663</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/849</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Stanley J. Folmsbee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ruth Stephens, LeRoy P. Graf</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1951-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>