<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Distribution and phylogenetic analyses of the genus &lt;em&gt;Auricularia&lt;/em&gt; in the southeast United States</title>
<publication-date>2012-04-14T15:45:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Looney</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Birkebak</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Matheny</lname>
<fname>P.</fname>
<mname>Brandon</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A recent discovery of &lt;em&gt;Auricularia fuscosuccinea&lt;/em&gt; in east Tennessee has led to a study of the diversity within the genus&lt;em&gt; Auricularia&lt;/em&gt; in the southeast United States. &lt;em&gt;Auricularia&lt;/em&gt; currently comprises 10-15 well-established species, and most are considered to have intercontinental to cosmopolitan distributions. Though most regional field guides treat only one or two species for the southeast USA, five species, &lt;em&gt;A. fuscosuccinea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;A. auricula-judae&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; A. mesenterica&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt; A. polytricha&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;A. delicata&lt;/em&gt; have been reported from the region. This study seeks to evaluate current species concepts using phylogenetic and morphological analysis in order to understand regional diversity as well as provide new reports of geographical distributions. Historical collections from the University of Tennessee Herbarium, as well as fresh material observed in the field, have been examined and sequenced at two loci, ITS and &lt;em&gt;rpb2&lt;/em&gt;. Phylogenetic trees have been constructed using maximum likelihood analysis, and preliminary results show diverse clades in need of taxonomic revision. Variation within traditional taxonomic characters has made it evident that additional characters are required to reflect the genetic diversity in the group. To this end, a new taxonomic character, the schizomedullum, is discussed as an important character to distinguish a new species from the morphologically similar species &lt;em&gt;A. delicata&lt;/em&gt;. In addition, a reticulate, merulioid hymenial surface can no longer be considered a character unique to &lt;em&gt;A. delicata.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/masmc2012/2012/April14/8</coverpage-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-07-05T12:23:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Middle Atlantic States Mycological Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>3057867</context-key>
<submission-path>masmc2012/2012/April14/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T16:05:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Toyota Auditorium, Howard H. Baker Jr. Center for Public Policy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T15:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2012-04-14T15:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>