<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Metathesis of dicobalt hexacarbonyl systems and subsequent applications</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Burlison</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A new method for the preparation of seven to nine-membered rings using ringclosing metathesis of a dicobalt hexacarbonyl alkyne- complex as the critical step is described. Involvement of the organometallic complex introduces a conformational constraint at the metathetical stage and serves as a mask for the alkyne functionality. Metathesis of a variety of substrates containing various types of oxidation in the pseudoparpargyl position is described. Thus, silyl ethers, acetates, and ketones were found to be compatible with metathesis. Results in a homologous series of pseudopropargyllic alcohols were found to metathesize in somewhat lesser yield due to a suspected chelation mechanism. Applications of the complexes in synthesis were generally found consistent with known transformations of acyclics, for example, decomplexation of nine-membered ring complex yielded a cyclononyne. Bicyclic and tricyclic ring systems were found to be accessible using maleic anhydride conversion, Nicholas reaction, or a Pauson-Khand reaction. An approach to a functionalized B-ring related to the curcusone framework resulted in successful closure of the B-ring using ring-closing metathesis of a dicobalt hexacarbonyl alkyne complex. Preliminary studies on the cyclopentenone A-ring using a silicon-tethered reductive Pauson-Khand reaction are also described.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5895</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7528&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5895</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7528</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467551</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5895</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David G. J. Young</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>