<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of the Surface Nanocrystallization and Hardening (SNH) Process on Fatigue Resistance</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wei</lname>
<fname>Yuan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Nanocrystalline and coarse-grained materials have shown high resistances for the fatigue-crack initiation and growth, respectively. In this thesis, the surface- mechanical-attrition (SMA) treatment has been employed for the surface- nanocrystallization and hardening (SNH) process to produce engineered materials with coarse grains in the interior and grain-refinement progressively down to the nano-size on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects of the different processing parameters of the SMA treatment, including the ball size, materials, and treatment time, on the SNH process of the Ti-6Al- 4V and Ni-based Hastelloy® C-2000 Alloys were investigated from the viewpoints of the microstructure, microhardness, surface roughness, and fatigue behavior, by means of the optical microscopy, scanning-electron microscopy, transmission-electron microscopy, X-ray diffraction, Vickers-microhardness indentation, three-dimensional (3D) non-contact scanning white light interferometry profilometer, as well as four- point-bend tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surface-grain refinement was found in all the samples. The surface hardness was improved in the Ni-based Hastelloy® C-2000 superalloys. After the treatment, the surface roughness definitely increased. The fatigue results and fractographes showed that the SMA treatment could improve the fatigue lives. However, the longer-time plus greater-size-balls treatment has the adverse effect on the fatigue lives. The fatigue behaviors of the treated samples were highly influenced by the adhesion-fracture region on the surfaces due to the interaction between the balls and the sample surface during the treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further research activities were suggested in this thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2210</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3615&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2210</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3615</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T12:35:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4693529</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2210</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Raymond A. Buchanan, Hahn Choo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>