<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Training Needs Assessment Model Developed by the Delphi Process for Technology Transfer Programs</title>
<publication-date>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Neal</lname>
<fname>Danal</fname>
<mname>Wayne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine the components of a training needs assessment and to combine these components into a training needs assessment model. The model was developed through a Delphi process using a panel of experts. The model was rated with a survey instrument distributed to and received from a population of technology transfer program planners (practitioners). A review of the literature revealed that even though many training needs assessment methods have been identified, little work was done to build a model which would assist technology transfer programs in determining the training needs of program incumbents. The study was conducted in two parts. In the first part a panel of experts, participating in a Delphi study, identified and classified 18 components into 5 different model phases. The phases identified were Background, Investigation, Implications, Outcome, and Impact. Each of the 18 components was placed in one of these five model phases. In the second part of the study, the identified components were assembled into a questionnaire and rated by technology transfer practitioners from 51 technology transfer programs sponsored by the Federal Highway Administration. The major findings from this study included a critical review of the Delphi model-building process. This review was followed by an analysis of the data from the rating phase of the study. The major findings included the following. 1. The Delphi process was invaluable in initiating and categorizing the components of the Training Needs Assessment for Technology Transfer Model. 2. Using the Delphi process for model-building requires administration and direction from the researcher. 3. The Delphi process is time-consuming for members of the panel of experts. The researcher needs to continue encouragement and &quot;cheerleading&quot; to receive results. 4. When using the Delphi process to build models, the number of rounds can become overly extensive due to the need to summarize and present the expert responses. 5. The final approval of the research required consensus. Consensus, even when the experts are not dealing face to face, is a demanding process of ensuring that each of the experts is content with the model. 6. A model built using a panel of experts and the Delphi process can potentially alienate practitioners. Practitioners may resent using a model designed by others. This situation is inherent to the implementation of any process and is generally dealt with by requiring more participation from the practitioners. The findings in Part II of the study indicated the reactions of the practitioners to the components identified by the experts. 1. The components rated lowest in importance by the practitioners were: determine the setting for training needs assessment, identify performance differences, and initiate environmental scanning. 2. The components rated lowest in amount of use by the practitioners were: determine the setting for training needs assessment, evaluate existing performance levels, determine optimal performance, identify performance differences, and initiate environmental scanning. 3. The components rated lowest in appropriateness by the practitioners were: determine the setting for training needs assessment, determine optimal performance, identify performance differences, and initiate environmental scanning. 4. The components rated lowest by the practitioners for willingness to use the component in a technology transfer program were: identify performance differences and initiate environmental scanning. 5. Ten of the practitioners sent letters expressing their feelings along with their complete or incomplete questionnaires. The dissatisfaction of some of the practitioners concerning the model is noted in the appendix of the dissertation. vii The results of the rating part of the study indicated that the panel of experts in the Delphi phase of the study identified, classified, and categorized effective components for a training needs assessment for use by technology transfer programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5093</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6634&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5093</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6634</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-17T08:04:41-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13496148</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5093</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Clifton P. Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roger Bowlby, Ralph Brockett, Greg Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>