<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Field Experience In Public Health Nutrition With the Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services</title>
<publication-date>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Huff</lname>
<fname>Becky</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis describes and analyzes a field experience in Public Health Nutrition with the Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services. The purpose of the field experience was to supplement a background in academic principles with knowledge acquired through practical work situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conferences and interviews with public health professionals were planned to increase understanding of public health organization. The broad scope of Florida&#39;s nutrition program provided a unique opportunity for the author to observe and participate in a variety of the responsibilities of a Public Health Nutritionist. Portions of the field experience were spent in four different parts of the state to exemplify nutrition programs designed for rural and metropolitan counties, and for groups with specific health and nutritional needs such as the no.grant agricultural workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall field experience showed the author that flexibility, cooperation, planning, coordination, and evaluation are key principles in public health. Communication and planning skills were improved through practice in counseling, teaching, in-service education, and consultation. The author also learned to establish good rapport with the black and Spanish-speaking populations through her work with the Migrant Nutrition Outreach Team. In applying public health principles as a nutritionist she found that her decision to pursue a career in Public Health was reinforced.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3838</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5313&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3838</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5313</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-10T08:20:26-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8957090</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3838</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1971-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>