<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The &lt;em&gt;Temascal&lt;/em&gt; and Humoral Medicine in Santa Cruz Mixtepec, Juxtlahuaca, Oaxaca, Mexico</title>
<publication-date>1981-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ibach</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This investigation reports on the present day use of the sweatbath among an indigenous people in Mexico. The purpose of this thesis was to provide evidence that aboriginal medicine in Mexico contained elements which were based on sets of opposing forces, and that these elements are present in the curing rites of the people of Santa Cruz Mixtepec.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional views of the disease causation and curing are described with particular attention given to the postpartum sweatbath ritual or &lt;em&gt;temascal&lt;/em&gt;. A comparison of this ritual in Santa Cruz Mixtepec to that seen in neighboring communities suggests that humoral medicine is aboriginal in nature, not solely an introduced trait resulting from acculturation to Spanish culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is recommended that because of the ubiquitous nature of the sweatbath in Mexico, future investigations should consider this trait for studying the amount of aboriginal views that remain in a community&#39;s curing techniques and also the amount of acculturation that the community has undergone.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2670</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4067&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2670</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4067</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-22T13:27:17-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5508832</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2670</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael H. Logan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Ann Bass, William M. Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1981-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1981-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>