<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) Tuber Quality as Measured by Starch and Cyanide (HCN) Affected by Nitrogen, Phosphorus, and Potassium Fertilizer Rates</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Cuvaca</lname>
<fname>Ivan</fname>
<mname>Bernardo</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Eash</lname>
<fname>Neal</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Zivanovic</lname>
<fname>Svetlana</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lambert</lname>
<fname>Dayton</fname>
<mname>McGregor</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Walker</lname>
<fname>Forbes</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Rustrick</lname>
<fname>B.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Science</discipline>
<discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) is an important subsistence crop for many poor rural families in Africa. Cassava contains cyanogenic glucosides (linamarin and lotaustralin) which liberate hydrogen cyanide (HCN) during tuber processing. Once liberated, HCN attaches to the processed tuber. Continuous consumption of processed tuber containing high HCN concentration coupled with low protein intake causes Konzo – a paralyzing disorder that impacts children and women of childbearing age. There are ways to reduce HCN concentration during tuber processing; however, this can also reduce the overall starch content in the cassava tuber. A study comprising twenty treatments consisting of different combinations of nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P), and potassium (K) fertilizer rates was initiated in 2013 in the coastal Dondo District of Mozambique to assess cassava tuber quality as measured by starch and HCN. Significant differences were observed in starch content (CSC) of unprocessed tubers due to combined addition of N, P and K fertilizer rates, sample size, and estimation procedure. However, no significant differences were observed in HCN concentration in tubers due to the addition of N, P and K fertilizer. The HCN concentration in cassava tuber appears to be a function of the physiology of the crop or possibly cassava variety rather than the environment or conditions under which the crop is grown.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biospubs/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1012&amp;amp;context=utk_biospubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1012</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-04T07:59:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Biosystems Engineering and Soil Science Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>8420047</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biospubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Cuvaca et al. &quot;Cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) Tuber Quality as Measured by Starch and Cyanide (HCN) Affected by Nitrogen, Phosphorus, and Potassium Fertilizer Rates.&quot; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Agricultural Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 7, no. 6 (2015). doi:10.5539/jas.v7n6p36.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.5539/jas.v7n6p36</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>