<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;An arrow called brotherhood&quot; : Alex Haley&#39;s Roots and Afrocentrism</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Cobb</lname>
<fname>C.</fname>
<mname>Casey</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Alex Haley wrote arguably the two most influential works of African American history of the second half of the twentieth century: The Autobiography of Malcolm X and Roots. Both books sold millions of copies and contributed to an Afrocentric consciousness among black Americans. The publication of Roots and the airing of the television miniseries based on the book became a cultural phenomenon. The book sold more than 12 million copies and more than 13 0 million Americans watched the miniseries. Such a powerful shared cultural experience affected the lives of many Americans during the 1970s. No historian has yet attempted to explain fully the Roots phenomenon. Also no study exists that explains how Alex Haley developed the book&#39;s Afrocentric theme. Questions concerning Haley&#39;s veracity remain unresolved, and no one has defined whether Roots is a novel or non-fiction. Haley&#39;s apparent plagiarism detracts from the legitimacy of Roots as a classroom tool. But the Kunta Kinte story is a powerful Afrocentric myth that explains the African-American experience within American history.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5901</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7534&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5901</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7534</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467557</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5901</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jeff Norrell</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>