<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Person-Environment Fit and Readiness for Change: Exploring the Moderating Role of Leader-Member Exchange and Perceived Organizational Support</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pimentel</lname>
<fname>Joana</fname>
<mname>R.C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Operations Research, Systems Engineering and Industrial Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper was aimed at investigating the interplay of multiple facets of personenvironment fit with individual readiness for change; and to expose potential moderators of this relationship, namely organizational support and quality of relationship with supervisors. The extant research on the relationships between person-environment fit and a number of individual- and organization-level outcomes reveals considerable discrepancies, mainly attributed to the measurement of person-environment fit and to potential moderators. With this in mind, moderated multiple regressions (MMR) were conducted in order to test the hypotheses of existing interaction effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results revealed no significant interactions between facets of personenvironment fit and the moderators proposed. However, the significant correlations found between tenure and readiness for change dimensions led to a series of post hoc analyses to explore whether different tenure groups exhibited different relationship patterns across the variables measured in this study, and to investigate a potential moderating effect of tenure on the relationship between person-environment fit and readiness for change. The results indicated that tenure significantly increased the prediction of readiness for change by person-environment fit, underscoring the importance of workforce composition on readiness for change research. The findings obtained hold interesting implications for both research and practice concerning the measurement of person-environment fit, and with respect to the impact of individual- and organization-level variables on the relationship between person-environment fit and readiness for change. These implications, along with limitations of the present study, are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/588</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1656&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>588</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1656</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-23T11:00:49-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1165045</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/588</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David J. Woehr</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael C. Rush, Joan Rentsch, David W. Schumann</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial and Organizational Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008Dissertations/PimentelJoanaRC.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>