<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A More Critical Use of Fairness Opinions as a Practical Approach to the Behavioral Economics of Mergers and Acquisitions</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>fairness opinions</keyword>
<keyword>mergers</keyword>
<keyword>acquisitions</keyword>
<keyword>behavioral economics</keyword>
<keyword>bias</keyword>
<keyword>systematic error</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  paper responds to Professor Donald C. Langevoort&#39;s essay entitled &quot;The  Behavioral Economics of Mergers and Acquisitions&quot; (12 Transactions:  Tenn. J. Bus. L. 65 (2011)). Together with Professor Langevoort&#39;s essay  and another responsive work written from the standpoint of behavioral  psychology – Eric Sundstrom&#39;s &quot;Tall Steps, Slippery Slopes &amp;  Learning Curves in the Behavioral Economics of Mergers &amp;  Acquisitions&quot; (12 Transactions: Tenn. J. Bus. L. 65 (2011)) – this paper  preliminarily explores solutions to behavioral issues in the context of  mergers and acquisitions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Specifically, this paper contends that  changes in the contents, construction, use, and assessment of fairness  opinions may better enable fairness opinions to counteract the potential  and actual biases of corporate management and shareholders in M&amp;A  decision-making. The paper begins by briefly reviewing the nature  (attributes, benefits and detriments), regulation, and utilization of  fairness opinions in the M&amp;A transactional process, including the  ways in which fairness opinions manifest, support, and attempt to  counteract behavioral norms. Next, the paper suggests best practices in  the construction and use of fairness opinions that take into account our  knowledge of behavioral psychology as it relates to M&amp;A  transactions. The net effect of these best practices is to transform  what may be unconscious behavioral norms into conscious biases that,  once exposed, can be confronted and, as desired, mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/25</coverpage-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1013</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-26T09:50:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2032380</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/25</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, A More Critical Use of Fairness Opinions as a Practical Approach to the Behavioral Economics of Mergers and Acquisitions. Transactions: Tennessee Journal of Business Law, p. 81, 2011 . Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1833406</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1833406</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>