<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Enron&#39;s Tangled Web: Complex Relationships; Unanswered Questions</title>
<publication-date>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Enron</keyword>
<keyword>Agency</keyword>
<keyword>Sarbanes-Oxley</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agency</discipline>
<discipline>Business Administration, Management, and Operations</discipline>
<discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This  essay originally was presented orally at the University of Cincinnati  College of Law&#39;s Sixteenth Annual Corporate Law Symposium. The essay  describes corporate agency and agency-related relationships as  implicated in the &quot;Enron affair&quot; and explores ways in which the  Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 fails or attempts to address the alleged  malfunctions in these relationships. The essay concludes that the  reforms enacted in Sarbanes-Oxley provide little assistance in resolving  agency and agency-related problems associated with Enron&#39;s public  misstatements and omissions. Ultimately, the essay exhorts scholars and  practicing lawyers to work together to resolve these problems through  (among other things) additional research into cognitive and behavioral  science and direct client assistance both in the decision making process  and in the search for and selection of corporate directors and  officers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/27</coverpage-url>
<label>27</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1033</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-06-01T13:57:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2042255</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/27</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Enron&#39;s Tangled Web: Complex Relationships; Unanswered Questions. University of Cincinnati Law Review, Vol. 71, p. 1167, 2003. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=491962</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=491962</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>