<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Development of Attention Systems and Working Memory in Infancy</title>
<publication-date>2016-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>greynolds@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Reynolds</lname>
<fname>Greg</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Romano</lname>
<fname>Alexandra</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>infancy</keyword>
<keyword>visual attention</keyword>
<keyword>recognition memory</keyword>
<keyword>working memory</keyword>
<keyword>event-related potentials</keyword>
<keyword>heart rate</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;x-x-x-__p3&quot;&gt;In this article, we review research and theory on the development of attention and working memory in infancy using a developmental cognitive neuroscience framework. We begin with a review of studies examining the influence of attention on neural and behavioral correlates of an earlier developing and closely related form of memory (i.e., recognition memory). Findings from studies measuring attention utilizing looking measures, heart rate, and event-related potentials (ERPs) indicate significant developmental change in sustained and selective attention across the infancy period. For example, infants show gains in the magnitude of the attention related response and spend a greater proportion of time engaged in attention with increasing age (Richards and Turner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4776056/#B79&quot; id=&quot;x-x-x-__tag_517964099&quot;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;). Throughout infancy, attention has a significant impact on infant performance on a variety of tasks tapping into recognition memory; however, this approach to examining the influence of infant attention on memory performance has yet to be utilized in research on working memory. In the second half of the article, we review research on working memory in infancy focusing on studies that provide insight into the developmental timing of significant gains in working memory as well as research and theory related to neural systems potentially involved in working memory in early development. We also examine issues related to measuring and distinguishing between working memory and recognition memory in infancy. To conclude, we discuss relations between the development of attention systems and working memory.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_psycpubs/13</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1020&amp;amp;context=utk_psycpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>13</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1020</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-13T11:02:30-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Psychology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>9263445</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_psycpubs/13</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Reynolds GD and Romano AC (2016) The Development of Attention Systems and Working Memory in Infancy. Front. Syst. Neurosci. 10:15. doi: 10.3389/fnsys.2016.00015</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.3389/fnsys.2016.00015</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>