<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessment of Public Attitudes and Knowledge Concerning Wastewater Reuse and Biosolids Recycling</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ma</lname>
<fname>Chun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A telephone survey instrument was developed and administrated to evaluate public attitudes and knowledge concerning wastewater reuse and biosolids recycling with respect to population demographics (gender, age, education level, and household income). Information from 300 Knox County area residents was collected and analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study indicated that 58% of respondents supported wastewater reuse and 75% of respondents supported biosolids recycling. Acceptance decreased with increasing possibility of contact for both wastewater reuse and biosolids recycling. For wastewater reuse, respondents were positive to applications not involving close personal contact (such as firefighting, car washing, lawn irrigation and agricultural uses), while uses of wastewater for possible consumption (released into potable surface or groundwater supplies) or applications involving close personal contact (laundry) were unfavorable. No significant difference was found between females and males concerning wastewater reuse; however, females tended to be more resistant to options that involved close personal contact. Age was significantly associated with attitudes. In particular, the 65 or over age group was significantly less supportive of wastewater reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For biosolids recycling, participants responded favorably for all eight application uses (on farmland, grazing land, public parks, highway medians, home gardens, lawns, forest land, and as mulch after composting), except those 65 years of age and older. This cohort felt significantly less favorable towards five of the options than did other age groups. No significant difference was found between females and males concerning biosolids recycling. Education was not statistically associated with attitudes; however, the high school or less group tended to be less positive than other groups. This study also found that the test population was not very knowledgeable of wastewater reuse and biosolids recycling issues. The overall level of correct responses to six topical questions was less than fifty percent. Knowledge was found to be lower with increased age (≥ 65) and lower educational attainment level (≤ high school degree). Knowledge was significantly and positively associated with attitudes, so increasing knowledge was likely to increase public support. Additionally, this study indicated that television and newspaper were dominant information sources for environmental news and that sources such as governmental agencies, local utilities and environmental groups were likely to be negligible information sources.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2108</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3469&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2108</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3469</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-04T13:21:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4671719</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2108</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kevin G. Robinson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory D. Reed, Chris D. Cox</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>