<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>‘Animal sentience and its implications for human-animal interaction – concepts for animal professionals’</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-13T10:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>katherine.van.ekert@gmail.com</email>
<institution>The University of Queensland</institution>
<lname>van Ekert</lname>
<fname>Katherine</fname>
<mname>E J</mname>
<suffix>Ms</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research investigating animal consciousness and mental states, and the recent Cambridge Declaration on Consciousness, have provided invaluable support to what many of us have always known. Animals are sentient beings, and like us, have the ability to perceive and feel, and therefore the ability to experience pleasure and pain. The implication of our recognition of animal sentience is interesting to consider in the context of human animal interactions. Of significance, is whether our current laws regarding animals, our codes of practice, and industry standards, would suffice if they were written with a full understanding and consideration of animal sentience. As professionals working in animal-related fields, this recognition of sentience can also place us with an often uncomfortable responsibility. As society places increasing value on animal welfare, it will be up to animal professions to maintain our standard as safeguards of animals’ best interests. We will be increasingly forced to consider factors other than those raised by the prevailing pressures of commercialism and utilitarianism; factors arising from the animal itself and his or her welfare needs. These decisions must be based on scientific evidence. But one must also be prepared to previous assumptions in this dynamic field, and work within an ethical framework that guides our decisions when the science lets us down by not answering our questions, or by providing us with answers that appear inconsistent. Our treatment of animals through actions that reflect their innate value, can only but enhance our humanity and our treatment of each other, as we learn to nurture that trait so highly revered in our own species: empathy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april13/4</coverpage-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1060</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-19T00:10:19-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utvswsummit/article/1060/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3549501</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april13/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Dr Katherine van Ekert, Veterinarian and PhD candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President - Sentient, The Veterinary Institute for Animal Ethics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katherine has worked as a veterinarian in various mixed and small animal practices in Australia, including the RSPCA. Most recently she worked as Veterinary Officer for Animal Welfare at the Bureau of Animal Welfare, Victorian Department of Primary Industries, Australia. She is also founding president of the veterinary-driven organisation, &#39;Sentient, The Veterinary Institute for Animal Ethics.&#39; Katherine has recently commenced a PhD examining the links between domestic violence and animal abuse.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52A Yarra St&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abbotsford, Victoria 3067&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AUSTRALUA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;katherine.van.ekert@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;+61411073270&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T11:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>SUMMIT ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>rtmp</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_url" type="string">
<value>//trace.lib.utk.edu/assets/VSW/2013/KatherinevanEkertOnay.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T10:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_file" type="string">
<value>VSW/2013/KatherinevanEkertOnay.mp4</value>
</field>
<field name="rtmp_streamer" type="string">
<value>rtmp://trace.lib.utk.edu:1935/stream</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-13T10:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Ethical dilemmas in social work and animals</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Workshop_handout_Katherine_van_Ekert.docx</archive-name>
<upload-name>Workshop_handout_Katherine_van_Ekert.docx</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1060&amp;amp;context=utvswsummit&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>