<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Collaborative Models for Supply Networks Coordination and Healthcare Consolidation</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>smohebbi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mohebbi</lname>
<fname>Shima</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Coordination</keyword>
<keyword>Game Theory</keyword>
<keyword>Agent-based Simulation</keyword>
<keyword>Supply Networks</keyword>
<keyword>Consolidated Healthcare Systems</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Industrial Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Operational Research</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This work discusses the collaboration framework among different members of two complex systems: supply networks and consolidated healthcare systems. Although existing literature advocates the notion of strategic partnership/cooperation in both supply networks and healthcare systems, there is a dearth of studies quantitatively analyzing the scope of cooperation among the members and its benefit on the global performance. Hence, the first part of this dissertation discusses about two-echelon supply networks and studies the coordination of buyers and suppliers for multi-period procurement process. Viewing the issue from the same angel, the second part studies the coordination framework of hospitals for consolidated healthcare service delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realizing the dynamic nature of information flow and the conflicting objectives of members in supply networks, a two-tier coordination mechanism among buyers and suppliers is modeled. The process begins with the intelligent matching of buyers and suppliers based on the similarity of users profiles. Then, a coordination mechanism for long-term agreements among buyers and suppliers is proposed. The proposed mechanism introduces the importance of strategic buyers for suppliers in modeling and decision making process. To enhance the network utilization, we examine a further collaboration among suppliers where cooperation incurs both cost and benefit. Coalitional game theory is utilized to model suppliers&#39; coalition formation. The efficiency of the proposed approaches is evaluated through simulation studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then revisit the common issue, the co-existence of partnership and conflict objectives of members, for consolidated healthcare systems and study the coordination of hospitals such that there is a central referral system to facilitate patients transfer. We consider three main players including physicians, hospitals managers, and the referral system. As a consequence, the interaction within these players will shape the coordinating scheme to improve the overall system performance. To come up with the incentive scheme for physicians and aligning hospitals activities, we define a multi-objective mathematical model and obtain optimal transfer pattern. Using optimal solutions as a baseline, a cooperative game between physicians and the central referral system is defined to coordinate decisions toward system optimality. The efficiency of the proposed approach is examined via a case study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3450</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4829&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3450</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4829</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-05-19T13:49:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7120515</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3450</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Xueping Li</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mingzhou Jin, Oleg Shylo, Hamparsum Bozdogan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>