<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect modification of the association between aerobic physical activity and diabetes-related mortality by race-ethnicity: a population-based prospective study using NHANES III and 1999-2006 NHANES</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>wboyer1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Boyer</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Robert</mname>
<suffix>II</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>exercise</keyword>
<keyword>diabetes</keyword>
<keyword>mortality</keyword>
<keyword>NHANES</keyword>
<keyword>prospective cohort</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; To examine potential effect modification by race-ethnicity of the relationship between physical activity (PA) and diabetes-related mortality risk using a sample of U.S. adults from the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES III). &lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; The sample (n=10,717) included adults (≥20 years) who attended the Mobile Examination Center (MEC). An age-standardized PA score (PAS) was calculated from the self-reported frequency and intensity of 12 leisure-time aerobic activities. The PA scores were then grouped into three categories: inactive (PAS = 0), insufficiently active (PAS &gt;0 - Results: There was no interaction between PA and race-ethnicity (p=0.83). Compared to inactive NHW, there was a significantly lower risk for diabetes-related mortality for insufficiently active (Hazard Ratio [HR] 0.51, 95% Confidence Interval [CI] 0.29-0.89) and active (HR 0.57, 95% CI 0.33-1.00) NHW adults. Statistical significance was not achieved for any level of activity for NHB and MA. A significant p-for-trend was revealed only for MA. &lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; The results of this study suggest that accumulation of any volume of PA is associated with a significantly lowered risk for diabetes-related mortality only in NHW. A significant dose-response relationship was only observed among MA. However, the interaction between race-ethnicity and PA did not attain statistical significance. Thus, the presence of effect modification could not be determined from the current study, but further investigation is warranted. Given longer follow-up time in the NHANES III cohort, the ability to estimate more precise risk reductions will become plausible.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4606</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6173&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4606</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6173</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-15T12:35:05-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/6173/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10310210</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4606</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James R. Churilla, Samantha F. Ehrlich, Scott E. Crouter, Lyndsey M. Hornbuckle</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>