<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Vision-Based Reinforcement Learning Using A Consolidated Actor-Critic Model</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Niedzwiedz</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>Allen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Computer Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Vision-based machine learning agents are tasked with making decisions based on high-dimensional, noisy input, placing a heavy load on available resources. Moreover, observations typically provide only partial information with respect to the environment state, necessitating robust state inference by the agent. Reinforcement learning provides a framework for decision making with the goal of maximizing long-term reward. This thesis introduces a novel approach to vision-based reinforce- ment learning through the use of a consolidated actor-critic model (CACM). The approach takes advantage of artificial neural networks as non-linear function approximators and the reduced com- putational requirements of the CACM scheme to yield a scalable vision-based control system. In this thesis, a comparison between the actor-critic and CACM is made. Additionally, the affect of observation prediction and correlated exploration has on the agent&#39;s performance is investigated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/548</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1582&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>548</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1582</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-26T11:30:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1176259</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/548</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Itamar Arel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gregory Peterson, Hairong Qi</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Computer Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>