<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Recapturing Urban Space: An Inhabited Bridge in Nashville, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bculber2@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Culbertson</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>Smith</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Inhabited</keyword>
<keyword>Bridge</keyword>
<keyword>Urbanized</keyword>
<keyword>Nashville</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architectural Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Density. A word used in the description of many large cities. It is how so many people can fit into a relatively compact area and still operate efficiently. Density, used as a tool to craft cities can generate spectacular moments. Several centuries ago, one of these moments was the inhabited bridge. It provided the continuity of the urban fabric by linking areas that were separated by rivers and other natural boundaries. They were nodes in the city that housed commerce, social activity, and residences. However, as cities grew to be more globally connected hubs, the needs of the pedestrian fell way to the needs of the bigger, faster transportation. With this shift in the socioeconomic status quo, the inhabited bridge was unable to meet the new demands of the city and thus fell out of favor within developing cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, we have seen a shift in population distribution; people are moving back to the city. They are seeking jobs, residences, and better lifestyles. We will soon be faced with an issue of providing enough amenities for this influx of new residents. How will cities adapt and change to suit the needs of this increase in population? One answer: density. The need for densification of the city will always lead to new innovations and solutions. I believe one solution to this impending issue can begin with a new take on the inhabited/urbanized bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this study, I intend to take the old typology, the inhabited bridge, as a base and begin to explore/expand the concept to see how it might provide solutions in the context of today. The case study will include a design proposition in downtown Nashville, TN, which has an estimated population increase of one million by the year 2035 (Nashville MPO). The intent of this study is not to completely solve the issue of city densification and connection of urban fabric. Rather, it is to explore the opportunities unique to this typology and hopefully stimulate conversation around the topic of crafting density within a city.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2803</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3989&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2803</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3989</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-28T06:52:14-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/3989/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5235433</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2803</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hansjoerg Goeritz, James D Matthews</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>