<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Report of Field Training With the Nutrition Unit of the Minnesota Department of Health</title>
<publication-date>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rider</lname>
<fname>Martha</fname>
<mname>Russell</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Seven weeks were spent in Public Health Nutrition field training with the Minnesota Department of Health under the direction of the Supervisor of the Nutrition Unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field training was planned for the purpose of helping the student obtain a practical understanding of the functions of an official health agency, and particularly of the role of the public health nutritionist within the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six weeks of the field training included orientation in selected divisions of the Minnesota Department of Health. It also included observation of the nutrition program within the department and with other official and voluntary agencies and professional groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observation of the nutrition program and the types of services rendered by the public health nutritionist has increased the student&#39;s understanding of the nutritionist&#39;s responsibilities and functions. The study of the philosophy, objectives, needs, and educational techniques of the Nutrition Unit of the Minnesota Department of Health enhanced the student&#39;s educational background, and should serve to increase her knowledge and awareness of her responsibility in the promotion of good nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3900</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5379&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3900</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5379</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-26T05:47:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9036130</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3900</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Beth Duncan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Florence L. MacLeod, Harold H. Walker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>