<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessing Motives for Consensual Sex: Development of the Sexual Motives Questionnaire</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>vtirone@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Tirone</lname>
<fname>Vanessa</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>sexual behavior</keyword>
<keyword>motives</keyword>
<keyword>sexuality</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study describes the development and preliminary validation of the Sexual Motives Questionnaire (SMQ), a measure of motives for consensual sex. The measure is informed two dispositional theories, functional theory and self-construal theories, which suggest that individuals are motivated to engage in behavior due to approach/avoidance and independent/interdependent tendencies, respectively. Items were also selected to reflect sexual scripts and fear of sexual and physical violence. A total of 81 items was administered to 920 undergraduates. Exploratory factor analysis was conducted utilizing the 821 participants with complete data. The final sample was predominately heterosexual (96%) and Caucasian (83%) with a mean age of 19.27 (&lt;em&gt;SD &lt;/em&gt;= 3.07). About half of participants were female. A 6 factor structure was obtained consisting of 2 approach factors (&lt;em&gt;Relational &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Pleasure&lt;/em&gt;) and 4 avoidance factors (&lt;em&gt;Appease-partner, Prevent-harm, Reassure-self,&lt;/em&gt; and&lt;em&gt; Reputation&lt;/em&gt;). Generally, the SMQ demonstrated convergent and discriminant validity consistent with expectations. Confirmatory factor analysis is needed to further validate the SMQ. However, preliminary data suggests that this measure has the potential to examine the relation between sexual motives and sexual health and functioning, and the impact of sexual victimization on these domains.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3205</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3040&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3205</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3040</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-10T06:12:09-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4209507</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3205</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Todd M. Moore</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kristina Gordon, Cheryl Travis, Suzanne Kurth, Jennifer Katz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>