<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Numerical methods for fully nonlinear second order partial differential equations</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Neilan</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Mathematics</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation concerns the numerical approximations of solutions of fully nonlinear second order partial differential equations (PDEs). The numerical methods and analysis are based on a new concept of weak solutions called moment solutions, which unlike viscosity solutions, are defined by a constructive method called the vanishing moment method. The main idea of the vanishing moment method is to approximate fully nonlinear second order PDEs by a family of fourth order quasi-linear PDEs. Because the method is constructive, we can develop a wealth of convergent numerical discretization methods to approximate fully nonlinear second order PDEs. We first study the numerical approximation of the prototypical second order fully nonlilnear PDE, the Monge-Ampère equation, det(D²u) = f (&gt; 0), using C¹ finite element methods, spectral Galerkin methods, mixed finite element methods, and a nonconforming Morley finite element method. We then generalize the analysis to other fully nonlinear second order PDEs including the nonlinear balance equation, a nonlinear formulation of semigeostrophic flow equations, and the equation of prescribed Gauss curvature.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6027</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7960&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6027</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7960</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467776</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6027</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Xiaobing Feng</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mathematics</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>