<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Vocational Education in the High School Curriculum</title>
<publication-date>1928-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bryan</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Leeman</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The title of this study &quot;Vocational Education in the High School Curriculum&quot; is more comprehensive than the study. The object of the study is to show, in part, the present status of Vocational Education in the High school Curriculum, with a proposed plan for Vocational Education in a specified school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly the study attempts to answer the following questions: Is our system of education wholly or partially democratic? What is the attitude of the Federal Government toward Vocational Education? To what extent does the Federal Government finance Vocational Education? To what extent is Vocational Agricultural Education being taught in the high schools of the United States? To what extent is Vocational Home Economics being taught in the high schools of the United States? To what extent do the high schools offer Commercial Vocational Training? To what extent do the high schools attempt to prepare the youth for trades and industrial occupation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end there is presented in the first chapter a brief historical background, giving the opinions of some early educational reformers, some of the early attempts at manual instruction, and the probable influence these opinions and experiments had on the succeeding educational leaders. Also a brief history of the apprenticeship system and the reasons why it is not a suitable institution for today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter II the writer has attempted to give several logical reasons why there is a need for Vocational Education in the high school curriculum today. Chapter III is concerned with Vocational Education since the passage of the Smith-Hughes Act (present status).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study has been purely academic. The material is so arranged that the reader may study the different phases of the research separately. The statistical material presented represents the latest to be found at this time, and as recorded in the most reliable sources. Reference is given as to the source of each table and diagram under each heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data of the tables and diagrams presented were arranged with the idea of simplicity in mind and of being self explanatory, for that reason very little comment is made on such material herewith presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the appendix is given some material which may be of interest to anyone who is attempting to organize a vocational training course in his school. The forms of contracts given and the requirements are specifically for Vocational Agricultural Education, but substantially the same forms and requirements are set up for other courses that may be organized under the provisions of the Smith-Hughes Act. The text of the Act is also included in the appendix so that any question regarding the distribution of money, administrative policies, or conditions that the Federal Government imposes upon the State and local community might be answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study is by no means comprehensive, but with the limited amount of source material examined, the purpose of the study fulfilled, the writer hopes that the findings will be of value to those interested in Vocational Education in the high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed plan as indicated and outlined in Chapter IV is for the six-year high school at South Charleston, West Virginia, where the writer serves in the capacity of principal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3070</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4436&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3070</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4436</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-08T13:57:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6513317</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3070</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ffe9fbdb0)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1928-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1928-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>