<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Curricular Elements of Problem-Based Learning That Cause Developments of Self-Directed Learning Behaviors Among Students and Its Implications on Elementary Education</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Karabulut</lname>
<fname>Ulku</fname>
<mname>Serezli</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Rapid technological and social changes and developments in the world put high demands on individuals. The high demanding world increases the pressure on educational systems to be more effective. “Therefore, educators have looked at constructivist pedagogical designs that are based of cognitive and social interactions in problem-centered environments” (Greeno, Collins, &amp; Resnick, 1996; Savery &amp; Duffy, 1994). It is claimed that the active learning emphasized in PBL promotes self-directed learning strategies needed for lifelong learning. Self-directed learning is related with cognitive ability, selfconcept, and achievement. Therefore, it is important to determine curricular elements of problem-based learning that cause self-directed behaviors among its students. Problem-based curriculum is student centered, students attempt to identify and solve a problem with their existing knowledge, they identify knowledge deficits and generate appropriate learning issues, they independently search the learning issues, critiquing the resources used for research, and apply the new knowledge to the problem, and students in the small group collaborative reflection on self-directed behavior improve students’ self-directed behaviors. It is believed that discussions in the tutorial group, content to be tested, lectures, tutor, and reference literature also impact on students’ self-directed behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the studies about problem-based learning and self-directed behaviors have been carried out among college students more particularly among medical students. On the other hand elementary students have different characteristics than do medical students. The basic elements of problem-based curriculum, which affect students’ self-directed learning behaviors, require some changes and modifications so that they can be effectively applied to elementary-aged students.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2078</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3440&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2078</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3440</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T09:02:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4662797</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2078</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas N. Turner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lester N. Knight, Colleen P. Gilrane</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>