<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Construction of Bacteriophage-Based Bioluminescent Bioreporters for &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Monitoring</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ozen</lname>
<fname>Aysu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Construction of two recombinant &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; bacteriophage-based bioluminescent bioreporters was undertaken to develop detection and monitoring systems for &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; spp. These systems take advantage of the high specificity of bacteriophage for their hosts and the &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fischeri lux&lt;/em&gt; operon responsible for quorum sensing bioluminescence. The detection system is composed of two elements, a recombinant phage with &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; which is specific for the target pathogen, and an acylhomoserine lactone (AHL)-inducible bioreporter cell line carrying the reporter &lt;em&gt;lux&lt;/em&gt; genes. The goal of this study was to construct &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt;- and &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt;-specific recombinant phages which contain &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; expression in &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; was controlled by cloning the gene into &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; under the control of a Gram-positive promoter and ribosomal binding site (RBS). The same construct was also placed into &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Bacillus subtilis&lt;/em&gt; for comparison purposes. Although light was produced by &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt;, there was no light from &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt;. The presence of &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; transcript was shown in all strains using real time qRTPCR. Western blotting detected &lt;em&gt;LuxI&lt;/em&gt; only in &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; but not in &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt;. After the construct RBS was shown to be effective, the codon utilization of &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; was adapted to &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; phage P68 genome to eliminate a possible codon preference problem. Optimization had no effect on &lt;em&gt;S. aureus&lt;/em&gt; while it resulted in a significant decrease of light from &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; and a non-significant increase in &lt;em&gt;B. subtilis&lt;/em&gt;. Additional studies are needed to determine reason(s) for &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; expression problem in &lt;em&gt;S. aureus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salmonella choleraesuis&lt;/em&gt;, which carries &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt; under the control of &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; phage P22 promoter and a Gram-negative RBS, produced high levels of light. The &lt;em&gt;luxI&lt;/em&gt;, under the control of the same promoter and RBS, was cloned into the phage P22 genome using homologous recombination. The recombinant phage P22luxI induced light from the bioreporter only when it was propagated using &lt;em&gt;S. choleraesuis&lt;/em&gt; which harbored the homologous recombination plasmid. The bioluminescent bioreporter &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; OHHLux was shown to produce light in the presence of P22luxI without the &lt;em&gt;S. choleraesuis&lt;/em&gt; host. Bioluminescence tests showed P22luxI as the source of the problem. &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; OHHLux was shown not to be lysed by P22 or P22luxI and not to uptake the P22luxI genome during bioluminescence tests. P22luxI and &lt;em&gt;S. choleraesuis&lt;/em&gt; in combination produced AHL by using an AHL bioreporter, &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium tumefaciens&lt;/em&gt; A136. Since &lt;em&gt;A. tumefaciens&lt;/em&gt; A136 is not specific enough to use for quantification of AHL, another bioreporter was constructed by placing the &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; OHHLux plasmid into &lt;em&gt;Klebsiella&lt;/em&gt; strains. They produced light with P22luxI without the host like the previous bioreporter. Future studies should focus on constructing a bioreporter strain which does not produce light when mixed with P22luxI without its host. Optimization, and sensitivity and specificity determination studies of the system should be performed using this bioreporter strain.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/258</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1311&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>258</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1311</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-04T12:32:45-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1132391</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/258</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gary S. Sayler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Steven Ripp, Pamela Small, Stephen Oliver, Steven Wilhelm</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/OzenAysu.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>