<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Black bear relocation as a method to reduce elk calf predation within Great Smoky Mountains National Park</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Yarkovich</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Gene</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Wildlife and fisheries science</keyword>
<keyword>Elk</keyword>
<keyword>Black bear</keyword>
<keyword>Wildlife management</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;An experimental release of elk was initiated in 2001 to assess the feasibility of population reestablishment in Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Initial analysis was conducted in 2006 and calf survival across that period averaged 0.592 with adult survival ranging from 0.689 to 0.926, differing by age and sex. Initial population projections produced annual growth rates that ranged from 1.051 at year 1 to 0.984 at year 25 with an average of 0.988. Under these conditions, the population failed to maintain a positive growth rate in 70% of projections. From May 2006 through July 2008, I trapped bears in Cataloochee Valley and relocated them to the western portion of the Park during elk calving season attempting to increase calf survival. We trapped and relocated 49 bears from 2006-2008, and most adult bears were radiocollared (n = 30).Forty-seven percent (n = 14) of collared bears returned to the capture area, 16% (n = 5) experienced mortality after release, 10% (n = 3) did not show homing behavior, and the fates of the remaining 27% (n = 8) were unknown. At the end of 2008, a total of 42 additional calves had been radio collared and tracked to determine fates. Average calf survival in program MARK changed from 0.592 to 0.690 from before (2001-2005) to after (2006-2008) bear relocation, but predation by black bears remained the largest known source of calf mortality from 2006 to 2008. Adult survival increased, with 2006-2008 rates ranging from 0.846 to 0.947 for males and 0.910 to 0.970 for females. Calf production rates for females from 2006-2008 increased to 0.429, 0.800, and 0.923 for females in the 2-year old, 3-9 year old, and 10-14 year old age classes, respectively.Using the 2006-2008 parameters, I estimated long-term growth rates and simulations maintained a positive growth rate in 100% of trials and produced an average annual growth rate of 1.117. Analyzing the entire reintroduction period, 2001-2008, simulations maintained a positive growth rate in 100% of trials and produced an average annual growth rate of 1.070.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5768</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7390&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5768</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7390</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467536</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5768</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph Clark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>