<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Lifetime-Prediction Approach to Understanding Corrosion: The Corrosion-Fatigue and the Corrosion Behavior of a Nickel-Based Superalloy and a Nanocrystalline Alloy</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of ten</institution>
<lname>Steward</lname>
<fname>Rejanah</fname>
<mname>Vernice</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Lifetime-prediction models are useful for simulating a material’s in-service behavior or outcome. Perhaps the greatest advantage of these models is the ability to use the predicted results to help optimize engineering designs and reduce costs. The Hastelloy&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; C-2000&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; superalloy is a single-phase material and face-centered cubic in structure at all temperatures. The C-2000&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; alloy is a commercially designed alloy manufactured to function in both reducing and oxidizing solutions. C-2000&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; is used as a fabrication material for heat exchangers, piping for chemical refineries, and storage repositories. The corrosion properties of C-2000&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; are excellent, and the ductility and fatigue properties are good. In this study, C-2000&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; is used to verify the theoretical basis of an electrochemical-micromechanical crack-initiation corrosion-fatigue model for materials under passive electrochemical conditions. The results from electrochemical and mechanical experiments, along with the findings from the conventional electron microscopy and a laser interferometer will be presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nanocrystalline Ni-18 weight percent (wt.%) Fe alloy is examined to investigate its electrochemical behavior in a 3.5 wt.% NaCl solution. Three Ni-18 wt.% Fe samples were annealed at 400ºC for 3, 8, and 24 hours (hrs.) to study the effects of grain sizes on the electrochemical properties of bulk Ni-18 wt.% Fe. The electrochemical results from the annealed samples are compared with those measured for the as-received Ni-18 wt.% Fe material consisting of an average grain size of 23 nanometers (nm). The samples annealed for times longer than 8 hrs. appear to have undergone an abnormal grain growth, where nanometer and micrometer (μm) grain sizes are present. Unlike the electrochemical results for the as-received material, the annealed nanocrystalline materials appear to be susceptible to localized corrosion. Consequently, these larger grains within the nanoncrystalline-grain matrix are preferentially attacked during electrochemical corrosion. Of the four materials studied, the as-received nanocrystalline alloy possesses the best corrosion properties, and the nanocrystalline material coarsened to an average grain size of 23 μm has the poorest electrochemical properties.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2038</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3474&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2038</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3474</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-25T10:14:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4627470</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2038</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Joy, Charles Feigerle, Claudia Rawn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>