<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Jump Rope
Connecting the Past, Present and Future</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Woodard</lname>
<fname>Nicholas</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Jump Rope</keyword>
<keyword>Sport History</keyword>
<keyword>Sport Participation</keyword>
<keyword>Youth Sport</keyword>
<keyword>International Sport</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Jump rope is an activity that most people have experienced at some point in their lives. It is the type of activity that can help bring joy, build physical fitness, and for some it is an internationally competitive sport. The competitive aspect of jump rope is unfamiliar to most people. The activity itself can be dated back to the 1600’s, but formally organized competitions did not take form until the 1970’s.	The sport of jump rope has a rich history, but the story has not been fully documented. This research paper examines the history and the current landscape of jump rope in the United States, as well as how the sport has spread around the world. An additional purpose of the study was to explore public awareness of the sport’s existence. The theoretical framework of leisure constraints was used to aid in understanding current participation in competitive jump rope and to discuss potential methods for increasing involvement in the future. 	Through this research we began to understand the history and evolution of jump rope, but there are aspects of the sport and organizational structure that still require further research. This paper is the first academic attempt to expound upon the vague bits of history that have been documented on jump rope websites. It also provides a systematic connection between the current state of the sport and its future potential for expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5562</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7096&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5562</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7096</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T08:30:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>20409603</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5562</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Steven Waller Ph.D.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jeffery Graham Ph.D., Angela Wozencroft Ph.D.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Recreation and Sport Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>