<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Southville Revisted</title>
<publication-date>1979-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rubenstein</lname>
<fname>Marvin</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Soloway</lname>
<fname>Cynthia</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Southville Revisited is a quantitative-descriptive study which examined (1) the extent to which Jews in Memphis identify with traditional Jewish values; (2) the effectiveness of current goals and objectives of the Memphis Jewish communal agencies in satisfying the needs of the community; (3) the comparison of the 1979 sample of the population with the respondents in the Southville Survey of 1959; and (4) new directions in planning and in expanding Jewish communal services to meet changing needs evidenced in the current study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to accomplish these goals, the researchers utilized approximately 75 percent of the questions derived from the 1959 Southville Survey of Jewish Attitudes. In addition, the researchers added seventeen questions pertaining to the Jewish educational level of the respondents, their views on Israel, and programming for the elderly and Russian immigrants. Sixty-four questions, covering 10 pages, were asked of the respondents in a self-administered questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selection of the 1979 sample was based on a systematic random selection of Jewish heads of households. A master list of current heads of households was obtained from the Memphis Jewish Federation from which every thirtieth name was selected. The target population was to represent 3 percent of the Jewish heads of households in Memphis, approximately one hundred persons. The researchers were able to obtain seventy-five completed questionnaires. The process of dissemination and completion of the questionnaires by the sample selected began in the month of October 1978 and was completed in January of 1979.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major findings of the Southville Revisited study included the following: (1) the present sample appears to be an older and more financially and occupationally secure population than the 1959 respondents; (2) the age, income, education, and length of residence of the respondents appears to have a significant influence on the Jewish identity of those questioned; and (3) the importance of Jewish communal agencies (e.g., Jewish Community Center, Jewish Service Agency) indicated by the respondents seems to be offset by the lack of Jewish identification seen in their programming. A lack of Jewish educational background among the 1979 sample was also noticed. Many of the findings of the 1979 sample were seen to be similar to those in the 1959 study in areas such as commitment to Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the knowledge gained from the 1979 sample, a number of program implications became evident. These recommendations included, among others, that communal agencies design programs that appeal to an educated population. These programs should incorporate identifiable Jewish values and customs. Programs related to single parents, separated, divorced, or widowed, should be initiated into the local Jewish community. Programs as well as direct services by the Jewish communal agencies must therefore be positively identified with Jewish values and practices in order to have impact upon the Jewish population in Memphis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4938</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6383&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4938</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6383</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-03-15T09:04:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>11782981</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4938</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marvin D. Feit</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hugh Vaughn, Michael Holosko</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1979-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1979-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>