<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Determining the Impact on Varying Methods for Acid Adaptation on Thermal Resistance of Shiga Toxigenic &lt;i&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/i&gt; (STEC), &lt;i&gt;Listeria monocytogenes&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Salmonella enterica&lt;/i&gt; in Orange Juice</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>vnettles@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Nettles</lname>
<fname>Valerie</fname>
<mname>Eunice</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Foodborne pathogens such as &lt;i&gt;Listeria monocytogenes, Salmonella enterica, and&lt;/i&gt; Shiga-toxigenic &lt;i&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/i&gt; (STEC) are consistently an issue for food safety. Controlling and preventing the spread of these pathogens is paramount for food processors. In January of 2001, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) implemented mandatory hazard analysis critical control points (HACCP) for juice manufactures to prevent the number of foodborne illnesses related to juice outbreaks that were increasingly frequent. Juice HACCP does not require traditional pasteurization of juice with heat but does require juice processors achieve a 5-log pathogen reduction of any pertinent foodborne pathogens.It is important to validate any process to assure consistent lethality when processing. Microorganisms, including foodborne pathogens, when given enough time and nutrients can adapt to a wide variety of environments (&lt;i&gt;e.g.&lt;/i&gt; low pH, desiccation) in food production. These adaptations may confer a competitive advantage when confronted with environmental stressors. To that end, it is important to understand what role, if any, acid adaptation may play in thermal inactivation rates of foodborne pathogens.The thermal inactivation rates of &lt;i&gt;Salmonella&lt;/i&gt; and STEC cocktails were determined for three different temperatures (60°C, 65°C and 70°C) with prior acid adaptation through two different mechanisms (hydrochloric acid and glucose supplementation) as well as a control. In a similar fashion, inactivation rates of &lt;i&gt;L. monocytogenes&lt;/i&gt; were determined for these treatments at 60°C and 70°C. The thermal death time curves were compiled from the observations of six independent replicates and evaluated for fit using linear and Weibull regression models, with Weibull models resulting in a better fit (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&gt;0.925). Overall, STEC cocktail was the most thermally resistant, and acid adaptation did not impact thermal resistance.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5138</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6545&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5138</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6545</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13415071</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5138</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Faith Critzer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Doris H. D&#39;souza, Mark T. Morgan</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>