<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The factors associated with presidential derailment at selected private, liberal arts higher education institutions</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>McNeal</lname>
<fname>Jason</fname>
<mname>Dyer</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Higher education administration</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to describe those factors perceived to be associated with presidential derailments at selected private, liberal arts higher education institutions. The research questions guiding the study were: 1. What factors are perceived to be associated with the derailment of the private higher education president? 2. What events are perceived to be associated with the derailment of the private higher education president? Data were collected from 17 in-depth, one-on-one interviews with sitting and derailed presidents, vice presidents, a governing board member, higher education consultants, executive coaches, and a derailed president&#39;s spouse related to four private, liberal arts colleges in North America. In addition, media accounts of the presidential derailment, field notes, and a personal journal served as sources of data. Findings of the study included support for four of five themes presented in the conceptual model. The four themes supported, problems with interpersonal relationships, failure to meet institutional objectives, inability to lead key constituents, and inability to adapt have been previously identified as themes associated with for-profit business executive derailment. The fifth theme included in the conceptual model, failure on the part of the president to act ethically, was not found. Two additional and distinct contextual themes, failure of the governing board to act ethically, and diminished governing board functionality, emerged as well. These findings suggest that presidential derailment within the higher education enterprise may be more complex than executive derailment within the for-profit business arena. Implications for practice and recommendations for future research are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6014</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7947&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6014</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7947</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467722</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6014</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>E. Grady Bogue</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Higher Education Administration</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>