<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Near-net-shape Fabrication of Ni(x)Al(y) – TiC Cermets by Binder Jet Additive Manufacturing and Pressure-less Melt Infiltration</title>
<publication-date>2018-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Arnold</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>Michael</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Binder Jet</keyword>
<keyword>Cermet</keyword>
<keyword>Infiltration</keyword>
<keyword>Nickel Aluminide</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Binder jet additive manufacturing effectively replaces preform preparation by traditional powder metallurgy methods and allows more complex geometries to be potentially fabricated. The use of a pressure-less melt infiltration technique provides a method of achieving a fully dense composite in a near-net-shape fashion, cost effective and scalable. TiC preforms (15 x 15 x 10/7.5 mm) were fabricated via Binder Jet Additive Manufacturing and then infiltrated by NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; and Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Al using a pressure-less melt infiltration technique. Two compositions, Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Al and NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, were used as infiltrant materials in order to compare wetting behavior and infiltration kinetics.A stark difference in shape retention between Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Al and NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; infiltrated preforms was observed after infiltration. It was found that the TiC particles in the as printed preform were arranged in an interconnected network structure as a result of the binder jet process and/or sintering step and is responsible for maintaining structural integrity of the printed preform. TiC dissolution by liquid Ni&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Al was significant enough to disband this network structure and force particle rearrangement and lead to poor shape retention. Conversely, TiC particle rearrangement did not occur during infiltration of the Al-rich NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; alloy and thus the network structure remained intact leading to excellent shape retention of the infiltrated preform.It was found NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; exhibits a complex melting and solidification behavior where an Al-rich phase segregates heavily from the melted material. The presence of an Alrich inter-particle matrix phase indicates the possibility of a “metered” infiltration process where multiple liquid phases of variant compositions infiltrate the “macro” and “micro” capillaries of the TiC preform in a staggered fashion. The composition and time of infiltration remains unknown and a topic of future work. Additionally, Thermodynamic simulation predicts a reaction at the TiC interface by liquid NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; to form Al&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, with an interfacial reaction product potentially explaining the lack of TiC dissolution and volumetric shrinkage during and after infiltration by NiAl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5113</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6520&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5113</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6520</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:29:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414989</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5113</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sudarsanam Suresh Babu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brett G. Compton, Claudia J. Rawn, Haixuan Xu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>