<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pedometer-Determined Physical Activity and Health Variables in African-American Women (40-62 years of age)</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hornbuckle</lname>
<fname>Lyndsey</fname>
<mname>Michelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to evaluate the relationship between pedometer-determined physical activity, measured in steps per day, and several health variables in middle-aged, African-American women. Height, weight, waist circumference, hip circumference, and % body fat were measured in 69 African-American females (mean age 51.4 ± 5.4 years). Subjects wore a pedometer for 7 consecutive days after their laboratory visit and average steps/day were compared to each health variable. For statistical analyses, subjects were categorized into 3 different groups based on their physical activity level. The categories were &lt; 5,000 steps/day, 5,000-7,499 steps/day, and &gt; 7,500 steps/day. A one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to examine the health variables among the three groups. Partial correlation coefficients controlling for age were calculated for steps/day and BMI, body fat, waist and hip circumference, and WHR. Significance was set at P&lt; 0.05 for all tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first study to investigate the relationships between steps/day and % body fat in middle-aged, African-American females. Significant differences were found among the least active and most active groups for age (P=0.013), average steps/day (P&lt;0.001), body weight (P=0.003), BMI (P=0.005), % body fat (P&lt;0.001), waist circumference (P=0.004), and hip circumference (P=0.043). When a partial correlation controlling for age was used to compare steps/day to body composition variables, negative correlations still existed for each variable. These correlations were significant for BMI (P&lt;0.001), % body fat (P&lt;0.001), waist circumference (P=0.002), and hip circumference (P=0.015). These results show that women who accumulated more steps/day had significantly lower body fat percentages, BMI values, waist circumferences, and hip circumferences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4666</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6239&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4666</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6239</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-02T08:13:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10530573</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4666</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson, Camille O&#39;Bryant</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>