<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tennessee healthcare provider childhood lead poisoning attitude, belief, and practice survey</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lowry</lname>
<fname>Karen</fname>
<mname>Adele Rasnake</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Childhood lead poisoning is a serious but preventable condition. It has been estimated by the Tennessee Department of Health that as many as one in eleven children in the state may be affected in some manner by lead poisoning. Lead poisoning can result in lifelong learning and neurological problems for a child. For these reasons it is imperative the healthcare provider be able to recognize risk factors associated with lead poisoning in the child’s environment. Recognition of these risk factors is done through asking a series of screening questions designed to assess areas of risk. Follow up blood testing to determine the extent of lead poisoning is a necessary measure once risk of lead poisoning to the child has been determined. The decision to ask appropriate screening questions and follow up with lead blood testing is often influenced by healthcare provider attitude. If the healthcare provider does not deem lead an important issue, then lead screening and testing may not be done as recommended by the Tennessee Department of Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and other governmental agencies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6264</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8216&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6264</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8216</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450361</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6264</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Susan M. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>