<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Body &amp; Context In The Discovery of Place</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fry</lname>
<fname>Beth</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(From the Thesis Statement) &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Sensations of experience become a kind of reasoning distinct to the making of architecture. Whether reflecting on the unity of concept and sensation, or the intertwining of idea and phenomena, the hope is to unite intellect and feeling, precision with soul.&quot;                                  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Anonymous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis investigates a methodology of using ones senses to experience, observe, and understand a place as a layered system with the intent of discovering the essence in order to create successful urban design that is connected to place. The layers Nature, Infrastructure, Built Structure and Culture, will be observed and considered through multiple journeys of experience via various modes of movement. After mapping the multiple past and present characteristics for each layer further analysis will occur through the overlay process in order to conceptualize the complete layered system. Experiencing through multiple modes of movement, taking the opportunity to pause, and creating graphic representations of what the senses inform me of will reveal a complete and comprehensive understanding of the place. Utilizing the described methodology will initially inform my decision making processes related to site and program selection. Information gained throughout the continued use of the methodology will further influence my decisions related to site and building design. As a result I will produce a conceptual design that is connected to the place its deeper meaning and intended users.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4489</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6001&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4489</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6001</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-12T06:31:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10009294</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4489</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard M. Kelso</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Barbara Klinkhammer, Max Robinson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>