<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Systematic Human Relations Training and Resident Assistant Effectiveness</title>
<publication-date>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hayes</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>Foster</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Educational Administration and Supervision</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Systematic human relations training has been shown to be an effective method for training both by lay and professional counselors. However, its usefulness for resident assistants in a residence hall setting has been sparsely documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is twofold: (1) to reaffirm existing evidence that a systematic human relations training program can make a group of resident assistants more effective helper and (2) to determine whether this change in effectiveness can be detected in the immediate environment for the resident assistant, that being his res residents and supervisor. In order to establish the first objective, resident assistants who received the training were asked to respond to client stimuli expressions. The responses were rated and compared to responses of resident assistants who did not undergo training. In pursuance of the second objective, evaluations presently being used in a residence hall system were administered before and after training. These were compared for the two groups. In addition, the frequency and duration of resident assistants&#39; contacts with residents were analyzed during the course of the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subjects in this study were two groups of seven resident assistants that were selected from four residence halls. The experimental and control groups were matched according to number, sex, and residence hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data supported existing evidence that systematic human relations training can significantly improve the level of functioning of a resident assistant helper. However, no significant transfer of this improvement into the resident assistant&#39;s environment was suggested by resident assistant evaluations or by contact frequency and duration data.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3080</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4465&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3080</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4465</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-14T11:55:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6527905</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3080</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eugene Schoch</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert B. Walker, John W. Edgerly</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>College Student Personnel</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>