<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Managing the Remaining Service Life of the T-34C Aircraft</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rousseau</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Howard</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerospace Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The T-34C Airplane has been the primary trainer aircraft of the United States Navy for more than twenty-five years and is reaching the end of its service life. The Navy has delayed the procurement of the replacement T-6A Texan II aircraft for five years, yet does not expect the future training requirements to diminish. This delay in T-6A procurement along with recent observed increases in primary trainer aircraft usage have resulted in the need for the Navy to pay considerable attention to the remaining service life of the T-34C aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis will discuss the methodology used to determine future primary trainer aircraft requirements and projected aircraft availability. With analysis of these results it is the author’s opinion that there will be a projected shortage of over 60 primary trainer aircraft in the coming years. In order to alleviate that shortfall a Service Life Extension Program (SLEP) is recommended for the T-34C aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In support of a SLEP for the T-34C aircraft it is recommended that the main wing spars and carry through structure be replaced instead of conducting a time consuming and costly Damage Tolerance Analysis (DTA) on those components. Replacement of these parts and an increased inspection interval on other airframe components on sixty-three aircraft will alleviate the projected shortfall until the T-6A is delivered in sufficient numbers to maintain the primary training requirement of our future Naval Aviators.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2288</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3770&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2288</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3770</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-17T12:45:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4733912</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2288</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. B. Richards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph Kimberlin, George Masters</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>