<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>James Fenimore Cooper, Professional Authorship, and the American Literary Marketplace, 1838-1851</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Harthorn</lname>
<fname>Steven</fname>
<mname>P.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation is a primary-source-intensive literary history that makes use of publishers&#39; records, correspondence, manuscript evidence, and literary works to study how James Fenimore Cooper refashioned his career as a professional author during its last major phase, approximately 1838 to 1851, to adapt to changing conditions he faced in the literary marketplace and to confront challenges-both externally- and self-imposed-to his status and reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter One, &quot;The Tortured Profession of Authorship: Novelist Again,&quot; narrates Cooper&#39;s return to fiction in 1837-38, considering the professional issues confronting him at the time, such as economic uncertainties, constraints of the typical two-volume format, and alienation from the contemporary literary scene. Cooper&#39;s arguments about the nature of fiction, as well as his positions on the proper ethics of authorship, are also treated. Chapter Two, &quot;Seamanship and Authorship: &lt;em&gt;The History of the Navy &lt;/em&gt;to &lt;em&gt;Afloat and Ashore,&lt;/em&gt;&quot; examines how Cooper&#39;s role as an expert on nautical matters contributed to his understanding of his profession as an author, especially in light of his &lt;em&gt;History of the Navy of the United States &lt;/em&gt;and the ensuing controversy it stirred in certain quarters. Cooper&#39;s other nautical works of the early 1840s are considered, with an in-depth discussion of his first-person double novel &lt;em&gt;Afloat and Ashore &lt;/em&gt;as a point of convergence for many of his concerns about authorship. Chapter Three, &quot;The Commercial Instinct: Leatherstocking Revived,&quot; considers Cooper&#39;s deliberate efforts to restore his commercial viability by reasserting his artistic powers, reviving his most famous character, Natty Bumppo, in &lt;em&gt;The Pathfinder &lt;/em&gt;and again in &lt;em&gt;The Deerslayer. &lt;/em&gt;Cooper&#39;s failed attempt to create a &quot;standard work&quot; out of the Columbus story, &lt;em&gt;Mercedes of Castile, &lt;/em&gt;and his never-realized plans of adding a sixth Leatherstocking tale are also investigated. Chapter Four, &quot;Periodical Publication: Cooper and &lt;em&gt;Graham&#39;s Magazine,&quot; &lt;/em&gt;treats Cooper&#39;s experiment in magazine writing, establishing factual foundations on a part of Cooper&#39;s career that has heretofore received little attention. His serialized novella &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Pocket-Handkerchief &lt;/em&gt;receives special consideration for its reflections of Cooper&#39;s attitudes on the work and rewards (or lack thereof) of authorship. Finally, Chapter Five, &quot;Publishing Realignments: Cheap Literature and Cooper&#39;s Late Career,&quot; details Cooper&#39;s accommodations to the cheap paperback publishing craze of 1841-43, his separation from publishers Lea &amp; Blanchard, his venture in self-publishing with &lt;em&gt;Afloat and Ashore, &lt;/em&gt;and his subsequent publishing alliances with Burgess, Stringer &amp; Co. and George Palmer Putnam. Taken together, the findings uncovered through these investigations suggest that the second half of Cooper&#39;s career, long treated by many critics as one of decline and retreat, be reconsidered as one of reconsolidation and engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4303</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6043&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4303</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6043</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-05-01T11:11:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10100137</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4303</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael A. Lofaro</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allison R. Ensor, Mary E. Papke, E. Wayne Cutler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>