<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Highway 11</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Asdell</lname>
<fname>Devon</fname>
<mname>Koren</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Created in 1926, US Route 11 runs from the Canadian border at Rouses Point, New York, to just shy of New Orleans at an intersection with US-90. In Bristol, Virginia, the highway splits in two -- 11-E and 11-W -- and then reunites in Knoxville, Tennessee. This highway serves as the main thoroughfare for many small towns and cities, and it is known by many names -- Lee Highway, Andrew Johnson Highway, and Kingston Pike, to name a few. As many of the residents of these small towns might attest, it is easy to take a highway for granted when it becomes such an integral part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &quot;Highway 11,&quot; a Creative Writing Graduate Thesis for the University of Tennessee, Devon Koren Asdell has collected a series of interconnected short stories which take place along the route of US-11. In particular, the stories in this collection draw from the rich Appalachian heritage of the region that surrounds the heart of the highway in the mountains of Virginia and East Tennessee. &quot;Highway 11&quot; is infused with tales of love, hope, fear, regret, loss, taboo, stagnation, and exploration. These are themes indicative not only to Appalachian culture, but to the modern American spirit, as well.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1491</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2933&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1491</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2933</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-23T11:39:25-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4339079</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1491</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Knight</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Allen Wier, Allison Ensor</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>