<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of the Color Wheel System on Disruptive Behavior and Classroom Climate: Validating the Color Wheel in Kindergarten Classrooms</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tbest3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Watson</lname>
<fname>Tiffany</fname>
<mname>Lynn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>color wheel system</keyword>
<keyword>inappropriate vocalizations</keyword>
<keyword>out-of-seat behavior</keyword>
<keyword>classroom climate</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>School Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The current study was initiated by a principal who was interested in implementing the Color Wheel System in her school. The purpose of the current study was to empirically validate the classroom management system for kindergarten students. Although there is some evidence that the procedure may be effective with kindergarten students, no scientific procedures have been applied to evaluate the Color Wheel System in kindergarten classrooms. Analyses were conducted on the average inappropriate vocalizations and out-of-seat behavior of the entire class (i.e., 16-17 students) across three classrooms. We also evaluated the effect of the Color Wheel System on students’ perception of classroom climate. Students whose parents provided consent participated in a measure of classroom climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A multiple baseline design was used to evaluate the effects of the Color Wheel System on kindergarten students&#39; inappropriate vocalizations and out-of-seat behavior. Across all phases, partial-interval recording and momentary time-sampling were used to record classwide inappropriate vocalizations and out-of-seat behavior respectively. Visual analysis of time series graphs showed immediate decreases in each dependent variable across classrooms when the intervention was applied. Results of the study revealed large effect sizes across phases for primary and secondary dependent variables. These data show that the Color Wheel System procedures effectively decreased inappropriate vocalizations and out-of-seat behavior in kindergarten classrooms. T-tests showed no significant changes in perception of classroom climate due to the Color Wheel System procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Survey and interview data show that, overall, the teachers found the intervention helpful in their classrooms. Our findings have theoretical and applied implications. Study limitations and directions for future research are provided.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3977</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4813&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3977</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4813</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-24T08:40:57-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4813/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>7028534</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3977</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Christopher H. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Amy Skinner, Tara Moore, Maribeth Coleman, R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>School Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>