<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Current Practices, Problems, and Opinions as They Relate to the Articulation of High School and College Programs of Home Economics</title>
<publication-date>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hackman</lname>
<fname>Ruth</fname>
<mname>Arkin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A focal point in educational circles today is that of improved articulation between the curriculum of the secondary school and that of the college or university. This situation is evidenced by the great amount of space given to the subject in educational literature. Concern is expressed over excessive duplication in college courses of content and experiences included in high school courses. Attention is focused on more effective continuity of study at the two levels with a minimum of overlap. There is considerable activity throughout the United States as organized groups of educators are studying this problem and making recommendations for ways of bringing about improvements. Practices are being re-examined and policies re-evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of taking a critical look at the home economics program in light of its policies and practices has been recognized by leaders in the field of home economics. A challenge to work toward more effective transition from one educational level to another has been made to home economics educators. A review of the literature, however, fails to reveal any organized effort by home economics personnel which is aimed at attacking this problem. Very few individual attempts to help improve the transition from high school to college for students of home economics have been reported.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2908</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4336&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2908</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4336</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-03T13:51:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6203504</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2908</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ilene Brown</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Florence MacLeod, Bernadine Meyer, Helen Starck, Elbert Henson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>