<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relative and Absolute Quantitation of Metabolites and Lipids using LC/MS/MS  on the TSQ Quantum Discovery MAX</title>
<publication-date>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jmiddle5@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Middleton</lname>
<fname>Jesse</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Roseobacter</keyword>
<keyword>Holstein</keyword>
<keyword>SRM</keyword>
<keyword>Lipidomics</keyword>
<keyword>Metabolomics</keyword>
<keyword>milk</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Analytical Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Two biological systems were studied using LC/ESI/MS/MS on a triple quadrupole operated in SRM (selected reaction monitoring) scan mode. The first bacterium system is aquatic and microscopic in size known as &lt;em&gt;Roseobacter.&lt;/em&gt; The second mammalian system is terrestrial and large in size relative to humans known as Holstein cows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Roseobacter&lt;/em&gt; is a clade of marine bacteria abundant in the ocean. Roseophages are viruses that infect &lt;em&gt;Roseobacter&lt;/em&gt; and cause viral lysis. &lt;em&gt;Sulfitobacter&lt;/em&gt; sp. 2047 was isolated and infected with Roseophages, and the fold change in the metabolic pool relative to a control was studied at discrete time points. The absolute concentration of glutamate and glutamine in the infected and control was determined at each time point using an external calibration curve. Flux analysis through the addition of &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C-acetate at early and late post infection was compared to the control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holstein cows are a breed of cattle known to be the world’s highest producers of milk. Twelve Holstein dairy cows were selected, and samples of blood and milk were taken at different weeks of lactation. The fold change in the phospholipid pool relative to the first week of lactation was studied from early, mid, and late lactation. The absolute concentration of lipids at each week of lactation was determined using isotope dilution mass spectrometry with the exception of GPC (glycerophosphocholine) where an external calibration curve was used due commercial unavailability of an isotope-labeled standard.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1649</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2679&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1649</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2679</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-01T15:50:21-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2679/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3820613</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1649</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Shawn R. Campagna</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael J. Sepaniak, Robert N. Compton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>