<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Investigation of the Relationship Between Reading Speed and General Reading Skill Development</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Jacqueline</fname>
<mname>Luann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies have shown that words correct per minute (WC/M) is a valid and reliable measure that correlates highly with standardized reading assessments (Marston, 1989). The current series of studies begins to investigate why WC/M and other rate measures correlate so strongly with these assessments. The goal across all three studies was to parse the variance in general reading development accounted for by the measure of reading speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first study, researchers found that reading speed taken from WC/M accounted for a significant amount of the variance with the Broad Reading Cluster (BRC) of the &lt;em&gt;Woodcock-Johnson III Tests of Achievement&lt;/em&gt; (WJ-III Ach.; Woodcock, McGrew, &amp; Mather, 2001) across 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-, 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-, and 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-grade students (Williams, Chapter 2, this dissertation). Results also indicated that converting reading speed to a rate measure (WC/M) accounted for an additional amount of variance. In the second study, researchers performed similar analyses with reading comprehension rate (RCR; comprehension questions correct/time required to read) (Williams, Chapter 3, this dissertation). Results from this study also indicated that reading speed accounted for much of the variance with the BRC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third study, researchers extended these research findings by analyzing 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;- and 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-grade students’ time required to read, WC, WC/M, highlighted punctuation correct per minute (HPC/M; punctuation highlighted correct/time required to read), and HPC with the Tennessee Comprehensive Assessment Program (TCAP) (Williams, Chapter 4, this dissertation). Results showed that both rate measures significantly correlated with the TCAP across both grade-levels. Non-hierarchal analysis results indicated that reading speed taken from HPC/M accounted for most of the variance in TCAP scores across 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;- and 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-grade students. Additionally, reading speed from 5&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;- grade students’ WC/M accounted for most of the variance in the TCAP scores. However, WC (the numerator) accounted for most of the variance among 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-grade students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results from these studies indicate that the time required to read (the denominator) can account for much of the variance with standardized reading assessments. Overall, results suggest that reading speed is what may account for the validity and sensitivity of reading rate measures.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/445</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1505&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>445</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1505</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T11:34:20-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1151178</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/445</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Christopher H. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum, Sherry K. Bain, Richard A. Saudargas</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/WilliamsJacquelineL.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>