<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The politics of God : theocratic empire building in the age of globalization</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Schendel</lname>
<fname>Joshua</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The acts of politico-religious influence by fundamentalist religious organizations in the United States is an empire-in-training, utilizing processes of historical co-optment and the imposition and incorporation of mythico-historical pasts. These politico-religious amalgams utilize their cosmology in efforts to steer governmental action in the United States towards a stated goal: one nation, under God. Their success largely depends on their ability to: (a) overcome the internal and external power struggle facing such a mixture of reality and dogma, and (b) re-embed modem social notions with their own &quot;&#39;legitimate&quot; vision of &#39;&#39;truth&quot; and &quot;&#39;tradition.&quot; The Christian Coalition of America and the Christian Broadcast Network, led by &quot;&#39;Messiah figure&quot; Pat Robertson, have used this formula in their efforts to guide governmental policy and challenge perceived &#39;&#39;threats&quot; to their social order. I argue that the results of their efforts to &quot;reform&quot; have, however, produced a frightening blend of ethnocentrism, imperialism, and globalized theocratic empire building.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5991</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7624&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5991</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7624</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467653</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5991</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mariana K. L. Ferreira</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Faye V. Harrison, Rosalind J. Hackett</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>