<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Cyclooxygenase-2 expression in feline pancreatic adenocarcinomas</title>
<publication-date>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Mrkonjich</lname>
<fname>L</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>carcinoma</keyword>
<keyword>cyclooxygenase</keyword>
<keyword>feline</keyword>
<keyword>neoplasia</keyword>
<keyword>pancreas</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-II) is an inducible enzyme that is responsible for the production of prostaglandin E2 (PGE2), which is often upregulated in neoplastic conditions. Expression of COX-II is documented in the majority of human pancreatic adenocarcinomas and in many epithelial neoplasms in humans and animals. The purpose of this study was to assess a series of feline pancreatic adenocarcinomas for the expression of COX-II. Eight feline pancreatic adenocarcinomas (5 poorly differentiated ductular variants and 3 well-differentiated acinar variants) were included. Immunohistochemical staining showed that COX-II was expressed in 2 (both poorly differentiated ductular variants) of the 8 neoplasms (25%). Approximately 10% of the epithelial cells from these 2 neoplasms expressed intense cytoplasmic staining. However, because feline pancreatic adenocarcinoma does not appear to consistently express COX-II, it is not a useful prognostic indicator for this group of feline neoplasms. In addition, COX-II inhibitors are not likely to be effective therapeutics for cats with this neoplasm.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/34</coverpage-url>
<label>34</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1033</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284757</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/34</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Shelley Newman and L Mrkonjich. &quot;Cyclooxygenase-2 expression in feline pancreatic adenocarcinomas&quot; Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation 18.6 (2006): 590-593.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://jvdi.org/cgi/content/abstract/18/6/590</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>