<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Ecological Study of the Distribution of Animals on Mt. LeConte and Along LeConte Creek</title>
<publication-date>1929-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McClure</lname>
<fname>Gervase</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this discussion we have tried to show the ecological distribution of the animals of Mount LeConte and along LeConte Creek, by first giving a brief description of the Great Smoky Mountains in general, its vegetation, and a number of animals that are known to be present in their various habitats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more detailed description of LeConte Creek has been attempted, and the area has been zoned according to the kind of vegetation that appears to be dominant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A detailed discussion of the methods and technique are given to enable the reader to surmise the immensity of the problem attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The animals peculiar to the various zones have been discussed briefly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The animal dominant in the Balsam Zone seems to be the Red-gilled salamander, Plethodon jordani; that of the Birch Zone,  a snail, the species not determined; that of the Transitional Zone, a large semi-aquatic drab-colored salamander, Desmognathus sp.; and that of the Chestnut Zone, snails, most of which are of the genus Helix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a whole, the animals of LeConte are scarce compared to those of the lower altitudes, but in general a great number exist in their various habitats.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1444</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2785&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1444</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2785</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-05-06T13:43:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4111395</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1444</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edwin B. Conor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George Bentley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1929-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1929-08-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>