<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Phospholipase A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Expression During the Estrous Cycle and Early Pregnancy</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ochs</lname>
<fname>Gregory</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Acute control of prostaglandin production is essential for normal estrous cyclicity and maintenance of early pregnancy. The rate limiting step for prostaglandin production is the activation of Phospholipase A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. There are many phospholipase A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;s, but few have been investigated in reproductive studies. The objective of this study was to examine PLA&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Groups IV and VI protein and mRNA expression in the uterine endometrium during the estrous cycle and early pregnancy in ewes. Ewes were monitored for estrous and uterine tissues were collected surgically on days 5 (n=3), 10(n=3) and 15(n=3) of the estrous cycle. Endometrium from pregnant animals were harvested on days 14(n=3), 15(n=1), 16(n=2), 17(n=1) or 20(n=2). Endometrial scrapings were collected in attempts to harvest luminal epithelial cells primarily and tissue samples were collected to harvest samples containing all cellular endometrial components. Samples were analyzed by western blot analysis and qRT-PCR to detect protein and mRNA expression of both PLA&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;s Group IV and VI. Western blot results revealed that protein expression of Group IVA was greatest on day ten of the estrous cycle but was not significantly different form days 5 and 15, possibly due to animal variation. Group IVA was significantly elevated on day 14 of pregnancy (P2 expression is not the sole regulator of prostaglandin production, but it does play an integral role that is tissue and cell type specific in both the estrous cycle and early pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/421</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1454&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>421</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1454</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-16T13:46:06-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1148594</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/421</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James D. Godkin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Patricia K. Tithof, Jun Lin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/OchsGregory.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>