<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fundamental Studies of Hydrogen Attack in C-0.5Mo Steel and Weldments Applied in Petroleum and Petrochemical Industries</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Peng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;High temperature hydrogen attack (HTHA) is a form of surface decarburization, internal decarburization, and / or intergranular cracking in steels exposed to high temperature (&gt; 400°F) and high hydrogen pressure. Hydrogen attack is an irreversible process which can cause permanent damage resulting in degradation of mechanical properties and failures such as leakage, bursting, fire, and/or explosion. The continuous progression of hydrogen attack in C-0.5Mo steel and weldments below the C-0.5Mo Nelson Curve has caused a significant concern for the integrity and serviceability of C-0.5Mo steel utilized for pressure vessels and piping in the petroleum refinery and petrochemical industries. In conjunction with this research, a state-of-the-art literature review was implemented to provide a comprehensive overview of the published research efforts on hydrogen attack studies. The evolution of “Nelson Curves”  for carbon steel, C-0.5Mo, and Cr-Mo steels was historically reviewed in regard to design applications and limitations. Testing techniques for hydrogen attack assessment were summarized under the categories of hydrogen exposure testing, mechanical evaluation, and dilatometric swelling testing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6131</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8119&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6131</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8119</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23359352</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6131</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carl D. Lundin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Metallurgical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>