<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using Micrometeorology to Gauge Agriculture&#39;s Potential to Sequester Soil Carbon</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>O&#39;Dell</lname>
<fname>Debra</fname>
<mname>Blumberg</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>CO2</keyword>
<keyword>carbon dioxide</keyword>
<keyword>micrometeorology</keyword>
<keyword>sustainable agriculture</keyword>
<keyword>soil carbon sequestration</keyword>
<keyword>CO2 emissions</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In addition to reducing carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) emissions from fossil fuel combustion, removing atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; may be critical to limit global warming to less than two degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels recommended by leading experts. Since cropland occupies 11% of the earth’s land and is intensively managed, cropland agriculture provides one approach for removing CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; from the atmosphere to mitigate climate change. However, current assessments indicate agriculture is a net emitter of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and other greenhouse gases, and it is unclear how soil management can effect carbon sequestration.In this work micrometeorological methods are used to measure the exchange (flux) of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; between the surface and atmosphere and can assess whether an agricultural ecosystem is a source or sink for carbon. Three studies were performed using micrometeorology to understand agriculture’s potential to sequester carbon.Using Bowen Ratio Energy Balance (BREB) micrometeorological methods, the first study measured CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; flux from a maize crop grown on no-till and tilled soils to determine tillage effects on CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions during 104 days of the 2015 maize growing season in north central Ohio. During this period, the no-till plot sequestered CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, while the tilled plot was a net emitter.A second study determined if industrial biotechnology waste reutilization in agriculture could reduce CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions and generate environmental benefits, while meeting farmer yield expectations. Using both BREB and eddy covariance (EC) micrometeorological methods, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; flux was measured over maize where heat-inactivated, spent microbial biomass (SMB) amendment was land applied and compared with typical farmer practices from October 2016 to October 2017 in Loudon, Tennessee. While treatments with SMB emitted more CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; than farmer practices, the SMB applications produced yields similar to farmer practices.Using BREB micrometeorology methods, the third study measured CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions over conservation agriculture (CA) practices as compared to conventional tillage from June 2013 to May 2016 in central Zimbabwe. The CA practices of no-till and cover crops produced significantly fewer CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions than conventional tillage.These studies demonstrate that micrometeorology can detect short- and long-term differences in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; flux between practices, providing data supporting agriculture’s potential to reduce CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions and sequester carbon.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5349</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6885&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5349</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6885</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545346</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5349</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Neal S. Eash</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas J. Sauer, Dayton M. Lambert, Joanne Logan, Bruce B. Hicks, James A. Zahn</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4968-2287&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant, Soil and Environmental Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2021-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>