<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of Methods for Detecting the Apramycin Resistance Gene in E.Coli Isolated from Cold-Stressed Swine</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Arnett</lname>
<fname>Debra</fname>
<mname>Beth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study was an attempt to locate the apramycin resistance gene in &lt;em&gt;E.&lt;/em&gt;coli &lt;em&gt;isolated from cold-stressed swine. Six pigs were administered apramycin for &lt;/em&gt;14 days during a 150-day study and were exposed to cold stress in the form of an 8 °C reduction in recommended daily temperature. Fecal swabs were taken on eight different days for the recovery of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli, &lt;/em&gt;and isolates were tested for sensitivity to apramycin. Plasmids were isolated from selected &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;from each day of sampling and were electroporated into receptive bacteria to see whether those bacteria in turn would become receptive so that a resistant plasmid could be identified. Electroporated plasmids could not be recovered so AP PCR was examined instead to identify resistant plasmids. Fingerprints were made of all plasmids using two different primers. PFGE of DNA, using two different restriction endonucleases, was also performed. Profiles from AP PCR and PFGE were compared separately for similarity by eye and also by using a molecular analyst software program that creates dendrograms. No resistant plasmids were identified, the source of resistance could not be linked to a plasmid or plasmids, and the apramycin resistance gene was not discovered.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1958</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3316&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1958</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3316</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-25T09:21:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4627011</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1958</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Alan G. Mathew</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frank Masincupp, David Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>