<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Psychometric Analysis of an Inventory Assessing Mental Toughness</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cherry</lname>
<fname>Heather</fname>
<mname>Leanne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study involved the development and psychometric validation ofthe Mental Toughness Questionnaire (MTQ). The MTQ is an 18-item questionnaire designed to evaluate an individual&#39;s competitive desire, focus, self-confidence, and resiliency. The responses of 117 varsity male and female athletes at a Division I-A university and Division II college were analyzed using a principal component factor analysis. The mean mental toughness score for males was significantly different from than the mean mental toughness score for females (M=2.07, SD=.54) and indicated that males self-reported being more mentally tough than females (t[115] = -3.29, p &lt; .001). The mean mental toughness score for athletes in Division I-A (M=2.03, SD= .51) was significantly different from that for athletes in Division II (M=I.69, SD=.37) and indicated that the Division II athletes self-reported being more mentally tough than Division I-A athletes (t[115] = 3.28, p &lt; .001). The mean mental toughness score on the Final MTQ was also significantly different between the eight different sports, F(7,116) = 2.87, p = .009. Post hoc analyses revealed that athletes in the sport of men&#39;s baseball self-reported being more mentally tough than athletes in the sport ofwomen&#39;s swimming&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/588</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1735&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>588</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1735</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-03T13:04:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1343000</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/588</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leslee Fisher</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Craig Wrisberg, John Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>