<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Examination of The Big Five And Narrow Traits In Relation To Learner Self-Direction</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jkirwan@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kirwan</lname>
<fname>Jeral</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>self-directed learning</keyword>
<keyword>personality</keyword>
<keyword>the Big Five</keyword>
<keyword>narrow traits</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Self-direction in learning is a major topic in the field of adult learning. There has been extensive coverage of the topic by theorists, researchers, and practitioners.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;However, there have been few studies which look at learner self-direction specifically as a personality trait. The present study addresses the relationship between learner self-direction and other personality traits of college students when the traits represented by the five-factor model of personality (&lt;a title=&quot;Digman, 1990 #17&quot;&gt;Digman, 1990&lt;/a&gt;) are differentiated from narrow personality traits. Archival data were used from an undergraduate sample at a large Southeastern U.S. university (sample size = 2102). Correlation and multiple regression analyses were used in examining the unique individual relationship between Big Five and narrow personality traits and learner self-direction. Analysis of the data revealed five significant part correlations between specific traits and learner self-direction. The part correlations for Work Drive (.310) and Openness (.207) were significantly higher than all other part correlations. Neither Conscientiousness nor Agreeableness had significant part correlations despite having significant zero-order correlations with learner self-direction. Extraversion did not have a significant zero-order correlation with learner self-direction but the part correlation was significant. Results were discussed in terms of the predictive relationship between personality variables and learner self-direction. Study implications, some limitations, and possible directions for future research were noted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1535</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2424&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1535</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2424</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-02-05T11:49:32-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2424/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2495440</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1535</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett, Mary F. Ziegler, Schuyler W. Huck, Tricia McClam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Educational Psychology and Research</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>