<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A potential proliferative gene, NUDT6, is down-regulated by green tea catechins at the posttranscriptional level</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Baek</lname>
<fname>Seung</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The main aims of this study were to elucidate the effect of green tea catechins on Nudix-type motif 6 (NUDT6) suppression and to characterize NUDT6&#39;s biological activity. Our microarray data showed that the green tea component epicatechin-3-gallate suppressed NUDT6 expression, and this was confirmed by RT-PCR. Subsequently, the use of different catechins showed that the effect of epigallocatechin-3-gallate (EGCG) was stronger than that of other catechins. At the posttranscriptional level, EGCG decreased the RNA stability of NUDT6, indicating it as a potential mechanism of NUDT6 suppression. Further cloning of the 3&#39; untranslated region of human NUDT6 mRNA resulted in reduced luciferase activity by EGCG treatment. This effect was at least, in part, mediated by the extracellular-signal-regulated kinase and p38MAPK pathways. Finally, increased cell proliferation and cell growth in soft agar were observed in NUDT6-overexpressing cells. These findings provide a novel mechanism for the suppression of the proliferative gene NUDT6 by green tea catechins in human colorectal cancer. Copyright 2010 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/50</coverpage-url>
<label>50</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1049</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T08:54:05-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_compmedpubs/article/1049/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2323571</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/50</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Seung J. Baek. &quot;A potential proliferative gene, NUDT6, is down-regulated by green tea catechins at the posttranscriptional level&quot; &lt;em&gt;J Nutr Biochem&lt;/em&gt; 21.2 (2010): 98.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://works.bepress.com/seung_baek/3/</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>J Nutr Biochem</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>