<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>W175-12 Common Landscape Mistakes and How to Avoid Them</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-21T10:46:08-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Landscaping</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;No one today would doubt that we live in the Information Age. It would be nice to say that some credit should be given to people submersing themselves in well-written books and magazines, but let’s face it— we can find pretty much anything we want on the Internet and from watching a huge variety of do-it-yourself cable programming. Yes, there is so much data at our fingertips that it doesn’t take too long before we have the confidence to believe we can do everything ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the areas where folks feel most tempted to bypass the advice of professionals is in the creation of gardens and landscape design. It’s very true that gardening is an extremely rewarding endeavor and the feeling of accomplishment that comes with creating a beautiful space is unmatched, but there are still some key guidelines to consider. What follows is my observation of the 12 most common landscape mistakes and some “cut-to-the-chase” advice on how you may avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexgard/82</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1081&amp;amp;context=utk_agexgard&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>82</label>
<document-type>landgen</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1081</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-21T10:45:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Home Garden, Lawn, and Landscape</publication-title>
<context-key>1282924</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexgard/82</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>W175 08-0055</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-04-21T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>