<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An evaluation of agricultural education programming in a correctional facility</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Lewis</lname>
<fname>Jeffrey</fname>
<mname>Monroe</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Agricultural and extension education</keyword>
<keyword>Prisoners</keyword>
<keyword>Criminals</keyword>
<keyword>Landscaping industry</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of the interior and exterior landscaping program in a correctional facility located in Mountain City, Tennessee. Rule violations were counted for one month for both the 20 active interior and exterior landscaping program participants and a 20 member, random sampling of the general inmate population. Rule violations were also counted for landscaping program graduates and compared to those of the general inmate population. In addition, this study examined the correlation between student perceptions of the interior and exterior landscaping program and inmate behavior. While it cannot be stated that participation in the interior and exterior landscaping program caused changes in behavior, this study did reveal program graduates had far fewer recorded rule violations when compared to the general inmate population, and it also revealed a substantial positive correlation (p = .52) between the inmate&#39;s perceptions of the program and fewer recorded rule violations. In addition, findings revealed that 75% of the class members believe the program has positively affected their behavior, and 100% of the class members believe the program is effective. Also, 95% of those in the program find furthering their education to be appealing because of the program, and 85% believe their outlook on the future has improved because of the landscaping program. Recommendations for furthering and enhancing correctional education are provided as are recommendations for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5769</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7391&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5769</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7391</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467537</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5769</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carrie A. Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>