<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>E-Access Changes Everything.</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>online databases</keyword>
<keyword>OPAC</keyword>
<keyword>e-resources</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;According to several of the plenary speakers, this reconception must involve essential local services built around ever-growing collections of e-resources. Research and pizza Kevin Guthrie, president of Ithaka, believes that the digital delivery of knowledge changes everything: &quot;books in electronic form will change our world.&quot; (Burke&#39;s company, ProQuest/Serials Solutions, produces Summon, which puts into action many of her suggestions, but her talk was not a sales pitch-she also mentioned competitors&#39; products and did not dwell on any one in particular.) Listen to the first-years Discovery solutions, including federated search, local discovery system software (such as Primo, Enterprise, Encore, VuFind, or Extensible Catalog), or web-based hosted systems (such as Summon, EBSCO Discovery Service, or WorldCat Local) are built on the &quot;belief that the information world is flat, every information object is equal in potential value.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/136</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1091&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>136</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1091</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-10-06T09:49:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15501208</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/136</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Tenopir, Carol. “E-Access Changes Everything,” Library Journal 135 (January 15, 2010).</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Library Journal</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>