<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Beta-decay, beta-delayed neutron emission and isomer studies around &lt;sup&gt;78&lt;/sup&gt;Ni</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mmr.utk@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rajabali</lname>
<fname>Mustafa</fname>
<mname>Moiz</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Beta-decay</keyword>
<keyword>beta-delayed neutron emission</keyword>
<keyword>isomer</keyword>
<keyword>&lt;sup&gt;78&lt;/sup&gt;Ni</keyword>
<keyword>&lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni</keyword>
<keyword>&lt;sup&gt;73&lt;/sup&gt;Ni</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear</discipline>
<discipline>Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A study of nuclei with few nucleons outside the closed shell provides benchmarks for the nuclear shell model especially in this modern era of physics where exotic doubly magic nuclei can be tested. The subject of this thesis is to experimentally investigate the properties of nuclei near &lt;sup&gt;78&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and to confront them with the predictions of modern large scale shell model calculations. In this regard, an experiment was performed at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory (NSCL) to measure excited states in  &lt;sup&gt;71-73&lt;/sup&gt;Ni populated via the beta-decay of  &lt;sup&gt;71-73&lt;/sup&gt;Co. Data collected from this experiment lead to partial level schemes for  &lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and  &lt;sup&gt;73&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and to improvements of existing level schemes for &lt;sup&gt;70&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and &lt;sup&gt;72&lt;/sup&gt;Ni. An objective of this experiment was to investigate the changes in excitation energy of the 5/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; state relative to the 9/2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; ground state as well as the search for the 1/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; isomeric state in odd-mass nickel isotopes approaching &lt;sup&gt;78&lt;/sup&gt;Ni. A second experiment was performed also at the NSCL where a two nucleon removal reaction from &lt;sup&gt;73&lt;/sup&gt;Cu was used to populate the low lying yrast states in &lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni. Results from this in-beam experiment aided in constructing the level scheme of &lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni. Systematics in shell model calculations using realistic interactions for odd mass &lt;sup&gt;69-77&lt;/sup&gt;Ni reveal a steady increase in energy spacing between the 1/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; level and 9/2&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; ground state - suggesting an increased role of the g&lt;sub&gt;9/2&lt;/sub&gt; correlations, but an almost constant energy separation between the 5/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; and 1/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; excited states. Using data from the two experiments, the position of the 5/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; state in &lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and &lt;sup&gt;73&lt;/sup&gt;Ni and 1/2&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; state in &lt;sup&gt;71&lt;/sup&gt;Ni were identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decay of &lt;sup&gt;74,76&lt;/sup&gt;Ni into &lt;sup&gt;74,76&lt;/sup&gt;Cu was also investigated. Low lying states revealed new level schemes which are presented with an interpretation of the position of 1&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; states populated via allowed GT transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second project in this thesis is on the design and development of a detector system using a dual micro channel plate configuration. The system was built to detect and measure nanosecond isomers in neutron rich &lt;sup&gt;73-76&lt;/sup&gt;Cu and &lt;sup&gt;76&lt;/sup&gt;Zn isotopes. The design of the instrument and preliminary beam and alpha source tests done on the system are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/648</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1022&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>648</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-11-20T10:54:32-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1069124</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/648</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Grzywacz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carrol Bingham, Witek Nazarewicz, Lawrence Townsend, Krzysztof Rykaczewski</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>