<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of Energy Resolution and Non-proportionality of YAlO3:Ce and Gd3Ga3Al2O12:Ce</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sdonnald@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Donnald</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>Bradley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Scintillator</keyword>
<keyword>non-proportionality</keyword>
<keyword>energy resolution</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nuclear Engineering</discipline>
<discipline>Semiconductor and Optical Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;For many radiation detection applications, energy resolution is one of the most important detector characteristics. In well designed scintillation detectors, the energy resolution is primarily driven by two main factors - the light output and light yield non-proportionality. A great deal of research has already focused on understanding and improving the light yield of scintillation detectors; however, light yield non-proportionality is less well understood. Until recently, light yield non-proportionality was thought to be an intrinsic scintillator property with very little sample-to-sample variation. In this work, two materials have been investigated that demonstrate a variable light yield non-proportionality. The first material investigated was Gd3Ga3Al2O12:Ce. For this material, it was determined that co-doping led to an observable change in light yield non-proportionality and light output, which in turn led to an improvement from 9.0% to 7.8% as a result of boron co-doping and a degradation to 10.1% as a result of calcium co-doping. The second scintillator investigated was YAlO3:Ce (YAP:Ce). This material was investigated because it is one of the few materials which exhibits a large sample-to-sample variation of light yield non-proportionality without intentional co-doping. Some of the best samples display a nearly ideal light yield non-proportionality and have an energy resolution as good as 4.3%, while some of the less optimal samples have an energy resolution as poor as 9% as a result of reduced light output, worsened proportionality, and a detrimental optical absorption band. Based on experimental evidence, it was determined that growth in a reducing atmosphere can suppress the detrimental optical absorption band and improve the light output. In addition, it was found that the Ce 3+ concentration was a key parameter in influencing the variable non-proportional behavior. Samples with a higher Ce 3+ concentration exhibited favorable proportionality, and it seems likely that the behavior can be explained by activator saturation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3120</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4331&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3120</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4331</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-01T16:10:59-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6194800</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3120</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jason P. Hayward</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles L. Melcher, Lawrence H. Heilbronn, Xiaodong Zhang</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>