<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Linking Work Stress, Parental Self-Efficacy, Ineffective Parenting, and Youth Problem Behavior</title>
<publication-date>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Anderson</lname>
<fname>Owen</fname>
<mname>Arthur</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Life Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the relationships among work stress, parental self-efficacy, ineffective parenting behavior, and youth problem behaviors. Questionnaires were collected from 297 families assessing parent perceptions of work stress and parental self-efficacy; youth perceptions of ineffective parenting behavior; and parent, youth, and teacher perceptions of youth internalizing and externalizing problem behavior. There was evidence of work to family spillover, in that work stress (mothers’ work-family conflict and fathers’ job dissatisfaction) was linked to diminished parental self-efficacy and increased ineffective parenting behaviors, which in turn, were associated with higher levels of youth internalizing and externalizing problem behavior. Additionally, lower mothers’ parental self-efficacy was directly related to youth externalizing problem behavior, and lower fathers’ parental self-efficacy was directly related to youth internalizing and externalizing problem behavior. Finally, higher work-family conflict for fathers was directly associated with youth internalizing problem behavior. The discussion included a suggestion of the implementation of workplace parenting and family support strategies which could increase parental self-efficacy and decrease the use of ineffective parenting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1632</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3142&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1632</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3142</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-23T10:01:18-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4338675</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1632</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cheryl Buehler</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brian K. Barber, John G. Orme, Michael Lane Morris</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>