<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Exercise Experiences of Active, Older African-American Women.</title>
<publication-date>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Leggett</lname>
<fname>Sue</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Increased longevity in the population makes the health benefits of exercise more pronounced. Although limited, research indicates that the majority of older African-American women are sedentary. Gaining a fuller understanding of theexercise experiences of those who are physically active may lead to successful interventions that promote healthier lifestyles and enhanced quality of life. In the present study, an attempt was made to identify physically-active African-American females over the age of 55 years and, using a qualitative interview methodology, characterize their exercise experience and identify reasons why they choose to participate in regular physical activity. By using an inductive approach, a window of understanding was opened to the exercise behavior of older AfricanAmerican women. One interview was conducted with each participant and lasted approximately one hour.  Five major themes emerged from these interviews: (1) The Segregated South, (2) Physical Work, Activity, and Walking as a Way of Life, (3) External Support, ( 4) Determination, Positive Attitude, Strong Sense of Self, and (5) Awareness of Aging and Commitment to Activity. This information could be beneficial to health professionals in the development of focused interventions to promote physical activity within this subgroup. Moreover, the results might allow the generation of more enlightened research hypotheses which could then be subsequently tested on larger samples using standard quantitative methods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5806</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7484&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5806</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7484</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23359284</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5806</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>