<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of Human Cdc14B&#39;s function in centrosome cycle control</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>junwu@salk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wu</lname>
<fname>Jun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Centrosomes are the only non-membranous organelles in most vertebrate cells and their major function is to nucleate microtubules, hence often recognized as the microtubule-organizing center (MTOC). Much like chromosome centrosome duplicates only once during the S phase of each cell cycle. The fidelity and timing of this duplication event will ensure equal division of duplicated chromosomes into the daughter cells. As a consequence, numerical and/or structural centrosome abnormalities will cause chromosome missegregation and lead to the generation of multiple mitosis and ultimately chromosomal instability, which typify many cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The molecular mechanism of centrosome duplication remains unclear. Previous studies found that a fraction of human proline-directed phosphatase Cdc14B associates with centrosomes. However, Cdc14B’s involvement in centrosome cycle control has never been explored. In this study, we identify Cdc14B as a negative regulator in centrosome cycle control: depletion of Cdc14B by RNA interference leads to centriole amplification in both HeLa and normal human fibroblast BJ and MRC-5 cells; ectopic expression of Cdc14B leads to stepwise loss of centrioles and attenuates centriole amplification in HU/APH arrested S phase cells and cells treated with proteasome inhibitor Z-L3VS. This inhibitory function requires centriole-associated Cdc14B catalytic activity. In addition, our data suggests counterbalancing effects between Cdc14B phosphatase and kinases such as Plk4, Cdk2/Cyclin-E/A in centrosome duplication control potentially through modulating phosphorylation status of their common downstream effectors, HsSas-6 and B23 respectively. Taken together, these results suggest a potential function for Cdc14B phosphatase in maintaining the fidelity of centrosome duplication cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2789</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4311&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2789</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4311</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-08-25T09:02:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>6029339</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2789</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Yisong Wang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brynn Voy, Hayes McDonald, Bruce Mckee, Sundar Venkatachalam</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Life Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>