<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Death In The Family:  Normalizing The Relationship Between Pet Owner And Pet</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cindy.wilson@usuhs.edu</email>
<institution>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</institution>
<lname>Wilson</lname>
<fname>Cindy</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>enetting@vcu.edu</email>
<institution>Virginia Commonwealth University</institution>
<lname>Netting</lname>
<fname>F.</fname>
<mname>Ellen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
<discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A bi-national, exploratory, pilot content analysis of companion animal (CA)-related content in published newspaper obituaries is reported. Of 11,818 obituaries in three newspapers over a three month period, 252 (2.13%) listed a pet or pet survivors and/or pet charities. Five themes emerged within obituaries containing CA data. First, the word “pet” was rarely used. CAs were typically listed as survivors along with human family members. Second, terms of endearment were consistently used to describe animal companions left behind. Third, some family members, who likely crafted these last statements about their loved ones, engaged in a personification of (and projections onto) the animals left behind. Fourth, there was variation in the roles played by each person with their animal companion. And fifth, donations were made to a wide variety of animal charities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possibility of CAs as fictive kin is explored as a means of normalizing the relationship between pets and their owners. We suggested that the fictive kin concept can be extended to describe those adoptive relationships in which a human being becomes the owner of an animal and in which their relationship holds great affection and significance in that person’s life. The ties that occur become very real and meaningful, making the relationship one of kinship, of seeing that animal as part of one’s family. Many ways of publicly manifesting that relationship can occur – including a pet’s name on a greeting card, taking a pet companion on family outings, even including that pet in the list of familial survivors when one dies. These animals have most likely been elevated to family status and may not be referred to as “pets” much of the time. To be listed in an obituary, is typically reserved for conventional kin, extends the concept of fictive kin to these animals that appear in the last tribute to their human companions. The familial theme is evident in the obituaries. On a macro level, examining obituaries raises the question of what might be changing in terms of societal norms that make this phenomenon more prevalent, even more acceptable. On a familial level, given the changing definitions of family and the multiple constellations of relationships, does this reflect a new or renewed role of the pet within the familial context? And on an individual level, does the public declaration of an animal companion as a survivor reflect the importance of attachment between humans and animals in a less conventional manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we explore the opportunity for veterinarians and veterinary social workers to assist clients in dealing with pet loss within the normal grieving process and “next steps” to be taken to extend these pilot data.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/17</coverpage-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1048</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-05T07:48:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3513866</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cindy C. Wilson, B.S., M.S., Ph.D., C.H.E.S. (1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor ,Department of Family Medicine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences (USUHS)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wilson has over 28 years of human animal interactions research experience. Currently she is publishing data on the impact of a CA on physical activity and metabolic markers for health in dog owners and their dogs. She is collaborating on a bi-national assessment of trends regarding companion animals in an individual’s life at the time of death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wilson has served on review panels for the NIH as well as for foundations in the areas of health and education. She serves as a reviewer for numerous biomedical journals and was an associate editor of &lt;em&gt;Anthrozoös&lt;/em&gt;. She has published over 100 peer reviewed articles, and co-authored/edited the book “Companion Animals in Human Health, and Most recently she has co-authored “The status of instrument development in the human-animal interaction field” with Ellen Netting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F. Ellen Netting&lt;/strong&gt; (2) is Professor Emerita of Social Work and the former Samuel S. Wurtzel Endowed Chair at Virginia Commonwealth University where she taught for 18 years, having previously taught 10 years at Arizona State University. Her B.A. is from Duke University, her M.S.S.W. from The University of Tennessee--Knoxville, and her Ph.D. from The University of Chicago. Her scholarship has focused on health and human service delivery issues for frail elders, human animal interaction, nonprofit management, and volunteerism. Most recently she has co-authored “The status of instrument development in the human-animal interaction field” with Cindy C. Wilson in Anthozoos.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Cindy C. Wilson, Ph.D., CHES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor &amp; Faculty Development Director Department of Family Medicine Civilian, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4301 Jones Bridge Road&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bethesda, Maryland 20814-4799&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;301-295-9471 (T) 301-295-3100 (F) cindy.wilson@usuhs.edu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F Ellen Netting, Ph.D., M.S.S.W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Emerita, Virginia Commonwealth University, School of Social Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9534 Old House Rd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richmond, Virginia 23238&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;804-747-5477 enetting@vcu.edu&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T12:15:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CUMBERLAND ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Grief and bereavement</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>