<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;Taking Action for Social Conscience: Hungry for Education. Thirsty for Hope. Starving for Change.&quot;</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-08T12:25:51-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hmadison@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Madison</lname>
<fname>Hollie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jjone167@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>Justina</fname>
<mname>P</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Your community does so much for you, what have you done for your community?&quot;- The presentation will deal with the importance of giving back to our community. We will focus on finding services/ projects that one can find passion and self- fulfillment and ways that can enhance your quality of life through giving back. Since TASC FORCE is a community service base organization, we can provide pictures and film on how community service has impacted our day to day life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will also go in-depth on how community service provides enjoyment, provides a quality lifestyle for others, the ability to broaden the spectrum of who you come into contact with, and even skill development. We will also discuss how community service brings global awareness on issues, that may in fact impact everyone in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic relates to the conference theme, &quot;Black in America...One Campus...One Community...and Unified for one Cause,&quot; because community service is a way to bring everyone together, no matter what ethnicity, culture, or backgroud. Community service provides a quality way to not only unify everyone, but complete service for the greater good. Thus connecting national and global communities in a positive and beneficial way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the audience involved during our presentation, we will provide interactive activities and handouts-for note taking and additional information regarding our topic.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2012/Session3/3</coverpage-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1060</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-01-31T16:03:56-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>2482751</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2012/Session3/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;T.A.S.C Force would love the opportunity to present at the NAACP Black Issues Conference. We are very passionate about bringing awareness to not only global issues but local issues as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would also love to share our unique perspective on the importance of community service. It&#39;s very important that we start within our own UT community and allocate that service isn&#39;t only a national issue, but also a global/international issue that can benefit us all. In our efforts to present the importance of community service, we hope to bring awareness of global and local issues and persuade others to be active participants within their community. Hopefully, by the end of our presentation others can share the same passion in giving back that we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Hungry for Education. Thirsty for Hope. Starving for Change.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Flip Chart/Markers</value>
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
<value>Dry Erase Board</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZH_hEhAQX-4</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>