<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Results of the Combined Isotonic-Isometric Execution Compared to the Isotonic Execution in Terms of Strength Development and Muscle Girth</title>
<publication-date>1966-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pedersen</lname>
<fname>Arnold</fname>
<mname>William</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Rehabilitation and Therapy</discipline>
<discipline>Sports Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although many studies have been made to determine a method of weight training which produces the greatest increases in muscle strength and muscle girth, the conclusions vary in theory and methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight training has been subjected to much research in the past. Many of the researchers agree on a method of weight training which produces the best results. However, some advocate the use of isometric contractions as the most desirable method of gaining strength. Others state that isotonic exercise is the only logical way to increase one&#39;s strength. Still others say a combination of the two will produce optimum results if maximum strength and maximum development of muscle girth are the objectives. (A combination of the two means that after completing the isometrics the performer does the isotonics or viceversa.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the methods mentioned have proved to be of value; therefore, further probing into the subject appears to have come to a standstill.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1420</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2755&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1420</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2755</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-22T14:32:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4056708</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1420</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ben A. Plotnicki</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Bill C. Wallace, Andrew J. Kozar</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise and Sport Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1966-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>