<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Invertebrate Biomass and Richness in Various Food Plot Types in East Texas</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:44:09-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Austin State University</institution>
<lname>Anderson</lname>
<fname>Charles</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Austin State University</institution>
<lname>Whiting</lname>
<fname>R.</fname>
<mname>Montague</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Temple-Inland Forest Products Corporation</institution>
<lname>Dietz</lname>
<fname>Donald</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Temple-Inland Forest Products Corporation</institution>
<lname>Capps</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>east Texas</keyword>
<keyword>food plots</keyword>
<keyword>invertebrate biomass</keyword>
<keyword>invertebrate richness</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As northern bobwhite (Colinus virginianus) chicks are dependent on invertebrates for food, land managers often use spring/summer food plots to meet these needs. We examined invertebrate production in native vegetation and 6 different food plot types (i.e., fallow disking only; fallow disking and fertilizing; or disking, fertilizing, and planting a single species [browntop millet, iron and clay peas, or sorghum] or a multi-species mix [browntop millet, catjang peas, iron and clay peas, Japanese millet, and pearl millet]) in the Pineywoods of east Texas. Invertebrates were collected weekly during the summers of 1997 and 1999 and for 5 weekly sampling periods during summer, 1998. For each food plot type, invertebrates were separated from debris, air dried, and weighed as a group. Bi-weekly, a 100-invertebrate sub-sample was randomly selected from each sample and sorted to order with weight and number of individuals recorded. When spring precipitation was sufficient, multi-species food plots produced greater (P &lt; 0.05) invertebrate biomass than fallow or native vegetation plots, and all cultivated plots had more (P &lt; 0.05) biomass than native vegetation. Likewise, all cultivated plots had more (P &lt; 0.05) biomass than fallow plots in early summer but not in mid- and late summer. A combination of multi-species (with legumes) food plots and fallow disking should provide bobwhite chicks with invertebrates throughout most summers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol6/iss1/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1260&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>brood_ecology</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1260</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472006</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol6/iss1/9</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>