<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Chemical reactivity measurement and the predicitve identification of skin sensitisers. The report and recommendations of ECVAM Workshop 64</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Miami Valley Innovation Center</institution>
<lname>Gerberick</lname>
<fname>G</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Aleksic</lname>
<fname>M</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Basketter</lname>
<fname>D</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennesee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schultz</lname>
<fname>Terry</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This is the 64th Report of a series of workshops organised by the European Centre for the Validation of Alternative Methods (ECVAM). A workshop on Chemical Reactivity Measurement and the Predictive Identification of Skin Sensitisers was held at ECVAM on 23–25 May 2007, under the chairmanship of Frank Gerberick. The workshop was attended by experts from academia, national organisations, and industries. The aim of the workshop was to review the state-of-the-art of methods for the identification of skin sensitisers based on measurements of chemical reactivity. Furthermore, consideration was given as to how such methods could contribute to integrated testing strategies for the eventual replacement of in vivo testing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/26</coverpage-url>
<label>26</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-27T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1288719</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/26</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>G F. Gerberick, M Aleksic, D A. Basketter, S Casati, A T. Karlberg, P Kern, I Kimber, J P. Lepoittevin, A Natsch, J M. Ovigne, C Rovida, H Sakaguchi, and Terry W. Schultz. &quot;Chemical reactivity measurement and the predicitve identification of skin sensitisers. The report and recommendations of ECVAM Workshop 64&quot; &lt;em&gt;Alternatives to laboratory animals : ATLA&lt;/em&gt; 36 (2008): 215-242.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Alternatives to laboratory animals : ATLA</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>