<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Interaction Model of Client Health Behavior as a conceptual guide in the explanation of children&#39;s health behaviors</title>
<publication-date>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Robinson</lname>
<fname>C.H.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>sthomas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Refereed Journal Articles</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>children</keyword>
<keyword>diet</keyword>
<keyword>physical activity</keyword>
<keyword>Interaction Model of Client Health Behavior</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study used the Interaction Model of Client Health Behavior (IMCHB) as a conceptual guide to explain the correlates of children&#39;s diet and physical activity and explore the relationships of sex with their diet and physical activity of the school-aged child. A descriptive correlational study was conducted on 371 fifth-grade students and their parents. Information on the family&#39;s demographics, health experience, social influence, and environmental resources was collected, as well as data on the children&#39;s intrinsic motivation, cognitive appraisal, and affective response to food/physical activity. Children&#39;s self-reports on diet and physical activity were collected, as were parents&#39; self-reports on health habits. Food preferences and diet self-efficacy explained the most variance in diet behavior for girls and boys. Girls scored healthier on food preferences and diet self-efficacy than did boys, but no difference was detected in their diet behavior. Girls participated in more low-intensity physical activity, but boys participated in more high-intensity physical activity than did girls. Findings provide strong support for the use of the IMCHB to explain children&#39;s diet but weak support for the explanation of children&#39;s physical activity. Further study of additional factors predictive of physical activity is indicated.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/91</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1106&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>91</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1106</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-11T09:44:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1473185</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/91</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Robinson, C.H., &amp; Thomas, S.P. (2004).  The Interaction Model of Client Health Behavior as a conceptual guide in the explanation of children’s health behaviors.  &lt;em&gt;Public Health Nursing&lt;/em&gt;, 21 (1), 73-84.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Public Health Nursing</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>