<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Spontaneous Abortion: Risk Factors Among WIC Participants in Cherokee, North Carolina</title>
<publication-date>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stivers</lname>
<fname>Deann</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to determine the rate and contributing factors of spontaneous abortion among participants in the Cherokee WIC Program. The data were collected from two sources: WIC Certification Records and personal interviews. The sample (N=500) consisted of both Indian (N=433) and Caucasian (N=67) women who participated in the Cherokee WIC Program from July 1976 to March 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spontaneous abortion rate for the total population studied is 24.89%, while the national rate of spontaneous abortion reported in the literature ranges from 10% to 20%. The Caucasian participants (N=67) in this study experience a higher rate (40.0%) than the Indian participants (N=433) (22.37%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A series of common factors among women who had experienced spontaneous abortion were identified by use of Stepwise Logistic Regression and Phi Coefficients. These were substance use/abuse, maternal diet (including caffeine intake, prepregnancy weight, practice of pica), physiological well-being, blood type, age, and the occurrence of vaginal infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information obtained from the personal interviews suggest that a coping mechanism for the women who experience spontaneous abortion occurs. This mechanism can be defined as habituation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information gained in this study will be incorporated into the education program for WIC participants and used as a basis for establishing the effectiveness of the education program.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4256</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5724&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4256</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5724</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-01-09T12:22:13-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9532116</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4256</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard L. Jantz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michael H. Logan, Mary Ann Bass</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>