<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Learning About Aging In Hong Kong Through A Linked Service Learning Project</title>
<publication-date>2013-07-23T12:05:53-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Colorado State University</institution>
<lname>Cook</lname>
<fname>Alicia</fname>
<mname>Skinner</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Colorado State University</institution>
<lname>Fruhauf</lname>
<fname>Christine</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
<discipline>International and Comparative Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;With the goal of enhancing knowledge and skills related to cross-cultural aging, a linked service learning project was implemented through a partnership with an elderly community center in Hong Kong. The project linked Semester at Sea (SAS) study abroad students with gerontology students at Colorado State University through collaborative service learning activities. SAS students served as English tutors to older adults in Hong Kong. Gerontology students helped SAS students prepare for their service learning activity by creating instructional materials specific to aging in Hong Kong. The project evaluation demonstrated that all groups benefited from their involvement. SAS students reported positive cognitive and attitudinal outcomes, gerontology students believed their support of study abroad students enhanced their own learning of course content, and the Hong Kong elders reported positive benefits from their interactions with American students.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1217&amp;amp;context=internationaleducation&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1217</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-23T11:36:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Education</publication-title>
<context-key>4339086</context-key>
<submission-path>internationaleducation/vol42/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-23T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Aging In Hong Kong</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>