<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Head Over Heels: Women in Supply Chain Management</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-19T07:08:18-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ply533@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mobley</lname>
<fname>Mary Margaret</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Operations and Supply Chain Management</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Being a woman in the Supply Chain Management major, I have seen the challenges females face in a male-dominated field. Just why is it that we see so few women in executive roles in the Supply Chain field? Is it because of the gender challenges, or is there another underlying issue that is causing the lack of women in upper-level Supply Chain roles? Through this research study, twelve female participants will tell about their experiences being an entry-level woman in Supply Chain field. These challenges will help to determine if these entry-level challenges are the reason why women are either not continuing to pursue a career in the Supply Chain field, or are not prepared for executive level Supply Chain roles. Through this research, five prominent themes arose from the experiences the participants had faced during their entry-level career. By having these finding, corporations and The University of Tennessee’s nationally ranked Supply Chain program, can better recruit and prepare women for the issues they will face in a male-dominated Supply Chain career.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2017/business/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1123&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1123</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-03T13:51:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>9969048</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2017/business/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Haslam College of Business</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Department of Marketing and Supply Chain Management</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Diane Mollenkopf</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>