<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>How does genome size affect the evolution of pollen tube growth rate, a haploid performance trait?</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Reese</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>DNA content</keyword>
<keyword>evolution of development</keyword>
<keyword>plant reproduction</keyword>
<keyword>macroevolution</keyword>
<keyword>polyploidy</keyword>
<keyword>pollen competition</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Premise of the Study – Male gametophytes of most seed plants deliver sperm to eggs via a pollen tube. Pollen tube growth rates (PTGRs) of angiosperms are exceptionally rapid, a pattern attributed to more effective haploid selection under stronger pollen competition. Paradoxically, whole genome duplication (WGD) has been common in angiosperms but rare in gymnosperms. Pollen tube polyploidy should initially accelerate PTGR because increased heterozygosity and gene dosage should increase metabolic rates, however polyploidy should also independently increase tube cell size, causing more work which should decelerate growth. We asked how genome size changes have affected the evolution of seed plant PTGRs.Methods - We assembled a phylogenetic tree of 451 species with known PTGRs. We then used comparative phylogenetic methods to detect effects of neo-polyploidy (within-genus origins), DNA content, and WGD history on PTGR, and correlated evolution of PTGR and DNA content.Key Results - Gymnosperms had significantly higher DNA content and slower PTGR optima than angiosperms, and their PTGR and DNA content were negatively correlated. For angiosperms, 89% of model weight favored Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models with a faster PTGR optimum for neo-polyploids, but PTGR and DNA content were not correlated. In comparisons of within-genus and intraspecific-cytotype pairs, PTGRs of neo-polyploids &lt; paleo-polyploids.Conclusions – Genome size increases should negatively affect PTGR when genetic consequences of WGDs are minimized, as found in intra-specific autopolyploids (low heterosis) and gymnosperms (few WGDs). But in angiosperms, the higher PTGR optimum of neo-polyploids and non-negative PTGR-DNA content correlation suggest that recurrent WGDs have caused substantial PTGR evolution in a non-haploid state.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5659</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7195&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5659</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7195</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-24T14:00:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>21246539</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5659</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph Williams Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brian O&#39;Meara, Randall Small, Andreas Nebenführ</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6105-0322</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Portions of this document have been previously published in American Journal of Botany.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>