<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hawks versus Doves: The Influence of Political Ideology on the Foreign Policy Behavior of Democratic States</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ccalin@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Calin</lname>
<fname>Costel</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>political ideology</keyword>
<keyword>state behavior</keyword>
<keyword>democratic states</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>International Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Political Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation examines the influence of executive ideological orientation on state foreign policy behavior. I advance an analytical model which asserts that foreign policy decisionmakers act in a manner consistent with the ideological principles presented in their political platforms, party manifestos, and their voters&#39; expectations. Thus, I assert that within developed democracies, the further right a government is, the higher the propensity to behave more aggressively. Oppositely, the further left a government is, the more likely it is to behave more cooperatively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I empirically analyze this theoretical argument by developing three models where the foreign policy behavior is measured uniquely in each separate model. I estimate executive ideology by using two proxies: one which estimates the overall ideology of the executive while the other captures only the foreign policy dimension of executive ideology. To test the hypotheses derived from the theoretical model, I create a new dataset of responses to international crises. Foreign policy behavior is operationalized as an ordinal variable which takes into account a complex range of actions that governments take in the international arena, such as providing aid, mediation, non intervention, condemnation, sanctions, and the use of force. I employ Logit and Orderd Logit statistical analyses on a large-N cross national model. My dissertation focuses on all 22 OECD countries, during the period 1977 to 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The empirical findings partially support my theoretical argument, contingent upon the proxy used for executive ideology and the way state behavior is estimated. I find consistent support to my argument if executive ideology is estimated with the proxy which contains only the party manifestos&#39; foreign policy variables.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/782</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1916&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>782</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1916</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-29T08:44:56-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1916/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1415013</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/782</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brandon Prins</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Brule, Robert Cunningham, Peter Gross</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Political Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>