<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Shortening Power and Related Properties of Lard as Affected by Substitution of Elaidinized Lipid</title>
<publication-date>1969-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Klouda</lname>
<fname>Judith</fname>
<mname>Ellen</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Shortening power and related properties of lard as affected by substitution of elaidinized lipid were investigated. Pastry wafers were prepared with shortenings of 0, 40, 60 and 80&lt;sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; percent levels of substitution of elaidinized lipid for lard. The shortenings were analyzed by gas-liquid and thin-layer chromatography. Penetrability of the worked fats and melting points were determined. Breaking strength of the wafers was measured on a Bailey Shortometer and indexes to flakiness and flavor. Extent of oxidation was estimated with a thiobarbituric acid (TBA) test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major component of the four shortenings was C18:1 fatty acid, ranging in concentration from 51.1 to 63.4 percent. The concentration of trans monoene ranged from 0 to 56 percent. Penetrability of shortening increased with level of substitution of elaidinized lipid and tended to increase with the extent of working of the fat. Wafers from the un-substituted shortening had lower breaking strength values than those from the substituted shortenings. Judges scored wafers from the un-substituted shortening as most tender but also considered those from the first increment of elaidinized lipid to be tender. Wafers from shortening substituted at the 40 percent level were most flaky as indicated by index to flakiness values. Most shrinkage occurred in wafers of shortenings substituted at the 40 and 60 percent levels. Judges did not detect any effect on flavor. TBA numbers indicated that wafers prepared with unsubstituted shortening were more susceptible to oxidative deterioration than those containing elaidinized lipid.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3780</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5299&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3780</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5299</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-04T13:15:29-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8928917</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3780</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ada Marie Campbell</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Grayce E, Goertz, John T. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1969-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1969-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>