<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Social Determinants of Child Trafficking addressed by Government and Non-Government Strategies in South and Southeast Asia: An Integrate Review</title>
<publication-date>2019-04-18T11:25:19-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ppoudel1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Gautam Poudel</lname>
<fname>Pragya</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>cbarroso@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Barroso</lname>
<fname>Cristina</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>child trafficking</keyword>
<keyword>child sexual exploitation</keyword>
<keyword>child sexual servitude</keyword>
<keyword>prevention</keyword>
<keyword>intervention</keyword>
<keyword>anti-trafficking</keyword>
<keyword>government</keyword>
<keyword>non-government organizations</keyword>
<keyword>social determinants</keyword>
<keyword>South Asia</keyword>
<keyword>Southeast Asia</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Community Health and Preventive Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Maternal and Child Health</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aims:&lt;/strong&gt; Child trafficking in South and Southeast Asia is widespread and deeply troubling. While several agencies have initiated anti-child trafficking interventions, it is unknown if they address the 21 social determinants of child trafficking identified by Perry and McEwing (2103). The aim of this integrative review was to explore the anti-child trafficking strategies employed by governments and non-government organizations (NGOs) that target the social determinants of child trafficking in South and Southeast Asia, and identify which levels of the Socio-Ecological Model (SEM) they address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; The authors performed a literature search for journal articles and reports by researchers, local or national governments, and international organizations on the prevention of child trafficking in eight South Asian and eight Southeast Asian nations. Identified manuscripts were analyzed to determine which social determinants and socio-ecological levels were addressed by the programs described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; 16 journals articles and 31 reports from the grey literature were identified. The government and NGO anti-child trafficking strategies in 16 South and Southeast Asian nations addressed 15 and 12 of the 21 social determinants, respectively. Social determinants at the intrapersonal, interpersonal, community, and policy levels of SEM were addressed, but failed to address the organizational level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; The gravity of child trafficking necessitates that interventions address all of the 21 social determinants of child trafficking at all levels of the SEM. The authors found no account on any anti-child trafficking intervention from four South Asian and five Southeast Asian nations. Dissemination and continuous evaluation of anti-trafficking interventions are warranted.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_publichealth/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1004&amp;amp;context=utk_publichealth&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1004</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-09-27T11:09:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Public Health Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>12951855</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_publichealth/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Post-print</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>