<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Psychosocial predictors of women&#39;s physical health in middle adulthood</title>
<publication-date>1992-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sthomas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Thomas</lname>
<fname>Sandra</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>ERIC Document</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>adult development</keyword>
<keyword>aging (individuals)</keyword>
<keyword>females</keyword>
<keyword>locus of control</keyword>
<keyword>physical health</keyword>
<keyword>predictor variables</keyword>
<keyword>role perception</keyword>
<keyword>social networks</keyword>
<keyword>stress variables</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Although health is a key element in one&#39;s experience of middle adulthood as a time of productivity and personal fulfillment, research on psychosocial factors predictive of mid-life health is sparse, especially for women. Psychosocial variables are not only highly salient to health, but also are potentially modifiable by women themselves. This study employed a multivariate, multitheoretical approach to the study of health, examining a variety of psychosocial predictors (locus of control/mastery, psychological well-being, role quality, social network ties, optimism, and demographic variables) in a secondary analysis of data collected by Baruch and Barnett on 238 women. Subjects were divided into four groups: never married (N=50), married without children (N=54), married with children (N=88), and divorced with children (N=46) and were interviewed in their homes (Brookline, Massachusetts), 1978-79. It was found that 27% of the variance in self-reported health of mothers (whether married or divorced) was accounted for by stress, optimism, employment outside the home, occupational prestige, and quality of experience in the maternal role. Twenty-two percent of the variance in health of married women was explained by stress, quality of experience in the wife role, employment, and occupational prestige. A comparison of the healthiest and the least healthy women revealed that women in better health in middle adulthood had fewer concerns regarding their work, marital roles, and child-rearing roles as compared to their less healthy counterparts. Contains approximately 120 references.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/100</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1115&amp;amp;context=utk_nurspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>100</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1115</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-13T10:38:30-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1473194</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/100</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Thomas, S. P. (1992).  Psychological predictors of women&#39;s physical health in middle adulthood.  (ERIC Document Reproduction Service No. ED 358 386)</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1992-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>ERIC</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>