<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Nutrition Field Observations and Experiences With the Florida State Board of Health</title>
<publication-date>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hawkins</lname>
<fname>Bettie</fname>
<mname>Chapman</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report describes and analyzes the observations and experiences of the student during eight weeks of field training with the Division of Nutrition in the Florida State Board of Health. The purpose of the training was to supplement the academic education in public health nutrition at The University of Tennessee and the previous background of the student. The experience was designed to increase her understanding of the function of the Institutional Nutrition Consultant in the total public health program in a state agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through selected readings,&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;conferences, and a planned orientation, data were obtained on the State of Florida; the history, organization, and programs of the Florida State Board of Health and the Division of Nutrition. Through the cooperative efforts of the staff, the student observed and participated in a variety of activities at the state, regional, and local levels. Information was gained by observing the techniques used in consultation, in communication, in program planning, in training programs, and in program evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variety of experiences provided the student.with an overview of the total state health program and the role of nutrition in the program. She gained an increased awareness of the importance,of planning nutrition programs to meet the needs of the population. The scope of events broadened her perspectives and contributed to her professional development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4105</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5512&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4105</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5512</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-29T07:41:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9209941</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4105</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Nelle Traylor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Grayce E. Goertz, Cyrus Mayshark</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>