<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Framework To Implement Varied Learning Environment Using Team Based Learning - Pyramid Hologram To Increase The Learning Outcome In Lean Training</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asatyana@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Satyanarayanan</lname>
<fname>Aravind</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Lean Manufacturing</keyword>
<keyword>Teaching</keyword>
<keyword>Team based Learning</keyword>
<keyword>3D Hologram</keyword>
<keyword>learning outcome</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The failure of Lean efforts can largely be attributed to the failure of organizations to prepare their employees for Lean implementation. Employees are provided with formal training that uses educational videos and classroom lectures. These videos and lectures are individual-oriented and do not engage employees by way of active participation. This indicates the need for learning environments which augment the formal experience to improve employee engagement in training. This research proposes a varied learning environment with the help of Team-Based Learning and 3D Hologram. Both techniques have individually been shown to be effective in teaching technical concepts which require a strong visual competence. Variables specific to the learning environment are identified based on research from multiple areas of learning, including inductive learning, cognitive thinking, constructivism, assistive technology and extrinsic motivation. The research is validated using a control group, which learns by way of educational videos, and a test group, which uses the presented varied learning environment. It is found that the technique learning value and the ability to maintain attention are higher in the test group. The framework presented in this research is widely applicable for Lean training efforts in multiple domains, including manufacturing, supply chain management and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5532</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7005&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5532</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7005</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914337</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5532</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rapinder Sawhney Dr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Kobza Dr, Lee Martin Dr</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>