<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Accuracy of the Omron HJ-720ITC in Free-Living Individuals</title>
<publication-date>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Silcott</lname>
<fname>Nathan</fname>
<mname>Andrew</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this investigation was to examine the accuracy of the Omron HJ- 720ITC piezo-electric pedometer in a free-living environment over a 24-hr period across 3 different BMI categories. A secondary purpose was to compare the accuracy the Omron HJ- 720ITC to that of a spring-levered pedometer (Yamax SW-200). 62 adult volunteers were placed in 3 BMI categories: Normal weight (N=19), Overweight (N=23), or Obese (N=23). Subjects wore five devices over a 24-hr period except when bathing or sleeping. The criterion pedometer (StepWatch-3) was worn on the lateral side of the right ankle. The Omron HJ-720ITC was worn in the mid-line of the right thigh, in the right pants pocket and on a lanyard around the neck. A comparison pedometer (Yamax SW-200) was worn on the belt, in mid-line of the left thigh. The Omron HJ-720ITC significantly underestimated steps taken per day in all three BMI categories compared to the criterion measure (P &lt; 0.001). The pocket position demonstrated mean percent errors in normal, overweight and obese BMI categories of -31.7%, -29.8%, and -35.1% respectively, and was the most accurate in obese individuals. However, in normal and overweight individuals, the Omron in each position was less accurate than the Yamax pedometer. (MPE = -19% and -21%). The Omron HJ-720ITC pedometer is a valid instrument for step counting during continuous walking bouts. However, the Omron significantly underestimates the number of steps taken in free-living individuals. A 4-second step filter that determines walking pattern may contribute to an underestimation of steps accumulated through light, intermittent activity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/558</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1592&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>558</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1592</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-01T08:11:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1181441</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/558</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson, Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>