<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Infratecture: Infrastructure as Architecture</title>
<publication-date>2018-06-25T12:49:16-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dwrigh29@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>David Aaron</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Design</discipline>
<discipline>Landscape Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In today’s society, we are given a systematic way to understand, think, and ultimately, exist in the world. These systems can be seen in christianity, eighteen- wheeler trucks, veganism, or plane travel. All distinctively different, yet similar in that each one defines the way you project yourself. In the layered nature of infrastructure, there are two stages where this primarily plays out: 1 Logistics - Whats it takes to get the latest, greatest iPhone to the market/the money it will take, the labor, the energy. 2 Culture - The reverberation of getting the latest, greatest iPhone to market. How it affects social status, how it connects us instantly to anyone, anything, anytime. The interesting thing about logistics and culture is the mutually beneficial relationship they have with one another - culture is affected by logistics and vice versa. The thesis is organized around a few basic question about these two infrastructures and the preexisting relationships they may already have, such as: Societal impact or privatized investing in the large-scale infrastructure is a relatively new concept, how will this affect the norm and will the changing landscape of technology play into it? Can the two systems be combined as a whole to work in synchronicity? Are they exclusive? Primarily, design projects have used technology as a cure for current economic [autonomous], societal [loading speeds], and infrastructural [defunct] ecologies. Why is technology the lynchpin in a multi-faceted system? Focusing on the social landscape that is incorporated with physical manifestations of infrastructure, the thesis seeks to manipulate multiple agents of society, utilizing technology, and logistical innovation to help design parameters for complex futures.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/architecturedesign/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1220&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1220</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-06-25T11:41:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>12368233</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/architecturedesign/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Akerman</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>