<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Quality of Abstracts</title>
<publication-date>1993-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Jasco</lname>
<fname>Peter</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>indexing</keyword>
<keyword>reference</keyword>
<keyword>ANSI</keyword>
<keyword>CD-ROM</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Printed, online, and CD-ROM indexing and abstracting publications are familiar reference tools in libraries. The American National Standards Institute (ANSI) recognizes 3 types of abstracts: 1. indicative or descriptive, 2. informative, and 3. combination (indicative and informative). The quality of the abstracts in 3 major CD-ROM general periodical indexes that contain abstracts - Reader&#39;s Guide Abstracts, Resource-One, and Magazine Article Summaries - was tested using quantitative or objective tests to provide a generalized view of quality. The abstracts were examined for: 1. consistency of style and readability, 2. the extent to which the ANSI standard was observed, and 3. informativeness. Readability was determined using Grammatik-IV software. The results indicate that the abstracts of Resource-One are the easiest to read, but the Reader&#39;s Guide abstracts, with an average of 110 words, most closely match the ANSI standards for recommended length (100 to 250 words). The Reader&#39;s Guide was also judged the most informative, with 81% of its abstracts of the informative type.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/128</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1134&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>128</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1134</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-11-09T18:44:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15741236</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/128</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1993-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Online Vol. 17</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>