<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Life-Cycle Cost Effectiveness and Safety Evaluation Involving Tennessee Bureau of Investigation Vehicles</title>
<publication-date>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sturgill</lname>
<fname>Curtis</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Health and Physical Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to identify and analyze the life-cycle effectiveness and safety factors involved in operating Tennessee Bureau of Investigation (TBI) motor vehicles from zero miles through life-cycle. The major concerns were to provide a balance of economic and safety factors for determining when vehicles should be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data were collected from TBI files, Department of Transportation (DOT) records, and the National Automobile Dealers Associations Guide (NADA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analysis consisted of entering the data into a computer where they were cross tabulated to determine the correlation between operational costs and mileage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major findings of the research were that economic savings could be achieved if TBI vehicles were traded at 85,000 miles as opposed to trading same vehicle at seventy thousand miles and that operating TBI vehicles past seventy thousand miles did not create safety hazards. A nomograph was utilized for determining when vehicles should be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three major conclusions were based on the findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. TBI vehicles, if traded at 85,000 miles instead of 70,000 miles would create economic savings for the organization;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. The operation of TBI vehicles past seventy thousand miles does not create safety hazards; and miles apparently have no bearing in terms of safety:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. If the procedure for determining the life-cycle or replacement of TBI vehicles was instituted, economic savings could be recognized.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4021</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5638&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4021</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5638</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-21T10:37:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9295707</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4021</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert H. Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William M. Bass, Bill C. Wallace, Robert J. Pursley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Health and Human Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1987-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>