<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sample Code of Ordinances for Small Cities and Towns in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1973-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ownby</lname>
<fname>Don</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This Sample Code has been drafted for use by small cities and towns in Tennessee that desire to have an organized body of municipal law. It is primarily the work of Don Ownby, but it has been critically reviewed by all other members of the MTAS staff and may be said to reflect our combined judgment and experience. This Sample Code may be used as a working basis for drafting a complete code to meet the conditions and requirements of a particular city. Particular attention should be given to provisions that must conform to charter requirements; for example, the ordaining clause of the adopting ordinace and numerous provisions in Title 1. All provisions herein should be carefully reviewed and revised if necessary to conform to the charter of a particular city or town.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/11</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1010&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1010</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-06T12:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2638695</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>