<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fact Book: 1989-1990</title>
<publication-date>1989-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The Office of Institutional Research and Assessment</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the second annual Fact Book of the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. With this edition, the sections on student enrollments, faculty, and research have been expanded. It is our goal to produce a fact book that is informative and helpful in providing a more complete understanding of the university&#39;s academic and administrative operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to edit and develop the document, we want you to feel that these are your data as well, and we hope that you will offer your suggestions as to how this book can better serve your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the first edition, the staff of the Office of Institutional Research is indebted to the many colleagues who collect and maintain the various university data bases. The magnitude of the effort required to manage the information of the university is not always fully appreciated until the need for that information is expressed. Most tables and graphs identify the source from whom more detailed information may be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you use this Fact Book, I hope that your pride in the university swells as has ours in putting these tables and graphs together.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_factbook/25</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1011&amp;amp;context=utk_factbook&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-12-21T12:19:37-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>UTK Fact Book</publication-title>
<context-key>3554837</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_factbook/25</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1989-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>