<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of the Pro-Inflammatory Cytokine IL-1[beta] on Butyrate Metabolism in Colorectal Cancer Cells</title>
<publication-date>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mjohnst8@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Johnstone</lname>
<fname>Megan</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Genetic and environmental factors impact colorectal cancer incidence [2, 3]. Environmental factors include fiber intake and exercise, which are both postulated to reduce colorectal cancer risk [4-6]. While much is understood in regards to how fiber and its derived nutrients influence inflammation; little is known about how inflammation influences how nutrient impact cell metabolism and physiology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short chain fatty acid butyrate, is derived from the fermentation of fiber in the colon and is the preferred energy substrate for colonic epithelial cells (colonocytes) [7, 8]. Butyrate also slows cell proliferation in cancerous colonocytes through its ability to inhibit histone deacetylases (HDACs) [20]. HDACs are enzymes that remove acetyl groups from histones [9]. Inhibition of HDACs results in hyperacetylation, which leads to changes in gene expression [10]. In cancerous colonocytes, inhibition of HDACs by butyrate induces cell cycle arrest, in part, via increased p21 expression [10]. Cancer cells deficient in p21 have been reported to be resistant to butyrate’s anti-cancer effects [11]. Thus, blocking p21 induction by butyrate would promote tumor development and may exclude the beneficial effect derived from a high fiber diet toward prevention of the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients with colorectal cancer have elevated serum levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines [12-14]. Pro-inflammatory cytokines have been shown to suppress butyrate metabolism in cancerous colonocytes [18]. In addition, colorectal cancer patients have a significant reduction in butyrate producing bacteria [15-17]. The significance of this reduction is unclear, however, taken in conjunction with decreased butyrate metabolism it is likely to impact of butyrate’s antiproliferation activity in the colon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identification of mechanisms that mediate decreased butyrate metabolism may aid in the understanding of fiber’s role in colorectal cancer. Here, we find that IL-1[beta] dampens butyrate metabolism in colorectal cancer cells. Furthermore, IL-1[beta] decreases butyrate’s ability to slow cell proliferation. We identify two mechanisms by which IL-1[beta] induces these effects. First, we determine that IL-1[beta] is operating through its receptor, IL-1RI, and second through a p38-mediated mechanism. These findings are consistent with previous reports that proinflammatory cytokines promote cancer cell survival and proliferation [19-22].&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4406</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5524&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4406</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5524</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-22T07:35:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9171242</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4406</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dallas R. Donohoe</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jay Whelan, Brynn Voy, Ling Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>