<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>One Spark Can Light a Fire: How to Become a Mental Health Advocate</title>
<publication-date>2021-01-22T12:11:33-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>marquintaharvey@gmail.com</email>
<institution>The Fearless Campaign and Belmont University</institution>
<lname>Harvey</lname>
<fname>Marquinta</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>sjackson1911@yahoo.com</email>
<institution>The Fearless Campaign and Shelby County Schools</institution>
<lname>Jackson</lname>
<fname>Shannon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Mental Health</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Epidemiology</discipline>
<discipline>Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Spark Can Light a Fire: How to Become a Mental Health Advocate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is increasing awareness surrounding mental health and conversations are beginning to make their way to the forefront of issues that demand significant attention. However, the path from awareness to advocacy remains poorly understood. Mental Illness is an important issue that affects 1 in 4 individuals and unlike most chronic illnesses the onset occurs early in the life spectrum, usually in adolescence and young adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of mental health is not limited to individual genetic predisposition and/or behaviors but involves many layers related to individual, family-related, social, economic, and environmental factors. It is our goal at The Fearless Campaign to educate, advocate and bring awareness to mental health issues with a focus on prevention. With the help of dedicated mental health advocates, we can spread the word that we are ending the stigma surrounding mental illness and taking action to promote mental wellness.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2021/session4/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1262&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1262</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-21T23:24:35-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1262/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>21220229</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2021/session4/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bio" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Marquinta Harvey Bio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Marquinta Harvey is an Assistant Professor of Epidemiology at Belmont University. Dr. Harvey is a leader within the fields of Public Health, Biostatistics, and Behavioral Neuroscience with over 15 years of experience ranging from biological and chemical warfare agent testing for the Department of Defense, to understanding the neurobiological mechanisms that control social stress. She is also the Co-founder of The Fearless Campaign, a movement that is dedicated to educating, advocating, and bringing awareness to mental health issues with a focus in prevention, and the co-host of the Nerdy Optimism podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harvey is a published author with publications in peer-reviewed journals including Stress and Behavioral Neuroscience. She has presented research at many local, state, and national conferences. Dr. Harvey was recently named as a recipient of the inaugural University of Tennessee Knoxville Alumni Volunteer 40 under 40 award. Dr. Harvey is a devoted public health advocate with a passion for understanding and applying information obtained from health data and research to improve processes that lead to better health outcomes for at-risk populations. She has expertise in fostering trusting relationships, team collaboration, problem-solving and innovation, while providing leadership, management, and strategic vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Marquinta Harvey is an active member within her community and gives of her time and treasure to organizations that focus on children and health-related causes. Dr. Harvey serves on the Board of Directors of Ronald McDonald House Charities of Nashville, the Research and Planning Committees for the Tennessee Public Health Association and is the Co-Director of the Locust Ridge Church Youth and Young Adult Ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Marquinta Harvey earned her Doctorate degree in Health and Human Performance from Middle Tennessee State University. She earned her Master’s and Undergraduate degrees from the University of Tennessee, Knoxville in Behavioral Neuroscience and Microbiology, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Harvey is a proud and devoted wife and mother of two children. In her spare time, she enjoys traveling, spending time with family and friends, reading, trivia, and singing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Shannon Jackson Bio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Shannon Jackson prides himself as one of the leaders in assisting teachers, community stakeholders, and school administrators with essential components that help achieve optimal learning and student engagement. Those components include, but are not limited to, peer relationships, psychological evaluations, Response to Instruction, Behavioral management, African American males’ self-conflict, masculinity and gender roles, minority disproportionality in Special education and mentoring, and initiatives that give schools, agencies, and youth organizations a step-by-step plan of action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jackson is a School Psychologist for Shelby County Schools. He has over 15 years of experience. He was born in the bluff city, Memphis, TN. It was here he witnessed the ill effects of poverty, crime and inequalities in education. He is passionate about all children being well prepared for their overall optimal being. Shannon is a lover of education, people, creativity and life. He attended the University of Tennessee, Knoxville where he earned a Bachelor’s degree in Psychology. He also received a Master’s of Science degree in Educational Psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He received a Doctor of Philosophy degree in School Psychology at Tennessee State University. It was here he honed in his primary research; gender role conflict and masculinity in African American adolescent boys. He also researched behavior modification and learning disabilities. Dr. Jackson continues to be a researcher on over-representation of African American males in special education, and he continues to be innovative with Response to Instruction. Dr. Jackson has a unique quality in obtaining the best out of teachers and squeezing the strengths out of students. Taking these strengths and creating greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is also the Co-founder of The Fearless Campaign, a movement that is dedicated to educating, advocating, and bringing awareness to mental health issues with a focus in prevention, and the co-host of the Nerdy Optimism podcast. Dr. Jackson has published work in peer-reviewed journals. He also has presented at conferences to advance the field of psychology and education. Dr. Jackson adores the opportunity to work at conferences and workshops that promotes community advancement. His overall philosophy of learning includes the element of mentorship and bringing information for discussion. Dr. Jackson believes this is how we advance as a collective whole. Throughout his professional work experiences, he has consistently demonstrated strengths as a dependable and reliable team player, possessing organizational skills that have allowed him to be highly productive with continued learning and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jackson serves his community with passion. He is married with 3 boys. Dr. Jackson enjoys traveling, spending time with family and friends and attending live shows and concerts. He is also a member of Kappa Alpha Psi Fraternity Inc.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Visit our website for more information about our movement, www.fearlesscampaign.com&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="learning_outcome" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Participants will learn how social and environmental factors impact mental health and wellbeing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will leave with tangible steps in how to become a mental health advocate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will gain awareness about the prevalence of mental health issues&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants will learn about the impact of mental health on family dynamics&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="relation" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Our talk entitled “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Spark Can Light a Fire: How to Become a Mental Health Advocate,” aims to bring the topic of mental health advocacy to the black community. Promoting mental health prevention is a topic that is not widely understood and can be enlightening and provide an understanding of mental healing that can positively impact human health and wellbeing. Recognizing the prevention of mental illness is possible can provide hope and propel many into action.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>