<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dissociation and Sexual Trauma: The Moderating Role of Somatization</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>aabbas@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Abbas</lname>
<fname>Amineh</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Dissociation</keyword>
<keyword>Somatization</keyword>
<keyword>Sexual Trauma</keyword>
<keyword>Gender</keyword>
<keyword>Age of Onset</keyword>
<keyword>Relationship to Perpetrator</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Cognition and Perception</discipline>
<discipline>Health Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Mental Disorders</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatric and Mental Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Psychoanalysis and Psychotherapy</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined various types of trauma, with an emphasis on sexual trauma across the lifespan, in a clinical sample of male and female adult outpatients assessed for trauma, somatization, and dissociation. Two hundred forty-five adult outpatients at the University of Tennessee Psychological Clinic were administered the Dissociative Experiences Scale (DES), the Traumatic Experiences Checklist (TEC), and Symptom Checklist-90-Revised (SCL-90-R), as part of the routine intake procedure. Of those individuals, 200 patients completed the questionnaires correctly and were included in the final study sample. The experience of sexual trauma indeed accounted for additional variance in somatization scores over and above the experience of other types of trauma, although it did not account for additional variance in dissociation scores. Also somatization was significantly correlated with dissociation. On the other hand, gender did not significantly increase the likelihood of having greater somatization. Furthermore, somatization did not significantly moderate the relationship between trauma and dissociation nor did it affect the non-significant relationship between gender and dissociation. Also, surprisingly in this sample, age of onset of sexual trauma did not significantly increase the likelihood of having greater dissociation or somatization. Finally, the experience of having a family member perpetrator did not account for additional variance in dissociation or somatization scores over and above having a non-family member perpetrator.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3105</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3130&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3105</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3130</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-15T13:09:57-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/3130/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4313627</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3105</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jenny Macfie</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kristina C. Gordon, Gina P. Owens, Edwin S. Rogers</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>