<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>“Enhancement of Sensitivity and Selectivity of Chemical Sensors Through Thin Film Coatings and Surface Modifications</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Headrick</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>Jeremy</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Chemical sensors have become major analytical tools for how we monitor&lt;br /&gt;and obtain information about the chemical nature of ourselves and our&lt;br /&gt;surroundings. Two characteristics of chemical sensors that are under constant&lt;br /&gt;development and improvement are their selectivity and their sensitivity.&lt;br /&gt;Selectivity is a concern of any chemical sensor, without it the signal obtained by&lt;br /&gt;a chemical sensor cannot be related to the target species concentration with any&lt;br /&gt;confidence. With chemical sensors the selectivity is generally created by the&lt;br /&gt;used of a chemical recognition layer such as a permeable membrane, or a thin&lt;br /&gt;chemical film. The sensitivity of a chemical sensor is a concern, as with any&lt;br /&gt;quantitative analytical method, so that small differences in analyte concentration&lt;br /&gt;are distinguishable and trace analysis can be performed. In this work the&lt;br /&gt;selectivity and sensitivity of two distinctly different devices used as chemical&lt;br /&gt;sensors are investigated. The first device combines a scintillation fiber with a&lt;br /&gt;selective polymer coating to create a chemical sensor selective for 137Cs. Both&lt;br /&gt;the selectivity and sensitivity of the scintillation fiber are improved with the&lt;br /&gt;addition of the chemical recognition layer. The second device investigated is a&lt;br /&gt;microcantilever sensor. Microcantilevers have been used to monitor chemicals&lt;br /&gt;present in both air and liquid environments. However, in moving from&lt;br /&gt;measurements made in air to measurements made in liquids, a great deal of&lt;br /&gt;sensitivity is lost due to differences in the interfacial energies of the&lt;br /&gt;v&lt;br /&gt;microcantilevers in these two different environments. To overcome this limitation&lt;br /&gt;surface modification of the microcantilevers was investigated to improve the&lt;br /&gt;sensitivity of these devices. Surfaces of the microcantilevers were modified by&lt;br /&gt;several different methods, the binding of gold nanobeads to the surface, creation&lt;br /&gt;of a roughened dealloyed surface, and the physical milling and chemical etching&lt;br /&gt;of grooves into the surface of the microcantilevers, each of these surface&lt;br /&gt;modifications was shown to enhance the sensitivity of microcantilever chemical&lt;br /&gt;senors over microcantilever chemical sensors with smooth surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2066</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3503&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2066</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3503</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-26T12:48:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4634384</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2066</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Michael J. Sepaniak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. James Q. Chambers, Dr. Ben Xue, Dr. Panos Datskos</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>