<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Transport Critical Currents in YBaCuO-based Coated Conductors: Angular, Magnetic Field, and Temperature Dependencies</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Travaglini</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Condensed Matter Physics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;High-temperature superconductivity has been a focus of much study over the past 20 years, particularly within the cuprate class of superconductors. The effectiveness of these cuprate superconductors is limited by factors including the formation of vortices within the superconductor, orientation within external magnetic fields, the strength of these magnetic fields, temperature, and whether any doping agents have been used. Any of these factors individually can affect the transport critical current levels. In this research, YBaCuO and NdBaCuO-based coated conductors were studied in a liquid-nitrogen-cooled environment at either 77 K or 65 K. Field levels were varied between 0 T and 8 T while orientation was held constant, as well as orientation varying through 140 degrees of rotation while the field was held constant. From the data, n-values (in the voltage-current power-law relation V / In) and  values (a power-law relation Jc / H) were calculated, and plots of angular and field dependencies were made. The results showed parallels between doping and improved pinning ability of vortices in addition to an unsuspected weak variation of n-values in relation to orientation within constant magnetic fields.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/233</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1265&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>233</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1265</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-10T10:37:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1139183</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/233</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>James. R. Thompson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Pengcheng Dai, Tolga Aytug</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Physics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/TravagliniSam.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>