<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Another part of the risk communicatin model:  Analysis of risk communication process and message content</title>
<publication-date>2002-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mpalench@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Palenchar</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Houston</institution>
<lname>Heath</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The authors undertook a study to define the messages that exist in 2 communities of risk (e.g., high concentration of chemical facilities) using the principles of fantasy theme analysis and symbolic convergence theory. Through several methodological steps including a document review, interviews, focus groups, and a telephone survey (N = 450), the researchers determined the messages that dominate in the community, and were able to segment them into rhetorical visions based on master analogues. Analysis indicated that persons who adhere to different perspectives or opinions (measured as rhetorical visions) experience different amounts of uncertainty, control, and support or opposition for the industries that create the risks. This analysis adds depth to the risk communication literature and suggests that public relations practitioners can and should attempt to understand risk discourse content as well as the communication processes and risk perceptions held by key publics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>158</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_advepubs/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1002&amp;amp;context=utk_advepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-05-14T06:03:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Advertising and Public Relations Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1338346</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_advepubs/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Public Relations Research</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>