<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Proactive model to determine information technologies supporting expansion of air cargo network</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gmcclain@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McClain</lname>
<fname>Grayson</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>air cargo</keyword>
<keyword>fixed charge</keyword>
<keyword>information technology</keyword>
<keyword>capacity expansion</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Operations Research, Systems Engineering and Industrial Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Shippers and recipients expect transportation companies to provide more than just the movement of a package between points; certain information must be available to them as well, to enable forecasts and plans within the supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transportation companies also need the information flow that undergirds a transportation grid, to support ad-hoc routing and strategic structural re-alignment of business processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research delineates the information needs for an expanding air cargo network, then develops a new model of the information technologies needed to support expansion into a new country. The captured information will be used by shippers, recipients, and the transportation provider to better guide business decisions. This model will provide a method for transportation companies to balance the tradeoffs between the operating efficiencies, capital expenditures, and customer expectations of their IT systems. The output of the model is a list of technologies – optimized by cost – which meet the specific needs of internal and external customers when expanding air cargo networks into a new country.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2714</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3945&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2714</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3945</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-30T08:16:35-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4947130</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2714</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rapinder Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Xueping Li, Joseph Wilck IV, Bogdan Bichescu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>