<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Gendered Racial Socialization as a Moderator of the Relations Between Gendered Racial Microaggressions and Traumatic Stress Symptoms for Black Women</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>amoody10@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Moody</lname>
<fname>Anahvia</fname>
<mname>Taiyib</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>gendered racism</keyword>
<keyword>gendered racial socialization</keyword>
<keyword>trauma</keyword>
<keyword>intersectionality</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to investigate the relations between gendered racial microaggressions (i.e., subtle gendered racism), gendered racial socialization, and traumatic stress symptoms for Black women. This study applies an intersectional lens to explore the influence of the intersection of racism and sexism (i.e., gendered racism) on traumatic stress symptoms. Specifically, we tested the possible protective or exacerbating role of gendered racial socialization based on extant literature that demonstrates protective and exacerbating influences of racial socialization. We hypothesized that gendered racial microaggressions would significantly predict traumatic stress symptoms; in addition, we hypothesized that gendered racial socialization would moderate the relations between gendered racial microaggressions and traumatic stress symptoms. Participants were 226 Black women across the United States who completed an online survey. Results from regression analyses indicated that gendered racial microaggressions significantly predicted self-reported traumatic stress symptoms. In addition, results from a series of eight moderation analyses indicated that there were no moderating effects of gendered racial socialization. However, two types of gendered racial socialization messages (internalized gendered racial oppression and sisterhood) were found to significantly predict traumatic stress symptoms. The results of this study can inform future research on Black women’s experiences of gendered racism and the role of gendered racial socialization in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5023</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6430&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5023</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6430</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-03T13:06:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13414680</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5023</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jioni A. Lewis</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Gina P. Owens, Dawn M. Szymanski</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8698-1118</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>