<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mediations for Stuttering Reduction: Lessons from African American and Mexican-American Children</title>
<publication-date>2007-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>nradford@uthsc.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Health Science Center</institution>
<lname>Radford</lname>
<fname>Nola</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Tanguma</lname>
<fname>Jesus</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>stuttering</keyword>
<keyword>stuttering modification</keyword>
<keyword>fluency-shaping</keyword>
<keyword>multicultural</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the article is to provide clinicians examples of best practices for the remediation of stuttering in school-age children. The recommended approach to treatment is based on best practices as espoused in the professional literature (ASHA) and based on the author&#39;s seven years of research with over 40 African American, White, and Mexican-American children who stutter. The article is an outgrowth of a recent workshop presentation (NBASLH, 2006) and disseminates results of ongoing research to address the needs of children who exhibited chronic stuttering with little or no improvement resulting from school-based therapy. Recent case studies indicate that children, particularly those who experience limited success in school-based therapy, have significantly improved outcomes when stuttering modification or fluency-shaping approaches are combined with mediated learning strategies to promote cognitive change, family support, and learning transfer (Radford, Tanguma, Gonzalez, Nericcio, &amp; Newman, 2005). A consistent theme throughout the article is that clinicians should adopt a view from the perspective of the speaker to promote clients&#39; successful management of their stuttering (Plexico, Manning, &amp; Dilollo, 2005). However, successful management should include strategies to reduce stuttering as the factor significant to disruption of communication, social isolation, and quality of life. Further, successful management may include prosthetic devices.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_audipubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1004&amp;amp;context=utk_audipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1004</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-02-19T09:24:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Audiology and Speech Pathology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>11588346</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_audipubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-04-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>ECHO Journal of the National Black Association for Speech-Language and Hearing</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>