<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Evaluation of a Two-way Datalink for Airborne Surveillance of and Communication with a Remotely Operated Aircraft Operating in the National Airspace System</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Clark</lname>
<fname>Timothy</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Systems Engineering and Multidisciplinary Design Optimization</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to examine the use of a two-way digital datalink to implement the airborne surveillance and communication functions with a Remotely Operated Aircraft in the National Airspace System. These Air Traffic Control functions are currently implemented using primary and secondary radar systems for airborne surveillance, and radio transmissions for voice communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present Air Traffic Control system was examined, as well as existing datalink technologies and surveillance and communication equipment. Remotely Operated Aircraft are currently employed almost exclusively by the military, and operational experience in the National Airspace System is very limited. Several key military Remotely Operated Aircraft systems were evaluated, including their operations in the National Airspace System. There are numerous potential uses for commercial Remotely Operated Aircraft operations in the National Airspace System to satisfy varied missions and roles, and the issues associated with large numbers of unmanned aircraft operating in the National Airspace System was investigated. The information used in this study was collected from various published sources, as well as from a number of interviews with knowledgeable persons in the Remotely Operated Aircraft industry and the Federal Aviation Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remotely Operated Aircraft have been established as viable military platforms, and a variety of civilian missions are under consideration to extend their demonstrated usefulness. As civilian Remotely Operated Aircraft system designs and concepts of operation are refined, many cost-effective applications have been identified for using Remotely Operated Aircraft in new roles or in roles currently being performed by manned aircraft. Large numbers of Remotely Operated Aircraft are expected to be operated in the National Airspace System in the future, and the Air Traffic Control system must be able to accommodate their unique needs and facilitate the safe and efficient operation of Remotely Operated Aircraft in the National Airspace System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-way digital datalink technology has significant potential for use in implementing the airborne surveillance and communication functions with Remotely Operated Aircraft in the National Airspace System. A datalink-based Air Traffic Control system provides more accurate and comprehensive time-critical surveillance information to the air traffic controller, and facilitates more efficient communications of large amounts of useful information between the air traffic controller and Remotely Operated Aircraft remote operator. It is recommended that two-way digital datalink technology should be pursued for implementing the airborne surveillance and communication functions with a Remotely Operated Aircraft in the National Airspace System. Although this technology has many key benefits, there are several important operational, safety and security issues that must be addressed before the system can be fully implemented in the National Airspace System.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2044</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3396&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2044</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3396</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-01T08:34:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4651750</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2044</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Frederick W. Stellar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ralph D. Kimberlin, Dr. George W. Garrison</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aviation Systems</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>