<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Collaborative learning in a high technology start-up business</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Naujock</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
<mname>Jo</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study investigated the role of collaborative learning in a new hightechnology business. It included a description of the experience of the facilitator. who was also a co-founder and officer of the company. Peters&#39; (1998, 2002) action research model was used to frame the research. Data were collected using phenomenological interviews, semi-structured interviews, and field notes. A thematic analysis revealed four themes: relationship dynamics, knowing, the facilitator&#39;s role, and business outcomes. Four sub-themes appeared within the theme of relationship dynamics: team composition, early loss and change in team member participation, commitment to members, and virtual and face-to-face communication. Two sub-themes appeared within the theme of knowing: intuition and experience. These results indicated that company founders and other team members successfully engaged in collaborative learning as described by Peters and Armstrong ( 1998). Participants were able to jointly develop a dialogical space conducive to collaborative learning, practice cycles of action and reflection, utilize multiple ways of knowing, and achieve pre-start-up and start-up business outcomes such as completing incorporation documents, negotiating a technology transfer license agreement, and pursuing funding. Results also informed the way in which the researcher performed facilitator tasks within her role as company co-founder and officer. Implications for practitioners in similar start-up companies and recommendations for additional action research on collaborative learning in business contexts are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6278</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8230&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6278</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8230</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450376</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6278</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John M. Peters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William Q. Judge, John W. Lounsbury, Mary F. Ziegler</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>