<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthesis and Application of Polymer Brush-Grafted Nanoparticles as Hydrogel Gelators and Lubricant Additives</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rwrigh23@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wright</lname>
<fname>Roger</fname>
<mname>Anthony Emory</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>hairy particles</keyword>
<keyword>physical hydrogels</keyword>
<keyword>stimuli-responsive polymers</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation describes the synthesis of polymer brush-grafted nanoparticles (hairy NPs) and an analysis of their behavior or utility in multiple areas. The hairy NPs were synthesized from silica NPs functionalized with initiating moieties by surface-initiated atom transfer radical polymerization. A brief introduction to hairy NPs, with a focus on the synthesis and behavior of stimuli-responsive polymer brush-grafted particles, is given in Chapter 1 to provide context for this work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapters 2 and 3 present the synthesis of thermosensitive diblock copolymer brush-grafted nanoparticles designed as hairy NP analogues in place of thermosensitive block copolymers micelles for the construction of hybrid, physical hydrogels. Chapter 2 details a series of hairy NPs with a thermosensitive poly(methoxydi(ethylene glycol) methacrylate) (PDEGMMA) inner block and a charge-bearing, poly(DEGMMA-&lt;em&gt;co&lt;/em&gt;-2-(methacryloyloxy)ethyltrimethylammonium iodide) (PDEGMMA&lt;em&gt;-co-&lt;/em&gt;TMAEMA-I) outer block. These hairy particles underwent a reversible, cooling-induced gelation at moderate concentrations in water, based on the packing of hairy NPs due to the LCST-driven increase in brush volume fraction upon cooling. Another series of thermosensitive hairy NPs was made with brushes composed of P(TMAEMA-I)&lt;em&gt;-b-&lt;/em&gt;PDEGMMA, which exhibited a heating-induced reversible gelation at concentrations as low as 3 wt % in water, due to the association of PDEGMMA outer blocks at temperatures above their LCST. The inner hydrophilic polyelectrolyte block served to bridge these domains and NPs to form a three-dimensional gel network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4 details the use of NPs grafted with oil-soluble poly(lauryl mathacrylate) as lubricant additives. These hairy NPs showed superior stability in a poly(alphaolefin) (PAO) base lubricating oil, and the addition of 1.0 wt % hairy NPs to PAO yielded significant reductions in both friction and material wear. These gains were attributed to the formation of a load-bearing tribofilm at the rubbing interface. Chapter 5 explores the brush microphase separation of poly(&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;-butyl acrylate)&lt;em&gt;-b-&lt;/em&gt;polystyrene (P&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;BA&lt;em&gt;-b-&lt;/em&gt;PS) brush-grafted particles with P&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;BA as inner block. From TEM analysis, there appeared an evolution of phase morphology from a stripe-like nanostructure to a more uniform layered structure with increasing PS molecular weight, in qualitative agreement with simulation studies. Chapter 6 includes a look back on this dissertation work in its entirety and possible future work.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3982</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5359&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3982</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5359</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-17T11:15:49-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8745917</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3982</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bin Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Brian Long, John Bartmess, Hong Guo</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>