<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An Evaluation of CHARACTER COUNTS!&lt;sub&gt;SM&lt;/sub&gt; Character Education Activities in Relationship to the Behavior of Elementary School Children in Sullivan County Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wiebers</lname>
<fname>Justin</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the correlation between schools’ level of involvement in CHARACTER COUNTS! activities and the desired behaviors of elementary school students in Sullivan County, Tennessee. General perceptions of educators and administrators about the CHARACTER COUNTS! program were collected from 328 respondents from 27 public elementary schools, and a profile of school involvement in CHARACTER COUNTS! activities was developed for schools with the best student behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it cannot be stated that CHARACTER COUNTS! caused changes in behavior, this study revealed a substantial positive correlation (P=.64) between school involvement in CHARACTER COUNTS! activities and desired student behaviors perceived by elementary school educators and administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings also revealed that 95.2% of respondents agreed (38.3%) or strongly agreed (56.9%) that character education is an important part of their work, and more than 80% of respondents believe CHARACTER COUNTS! is an effective program. Respondents also agreed (35.3%) or strongly agreed (4.4%) with the statement, &quot;I have fewer discipline problems because of CHARACTER COUNTS!.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for primary strategies for school efforts in developing a CHARACTER COUNTS! program are provided as well as recommendations for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2003</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3360&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2003</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3360</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-27T12:26:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4640826</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2003</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Rich Polling, Martha Jo Tolley, Peggy Adkins</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>