<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and Reading Abilities: A Comprehensive Review</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:52:08-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mmart117@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Martin</lname>
<fname>Mckenzie Rose</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>hflatt@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Flatt</lname>
<fname>Holly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), is a neurodevelopmental disorder that is characterized by “a consistent pattern of inattention and/or hyperactivity/impulsivity symptoms that interferes with functioning in at least two domains” (DSM-V, 2013). While most studies link reading impairments to attention symptoms, Kagan’s (1965) seminal work documents a significant positive correlation between cognitive impulsivity and reading abilities in typically developing school-aged children (Kagan 1965). Moreover, extant research documents a relation between academic achievement impairments and ADHD-related cognitive impairments (i.e., executive functions). The purpose of this review is to examine ADHD-related reading abilities. We aim to outline the foundation for research on the relation between reading abilities and ADHD symptoms. We will examine both reading abilities broadly and examine specific reading-related processes (i.e., reading comprehension and reading decoding). Moreover, we will examine the relation between impulsivity and reading abilities in school-aged children diagnosed with ADHD. Our goal is to understand the etiology (i.e., root cause) of impaired reading abilities in school-aged children diagnosed with ADHD. Clinical and research implications will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1203&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1203</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-25T14:58:33-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1203/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>12022332</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/artsandsciences/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Arts &amp; Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Jennifer Bolden</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>