<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>De la Progression de Rousseau dans les Confessions</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Monson</lname>
<fname>Reed</fname>
<mname>Martin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>French and Francophone Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to examine the question of progress in Jean-Jacques Rousseau’s autobiograpphy, The Confessions. Rousseau (1712-1778) is considered the father of the autobiographical genre in French and one of the most influential writers of the European 18th Century Age of Enlightenment. Along with Voltaire, he is the most studied author of this period. One of Rousseau’s goals in writing his Confesssions was to justify the manner in which he lived his life. One of Rousseau’s main paradoxes was that while considering himself a virtous man all his life, he also admitted that he at times changed for the better. In order to study this paradox, this study has examined three important episodes of his life!: one from childhood!; the second from his late adolescence and the last from his mature period. This study has focused on the strong influence the ancient Romans had on Rousseau as a child and that the notion of virtus was all-important in the way he lived his life and also how he viewed his own life. Our study has concluded that in spite of appearances, Rousseau’s attempt to attain the seemingly impossible goal of living a virtuous life was gained through the sincerety of his intentions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2110</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3483&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2110</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3483</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-04T14:55:50-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4672272</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2110</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Mary McAlpin</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Karen Levy, Dr. John Romeiser</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>French</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>