<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>On Compressible Gaseous Motions in Swirl Dominated Combustors</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bmaicke@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Maicke</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>asymptotics</keyword>
<keyword>vortex</keyword>
<keyword>compressible</keyword>
<keyword>propulsion</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Aerodynamics and Fluid Mechanics</discipline>
<discipline>Propulsion and Power</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this dissertation, a number of models are derived to describe swirling flows. Both generalized compressible Bragg-Hawthorne and vorticity-stream function frameworks are determined and left in a generic form suitable for describing a number of different scenarios. These systems are solved for the bidirectional vortex flowfield by means of a Rayleigh-Janzen perturbation, which expands the governing equations in terms of the Mach number squared. The resulting equations are solved to provide a semi-analytical solution after the evaluation of a handful of numerical integrals. These solutions further the understanding of compressible flow in swirl-combustors, as previous compressible studies are primarily experimental or numerical in nature. Additionally, an alternative swirl velocity model is discussed which uses the balancing of pressure and shear forces to arrive at a piecewise velocity model. The model is compared to experimental data using a method that enables the adjustment of laminar models to account for the effects of turbulence. A modified least-squares approach is developed to handle the movable boundary in the piecewise velocity formulation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1427</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2619&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1427</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2619</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-06-22T13:13:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>3019090</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1427</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph Majdalani</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Trevor Moeller, Christian Parigger, Kenneth Kimble</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Aerospace Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>