<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Agents of Change</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:37:11-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>adixon22@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Dixon</lname>
<fname>Aaron</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mmerrifi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Merrifield</lname>
<fname>Madison</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;x-x-x-docs-internal-guid-a29d102b-7fff-9fb8-e20c-2ebec9428dba&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth sets us free, but how do we use that freedom to light the way for others? Join the presenters for an illuminating discussion about issues that people of color who are LGBT+ face both globally and locally. Participants will leave this session with action points for being an agent of change in their own circles of influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies show that the majority of individuals of color who are LGBT+ reside in the South, a section of the country of which the University of Tennessee and Knoxville are a part (Human Rights Campaign, 2018). Moreover, individuals with multiple oppressed identities face greater threats than individuals with one or no oppressed identity (Crenshaw, 1989; Reynolds &amp; Pope, 1991; Human Rights Campaign, 2018). As members and allies of the Black community seek to highlight truth, they must also recognize the many unique subpopulations of the community, including people who are LGBT+, who need specific support for the distinct challenges they face daily. This session will provide individuals the tools they need--both in facts and action plans--to support the Black LGBT+ community at the University of Tennessee, in Knoxville, and in other circles of influence. When all subpopulations are supported, the whole Black community will shine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After attending this session, participants will be able to:  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describe the characteristics and common issues of people of color who are LGBT+  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognize issues that students of color who are LGBT+ face at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Construct action points to become an agent of change for communities of color who are LGBT+  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Program Content/Outline&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome and Introduction (5 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kahoot Interactive Game (8 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o What do you know about communities of color who are LGBT+?  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review of communities of color who are LGBT+ (7 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review of the University of Tennessee’s recent LGBT+ issues (12 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategies to create an LGBT+-friendly campus for communities of color (15 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o Your sphere of influence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;o Where do we go from here?  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions (3 min.)  &lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participant Engagement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenters will share relevant, practical information by inviting audience members to participate in an online Kahoot game as well as a think, pair, share activity to discuss strategies and recommendations for creating a more inclusive environment for students, faculty and staff, and community members of color who are LGBT+.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/10</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1212&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>10</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1212</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-10T07:42:57-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1212/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13597374</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/10</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>