<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Students’ Perspectives of Experiential Learning in an Addictions Course</title>
<publication-date>2019-02-25T10:00:08-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tmillike@odu.edu</email>
<institution>Old Dominion University</institution>
<lname>Dice</lname>
<fname>Tammi</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>kcarlisl@odu.edu</email>
<institution>Old Dominion University</institution>
<lname>Carlisle</lname>
<fname>Kristy</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>byrdrj@etsu.edu</email>
<institution>East Tennessee State University</institution>
<lname>Byrd</lname>
<fname>Rebekah</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>addictions training</keyword>
<keyword>addictions course</keyword>
<keyword>experiential learning</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Substance use disorder practitioners may identify as individuals in recovery, while others may have never experienced the challenge of abstinence. Without this lived experience, it may be difficult to accurately empathize with clients in recovery. Experiential learning is a way for students to live through an exercise in abstinence. The value of utilizing experiential learning for skill development and application of theory is established. However, there is no empirical research examining the use of experiential learning with undergraduate substance use disorder practitioner trainees not in recovery from addiction as a means to increase their ability to empathize with clients’ experiences. This article explored the impact of an experiential learning assignment in an undergraduate addictions course. A qualitative analysis of students’ written reflections revealed four primary themes. Authors offer suggestions for substance use disorder educators and recommendations for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tsc/vol1/iss1/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1009&amp;amp;context=tsc&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1009</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-10-21T11:54:43-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/tsc/article/1009/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Teaching and Supervision in Counseling</publication-title>
<context-key>13133440</context-key>
<submission-path>tsc/vol1/iss1/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Tammi Dice, Department of Counseling and Human Services, Old Dominion University. Kristy Carlisle, Department of Counseling and Human Services, Old Dominion University. Rebekah Byrd, Department of Counseling and Human Services, East Tennessee State University.
Correspondence concerning this article should be addressed to Tammi Dice, Department of Counseling and Human Services, Education Bldg., Norfolk, VA 23529. 
Contact: tmillike@odu.edu</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.7290/tsc010106</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xdc745d8)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>