<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sheep in Wolves’ Clothing: How Composition’s Social Construction Reinstates Expressivist Solipsism (And Even Current-Traditional Conservatism)</title>
<publication-date>2013-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rhodekei@gvsu.edu</email>
<institution>Grand Valley State University</institution>
<lname>Rhodes</lname>
<fname>Keith</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>robinsmo@gvsu.edu</email>
<institution>Grand Valley State University</institution>
<lname>Robinson</lname>
<fname>Monica</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Creative Writing</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Disability and Equity in Education</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
<discipline>Liberal Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other Education</discipline>
<discipline>Special Education and Teaching</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Reframing the theory of social construction from Romantic/ Classic perspectives yields surprising insights about writing studies.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jaepl/vol19/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1234&amp;amp;context=jaepl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>essay</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1234</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-07-15T09:19:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>The Journal of the Assembly for Expanded Perspectives on Learning</publication-title>
<context-key>5785883</context-key>
<submission-path>jaepl/vol19/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Keith Rhodes is an Associate Professor and the Director of First-year Composition at Grand Valley State University. A former business lawyer, he has served as Secretary of the Council of Writing Program Administrators, as book review editor for JAEPL, and as a member of the five-person Steering Committee that finalized the original CWPA Outcomes Statement for First-year Composition. Perhaps as a result of his attachment to American pragmatist philosophy, his scholarship tends, though not exclusively, toward practical matters like teaching style and modifying business-world thinking for use in composition administration. (rhodekei@gvsu.edu)

Monica McFawn Robinson is an Affiliate Professor of Writing at Grand Valley State University, where she teaches both composition and creative writing. Her scholarly and creative output spans from pedagogy to fiction and playwriting. Her most recent pedagogical inquiry has been on how classroom game design can benefit the teaching of writing. Her fiction and poetry has been published in several literary journals, and her collection of short stories, Bright Shards of Someplace Else, to be published by University of Georgia Press in 2014, won the 2013 Flannery O’ Connor Award. (robinsmo@gvsu.edu)</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Sheep in Wolves’ Clothing</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>