<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Estimating population parameters of the Louisiana black bear in the Upper Atchafalaya River Basin</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>clowe10@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Lowe</lname>
<fname>Carrie Lynne</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>abundance</keyword>
<keyword>black bear</keyword>
<keyword>robust design</keyword>
<keyword>Atchafalaya</keyword>
<keyword>Ursus americanus luteolus</keyword>
<keyword>DNA</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Life Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In 1992, the Louisiana black bear (&lt;em&gt;Ursus americanus luteolus&lt;/em&gt;) was granted threatened status under the Endangered Species Act primarily because of extensive habitat loss and fragmentation.  Currently, the Louisiana black bear is restricted to 3 relatively small, disjunct breeding subpopulations located in the Tensas River  Basin of northeast Louisiana, the upper Atchafalaya River Basin (ARB) of south-central Louisiana, and coastal Louisiana.  The 1995 Recovery Plan mandates research to determine the viability of the remaining subpopulations.  I conducted a capture-mark-recapture study during 2007–2009 to estimate population parameters for the ARB bear subpopulation by collecting hair samples (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 2,977) from 115 barbed-wire hair traps during 8 1-week periods each summer.  DNA was extracted from those hair samples and microsatellite genotypes were used to identify individuals.  I analyzed encounter histories using the Huggins full heterogeneity estimator in a robust design framework in Program MARK.  I compared candidate models incorporating heterogeneity, behavior, and time effects on capture using information-theoretic methods.  I directly estimated apparent survival, temporary emigration, probability of capture and recapture, and probability of belonging to 1 of 2 mixtures; population abundance was a derived parameter.  Apparent survival was 0.91 (SE = 0.06) and did not vary by gender or year.  There was some evidence of temporary emigration for males only (0.10, 95% CI = 0.001–0.900).  I modeled capture probabilities with a 2-mixture distribution for both male and females.  Overall mean weekly capture probability was 0.12 (SE = 0.03) and 0.25 (SE = 0.04) for males and females, respectively.  Recapture rates indicated a positive behavioral response to capture.  Model-averaged mean annual abundance was 56 (SE = 4.5, 95% CI = 49–68).  I calculated population density using spatially-explicit maximum-likelihood methods; model-averaged density was 0.15 bears/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (SE = 0.03).  My results updated previous abundance estimates for the ARB bear subpopulation and will be used in a population viability analysis to determine if recovery criteria for the Louisiana black bear have been met.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/895</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2003&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>895</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2003</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-18T10:36:11-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2003/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1945171</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/895</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Joseph D. Clark</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lisa I. Muller, Arnold M. Saxton, Frank T. van Manen</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>