<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identifying Team Dysfunctions within Two Natural Resources Conservation Service Offices</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>npipkin@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pipkin</lname>
<fname>Norman</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Dysfunction</keyword>
<keyword>Teams</keyword>
<keyword>Leadership</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Leadership Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Other Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Many teams fail to recognize what causes dysfunction within their team. The purpose of this study is to examine team dynamics and produce an example of applied leadership research for leadership educators. By identifying the causes of dysfunction, teams will be able to advance the functionality and success of their team by achieving a higher level of cohesiveness and production for the customers and communities in which they serve. Leadership educators will be able to use this study in discussing how team functionality can be studied and improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NRCS offices in two counties were given the opportunity to participate in this study to evaluate dysfunction within their team. One instrument was used during this study for data collection, a &lt;em&gt;Team Dysfunction Assessment Questionnaire&lt;/em&gt; (Lencioni, 2002). The &lt;em&gt;Team Dysfunction Assessment Questionnaire &lt;/em&gt;was developed as a diagnostic tool for evaluating team susceptibility to five dysfunctions (Lencioni, 2002). The mean scores for NRCS Office One indicated all five dysfunctions could be a problem. The mean scores for NRCS Office Two indicated the dysfunctions were not a problem except for avoidance of accountability. The mean score for avoidance of accountability indicated the dysfunction could be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based upon the findings of this study, recommendations for future research were made. After results are shared with each office, a follow-up study should be conducted to determine if the dysfunctions are continuing to persist, and what techniques and team exercises were effective or not effective when seeking to correct the dysfunction. Future research should determine if the case study is an effective exercise in helping undergraduate students acquire the skills and dispositions needed to be better team members and leaders.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4066</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5229&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4066</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5229</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-06-16T18:40:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8743771</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4066</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Christopher T. Stripling</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Carrie A. Stephens, H. Dwight Loveday</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communications</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>