<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Role of 5-HT2A and 5-HT2C Receptors in Conditioned Defeat</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mlee4@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Marquinta Juvon</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>serotonin</keyword>
<keyword>anxiety</keyword>
<keyword>conditioned defeat</keyword>
<keyword>5-HT2A</keyword>
<keyword>5-HT2C</keyword>
<keyword>fear</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Previous research indicates that serotonin (5-HT) enhances the acquisition of stress-induced changes in behavior; although it is unclear which serotonin receptors mediate this enhancement. 5-HT2 receptors are potential candidates because activation at these receptors is associated with increased fear and anxiety. In this study we investigated whether pharmacological treatments targeting 5-HT2A and 5-HT2C receptors modulated the acquisition and expression of conditioned defeat. Conditioned defeat is a social defeat model in Syrian hamsters (&lt;em&gt;Mesocricetus auratus&lt;/em&gt;) that is characterized by increased submissive and defensive behavior and a loss of territorial aggression following social defeat. In experiment 1, we injected the 5-HT2C receptor agonist mCPP (0.3, 1.0, or 3.0 mg/kg) or vehicle prior to social defeat and tested subjects for conditioned defeat behavior in a social interaction test 24 hours later. In experiment 2, subjects received a social defeat, and 24 hours later we injected mCPP (0.3, 1.0, or 3.0 mg/kg) or vehicle prior to a social interaction test. We found that injection of mCPP increased the expression, but not acquisition, of conditioned defeat. In experiment 3, we injected the 5-HT2A receptor antagonist MDL 11,939 (0.5 or 2.0 mg/kg) or vehicle prior to a social defeat and tested subjects for conditioned defeat behavior. In experiment 4, subjects received a social defeat, and 24 hours later we injected MDL 11,939 (0.5 or 2.0 mg/kg) or vehicle prior to a social interaction test. We found that injection of MDL 11,939 significantly decreased the acquisition, but not expression, of conditioned defeat. These data suggest that pharmacological activation of 5-HT2C receptors enhances the expression of conditioned defeat, while pharmacological blockade of 5-HT2A receptors impairs the acquisition of conditioned defeat. These data extend other studies indicating that 5-HT signaling at 5-HT2A receptors facilitate memories for aversive events and 5-HT signaling at 5-HT2C receptors enhance stress-induced anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/891</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2023&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>891</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2023</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-20T12:30:46-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2023/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1948772</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/891</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Matthew A. Cooper</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Todd Freeberg, Rebecca Prosser</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>