<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Science, Government, and Information: Finding and Communicating the Results of Research</title>
<publication-date>2011-02-25T12:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Information International Associates</institution>
<lname>Carroll</lname>
<fname>Bonnie</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2011/keynote/1</coverpage-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-06T05:57:56-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1025/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>1921759</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2011/keynote/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;h1&gt;Bonnie C. Carroll, Founder and President&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Information International  Associates&#39; (IIa) founder and president, Bonnie Carroll brings a cross-cutting  vision of information management, policy, and technology and a deep commitment  to providing excellent service to all of IIa&#39;s  clients and partners. Her leadership roles outside of the corporate structure  put her at the forefront of  strategic  futures for information management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2005, Carroll was  awarded the Department of Interior&#39;s Conservation Service Award for her role in  developing the National Biological Information Infrastructure and in other  biological informatics efforts. Carroll serves as senior advisor to the U.S.  Geological Survey under whose auspices the NBII was developed. She is the  planning lead for NBII&#39;s Southern Appalachian Information Node (SAIN) and  serves as the co-chair for the NBII&#39;s National Coalition. Working with the  Associate Chief Biologist for Information at USGS, Carroll coordinates the  Biodiversity and Ecosystems Work Group under the White House Science Office National Science and Technology Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infointl.com/about/management_bios/carroll.shtml&quot;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; for Ms. Carroll&#39;s complete biography.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2011-02-25T14:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Scripps Convergence Lab, 402 Communications Bldg.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-02-25T12:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2011-02-25T12:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>