<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>&quot;The Specular Moment&quot; in Goethe&#39;s &quot;Willkommen und Abschied&quot;: David Wellbery&#39;s Interpretation</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Poe</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
<mname>Franklin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>German Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In &quot;The Specular Moment&quot; David Wellbery highlights the structure of Goethe&#39;s poem &quot;Willkommen und Abschied.&quot; His major interpretation is twofold: Firstly, the particular use of the verb &quot;sehen&quot; creates a referential structure that is the true focus of the poem and Wellbery points to the fissure of the subject from its organic unity that is expressed through the use of &quot;sehen.&quot; Secondly, &quot;Willkommen und Abschied&quot; is a poem about art and art&#39;s ability to heal this rupture. Chapter one examines Wellbery&#39;s interpretation of &quot;Willkommen und Abschied&quot; in his two publications entitled &quot;The Specular Moment.&quot; Chapter two is an account of previous scholarship on &quot;Willkommen und Abschied&quot; and of Wellbery&#39;s relation to various theorists. Chapter three includes reactions to Wellbery&#39;s interpretation, including extensive feminist criticisms. Chapter four presents the text history of &quot;Willkommen und Abschied&quot; and discusses Wellbery&#39;s argument for choosing an unauthorized variant of the text that best suits his interpretation. The conclusion underscores the great contribution made by Wellbery&#39;s structuralist approach while acknowledging that he does not adequately reveal the Lacanian foundations of his argument, that his introduction of the &quot;Source,&quot; an essentially religious and extra-textual concept, contradicts his intent to depend solely on the text for his interpretation, and that his justification for using an unauthorized version of the text lacks credibility.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2671</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4066&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2671</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4066</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-22T12:14:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5508359</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2671</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David E. Lee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Peter Hoyng, Stefanie Ohnesorg, Hiram Maxim</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>German</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>