<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Microbial Community Changes in Methyl tert-Butyl Ether (MTBE)-Contaminated Soils</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Bo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil and Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study addresses two questions regarding the microbial community structure shift in MTBE-contaminated soils: Are known MTBE-degradaers/utilizers present in MTBE-contaminated soils? How is the microbial community affected by the addition of oxygen and the addition of cometabolic substrate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new quantitative fingerprinting method, Real-time-t-RFLP, was applied to study the effects of aeration and cosubstrate (toluene) on the microbial community structure of MTBE-contaminated soils. Real-time-t-RFLP, developed from two novel molecular methods (Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism (t-RFLP)), is capable of quantifying each ribotype in a microbial community. Results of this study showed that microbial community shifted dramatically after the addition of MTBE, oxygen, and toluene. Results indicated that there might be some known MTBE-degraders/utilizers present in the MTBE-contaminated soils. And cloning of the PCR products is needed to confirm their positive identifications in the future study.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2223</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3594&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2223</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3594</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T09:40:24-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4692450</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2223</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kung-Hui Chu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Chris D. Cox, Paul D. Frymier</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>