<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Grade A milk producers in Marshall County, Tennessee : Problem A: Characteristics of Marshall County Grade A milk producers and their farms : Problem B: Management practices of Marshall County Grade A milk producers : Problem C: Factors influencing dairy management practice adoption by Marshall County Grade A milk producers : three related special problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Nutt</lname>
<fname>T.</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statewide, dairying ranks about fourth in importance as a source of agricultural income in Tennessee (20: 1).* Annual receipts averaged about 85 million dollars for the five-year period 1959- 1963. There were about 426,000 dairy cows in Tennessee in 1963. Average milk production per cow in Tennessee that year was 4,700 pounds, while the average American cow produced 7,545 pounds. Research has suggested that production of less than 6,000 pounds per cow is unprofitable, and that cows producing below that amount should be considered for culling and possible replacement (13: 1). Marshall County is located in the south section of Middle Tennessee. It is bordered by Lincoln and Giles County to the south, Williamson and Rutherford County to the north, Bedford County to the east and Maury County to the west. The agriculture of the county is rather diversified, with crops and livestock making up 60 percent of the income. Dairying ranks first in importance, accounting for 40 percent of the agricultural inco me in 1960 as compared to the income from the sale of cattle and calves, which amounts to 23.3 percent (21 :3,4).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6052</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7691&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6052</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7691</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074429</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6052</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles L. Cleland, Don O Richardson, William M. Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1967-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>