<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dietary fat and not calcium supplementation or dairy product consumption is associated with changes in anthropometrics during a randomized, placebo-controlled energy-restriction trial</title>
<publication-date>2011-10-05T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of California - Davis</institution>
<lname>Smilowitz</lname>
<fname>Jennifer</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Idaho</institution>
<lname>Wiest</lname>
<fname>Michelle</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Purdue University</institution>
<lname>Teegarden</lname>
<fname>Dorothy</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>mzemel@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Zemel</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of California - Davis</institution>
<lname>German</lname>
<fname>Bruce</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Western Human Nutrition Research Center</institution>
<lname>Van Loan</lname>
<fname>Marta</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Insufficient calcium intake has been proposed to cause unbalanced energy partitioning leading to obesity. However, weight loss interventions including dietary calcium or dairy product consumption have not reported changes in lipid metabolism measured by the plasma lipidome.  &lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to determine the relationships between dairy product or supplemental calcium intake with changes in the plasma lipidome and body composition during energy restriction. A secondary objective of this study was to explore the relationships among calculated macronutrient composition of the energy restricted diet to changes in the plasma lipidome, and body composition during energy restriction. Overweight adults (n = 61) were randomized into one of three intervention groups including a deficit of 500kcal/d: 1) placebo; 2) 900 mg/d calcium supplement; and 3) 3-4 servings of dairy products/d plus a placebo supplement. Plasma fatty acid methyl esters of cholesterol ester, diacylglycerol, free fatty acids, lysophosphatidylcholine, phosphatidylcholine, phosphatidylethanolamine and triacylglycerol were quantified by capillary gas chromatography.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adjustments for energy and protein (g/d) intake, there was no significant effect of treatment on changes in weight, waist circumference or body composition. Plasma lipidome did not differ among dietary treatment groups. Stepwise regression identified correlations between reported intake of monounsaturated fat (% of energy) and changes in % lean mass (r = -0.44, &lt;em&gt;P &lt;/em&gt;&lt; 0.01) and % body fat (r = 0.48, &lt;em&gt;P &lt;/em&gt;&lt; 0.001). Polyunsaturated fat intake was associated with the % change in waist circumference (r = 0.44, P &lt; 0.01). Dietary saturated fat was not associated with any changes in anthropometrics or the plasma lipidome.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dairy product consumption or calcium supplementation during energy restriction over the course of 12 weeks did not affect plasma lipids. Independent of calcium and dairy product consumption, short-term energy restriction altered body composition. Reported dietary fat composition of energy restricted diets was associated with the degree of change in body composition in these overweight and obese individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/30</coverpage-url>
<label>30</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-10T14:37:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4302749</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/30</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Nutrition &amp; Metabolism 2011, 8:67 doi:10.1186/1743-7075-8-67</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-10-05T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>