<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Molecular Approaches in Attempts to Identify the Flagellin b-type Gene in Clone pKW52</title>
<publication-date>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kirkpatrick</lname>
<fname>Yolanda</fname>
<mname>F.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/em&gt; is an important pathogen for susceptible individuals particularly those immunocompromised due to the prolonged use of drugs, noscomial infections, burns, or cancer. In addition, &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;infections are high among cystic fibrosis patients. &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;presents a unique health concern and challenge for researchers due to its multiple virulence factors and the increasing number of patients developing &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;infections. &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;produces a variety of toxins and enzymes. The flagellum of &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;allows the bacterium to be motile. Motility has enabled the &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;bacterium to rapidly colonize the host&#39;s body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major structural component of the &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;flagellum is the protein, flagellin. &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;flagellin was categorized two major groups, designated &lt;em&gt;a &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;b &lt;/em&gt;via slide and tube agglutination assays and immunofluorescence technique. The &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; -type flagellin is composed of a major &lt;em&gt;a&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;antigenic component and one to three subantigen types, &lt;em&gt;a&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, a&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, a&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;a&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;The a-type flagellins have molecular weights of 45,000 to 52,000. The &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt;-type flagellin appear to be antigenically homogenous and have a molecular weight of 53,000. It is the centermost region of the flagellin that is antigenic and highly variable even within one species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oligonucleotides 1N and 1C, derived from the N-terminal and C-terminal nucleotide sequence of the cloned &lt;em&gt;P. aeruginosa &lt;/em&gt;(strain PAK) flagellin a-type gene, annealed to clone pKW52 (flagellin b-type) and an approximately 600bp fragment was amplified by PCR. The 600bp fragment was cloned in vector pCRII, and a partial nucleotide and amino acid sequence of the resulting clone pKWII was determined. Southern hybridization with radiolabeled probes was used in attempts to locate and identify the flagellin b-type gene in pKW52 and pKWII, respectively. The 1.7kb flagellin (a-type) gene probe did not hybridize to pKW52 and pKWII under low and high stringency hybridization conditions. In immunological studies of pKW52 flagellin antigen expression was detected in &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;cells harboring clone pKW52. Flagellin expression was not detected in &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;cells harboring clone pKWII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this thesis research suggest: 1) based on Southern hybridization experiments the sequence identity between the PAK 1.7kb flagellin a-type gene and clone pKW52 is estimated to be less than 90%, 2) the expression of flagellin b-type protein in &lt;em&gt;E. coli &lt;/em&gt;cells harboring pKW52 suggested that clone pKW52 may contain the flagellin b-type gene, 3) colony immunoblotting experiments with antiflagellin antibodies correlated with Southern hybridization results demonstrating that pKWII did not contain the flagellin b-type gene, and 4) PCR and Southern hybridization experiments are molecular biology techniques that may be used to locate the flagellin b-type in clone pKW52.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4330</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5752&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4330</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5752</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-14T12:44:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9687485</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4330</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas Montie</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Beth C. Mullin, David A. Bemis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Microbiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1996-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>