<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Measuring the impact of knowledge sharing on quality improvement initiatives</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dukes</lname>
<fname>Collins</fname>
<mname>Landon</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Industrial engineering</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The contributions of knowledge-based processes in quality initiatives, though unfamiliar, may have been realized by the improvement in the efficiency and effectiveness of knowledge workers (Malhotra 2000). Effective knowledge management (KM) can provide an organization with a competitive edge through effective management of product and process quality. It is possible that quality initiatives can be directed using knowledge sharing practices by focusing on common themes throughout the organization. Hence, it stands to reason that knowledge sharing can be facilitated by understanding those factors that are critical to the success of quality improvement initiatives and, conversely, that the impact of quality initiatives can be enhanced through effective knowledge sharing. The purpose of this study is to identify the critical organizational factors that contribute to the impact of knowledge sharing on quality improvement initiatives. It will focus on quality and on production managers&#39; perception of the way knowledge is being shared to improve results. It will examine the key independent variables that influence public and private organizations&#39; and overall manufacturing industries&#39; performances. These variables include customer focus, involvement of leaders and employees, and horizontal and vertical communication. A 30-item survey instrument provided the data on which the statistical analysis was based, validating the conclusions presented in this thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5726</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7348&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5726</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7348</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467486</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5726</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles H. Aikens</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>