<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Early Quail Hunting Season in Tennessee: Reasons and Results</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-24T14:23:09-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Tennessee Game and Fish Commission</institution>
<lname>McConnell</lname>
<fname>Chester</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Bobwhite quail (Colinus virginianus) wings were collected and aged from 1952 through 1970. The wing age data indicated that Tennessee&#39;s quail hunting season could begin 20 days earlier than the traditional Thanksgiving Day opening, providing a larger quail harvest. A study involving a season opening date of 5 November was conducted on Laurel Hill Wildlife Management Area resulting in an 18% increase in quail kill over previous years. Only 18% of the quail bagged on Laurel Hill were &lt;12 weeks of age, indicating that birds were sufficiently developed to provide good sport. Based on these earlier studies, the Commission opened the statewide quail season on 6 November 1971. A total of 5,270 quail wings were collected and aged during the early season. An estimated 180,000 additional quail were harvested as a result of the earlier season. Approximately 18 to 19% of the quail were &lt;12 weeks of age. Based on data resulting from a questionnaire, approximately 80% of the quail hunters furnished information favorable to the early season. Weather conditions during the early season were unseasonably warm, but 64% of the hunters indicated that warm weather was only a minor problem. Landowners (87%) indicated that unharvested crops were only a minor problem. Hunters (80%) indicated that young quail presented only minor problems. Sportsmen responding to the questionnaire averaged 8.1 hunting trips and bagged an average of 5.0 quail per trip in November.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol7/iss1/16</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>16</label>
<document-type>technical_session1</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1015</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-24T12:06:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10468811</context-key>
<withdrawn>2017-07-24</withdrawn>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol7/iss1/16</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>