<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Stewards of the mountains: A case study of the Lindquist Environmental Appalachian Fellowship, a faith-based environmental organization</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dawson</lname>
<fname>Lyndsay</fname>
<mname>Hughes</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Sociology</keyword>
<keyword>Mountaintop removal mining</keyword>
<keyword>Landscape protection</keyword>
<keyword>Environmentalism</keyword>
<keyword>Coal mines and mining</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The case study explores the concepts of the mental constructions of humans&#39; perceptions of their relationships to the environment. The ancients were intricately connected with the biophysical environment. Ancient religions such as Paganism and Pantheism produced environmental sentiments to revere and respect nature. As pantheistic and pagan ideologies transitioned to Judeo-Christianity, humans&#39; mental constructs of nature and their environmental attitudes substantially shifted. Environmental attitudes transitioned from a deep connection with the biophysical world to dominance, superiority, and hierarchy. To explore subjects&#39; perceptions of the relationship between humans and the environment, my primary research question investigates the influence of LEAF members&#39; religious values on their environmental attitudes. The secondary research question compares LEAF to the characteristics of grassroots environmental groups.Together, the two research questions provide a framework to examine the human mental constructions of the biophysical environment. The social movement and environmental concern literature are explored for concepts pertaining to the two research questions: 1) how does LEAF compare to grassroots environmental organizations? and 2) how do the religious values of LEAF members influence their environmental attitudes? The six characteristics of grassroots environmental movement organizations are used to analyze the first question. Data were gathered from interviews, participant observation, and document research. To analyze the second question, established concepts on value bases are engaged. The data collection for the second question was limited to interviews. Analyzing the responses to the first question, I found LEAF to be a new genus of organization as it exhibits characteristics beyond grassroots environmental organizations and mainstream organizations.Analyzing responses to the second question, I find that the members of LEAF care for the environment because of a religious value basis. Religion causes a theocentric paradigm influencing LEAF members&#39; perceptions of their relationship to the environment. That is, their faith creates reasons for environmental concern. LEAF members perceive humans&#39; relationship to the environment as damaged by the consequences of sin. To resolve the issue, the individuals become missionaries with the goal of ecological conversion to create a renewed relationship of environmental stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5755</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7377&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5755</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7377</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467520</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5755</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sherry Cable</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>