<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>How A Group of Elementary Deaf Students Interact with LEGO LOGO Activities: A Case Study</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McDaniel</lname>
<fname>Amy</fname>
<mname>Rebecca</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this case study was to discover how deaf students used problem solving skills as a group and to discern language expression they used during sessions with LEGO LOGO activities. This case study was conducted at Missouri School for the Deaf, a residential school in Fulton, Missouri with five deaf students from grades four and five.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five sessions of LEGO LOGO activities with the students were conducted and videotaped. During the sessions, the participants completed the activities with LOGO commands, LEGO constructions, LEGO LOGO, and related paper assignments. Transcriptions of selected segments of the videotapes were made and review of all data were conducted for analysis of the group work and language used. In the analysis several themes emerged: group work skills, language, time management, and gender issues. They were presented, described, and discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple suggestions were offered for changes in classroom instruction so that the students could gain skills necessary for improvement in academic skills. Changes for a repeat study were offered, as well as implications for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2300</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3881&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2300</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3881</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-18T13:09:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4739967</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2300</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edward L. Counts, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Ray, Kathleen Warden, Connie Hollingsworth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>