<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The spatial and temporal distribution of fishes in the Holston River system of North Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia</title>
<publication-date>1994-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hughes</lname>
<fname>Mark</fname>
<mname>Handly</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Holston River system</keyword>
<keyword>Holston River</keyword>
<keyword>fish</keyword>
<keyword>fish species</keyword>
<keyword>Cherokee Lake</keyword>
<keyword>South Holston Lake</keyword>
<keyword>Watauga Lake</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Over 1,000 fish collections from 1867 to 1994 resulted in the reporting of 134 species of fishes from the Holston River system. One-hundred thirty of those species are considered within as valid records. About 14% of those species were introduced into the system, leaving 112 indigenous species reported from the Holston River system. V Distribution of species throughout space and time is presented in tabular form in the appendices, based on the availability of collection records. Catalogued specimens are listed for 117 species. Perturbations of species assemblages due to mercury pollution and impoundment of the Holston River system arc considered. The preimpoundment and postimpoundment distribution of 134 species are covered individually. Collectively, assemblages are discussed in regard to changes induced in the watershed in the vicinity of three major impoundments to the river, Cherokee Lake, South Holston Lake, and Watauga Lake.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6123</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8111&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6123</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8111</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23359344</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6123</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Zoology</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1994-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>