<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Growing the Resistance: A Call to Action for Transactional Lawyers in the Era of Trump</title>
<publication-date>2019-01-18T11:20:46-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>Gowri.krishna@nyls.edu</email>
<institution>New York Law School</institution>
<lname>Krishna</lname>
<fname>Gowri</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Trump</keyword>
<keyword>Country</keyword>
<keyword>Economic</keyword>
<keyword>Justice</keyword>
<keyword>Politics</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil Rights and Discrimination</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Politics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;New Yorkers woke to a dreary, drizzly day on November 9, 2016. The weather matched the mood of many of the city’s inhabitants. Tears streamed down my face as I sat in the subway waiting for my stop. One by one, as my colleagues in the Community Development Project at the Urban Justice Center came into the office that morning, we shared expressions of shock, anger, fear, and sadness. We feared for what Trump’s election meant for our clients, for ourselves and our families, for our country, and for our world. In the days and weeks that followed, we coalesced around a resolve to continue our work in support of grassroots and community-based groups that organized for power within the city’s low-income immigrant communities and communities of color. Our model of partnership with these groups, wherein they take the lead in determining the priorities and goals for our work, would be especially critical in the times ahead.1 We knew we needed to keep doing what we had been doing. For me, that meant advising non-profit organizations and working with low-wage immigrant workers, many undocumented, to create safe, dignified jobs free from workplace abuses.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/rgsj/vol7/iss2/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1146&amp;amp;context=rgsj&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1146</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-12-23T10:36:52-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Race, Gender, &amp; Social Justice</publication-title>
<context-key>13528883</context-key>
<submission-path>rgsj/vol7/iss2/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-12-23T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Growing the Resistance</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>