<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Becoming a Creatrix: Women’s Religious Roles in W. B. Yeats and Olivia Shakespear</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>echilds@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Childs</lname>
<fname>Elaine</fname>
<mname>Kathyryn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Yeats</keyword>
<keyword>women</keyword>
<keyword>feminism</keyword>
<keyword>Olivia Shakespear</keyword>
<keyword>A Vision</keyword>
<keyword>The Winding Stair</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Literature in English, British Isles</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This project is the biography of a symbol: that of the holy woman motif in William Butler Yeats’s oeuvre. For most of Yeats’s writing life, beautiful women have a place of spurious privilege in his spiritual imagination because they have an intrinsic connection with the divine otherworld.  In chapters on Yeats’s beauty-worship in his long fin de siecle, Olivia Shakespear’s critique of that beauty-worship in her fiction, and the role of &lt;i&gt;A Vision&lt;/i&gt; in &lt;i&gt;The Winding Stair and Other Poems&lt;/i&gt;, I argue that Yeats revised the holy woman motif from a limited and limiting goddess or helpmeet role in his youthful work to a full-fledged religious meaning-maker--a Creatrix--in the last decade of his career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I include a study of Olivia Shakespear’s fiction in this project because each of her seven fictional works critiques what she saw as the male tendency from which Yeats’s symbology sprang: the tendency to feign worship of a beautiful woman while simultaneously limiting her ability to be a Creatrix.   However, the transformation that Yeats’s system underwent between the 1925 and 1937 versions of &lt;i&gt;A Vision&lt;/i&gt; enabled the poet to create a model of religious identity that does not require the erasure of the self and its human desires and therefore makes space in his pantheon for the Creatrix.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/682</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1752&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>682</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1752</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-12T06:10:33-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1270405</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/682</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lisi M. Schoenbach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nancy Goslee, Allen Dunn, Mark Hulsether</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>