<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Novel Method for Recovery of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 from Beef Surfaces</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Becher</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Adam</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A study was conducted to compare the efficiency of detection of &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 EDL 933 on external beef trim by commercial recovery systems based upon of the Microbial-Vac System (M-Vac) and excision sampling. &lt;em&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 EDL 933 was cultured in tryptic soy broth for 24 hr at 37°C and transferred for three consecutive days before diluting and spot inoculating onto a 684 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; piece of beef trim (10 CFU/684 cm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;). Beef trim was sampled with the M-Vac by passing the sampling head over the entire surface area in a vertical sampling pattern. The sampling head sprayed sterile buffer over the beef surface and instantly vacuumed the contents into a sample collection bottle. For the excision method, samples were cut from the beef trim using a coring knife. Sixty cores (3.8 cm diameter) were used per sample with one core directly inoculated by the &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7. Samples (M-Vac collection fluid and 60 excised cores) were held overnight at 4°C to simulate processing conditions, enriched in mEHEC broth at 42°C for up to 18 h, and confirmed positive using the BioControl Assurance Genetic Detection System (polymerase chain reaction based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of 75 inoculated beef trim surfaces, 96 (± 3.86) and 76% (± 3.86) of samples tested positive for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 by the M-Vac and excision methods, respectively. The ability of the M-Vac to detect &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; O157:H7 significantly better (P&lt;0.05) than excision, combined with the nondestructive nature of the MVac demonstrates that it is a suitable choice for sampling beef surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/365</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1398&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>365</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1398</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-15T11:38:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1145907</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/365</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>P. Michael Davidson, Doris H. D’Souza, Arnold M. Saxton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/BecherMatthewAdam.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>