<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Experiences with the Nutrtion Service of the Ohio Department of Health</title>
<publication-date>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kline</lname>
<fname>Angeline</fname>
<mname>Joyce</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report is based upon the 7 weeks&#39; field experiences obtained with the Ohio Department of Health, under the direction of the Chief of the Nutrition Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the supervised field work was to supplement the on-campus requirements of graduate study in Public Health Nutrition at the University of Tennessee, and to provide an understanding of the functions of a nutritionist in various official and non-official agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information was obtained on organization, facilities, policies, and services during a two-week orientation program of the state health department. The remaining 5 weeks demonstrated the activities and methods of operations of nutritionists.  It provided opportunities for participation in school health programs and institution consultations; and permitted observation of in-service education and well-child conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student gained an understanding of the functions of some official and non-official health agencies on the state, district, and local levels through the supervised field work.  An appreciation of team approach was gained as a result of observing the effectiveness of coordinated activities and &lt;em&gt;cooperation &lt;/em&gt;extended between the various disciplines to promote and improve programs.  The student is convinced that suggestions for changes should be feasible and &lt;em&gt;prevailing &lt;/em&gt;conditions must be accepted as a basis for improvement.  She has a clearer concept of the relationship of nutrition in the over-all public health program than she had prior to the field experiences, and believes she is now better equipped to contribute worthwhile services as a public health nutritionist.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3892</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5362&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3892</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5362</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-23T07:45:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9017500</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3892</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Beth Duncan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harold H. Walker, Drusilla Kent</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1960-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>