<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthetic studies on anti-cancer and anti-HIV compounds</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Headrick</lname>
<fname>Sarah</fname>
<mname>Autumn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The research discussed in this dissertation focuses on the synthesis and biological evaluation of two families of therapeutic agents. In 1999 a group of scientists at the National Cancer Institute reported that during a screening of their database they had found an active non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor. This compound (NSC-108406) was substantially more potent than the other inhibitors identified during their screening with an IC50 of 0.5 ± 0.3 μM. During a cell-based antiviral screen, it was found to provide an EC50 of 1.5 ± 1.0 μM. In an effort to increase the potency of the lead, a set of analogs of NSC-108406 was synthesized in our laboratories, providing a compound with an EC50 of 0.036 μM. Hydramycin is a naturally occurring pluramycinone that is a potent antimicrobial and antitumor agent and whose biological activity has created an interest in its synthesis. Our work began with a model study that established a strategy by which the pyranone system and associated functionality could be realized. The route makes use of a novel alkyne and a fluoride-induced ring closure that provided a molecule consisting of a chromenone with the essential moieties analogous to those of hydramycin. The protocol was applied to a compound containing the hydramycin anthraquinone system via a 2-formyl-1- hydroxy anthraquinone that was coupled with an alkyne.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5137</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6681&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5137</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6681</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-11T12:24:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13799724</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5137</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Baker</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>