<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Teachers&#39; Perceptions and Concerns of Year-Round Education in Tennessee High School Agriculture Programs</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Blackwell</lname>
<fname>Gary</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to focus on the emergence of year-round education and its possible effects on agricultural education programs throughout the state of Tennessee. The study collected perceptions of teachers who currently teach in a Tennessee high school agriculture program regarding the implementation of a year-round program at their school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey was designed and sent to all 284 teachers identified in the 2002-2003 Tennessee Agriculture teacher directory. Findings were based upon a 69% response rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Findings &lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The total number of survey respondents was 197; of these 93 .1 % taught in schools operating on a traditional schedule, while 6.9% taught in schools that operate on a year-round schedule.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Of the 197 respondents 73.9% stated no schedule change was being proposed by their respective school district, 25% are proposing a change from a traditional schedule to a year-round schedule, and 1.1 % stated their school system is proposing a change from a year-round to a traditional schedule.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The majority (59.1 %) of the agriculture education instructors at schools on traditional schedules showed some level of concern regarding the implementation of a year-round schedule at their school.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Of the respondents on a traditional schedule the largest percentage (38.7%) showed some level of agreement with the statement: &#39;If a year-round schedule is implemented at my school my instructional methods would not change.&#39; However, the largest number (41.7%) of teachers on a year-round schedule were neutral regarding this statement.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The largest percentage of respondents on a traditional schedule felt that both teacher (43.4%) and student burnout (45.7%) would increase following the implementation of a year-round schedule. The largest number (50%) of teachers on a year-round schedule felt that teacher burnout would decrease even though the respondents were evenly divided regarding increased/decreased student burnout. vi&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The majority (59.8%) of respondents on a traditional schedule felt that student discipline problems would remain the same following the implementation of a year-round schedule. The largest percentage of respondents (41.7%) on a year-round schedule felt that discipline problems would increase.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Of the teachers on a traditional schedule 39.5% felt that the time students spend on S.A.E.&#39;s would decrease while 39% were neutral. The majority of the respondents on a year-round schedule were neutral.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The majority (68.2%) of respondents on a traditional schedule as well as those on a year-round schedule, felt that it would be more difficult to schedule events such as State Convention and FF A Camp.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Forty-nine (26.1 % ) teachers stated their schools are proposing schedule changes indicating that schedule changes may be forthcoming for some Tennessee high school agriculture programs.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The majority of teachers on a traditional schedule are concerned about the implementation of a year-round schedule at their school while the majority of teachers on a year-round schedule are not concerned. This possibly makes the concerns of teachers on a traditional schedule unwarranted and influenced by inexperience with the schedule itself.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;There are differing &quot;biggest concerns&quot; regarding the implementation of a year-round schedule between the two statistical groups. This raises the question, &quot;Are changes in curriculum and instruction the biggest concern of teachers beginning to teach on a year-round schedule?&quot;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The largest number of teachers on a traditional schedule feel that teacher burnout would increase following the implementation of a year-round schedule at the school where they currently teach. However, the largest number of teachers on a year-round schedule feel that teacher burnout would decrease reaffirming the data given from Ballinger, Kirschenbaum, and Poimbeauf ( 1987).&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The largest number of respondents currently on a year-round schedule stated that student discipline problems would increase, contradicting the data collected from the Oxnard School District (Oxnard, 1992).&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4928</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6368&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4928</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6368</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-01-16T06:35:33-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>11367762</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4928</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Randol G. Waters</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Norma Mertz, Roy Lessly</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>