<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Hard target performance testing of non-lead, frangible ammunition</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Oglesby</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
<mname>Samuel</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The health and environmental hazards of firing lead-containing small arms ammunition for training, sporting, law enforcement, and military purposes are well known. These dangers have prompted the development and evaluation of alternative ammunition that eliminates the undesirable aspects of lead. Any new ammunition, however, must be fully functional and provide characteristics similar to those of &quot;standard issue&quot; analogs to allow personnel to maintain the highest degree of proficiency in training, and to meet the many needs of protective forces, law enforcement, and the military. Numerous commercial, non-lead products are available, with many having the added feature of being &quot;frangible&quot;, easily fragmenting upon impact with a hard surface thus minimizing collateral damage and ricochet during use. Although most frangible, non-lead ammunition has been designed for &#39;&#39;training,&quot; there is considerable interest in the service use of this new class of ammunition. The utilization of frangible ammunition in sensitive indoor facilities has many benefits, however, level of frangibility varies greatly thus the selection of the appropriate product can be challenging. The penetration and ricochet behavior of frangible ammunition has been and continues to be evaluated by many organizations. Difficulties arise in the sharing of results, for each user has very specific requirements, differing needs, and differing types of targets. The purpose of this exploratory study is to summarize the examination of the impact behavior of non-lead, frangible ammunition when fired against hard targets. A variety of laboratory tests were considered in an attempt to establish a standard for assessing ammunition performance characteristics upon impacting hard targets. Current protocols for evaluating penetration and frangibility, including those employed by Department of Defense and other organizations were reviewed. New test protocols were developed to examine, both damage to the target, in addition to the nature of the impact process including fragment size and energy. Targets of interest included, but were not limited to steel, concrete, and other metal and masonry products. The results can help define &#39;&#39;frangibility,&quot; and assist the user in the selection of the proper product for a given scenario.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5273</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6681&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5273</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6681</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847164</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5273</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Tyler Kress</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>