<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Validation of the Cosmed Fitmate for predicting maximal oxygen consumption</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Jung</fname>
<mname>Min</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to assess the validity of the Cosmed Fitmate (FM) in predicting maximal oxygen consumption (VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;), compared to the Douglas bag (DB) method. In addition, this study examined whether measuring submaximal VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, rather than predicting it, can improve upon the prediction of VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;. Thirty-two males and sixteen females (Mean ± SD: age 31 ± 10 yr, body mass 72.9 ± 13.0 kg, height 1.75 ± 0.09 m, BMI 23.4 ± 3 kg·m&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;) volunteered to participate in the study. Each participant completed a submaximal and a maximal treadmill test using the Bruce protocol on two separate occasions. During the submaximal test, VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; was predicted using the FM, while during the maximal test VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; was measured using the DB method. The Cosmed Fitmate predicts VO2max by extrapolating the linear regression relating heart rate and measured VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; to age-predicted maximum heart rate (HR = 220-age). This study also examined the validity of predicting VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; by using the ACSM metabolic equations to estimate submaximal VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; values from the FM, the DB method, and ACSM prediction equations were analyzed using repeated measures ANOVA and linear regression analyses. The level of significance was set at P &lt; 0.05 for all statistical analyses. There was no significant difference between VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; predicted by the FM (45.6 ml·kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, SD 8.8) and measured by the DB method (46.5 ml·kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, SD 8.8) (p = 0.152). The results of this study showed that a strong positive correlation (r = 0.897) existed between VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; predicted by the FM and VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; measured by the DB method, with a standard error of the estimate (SEE) = 3.97 ml·kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. There was a significant difference in VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; predicted by the ACSM metabolic equations (51.1 ml·kg-1·min-1, SD 7.98) and VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt; measured by the DB method (p = 0.01). The correlation between these variables was r = 0.758 (SEE = 5.26 ml·kg&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;·min&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;). These findings suggest that the Fitmate is a small, portable, and easy-to-use metabolic system that provides reasonably good estimates of VO&lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;, and that measuring submaximal VO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, rather than predicting it from the ACSM metabolic equations, improves the prediction of &lt;sub&gt;2max&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/462</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1498&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>462</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1498</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-17T13:29:06-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1151612</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/462</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dixie L. Thompson, Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008MastersTheses/LeeJungMin.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>