<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Kinesthetic Haptics Sensing and Discovery with Bilateral Teleoperation Systems</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>tqiu@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Qiu</lname>
<fname>Tian</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Teleoperation</keyword>
<keyword>Haptics</keyword>
<keyword>Kinesthetic</keyword>
<keyword>Transparency</keyword>
<keyword>Control</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Acoustics, Dynamics, and Controls</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the mechanical engineering field of robotics, bilateral teleoperation is a classic but still increasing research topic. In bilateral teleoperation, a human operator moves the master manipulator, and a slave manipulator is controlled to follow the motion of the master in a remote, potentially hostile environment. This dissertation focuses on kinesthetic perception analysis in teleoperation systems. Design of the controllers of the systems is studied as the influential factor of this issue. The controllers that can provide different force tracking capability are compared using the same experimental protocol. A 6 DOF teleoperation system is configured as the system testbed. An innovative master manipulator is developed and a 7 DOF redundant manipulator is used as the slave robot. A singularity avoidance inverse kinematics algorithm is developed to resolve the redundancy of the slave manipulator. An experimental protocol is addressed and three dynamics attributes related to kineshtetic feedback are investigated: weight, center of gravity and inertia. The results support our hypothesis: the controller that can bring a better force feedback can improve the performance in the experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2722</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3911&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2722</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3911</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-11-21T13:56:11-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4845130</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2722</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>William R. Hamel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dongjun Lee, Seddik Djouadi, Xiaopeng Zhao, Joseph Boulet</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>