<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Systematics, Distribution, and Biology of Fishes Currently Allocated to &lt;em&gt;Erimystax&lt;/em&gt; (Jordan), a Subgenus of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis&lt;/em&gt; (Cyprinidae)</title>
<publication-date>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Harris</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
<mname>Lowrey</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Intra- and interspecific variation of species of the subgenus Erimystax, genus &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis, &lt;/em&gt;are analyzed using multivariate statistical techniques. Diagnoses, descriptions, figures, supporting tables, and distribution maps are provided to facilitate identification of the subgenus and component species. Results of multivariate analyses support the elevation of the Ozark subspecies of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis dissimilis &lt;/em&gt;to specific standing as &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis i. insignis&lt;/em&gt; distributed in the lower Tennessee and Cumberland river drainages and &lt;em&gt;H. insignis eristigma &lt;/em&gt;found in eastern tributaries of the upper Tennessee River drainage. Populations interpreted as intergrades occur in the Clinch, Powell, and Holston rivers. Two subspecies of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis x-punctata&lt;/em&gt; are recognized with &lt;em&gt;H. x. x-punctata&lt;/em&gt; occurring in the upper Mississippi, Missouri, Neosho, and Ouachita river drainages and &lt;em&gt;H. x-punctata trautmani&lt;/em&gt; inhabiting the Ohio, Thames, and White (Arkansas and Missouri) river drainages. Missouri River drainage populations are possible intergrades, pending further analysis. Two species groups are recognized within &lt;em&gt;Erimystax.&lt;/em&gt; These are the &lt;em&gt;dissimilus &lt;/em&gt;species group, composed of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis dissimilis, H. harryi, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. insignis,&lt;/em&gt;and the &lt;em&gt;x-punctata&lt;/em&gt; species group, composed of &lt;em&gt;H. x-punctata&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;H.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;cahni.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phylogenetic comparisons among the subgenus &lt;em&gt;Erimystax, Hybopsis monacha, &lt;/em&gt;and subgenus &lt;em&gt;Cyprinella&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt; Notropis&lt;/em&gt; reveal &lt;em&gt;H. monacha&lt;/em&gt; is an enigmatic species sharing characters with both subgenera. The exact phylogenetic placement of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis monacha&lt;/em&gt; is not known, but it is not considered a member of &lt;em&gt;Erimystax.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life history studies of &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis x-punctata, H. harryi, H. dissimilis, &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;H. insignis&lt;/em&gt; were conducted and the findings are presented. Dietary analyses show &lt;em&gt;H. harryi&lt;/em&gt; feeds primarily on periphytic detrital aggregate (PDA) and algae, whereas, the other species are more omnivorous and feed or relatively equal amounts of benthic invertebrates and PDA. &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis harryi&lt;/em&gt; is the only &lt;em&gt;Erimystax&lt;/em&gt; with a coiled gut configuration. The remaining species have a simple s-shape gut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All species spawn over clean, gravel substrate during a three to four week period in April or May. Spawning may be initiated by a combination of rising water temperature and increased stream discharge. Males grow faster during the first 12 months of live but females are larger by the end of the second year. Females reach a larger maximum size and generally have higher survival rates than males. Maximum age recorded for each species is: &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis harryi&lt;/em&gt;--42 months; &lt;em&gt;H. x-punctata&lt;/em&gt;--32 months; &lt;em&gt;H. insignis&lt;/em&gt;--30 months; and &lt;em&gt;H. dissimilis&lt;/em&gt;--approximately 30 months.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2174</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3616&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2174</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3616</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-07T08:23:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4675488</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2174</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Etnier</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>A. C. Echternacht, D. L. Bunting, P. W. Parmalee</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1986-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>