<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis transmission from human to canine</title>
<publication-date>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Erwin</lname>
<fname>P</fname>
<mname>C</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Bemis</lname>
<fname>D</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dmawby@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mawby</lname>
<fname>Dianne</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>McCombs</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
<mname>B</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Sheeler</lname>
<fname>L</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Himelright</lname>
<fname>I</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Halford</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Diem</lname>
<fname>L</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Metchock</lname>
<fname>B</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>T</fname>
<mname>F</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Schilling</lname>
<fname>M</fname>
<mname>G</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Thomsen</lname>
<fname>B</fname>
<mname>V</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Small or Companion Animal Medicine</discipline>
<discipline>Veterinary Medicine</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A 71-year-old woman from Tennessee, USA with a 3-week history of a productive, nonbloody cough was evaluated. Chest radiograph showed infiltrates and atelectasis in the upper lobe of the right lung. A tuberculosis (TB) skin test resulted in a 14-mm area of induration. Sputum stained positive for acid-fast bacilli (AFB) and was positive for Mycobacterium tuberculosis by DNA probe and culture. Treatment was initiated with isoniazid, rifampicin, and pyrazinamide. After 14 days of daily, directly observed therapy, the patient complained of nausea, vomiting and diarrhoea. Treatment adjustments were made, and therapy was completed 11 months later with complete recovery. Six months after the patient&#39;s TB diagnosis, she took her three and a half-year-old male Yorkshire Terrier to a veterinary clinic with cough, weight loss, and vomiting of several months&#39; duration. Initial sputum sample was negative on AFB staining. Eight days after discharge from a referral veterinary teaching hospital with a presumptive diagnosis of TB, the dog was euthanized due to urethral obstruction. Liver and tracheobronchial lymph node specimens collected at necropsy were positive for M. tuberculosis complex by polymerase chain reaction. The M. tuberculosis isolates from the dog and its owner had an indistinguishable 10-band pattern by IS6110-based restriction fragment length polymorphism genotyping.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>2258</fpage>
<lpage>2259</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_smalpubs/8</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;amp;context=utk_smalpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>8</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1007</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-11-15T09:02:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Small Animal Clinical Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2117266</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_smalpubs/8</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Emerging Infectious Diseases</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>