<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Terpene Synthase Genes Originated from Bacteria through Horizontal Gene Transfer Contribute to Terpenoid Diversity in Fungi</title>
<publication-date>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jia</lname>
<fname>Qidong</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Xinlu</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology, Germany</institution>
<lname>Köllner</lname>
<fname>Tobias</fname>
<mname>G</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Bonn, Germany</institution>
<lname>Rinkel</lname>
<fname>Jan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou, China</institution>
<lname>Fu</lname>
<fname>Jianyu</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</institution>
<lname>Labbé</lname>
<fname>Jessy</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Xiong</lname>
<fname>Wangdan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Bonn, Germany</institution>
<lname>Dickschat</lname>
<fname>Jeroen</fname>
<mname>S</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology, Germany</institution>
<lname>Gershenzon</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Feng</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Fungi are successful eukaryotes of wide distribution. They are known as rich producers of secondary metabolites, especially terpenoids, which are important for fungi-environment interactions. Horizontal gene transfer (HGT) is an important mechanism contributing to genetic innovation of fungi. However, it remains unclear whether HGT has played a role in creating the enormous chemical diversity of fungal terpenoids. Here we report that fungi have acquired terpene synthase genes (&lt;em&gt;TPSs&lt;/em&gt;), which encode pivotal enzymes for terpenoid biosynthesis, from bacteria through HGT. Phylogenetic analysis placed the majority of fungal and bacterial &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes from diverse taxa into two clades, indicating ancient divergence. Nested in the bacterial &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; clade is a number of fungal &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes that are inferred as the outcome of HGT. These include a monophyletic clade of nine fungal &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes, designated as &lt;em&gt;BTPSL&lt;/em&gt; for bacterial TPS-like genes, from eight species of related entomopathogenic fungi, including seven &lt;em&gt;TPSs&lt;/em&gt; from six species in the genus &lt;em&gt;Metarhizium&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;In vitro&lt;/em&gt; enzyme assays demonstrate that all seven &lt;em&gt;BTPSL&lt;/em&gt; genes from the genus &lt;em&gt;Metarhizium&lt;/em&gt; encode active enzymes with sesquiterpene synthase activities of two general product profiles. By analyzing the catalytic activity of two resurrected ancestral BTPSLs and one closely related bacterial TPS, the trajectory of functional evolution of BTPSLs after HGT from bacteria to fungi and functional divergence within &lt;em&gt;Metarhizium&lt;/em&gt; could be traced. Using &lt;em&gt;M. brunneum&lt;/em&gt; as a model species, both BTPSLs and typical fungal TPSs were demonstrated to be involved in the &lt;em&gt;in vivo&lt;/em&gt; production of terpenoids, illustrating the general importance of HGT of &lt;em&gt;TPS&lt;/em&gt; genes from bacteria as a mechanism contributing to terpenoid diversity in fungi.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_planpubs/99</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1099&amp;amp;context=utk_planpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>99</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1099</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-08-29T09:05:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Plant Sciences Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15229994</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_planpubs/99</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-45532-1</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Scientific Reports</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>