<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PAH biodegradative genotypes in Lake Erie sediments:  Evidence for broad geographical distribution of pyrene-degrading Mycobacteria</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>DeBruyn</lname>
<fname>J.M.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Mead</lname>
<fname>T.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wilhelm</lname>
<fname>S.W.</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Sayler</lname>
<fname>G.S.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Despite a long history of anthropogenic contamination of Lake Erie sediments, little work has been done to understand the potential for PAH biodegradation by indigenous microbial communities. Pyrene-degrading &lt;em&gt;Mycobacterium&lt;/em&gt; are prevalent in many polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH)-contaminated freshwater sediments, and are of interest for their ability to degrade environmentally recalcitrant high molecular weight PAHs. This work tested the hypothesis that pyrene-degrading mycobacteria are prevalent in Lake Erie; an additional aim was to gain a baseline picture of the sediment microbial communities through sequencing a 16S rDNA clone library. Biodegradation potential of Lake Erie &lt;em&gt;Mycobacterium&lt;/em&gt; populations was assessed through quantification of pyrene dioxygenase genes (&lt;em&gt;nidA&lt;/em&gt;) and mycobacteria 16S rDNA genes using quantitative real time PCR. &lt;em&gt;nidA&lt;/em&gt; was detected at all seven sampling sites across Lake Erie, with abundances ranging from 2.09 to 70.4 × 106 copies per gram sediment, with highest abundances at the most PAH-contaminated site (Cleveland Harbor). This is in contrast to naphthalene dioxygenase genes commonly used as biomarkers of PAH degradation: &lt;em&gt;nahAc&lt;/em&gt; (from γ-proteobacteria) was not detected anywhere, and &lt;em&gt;nagAc&lt;/em&gt; (from β-proteobacteria) was detected only in Cleveland Harbor, despite dominance by proteobacteria in Lake Erie sediment 16S rDNA clone libraries (&gt;50% of clones). The prevalence of &lt;em&gt;Mycobacterium nidA&lt;/em&gt; genotypes corroborated previous studies indicating that PAH-degrading &lt;em&gt;mycobacteria&lt;/em&gt; have a cosmopolitan distribution and suggests they play an important but overlooked role in natural attenuation and cycling of PAHs in Lake Erie.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/9</coverpage-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1011</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-28T11:48:35-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1584168</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es803348g</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>