<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Integrating neuroscience knowledge into social work education: A case-based approach</title>
<publication-date>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Egan</lname>
<fname>Marcia</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Combs-Orme</lname>
<fname>Terri</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Neely-Barnes</lname>
<fname>Susan</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;New knowledge from the rapidly growing field of neuroscience has  important implications for our understanding of human behavior in the  social environment, yet little of this knowledge has made its way into  social work education. This article presents a model for integrating  neuroscience into instruction on human development, the bio psychosocial  model, psychopathology, and social work theory. Key concepts such as  critical periods of brain development, neural plasticity, memory,  cognition, and the impact of stress and trauma are discussed. Case  studies and discussion questions are used to demonstrate the integration  of neuroscience knowledge into social work education. We argue that  teaching neuroscience will enhance students’ critical thinking skills  and better prepare them for direct and policy practice.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_socipubs/20</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1019&amp;amp;context=utk_socipubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>20</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1019</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-31T08:09:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Social Work Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>2039707</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_socipubs/20</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Marcia Egan, Terri Combs-Orme, and Susan L. Neely-Barnes. &quot;Integrating neuroscience knowledge into social work education: A case-based approach&quot; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Social Work Education&lt;/em&gt; 47.2 (2011): 269-282.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>