<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Scholarly productivity, publication outlets and article themes of faculty in APA-accredited school psychology programs : 1995-1999</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Carper</lname>
<fname>Robin</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study examined the scholarly productivity of faculty in school psychology programs accredited by the American Psychological Association (APA) from 1995-1999. In addition, the author identified the major journals in which faculty published their work and the article themes for the most productive programs. Faculty members’ productivity ratings were based on journal article abstracts identified in the PsycINFO database. Productivity ratings were computed primarily via an authorship credit formula in which first authors receive the greatest amount of credit and succeeding authors earn decreasing amounts of credit for publications. However, the actual number of publications also was computed for comparison with the authorship credit ratings. The analysis of the principal journal outlets for school psychology faculty profiled the primary journals in which school psychology faculty published their work. Data were divided into two journal sets: primary and secondary. The primary set included only the major school psychology journals and the secondary set included journals outside of the major school psychology journals.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6212</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8164&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6212</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8164</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450303</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6212</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert Williams</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William Calhoun, Tom George, Chris Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>