<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Legislative Prerogative or Judicial Fiat: Mandating Electronic Recording of Stationhouse Interrogations in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2014-02-19T14:05:34-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Middle Tennessee State University</institution>
<lname>Selva</lname>
<fname>Lance</fname>
<mname>H</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Middle Tennessee State University</institution>
<lname>Shulman</lname>
<fname>William</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The pendulum of credibility weighs heavily against a defendant who challenges the admissibility of his confession. If admitted, it will prove a virtual guarantee of conviction, as it is the most &quot;potent of weapons for the prosecution.&quot;&#39; Although prosecutors lament the layers of constitutional rights in place to protect a defendant against coercive interrogation methods, most challenges to admissibility will come down to the detective&#39;s word against that of the defendant. Absent a recording, the court will be called upon to decipher events that took place in communicado and will be consigned to speculate about what actually took place, weighing the relative credibility of witnesses. Where the court is left to speculate about what actually transpired, it is no secret that the defendant rarely prevails when a confession is in evidence. The entire set of rules governing the relationship between the suspect and interrogators is built on a house of cards whose major weakness resides in the premise that a court can accurately determine what transpired during the interrogation process.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/tjlp/vol1/iss3/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;amp;context=tjlp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1015</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-19T09:12:27-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Tennessee Journal of Law and Policy</publication-title>
<context-key>5160627</context-key>
<submission-path>tjlp/vol1/iss3/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Saul M. Kassin &amp; Holly Sukel, Coerced Confessions and the
Jury: An Experimental Test of the &quot;Harmless Error&quot; Rule, 21
L. &amp; HUM. BEHAV. 27 (1997); see also Gail Johnson, False
Confessions and Fundamental Fairness: The Need for
Electronic Recording of Custodial Interrogations, 6 B.U.
PUB. INT. L. J. 719, 741-43 (1997); Paul G. Cassell &amp; Bret S.
Hayman, Police Interrogation in the 1990s: An Empirical
Study of the Effects of Miranda, 43 UCLA L. REV. 839, 906-
07 (1996).</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Legislative Prerogative</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>