<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterizing the 3D structure and dynamics of chromosomes and proteins in a common contact matrix framework</title>
<publication-date>2018-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lindsay</lname>
<fname>Richard</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>cpham3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pham</lname>
<fname>Bill</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>tshen@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Shen</lname>
<fname>Tongye</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>rmccord@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McCord</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>Patton</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Computational Methods</keyword>
<keyword>Chromatin and Epigenetics</keyword>
<keyword>Genomics</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Conformational ensembles of biopolymers, whether proteins or chromosomes, can be described us- ing contact matrices. Principal component analysis (PCA) on the contact data has been used to in- terrogate both protein and chromosome structures and/or dynamics. However, as these fields have de- veloped separately, variants of PCA have emerged. Previously, a variant we hereby term Implicit-PCA (I- PCA) has been applied to chromosome contact ma- trices and revealed the spatial segregation of active and inactive chromatin. Separately, Explicit-PCA (E- PCA) has previously been applied to proteins and characterized their correlated structure fluctuations. Here, we swapped analysis methods (I-PCA and E- PCA), applying each to a different biopolymer type (chromosome or protein) than the one for which they were initially developed. We find that applying E-PCA to chromosome distance matrices derived from mi- croscopy data can reveal the dominant motion (con- certed fluctuation) of these chromosomes. Further, by applying E-PCA to Hi-C data across the human blood cell lineage, we isolated the aspects of chromo- some structure that most strongly differentiate cell types. Conversely, when we applied I-PCA to simula- tion snapshots of proteins, the major component re- ported the consensus features of the structure, mak- ing this a promising approach for future analysis of semi-structured proteins.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biocpubs/97</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1107&amp;amp;context=utk_biocpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>97</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1107</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-07-21T12:54:38-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biochemistry, Cellular and Molecular Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>14966483</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biocpubs/97</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Richard J Lindsay, Bill Pham, Tongye Shen, Rachel Patton McCord, Characterizing the 3D structure and dynamics of chromosomes and proteins in a common contact matrix framework, Nucleic Acids Research, Volume 46, Issue 16, 19 September 2018, Pages 8143–8152, https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky604</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1093/nar/gky604</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2018-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Nucleic Acids Research</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Tongye_gky604_supplemental_figures.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>Tongye_gky604_supplemental_figures.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1107&amp;amp;context=utk_biocpubs&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/x-empty</mime-type>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>