<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Understanding Mechanical and Fatigue Behavior of a Wrought Magnesium Alloy using In-situ Neutron and Synchrotron X-ray Diffraction</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>wwu7@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wu</lname>
<fname>Wei</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Mg alloys; fatigue; neutron diffraction; synchrotron X-ray diffraction; deformation mechanism; twinning</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Metallurgy</discipline>
<discipline>Structural Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Magnesium (Mg) alloys have received great attentions in the past several decades, due to their unique properties of low density, high strength-to-weight ratio, and high specific stiffness. Previous work on fatigue behavior of Mg alloys typically relies on ex situ microstructural characterization and crack-growth monitoring with replica techniques. The &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; challenge is thus the lack of an &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt;, non-destructive measurement on microstructural length scales, which prevents us from linking the stress analyses (top-down point of view) to the failure mechanisms on inter- and intra-granular scales (bottom-up point of view). A unique opportunity that resolves many of these difficulties and challenges is provided by in situ neutron and synchrotron X-ray diffraction methods, which provide the unprecedented information on inter- and intra-granular deformation characteristics at different length scales from mm to sub-μm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;primary objective&lt;/em&gt; aims to identify deformation mechanisms during strain-path changes, low-cycle fatigue, and fatigue crack growth tests of Mg alloys from in-situ diffraction and micromechanical studies. We took advantage of the state-of-art VULCAN engineering materials diffractometer of Spallation Neutron Source (SNS), Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) to achieve the real in-situ neutron diffraction measurement. Instead of the “traditional” step loading method, the neutron diffraction measurements were performed under continuous loading condition at a slow loading rate, which provided the detailed information related to the plastic deformation dynamics of the wrought magnesium alloy. Full-field mapping around fatigue cracks can be performed at ISIS facility, Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, UK. The multiscale nature of deformation near the fatigue crack tip permits a scale-bridging modeling method. Moreover, the twinning and detwinning behavior in an individual grain inside a polycrystalline wrought Mg alloy has been investigated using sub-micron level synchrotron X-ray microbeam diffraction at 34ID-E, Advanced Photon Source (APS), Argonne National Laboratory (ANL), USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critical issues&lt;/em&gt; lie on the deformation dynamics, twinning-detwinning behavior at the grain level, and fatigue crack growth mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;principal outcome&lt;/em&gt; of this research will be the improved microstructural level understanding on deformation dynamics and fatigue mechanisms with which materials scientists can improve the practical applications of Mg alloys.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2629</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3701&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2629</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3701</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-09T14:38:31-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/3701/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4690332</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2629</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter K. Liaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ke An, Yanfei Gao, John D. Landes</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>