<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Sports nutrition practices of selected elite NCAA Division I athletic departments</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lehmann</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate the sports nutrition practices of NCAA Division I elite-level college athletic departments. More specifically, this study examined the perceptions of Registered Dietitians (RDs ), Strength and Conditioning Coaches (SCCs), and Athletic Trainers (ATCs) on the following considerations of sports nutrition services: a) qualifications, classifications, and attributes of RDs, b) roles and responsibilities of RDs, c) factors influencing the employment of RDs, d) resources available to implement sports nutrition services, and e) the nutrition needs of student athletes and benefits of nutrition for student-athletes. Data were collected through a two part survey consisting of open and closed-ended questions the respondent being the principal provider of sports nutrition services at each athletic department. Participants of the study were determined by athletic ranking in football and post season bowl game appearances. Seventy-two universities in six conferences: SEC, Big 12, Big 10, ACC, PAC 10, and Big East as well as three teams placing in the top 25 AP Poll for 2002 were included in the present study. From this sample, 19 Division I athletic departments. confirmed employment of an RD. While this research showed that RDs are increasingly being utilized by athletic departments to provide sports nutrition services, a comparison of current implementations of RD services to the advances documented in sports nutrition and dietetics literature in the dietetics indicated abundant potential for increased utilization of RDs by college athletic departments&#39;. RDs must participate in evidence-based research to develop benchmarks or standards of best practice validating RDs as the authority of sports nutrition services for athletes. In this way, RDs in college athletic departments can document the benefits they provide in the development of student-athletes. Evidence-based research documents the benefits RDs provide to college athletic department, and shows the usefulness of RDs for college athletic departments. It can be used to increase the demand for RDs in college athletics and validate their employment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5254</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6662&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5254</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6662</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847119</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5254</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Terese Stratta</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>