<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>In Person, Online and In Between: Finding Balance as Instruction Increases</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>asandell@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sandelli</lname>
<fname>Anna</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>information literacy</keyword>
<keyword>online instruction</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;One‐shot sessions. Larger‐scale auditorium assemblies. An assignment‐embedded LibGuide. Over the span of three years, library instruction for Public Speaking, one of our university’s largest enrollment general education courses, has shifted from the classroom to the computer screen. This shift has presented new opportunities for assessment while promoting scalability and flexibility. At the same time, it has limited opportunities for enrolled students to see librarians as partners in, and resources for, their research process. This session will highlight learnings involved in transitioning to an online information literacy approach and librarians’ exploration of supplementary offerings to support both students and instructors. In addition to discussing takeaways applicable to a variety of instructional settings, participants will be encouraged to join in an ongoing conversation about finding equilibrium between fostering student connections and providing scalable, sustainable instruction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_libfac/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_libfac&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-05-26T08:49:01-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>UT Libraries Faculty: Other Publications and Presentations</publication-title>
<context-key>8653685</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_libfac/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Sandelli, A. “In person, online and in-between: Finding balance as instruction increases.” Presentation at The Innovative Library Classroom conference. Radford, VA, May 12, 2016.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>The Innovative Library Classroom</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>CMST_TILC_Handout_Sandelli.pdf</archive-name>
<upload-name>CMST_TILC_Handout_Sandelli.pdf</upload-name>
<url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_libfac&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/pdf</mime-type>
<description>TILC_2016_Handout_Sandelli</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>