<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Handbook for the Office of the City Recorder/Finance Officer in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1984-04-11T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Meisenhelder</lname>
<fname>E.</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
<suffix>III</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This technical assistance manual, Overview: The Tennessee City Recorder, is intended to be a detailed guide to the functions of the City Recorder and/or Finance Director in Tennessee.  In view of the diverse chores performed by City Recorders/Finance Directors, it would be impossible and unprofitable to catalog all the various functions, however this manual covers the most important and most common responsibilities.  It is hoped that newly elected or appointed City Recorders will find this publication invaluable as they get started in their new jobs, and that experienced City Recorders will find useful information contained throughout the pages of this manual.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/25</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1024&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>25</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1024</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-06T12:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2638714</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/25</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-04-11T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>