<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>WHO IS MY NEIGHBOR?  The Importance of Global Education for Kinesiology Students</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jessica.ventura@gordon.edu</email>
<institution>Gordon College - Wenham</institution>
<lname>Ventura</lname>
<fname>Jessica</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Multicultural</keyword>
<keyword>health professions</keyword>
<keyword>Christian undergraduate</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Curriculum and Social Inquiry</discipline>
<discipline>Educational Methods</discipline>
<discipline>Liberal Studies</discipline>
<discipline>Religious Thought, Theology and Philosophy of Religion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The parable of the Samaritan in the Gospel of Luke illustrates that helping others requires both the ability to reach out to &lt;em&gt;any person&lt;/em&gt; and the humility to receive mercy from &lt;em&gt;any person&lt;/em&gt;. This active love requires a basic understanding of culture and the ways in which it may affect the values and actions of others. As believers seeking to express God in careers that bring them in contact with &lt;em&gt;any person&lt;/em&gt;, kinesiology students have a specific need to understand their global neighbors. This paper first explores the importance of multicultural education as illustrated in the book of Acts and the epistles to the churches. Educational outcomes for guiding students through different stages of intercultural sensitivity are provided. Finally, examples of multicultural programs that colleges and universities are implementing in the health professions are presented.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jcskls/vol6/iss1/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;amp;context=jcskls&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1015</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-08-09T16:05:10-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Journal of the Christian Society for Kinesiology, Leisure and Sports Studies</publication-title>
<context-key>15093886</context-key>
<submission-path>jcskls/vol6/iss1/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Theories and Frameworks Used in the Study of Sport and Religion</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>