<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Development Along the Northwestern Boundary of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park: Can the Park&#39;s &#39;Soft-Edge&#39; Boundary Be Preserved?</title>
<publication-date>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>James</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geography</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Development along the Great Smoky Mountains National Park&#39;s northwestern boundary threatens the &quot;soft-edge&quot; characteristics of its bordering communities. The &quot;soft-edge&quot; characteristics enable visitors to gradually transition from the urban to natural environment, and mitigate human impacts on the natural environment. Between 1970and 1994  the Knoxville Metropolitan Area population grew from 424,586to 631,097. Between 1988and 1997Park visitation increased from 8.8million to 9.9million. This thesis questions whether the &quot;soft-edge&quot; character of the Park&#39;s northwestern boundary can be preserved in light of the increasing population and development pressures on the bordering communities. In this thesis I have reviewed the roles of the parties who have an interest in the land-use decisions occurring along the Park&#39;s boundary. These parties include the National Park Service; the communities of Pittman Center, Gatlinburg and Townsend; federal, state, and local governments; and locally-based conservation organizations. I reviewed a significant amount of literature including National Park Service publications; community land use plans and zoning ordinances; federal, state and county government documents; as well as books and articles concerning the subject. I also interviewed NPS, community, and local conservation officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show that none of the parties acting alone are likely to be able to take actions that would be adequate to preserve the character of the &quot;soft-edge&quot; boundary. Eventually, the NPS will likely have to seek additional regulatory authority or provide financial incentives or other assistance to enhance the communities&#39; preservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3310</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4746&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3310</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4746</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-09T10:35:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6963239</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3310</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carol Harden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ron Foresta, David Feldman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geography</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>