<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Aspects of the Reproductive Biology and Growth of the Mississippi Silvery Minnow, &lt;i&gt; Hybognathus nuchalis &lt;/i&gt;(Agassiz, 1855) (Teleostei: Cyprinidae) from the Pearl River, Louisiana.</title>
<publication-date>2018-11-30T07:12:33-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>are.ly32@live.com.mx</email>
<institution>Universidad Michoacana de San Nicolás de Hidalgo</institution>
<lname>Ramírez-García</lname>
<fname>Arely</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>Kyle.Piller@selu.edu</email>
<institution>Southeastern Louisiana University</institution>
<lname>Piller</lname>
<fname>Kyle</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Cyprinidae</keyword>
<keyword>life-history</keyword>
<keyword>reproduction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Integrative Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The reproductive biology and growth of the Mississippi Silvery Minnow, &lt;em&gt;Hybognathus nuchalis, &lt;/em&gt;is described from multiple sites in the Pearl River, Louisiana. Individuals were collected from August 2011 to August 2012. Ovarian weights, expressed as a percentage of body weights, peaked in December. Size structure ranged from 29.0 to 60.0 mm SL for females and 25.0 to 56.0 mm SL for males. Mature ova were found from November to January. Females reached first maturity (L50) at 37.0 mm SL and L50 for males is at 41.0 mm SL. Sex ratio (females:males) is biased towards females (X&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;= 18.57 p &lt; 0.05). Fecundity of mature individuals ranged from 118 to 830 ova (mean 433±256.8 SD) in fish 30-50 mm SL. There was negative allometric growth for both sexes and there was a significant relationship significant between SL and body weight for both sex (R&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=0.9, p&lt;0.05).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1290&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1290</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-08-07T08:41:23-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1290/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>12615756</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss58/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Acknowledgments
We would like to thank D. Spencer, R. Frught, C. Agosta, K. Francis, K. Jefferis, E. Marchio, D. Spaulding, M. Foster and C. Foster and other members of Environmental Business Specialists for assistance with the fieldwork and other logistical aspects of this study. All fishes were sampled in accordance with a Louisiana Scientific Collecting Permit and an Animal Care Protocol (SLU-IACUC #0002) issued to KRP. Arely Ramírez-García thanks the División de Estudios de Posgrado de la Universidad Michoacana de San Nicolás de Hidalgo and CONACYT for providing economic resources during her visit to Southeastern Louisiana University.We would also like to acknowledge the natural history collections and their respective curators and collection managers for providing access to their distributional data (for Figure 1) through the fishnet2 portal including: OMNH, ANSP, UMMZ, OSUM, INHS, UAIC, UWFC, TCWC, USNM, MMNS, UF, CAS, TU, YPM, FMNH, KU, TNHC, AU, CUMV, and UAFMC.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-08-07T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xdc610a0)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Reproductive Biology and Growth of the Mississippi Silvery Minnow</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>