<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The effect of self-directed work teams on work ethic</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Fontan</lname>
<fname>Johnny</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to compare work ethic between machine operators in a self-directed work team manufacturing facility and machine operators in a traditional work systems manufacturing facility based on four subscales (dependable, cooperative, ambitious, considerate). Secondly, the study investigated differences between machine operators in a self-directed work team manufacturing facility and machine operators in a traditional work systems manufacturing facility based on six demographic factors (age, gender, level of education, years of full-time work experience, years of experiences as a supervisor, work shift preference). The Occupational Work Ethic Inventory (OWEI) (Petty, 1991) was the sole instrument used for the study. The machine operators of Kimberly-Clark, Loudon Mill and Kimberly-Clark, Nt?enah Nonwovens was used as participants in the study. A total number of 396 surveys were distributed to the machine operators. There were 252 surveys completed, which accounted for a 64% response rate. Descriptive statistics including the mean, standard deviation, and frequencies were gathered for the demographic data to help interpret employees&#39; work ethic scores. A uni-variate analysis of variance (UNIANOVA) and the Tukey post hoc tests were used to analyze the data from the OWEI. The UNIANOVA test divided the survey into four descriptors in order to measure the machine operators work ethic scores. Finally, descriptive statistics and the Tukey Honestly Significant Difference (HSD) post hoc test were used to analyze any differences that existed between the six demographic variables.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            The major findings from the study implied (a) there are significant differences work ethic of machine operators in self-directed work team manufacturing facilities and traditional work systems manufacturing facilities. (b) there are significant differences on the considerate subscale of the OWEI based on age.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5916</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7549&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5916</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7549</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467572</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5916</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory C. Petty</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Development</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>