<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Prescribed Burning in Tennessee: Importance and Barriers, Goals, and Information Needs of Private, State, and Federal Managers</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hemel</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Forest Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Early in the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, intense and severe wildfires were frequent due to abundant fuels generated by logging and the presence of anthropogenic ignition sources in close proximity to these fuels.  As timber was depleted, this period of lumbering ceased and the realization that vast tracts of cutover land had to be reforested and protected led to the inception of fire suppression organizations and techniques. The fire exclusion that occurred over much of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century due to organized fire suppression efforts has led to two sets of problems: the buildup of fuels and the decline of fire-adapted species and fire-dependent ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectives of this research included: 1) Determining the current level of use of prescribed fire by forest types, local regions, and management agencies and individuals, 2) Determining specific fire research and technology transfer needs and the barriers to implementation of prescribed fire across forest types, local regions, and management agencies and individuals, and 3) Comparing effects of two fire regimes on Table Mountain Pine (&lt;em&gt;Pinus pungens&lt;/em&gt;) in East Tennessee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey was developed to address the first two objectives and was programmed in SPSS Data Entry format.  The survey was e-mailed to approximately 350 Natural Resource Managers across the state of Tennessee.  A modified Dillman Total Design Method (TDM) (Dillman 2000) was applied to the survey administration, whereby managers received an initial e-mail introducing the project and telling them when it would arrive.  Next, managers were sent an e-mail message with a cover letter along with the web-site to answer the questionnaire.  Reminder e-mail messages were sent to the residents that had not responded within one and a half weeks of the initial mailing.  Cross Tabulations and MANOVAs were run in SPSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the third objective, two &lt;em&gt;P. pungens&lt;/em&gt; stands of differing age structure and disturbance history at Horsehitch Gap on the Cherokee National Forest in Greene County, Tennessee were analyzed using dendrochronology and stand reconstruction techniques.  The stands studied at Horsehitch Gap represented two regeneration cohorts resulting from two stand replacing fires in 1941 and 1981.  The 1941 stand has experienced disturbances from low intensity ground fires and the Southern pine beetle (&lt;em&gt;Dendroctonus frontalis&lt;/em&gt;).  The 1981 stand is in the stem exclusion stage and is experiencing waves of density dependent mortality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Survey results suggested the Tennessee Wildlife Resources Agency definitely uses prescribed burning the most in their management for wildlife and recreation.  Private consultants use prescribed burning the least, but a majority of them would like to use prescribed burning on the land they manage.  These two groups could be combined with federal/state agencies or with private firms.  Different emphasis on economic returns were the main factors distinguishing these two groups.  The private agencies are likely more concerned with having a sellable product in the future.  The state/federal agencies have greater manpower to conduct these burns and are less likely to need the forest products to generate income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results for Table Mountain pine at Horsehitch Gap indicate that both stands of Table Mountain pine are in danger of being replaced by other species.  This is particularly evident in the 1941 stand, where &lt;em&gt;P. pungens&lt;/em&gt; individuals in the intermediate size classes are absent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, prescribed burning is an effective, economic, and ecological management tool.  Managers spend less than 6.5 percent of their time on prescribed burning in forested land in Tennessee.  According to managers, additional research on prescribed burning is needed in both hardwood and mixed pine/hardwood stands, and the correct seasons to burn in these ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on measurements in the 1941 and 1981 stands, a stand replacing fire regime favored the regeneration of Table Mountain pine at Horsehitch Gap.  Measurements obtained at Horsehitch Gap support the hypothesis forwarded previously by other researchers that a lack of stand replacing fire is likely to result in losses of many &lt;em&gt;P. pungens &lt;/em&gt;stands from the landscape.  Further, Southern Pine Beetle outbreaks have the effect of hastening conversion of &lt;em&gt;P.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;pungens &lt;/em&gt;stands to other forest types.  Further investigation of appropriate burning practices in hardwood stands will facilitate increased use of prescribed burning in Tennessee forests.  For example, research on relationships between intensities of fire and season of burning in hardwoods will allow managers to determine when to burn in ecosystems without damaging crop trees.  Additional research in areas such as smoke management will also facilitate increased use of prescribed burning for habitat improvement and other goals.  Therefore, with managers, landowners, researchers and the general public working together, information on this management practice can be useful for everyone. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2568</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3642&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2568</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3642</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-11T11:22:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4698132</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2568</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David S. Buckley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Wayne K. Clatterbuck, J. Mark Fly, Donald G. Hodges, Arnold M. Saxton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Forestry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>