<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>[Re]Constructing Community: A Strategy for Post-Disaster Recovery</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rstechma@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Stechmann</lname>
<fname>Ryan</fname>
<mname>James</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Recovery</keyword>
<keyword>Post Disaster</keyword>
<keyword>Rebuilding</keyword>
<keyword>Community</keyword>
<keyword>Hurricane</keyword>
<keyword>Coastal</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Civic and Community Engagement</discipline>
<discipline>Urban Studies and Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis focuses on exploring a viable solution for permanent housing after a natural disaster with an emphasis on community rebuilding in a southern coastal context. This region will continue to be affected by hurricanes and it is only a matter of time until another major disaster will happen. In any major disaster the fabric of the community is torn and takes a long time to recover. Communal places are vital to recovery after such disasters because they serve as a place where the people of the community can gather and provide support or receive support from each other and outside organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In current disaster response strategies, establishing shelter immediately after such an event is paramount, while community rebuilding is given secondary importance. Current practices in the aftermath of natural disasters, while well intended, often turn into poor solutions. A “quick-fix” solution to this issue often leaves the community out of the equation, both its members and the sense of community. As a result there is too much focus on housing and community places are only addressed later in the recovery process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing from personal experience in the disaster recovery process post-Katrina, this thesis proposal challenges the existing disaster response strategies and focuses on simultaneous rebuilding of both housing and community places, approaching the problem of housing and community place as a synergetic issue. Housing is an integral part of a community, just as is community place, and by approaching the issue as if the two are one in the same, then community becomes the focus. A community is more than just its buildings, but its built environment provides a framework for community. By focusing on community rebuilding, both in housing and community space, the design solution will provide a greater quality of life for a community. The design proposal will have two aspects: housing and public community place. Both aspects will focus on community engagement and community rebuilding. The overall goal is to form a solution to reestablish the sense of community and address the need of adequate housing borne out through design.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3514</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4655&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3514</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4655</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-02-27T13:16:30-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6744998</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3514</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John M. McRae</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer A. Akerman, Tricia A. Stuth</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>