<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Changes in Data Sharing and Data Reuse Practices and Perceptions among Scientists Worldwide</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tenopir</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>eddalton@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dalton</lname>
<fname>Elizabeth</fname>
<mname>D</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Allard</lname>
<fname>Suzie</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>US Geological Survey</institution>
<lname>Frame</lname>
<fname>Mike</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Georgia</institution>
<lname>Pjesivac</lname>
<fname>Ivanka</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Birch</lname>
<fname>Ben</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pollock</lname>
<fname>Danielle</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dorsett</lname>
<fname>Kristina</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>data management</keyword>
<keyword>scientists</keyword>
<keyword>regional geography</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The incorporation of data sharing into the research lifecycle is an important part of modern scholarly debate. In this study, the DataONE Usability and Assessment working group addresses two primary goals: To examine the current state of data sharing and reuse perceptions and practices among research scientists as they compare to the 2009/2010 baseline study, and to examine differences in practices and perceptions across age groups, geographic regions, and subject disciplines. We distributed surveys to a multinational sample of scientific researchers at two different time periods (October 2009 to July 2010 and October 2013 to March 2014) to observe current states of data sharing and to see what, if any, changes have occurred in the past 3–4 years. We also looked at differences across age, geographic, and discipline-based groups as they currently exist in the 2013/2014 survey. Results point to increased acceptance of and willingness to engage in data sharing, as well as an increase in actual data sharing behaviors. However, there is also increased perceived risk associated with data sharing, and specific barriers to data sharing persist. There are also differences across age groups, with younger respondents feeling more favorably toward data sharing and reuse, yet making less of their data available than older respondents. Geographic differences exist as well, which can in part be understood in terms of collectivist and individualist cultural differences. An examination of subject disciplines shows that the constraints and enablers of data sharing and reuse manifest differently across disciplines. Implications of these findings include the continued need to build infrastructure that promotes data sharing while recognizing the needs of different research communities. Moving into the future, organizations such as DataONE will continue to assess, monitor, educate, and provide the infrastructure necessary to support such complex grand science challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/54</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1053&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>54</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1053</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-13T12:26:40-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>9263994</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/54</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons CC0&lt;/a&gt; license.  &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Tenopir C, Dalton ED, Allard S, Frame M, Pjesivac I, Birch B, et al. (2015) Changes in Data Sharing and Data Reuse Practices and Perceptions among Scientists Worldwide. PLoS ONE 10(8): e0134826. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0134826</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1371/journal.pone.0134826</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>PLOS One</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>