<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>JAEPL, Vol. 22, Winter 2016-2017</title>
<publication-date>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Emory University</institution>
<lname>Trapp</lname>
<fname>Joonna</fname>
<mname>Smitherman</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Northern Illinois University</institution>
<lname>Peters</lname>
<fname>Brad</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Editors’ Message Essays SPECIAL SECTION: DEEP READING STRATEGIES Jane Thompkins - Deep Reading Vajra Watson - Life as Primary Text: English Classrooms as Sites for Soulful Learning Tisha Ulmer - Using Pre-reading Strategies to Provide Historical Context in a Literature Course Grace Wetzel - ‘The Most Peaceful I Ever Felt Writing’: A Contemplative Approach to Essay Revision TEACHING AND LEARNING Kate Chaterdon - Contemplative Neuroscience and the Teaching of Writing: Mindfulness as Mental Training Ondine Gage - Resisting a Restrictive Discourse Policy J. Michael Rifenburg - The Performance of Literate Practices: Rhetoric, Writing, and Stand-up Comedy Rosanne Carlo - Getting Centered: A Meditation on Creating Pottery and Teaching Writing Robbie Clifton Pinter - The Transformative Practice of Writing and Teaching Writing Out of the Box Pamela B. Childers - Rattling Cages Book Reviews Julie Nichols - Threshold Concepts. Brad E. Lucas, et al. - Adler-Kassner, Linda, and Elizabeth Wardle, eds. Naming What We Know: Threshold Concepts of Writing Studies. Logan: Utah State University Press, 2015. Maureen Hall - Waxler, Robert P. The Risk of Reading: How Literature Helps Us to Understand Ourselves and the World. New York: Bloomsbury, 2014. Gae Lyn Henderson--Goodson, Ivor, and Scherto Gill. Critical Narrative as Pedagogy. New York: Bloomsbury, 2014. Connecting Christy Wenger—Risks and Rewards of Purposeful Vulnerability Christina Martorana - Embracing Vulnerability in Teaching  Jacquelyn E. Hoerman-Elliot - Writing as a Sea of Oms: A “This I Believe” Essay for Contemplative Writing in First-Year Composition  Beth Godbee and Adrianne Wojcik - Decoding Each Other through Coding: Sharing Our Unlikely Research Collaboration  Laurence Musgrove—Dress Up Laurence Musgrove—Trees&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/jaepl/vol22/iss1/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1299&amp;amp;context=jaepl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>fullissue</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1299</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-24T12:30:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>The Journal of the Assembly for Expanded Perspectives on Learning</publication-title>
<context-key>10655551</context-key>
<submission-path>jaepl/vol22/iss1/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>