<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Risk communication and community right to know: A public relations obligation to inform</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mpalench@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Palenchar</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>J</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>risk communication</keyword>
<keyword>community right to know</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Relations and Advertising</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Risk communication and community right to know are increasingly important functions of public relations within communities that face a considerable amount of health, safety and environmental risk related to chemical manufacturing. Following Susan G. Hadden’s (1989) claim that community right to know is not only a legal subject but a powerful approach to risk communication and by extension public relations, this research project analyzed, through an ethnographic case study of participant observations (n=193 days), interviews (n=27) and focus groups (n=15), how community residents perceive and construct their awareness and understanding of significant federally mandated and industry initiated community-right-to-know initiatives within risk communication. Findings include a general lack of awareness and understanding of community-right-to-know programs and risk management protocols, with differences among communities, cultures and genders, and the social justification of risks via narratives.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_advepubs/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;amp;context=utk_advepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1000</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-01-19T14:44:02-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Advertising and Public Relations Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1140454</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_advepubs/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Public Relations Journal</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>