<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>I Think I Love Her: The Untold Realities of Marriage and Commitment in African American Communities</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:37:25-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>adavenp7@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Davenport</lname>
<fname>Max Ray</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>ebrewe11@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Brewer</lname>
<fname>Elisha</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Aimed at cultivating spaces for persons of color to engage in fruitful conversations concerning the creation and development of romantic relationships in the 21st century, this presentation seeks to use peer-reviewed research articles, lived experiences, and societal expectations to guide this work. Seeking to demonstrate and identify the harmful implications of relational schemas, we seek to address the role of institutionalized narratives, socialization processes, and traditional gender roles as individuals evaluate causal attributions about the following: relational tensions, reluctance to marry, and the decline of marriage rates in the AA community. Primarily, we seek to challenge social definitions of what it means to love and be loved in romantic dyads. Furthermore, we aim to provide audience members with the necessary tools to engage in healthy practices that promote growth, understanding, and cohesion. Through this, we strive to &lt;em&gt;unveil the truth&lt;/em&gt; regarding the continual decline in marital relationships amongst African Americans.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/14</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1208&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>14</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1208</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-08T07:31:26-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1208/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13583410</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/14</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>https://prezi.com/view/9iUnz6oETJyaMDmsMPMb/</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>