<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>High and low active transit accessibility on greenways:  The relationship with physical activity</title>
<publication-date>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dwolff@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wolff</lname>
<fname>Dana Lizbeth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Greenway</keyword>
<keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
<keyword>Accessibility</keyword>
<keyword>Built Environment</keyword>
<keyword>Active Transit</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Kinesiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Greenways (GW) can be sited to increase the potential for individuals to access the GW through active transit (AT) and provide opportunities for individuals to meet PA guidelines.  PURPOSE: To determine if GWs, with varying AT access potential, relate to user characteristics and their GW-related PA.  METHODS: A trail intercept survey measuring access mode, GW-specific PA, and demographics of GW users was administered to 611 adults on 2 GWs with high and low AT potential (GW&lt;sub&gt;high&lt;/sub&gt; vs. GW&lt;sub&gt;low&lt;/sub&gt;). RESULTS: Users of GW&lt;sub&gt;high&lt;/sub&gt;(N=216) compared to GW&lt;sub&gt;low&lt;/sub&gt; (N=400) were more likely to be younger, male, never married, employed, and affluent; accessing the GW via AT modes and accumulating greater volumes of GW-only and total GW-related PA (GW-only &amp; AT PA).   No difference in the proportion GW users meeting the 2008 PA Guidelines from GW-only PA was found however, 10.5% more users of GW&lt;sub&gt;high&lt;/sub&gt; met the guidelines from total GW-related PA compared to GW&lt;sub&gt;low&lt;/sub&gt; (p=0.039).  Users who accessed GW&lt;sub&gt;high &lt;/sub&gt;by AT rather than cars were more likely to be not married (OR=2.6, 95% CI:  1.1 – 6.3), under 35 years old (OR=6.0, 95% CI:  1.9 – 19.26), live a mile from the GW (OR=5.39, 95% CI:  2.3 – 14.3).  CONCLUSION:  The profile of GW user and the way PA is acquired is related to the AT accessibility of GWs.  Although PA levels of GW&lt;sub&gt;high &lt;/sub&gt;users were significantly higher, GW&lt;sub&gt;low&lt;/sub&gt; usage was greater.  Therefore, GW planners and designers should incorporate universal design concepts and conduct needs based assessments to properly site and design GWs to serve the greatest portion of the population.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1038</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2157&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1038</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2157</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-08-04T11:30:37-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/2157/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>2132623</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1038</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eugene C. Fitzhugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Bassett, Christopher Cherry</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Kinesiology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>