<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The &lt;em&gt;Tractatus&lt;/em&gt; as an Ethical Deed: Seeing and Feeling the World &quot;&lt;em&gt;Sub Specie Aeternitatis&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>von Mizener</lname>
<fname>Sam</fname>
<mname>Matthew</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Philosophy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Tractatus Logico Philosophicus &lt;/em&gt;is primarily the expression of a transcendental perspective with respect to language and the world - &quot;viewing the world &lt;em&gt;sub specie aeterni&lt;/em&gt;&quot; (6.45) - that has an aesthetic-ethical aspect to it - &quot;feeling the world&quot; &lt;em&gt;sub specie aeterni &lt;/em&gt;(6.54). Interpreting the &lt;em&gt;Tractatus &lt;/em&gt;in this way enables me to explain, in a way that no other interpretation of his early work has (1) why Wittgenstein regarded the &lt;em&gt;Tractatus &lt;/em&gt;as an &quot;ethical deed&quot; or as having an &quot;ethical point&quot;; (2) how his &#39;propositions&#39; about the connection between language and the world are nonsense but at the same time intelligible; (3) how his &#39;propositions&#39; about value, ethics and&lt;em&gt; Das Mystische &lt;/em&gt;are nonsense but at the same time intelligible; (4) why he identifies ethics with aesthetics and what this means; and (5) why &quot;resolute&quot; or &quot;austere&quot; readings of the &lt;em&gt;Tractatus &lt;/em&gt;are fundamentally wrong. Viewing or contemplating the world &lt;em&gt;&quot;sub specie aeterni&quot; &lt;/em&gt;or as a &quot;limited whole&quot; ( 6.45) is to view it as a collection of all the facts and &lt;em&gt;at the same time &lt;/em&gt;to take an aesthetico-ethical perspective with respect to the world. It is in this sense that Wittgenstein regards ethics and aesthetics as identical. The aestheticoethical aspect of this perspective amounts to our &quot;feeling the world as a limited whole&quot; (6.54). What it means to &quot;feel&quot; the world in this way cannot be given any descriptive meaning, and is indeed characterized by Wittgenstein as&quot; the mystical&quot;, but there are certain experiences that point toward it. According to Wittgenstein, it is our sense of wonder that the world &lt;em&gt;is &lt;/em&gt;that is the quintessential mystical experience. And it is in virtue of taking the transcendental perspective on language and the world that the mystical &quot;shows&quot; itself (6.522) in this way. Thus, &quot;seeing the world aright&quot; (6.54) is to see it from the &quot;right&quot; perspective both logically and aesthetico-ethically.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4270</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5970&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4270</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5970</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-06T09:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9984215</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4270</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Holt</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Richard Gale, Allen Dunn, Richard Aquila, Kathleen E. Bohstedt</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>