<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Message Strategy and the Perception of Self-Efficacy in Behavioral Intentions resulting from Advocacy Advertising</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Yoon-Joo</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis uses the Haley (1996) study as a conceptual framework for the study of advocacy advertising. The purpose of this thesis was to explore the role of message strategy in increasing the consumers&#39; perception of self-efficacy, perceived consumer effectiveness (PCE) in behavioral intentions resulting from advocacy advertising. Additionally, the thesis explored the correlations and causal relationships between self-efficacy/ PCE, and behavioral intention and behavioral intention and the consumers&#39; evaluation of the organization as good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quasi-experimental design was used. A questionnaire along with one of the two experimental stimuli (a print advertisement with the transformational-ego or the informational-ration message strategy) was presented to college students. The results are based on 154 completed questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results showed that a transformational message strategy enhanced receivers&#39; perception of self-efficacy more than an informational strategy but did not enhance PCE. Secondly, higher perceived self-efficacy or PCE completed with higher behavior intention toward the action recommended m the advocacy ads. The transformational-ego message strategy resulted in higher results of behavioral intention. Thirdly, the higher behavioral intentions led to higher evaluations of the sponsoring organization. However, the behavioral intentions did not explain the positive evaluations of the sponsoring organization. Behavioral intentions and evaluations of the organization had positive correlations but not a causal relationship. Six items other than behavioral intention items were identified as predictors of a positive evaluation of the organization&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4635</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6187&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4635</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6187</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-14T07:15:51-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10297889</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4635</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eric Haley</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>S. McMillan, R. Taylor</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>