<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Experiences and Observations with the Nutrition Section of the Louisiana State Department of Health</title>
<publication-date>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Livers</lname>
<fname>Nancy</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis is a description and an analysis of the student&#39;s field experience with the Nutrition Section of the Louisiana State Department of Health. The purpose of the field experience was to provide the student an opportunity to observe and participate in a state nutrition program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the field experience were accomplished through participation in a variety of nutrition related activities and through interviews and conferences with personnel of the health department. Program evaluation and statistical data manipulation skills were strengthened as the student planned, developed, and wrote a statistical report. The student expanded her professional knowledge by attending various professional meetings and communicating with professionals. Clinical experiences and supervision aided the student in the development of counseling and diet therapy techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching classes, counseling patients, and writing reports helped the student to develop skills needed by a nutritionist. The student learned that continued self evaluation will assist in strengthening her nutritional knowledge and in furthering her professional development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3876</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5358&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3876</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5358</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-18T12:53:43-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8999805</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3876</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel W. Hubbard</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Robert H. Kirk</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1974-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>