<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Relations Between 4-H Enrollment and Selected Characteristics of Tennessee&#39;s County 4-H Extension Programs</title>
<publication-date>1969-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ahmad</lname>
<fname>Syed</fname>
<mname>Zubair</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The study was concerned with the problem of decreasing county 4-H enrollment in Tennessee. Twenty-one independent variables concerning the characteristics of Tennessee&#39;s county 4-H Extension programs and five independent variables concerning total 4-H enrollment were studied. The independent variables were classified under the headings of 4-H leadership, organization, participation, place of 4-H member residence, potential number of 4-H members, and number of Extension staff members. The purpose was to identify the association between the selected variables concerning county 4-H programs and the total 4-H enrollment in the Tennessee counties. Another purpose was to determine which variable, within each group of 4-H Extension program variables, accounted for the highest percent of variation in the number of 4-H members enrolled per county.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was found that total 4-H enrollment in the ninety-five Tennessee counties was directly related to each of the following variables: total number of adult 4-H leaders, total number of junior 4-H club leaders, total number of basic four organizations, total number of 4-H all stars, total number of honor club members, total number of 4-H senior clubs, total number of junior 4-H clubs, total number of 4-H clubs, average number of senior 4-H members per senior club, total number of senior 4-H district winners, total number of 4-H members participating in 4-H judging and in 4-H camp, total number of full-time Extension staff equivalents responsible for 4-H work, and total number of Extension staff members per county.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variables, within each group of county 4-H program variables, which accounted for the largest percents of variation in total county 4-H enrollment were: total number of junior 4-H leaders (50 percent), total number of 4-H clubs per county (60 percent), total number of 4-H members per county participating in 4-H camp (31 percent), total number of 4-H members per county residing on farm (55 percent), total number of full-time Extension staff equivalents per county (54 percent). Variables under potential number of 4-H members were not significantly relates with enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was implied that 4-H enrollment in Tennessee counties might tend to increase if either the number of 4-H leaders, number of 4-H clubs, number of members participating in 4-H events and activities, and/or the number of full-time Extension staff equivalents responsible for 4-H work increased. Implications for program emphasis were made.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3534</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4893&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3534</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4893</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-02T08:04:44-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7669726</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3534</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Cecil E. Carter, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson, Franklin O. Leuthold</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1969-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1969-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>