<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Management of Montezuma Quail in Texas: Barriers to Establishing a Hunting Season</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:46:15-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Sul Ross State University</institution>
<lname>Harveson</lname>
<fname>Louis</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>barriers</keyword>
<keyword>biological</keyword>
<keyword>Cyrtonyx montezumae</keyword>
<keyword>hunting season</keyword>
<keyword>Montezuma quail</keyword>
<keyword>sociological</keyword>
<keyword>Texas</keyword>
<keyword>Trans-Pecos</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Montezuma quail (Cyrtonyx montezumae) occur throughout the desert southwest, ranging from Vera Cruz, Mexico to southern Arizona, New Mexico, and western Texas. In Mexico, Montezuma quail are a protected species and in New Mexico and Arizona they are a harvested gamebird. The distribution of Montezuma quail has changed significantly during the past century. Currently Montezuma quail are limited in Texas to the Trans-Pecos with remnant populations in the Edwards Plateau. Although Montezuma quail are classified as a gamebird in Texas, seasons are currently closed. Recently, Texas Parks and Wildlife Department has expressed interest in opening the season on Montezuma Quail. In this manuscript I review and chronicle the sociological and biological barriers associated with opening a hunting season for Montezuma quail in Texas. Sociological barriers include landowner competency and trust in state agencies, a growing voice among nonconsumptive users in Texas, a localized ecotourism industry centered on Montezuma quail, and other cultural factors. Biological barriers include lack of data on Montezuma quail population distribution, trends, and abundance; lack of scientific data relative to habitat management for Montezuma quail; or studies simulating the effects of harvest on Montezuma quail. Prior to implementing a hunting season on Montezuma quail in Texas, resource agencies will need to address the biological and sociological challenges outlined in the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol6/iss1/35</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1319&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>35</label>
<document-type>policy_and_conservation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1319</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472070</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol6/iss1/35</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>