<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>NPACC-X: A Further Evolution of Gas Centrifuge Cascade Analysis</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Centrifuge</keyword>
<keyword>Cascade</keyword>
<keyword>Analysis</keyword>
<keyword>NPACC</keyword>
<keyword>Dynamics</keyword>
<keyword>Enrichment</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As more countries seek nuclear power, some of these actors will find it necessary to develop their own domestic uranium enrichment facilities to support the peaceful production of nuclear power. These enrichment facilities pose an unquantifiable proliferation risk to the international community and are of great concern. In Dr. David Vermillion’s PhD dissertation “Improving Predictive Capabilities of Classical Cascade Theory,” he introduced the incorporation of “cascade dynamics” into classical cascade theory. This proved to be a great improvement over previous gas centrifuge cascade analysis methodologies. However, the original code base for this dissertation was lost to the university. The goal of this study will be to recreate that original code base in a more modernized format to have a greater understanding of multi-component isotopic streams and the processes they undergo during enrichment. Ultimately, this proved to be relatively successful. While the data provided in this study does not match the aforementioned data provided in the original dissertation, it does serve as a strong base for future cascade modeling programs. This provides the university with previously unobtainable analytical techniques that can be improved upon in the future. Additionally, this would be the first program of its kind to incorporate cascade dynamics in an open-academic setting. This study resulted in a step forward in developing better cascade modeling methodologies which would be of great use to the international nonproliferation community.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5652</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7186&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5652</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7186</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-11T13:30:06-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>20540247</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5652</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Howard Hall</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lawrence Heilbronn, Jason Hayward</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;/https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7088-5084&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2021-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>