<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Local Beer Tax: An Administrative Guide</title>
<publication-date>1951-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Municipal Technical Advisory Service</institution>
<lname>Hobday</lname>
<fname>Victor</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>taxes</keyword>
<keyword>beer licenses</keyword>
<keyword>alcohol</keyword>
<keyword>liquor</keyword>
<keyword>regulations</keyword>
<keyword>retailers</keyword>
<keyword>sin tax</keyword>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of legislation passed by the 1951 General Assembly, cities and counties in Tennessee have been authorized to levy a tax on the retail sale of beer, effective April 1, 1951. This bulletin has been prepared as a guide for city officials in the preparation of necessary local legislation and in the establishment of essential administrative procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sample ordinances, suggested rules and regulations, and forms in this bulletin were prepared by Anders O. Hustvedt and Porter C. Greenwood, MTAS Consultants. Other MTAS staff members have contributed to the various steps required to bring this bulletin to its final published form. (Forward by Gerald W. Shaw, MTAS Executive Director)&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtashist/9</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;amp;context=utk_mtashist&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1007</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-04-18T07:23:22-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS History</publication-title>
<context-key>4041957</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtashist/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-18T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1951-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>