<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Aelius Aristides as Orator-Confessor: Embodied Ethos in Second Century Healing Cults</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jportz@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Portz</lname>
<fname>Josie</fname>
<mname>Rose</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Aristides</keyword>
<keyword>second century</keyword>
<keyword>healing cult</keyword>
<keyword>confessor</keyword>
<keyword>embodiment</keyword>
<keyword>ethos</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The diverse corpus of Aelius Aristides helps to demonstrate the various ways ancient ritual practice in the second century influenced rhetorical production, especially through the orations composed in the kathedra--the two-year period he spent in the Pergamene Asclepion. The rhetorical moves of religious hymns and orations composed during this time parallel closely with a certain non-ordained, yet distinct role called the confessor. Using this traditional role as a paradigm, I explore how ritual practice characterizes the orations Aristides writes in and about the kathedra. I suggest that considering this section of Aristides’ work through the cultic confessor paradigm helps to explicate Aristides’ unique way of constructing ethos. To this end, I give special attention to an oration Aristides composed for a wide audience: In Defense of Oratory. Like a confessor, Aristides uses this argument to position himself between both human and divine as a divinely-inspired orator. In this way, Aristides provides a starting point for thinking about intimacy with the divine as a strategy for ethos-construction in the second century.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5509</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6982&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5509</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6982</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914300</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5509</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Janet Atwill</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jeffrey Ringer, Tanita Saenkhum</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>