<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The &lt;em&gt;Tennessee Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt;</title>
<publication-date>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Rogers</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Donald</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>German Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Tennessee Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt; was a German newspaper published in Nashville, Tennessee from 1866 to 1869. It had a daily circulation of approximately 1,000 and a weekly circulation of approximately 1,200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt; was dominated by its editor, a German immigrant named John Ruhm. Ruhm took an active interest in politics at all levels. He was a staunch advocate of republicanism both at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruhm was a harsh critic of the two leading German powers of his day, Austria and Prussia, because he disapproved of their aristocratic, authoritarian governments. Bismarck was for him the personification of Prussian Junkerdom and yet he grudgingly conceded that Bismarck had accomplished what German Liberals had only dreamed of for decades--German unification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruhm was very much committed to American politics. He had fought for the Union during the Civil War. Afterwards he enthusiastically supported the Radical reconstruction policies of such prominent national figures as Charles Sumner and Thaddeus Stevens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt; considered President Andrew Johnson and his followers traitors to the Union. It suggested that unless they had their own way they might form a coalition of Northern Copperheads and ex-Rebels and try to take over the government by force thus, in effect, precipitating a second civil war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Tennessee Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt; was an outspoken supporter of the East Tennessee Radicals who were led by the Methodist preacher turned governor, William Brownlow. It was later rewarded for this by being designated the official government newspaper for the local congressional district. The &lt;em&gt;Staatszeitung&lt;/em&gt; nevertheless maintained its independent editorial stance and was often at odds with the administration, particularly with regard to issues which directly affected the German community such as Sunday drinking laws.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3731</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5287&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3731</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5287</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-07-29T09:38:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8897719</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3731</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David Lee</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nancy Lauchner, Reinhold Nordsieck</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Plate 1 included at the end of the document.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>German</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1975-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>