<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Problem B: Factors Associated with Levels of Living of the Elderly in Hamblen County, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1972-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Griffin</lname>
<fname>Anthony</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agriculture</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this investigation was to identify some of the factors associated with the levels of living of elderly residents of Hamblen County, Tennessee. Levels of living were determined by the number of selected home improvements items possessed by each household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple regression analysis was the statistical tool used to assess levels of living. Possession of these home improvement items was analyzed according to 11 independent variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variable &quot;education of the female&quot; accounted for approximately 18 percent of the variation in levels of living, and appeared to be the best overall predictor of variations in level of living of the households surveyed. Women with more education tended to have a significantly larger number of home items than did those with less education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 6 percent of the variation in levels of living was accounted for by where the senior female member of the household was reared. Elderly women reared outside Hamblen County tended to have a significantly larger number of home items than those reared in Hamblen County. Approximately 4 percent of the variation in levels of living was accounted for by marital status. Married couples tended to have a significantly greater number of home items than those who were not married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Income of the household head accounted for approximately 2 percent of the variation in levels of living. Those elderly with higher incomes tended to have a significantly larger number of home items than those with lower incomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major lifetime occupation of the male household head accounted for nearly 1 percent of the variation in levels of living. Those who worked in professional or semi-professional occupations tended to have a significantly greater number of home items than those who worked in skilled or semi-skilled jobs. Also, those who worked in skilled or semi-skilled occupations tended to have a significantly larger number of home items than those who reported farming to be their major lifetime occupation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These five independent variables accounted for approximately 31 percent of the variation in levels of living of the households surveyed. While other variables were also significantly related to level of living, they did not appreciably add to the percent of variation accounted for in levels of living.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4364</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5854&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4364</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5854</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-27T06:45:58-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9753671</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4364</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ff9860820)</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Problem in Lieu of Thesis. Major is listed as Agricultural Extension. Signature page is unsigned.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agriculture and Extension Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1972-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1972-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>