<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Finding Work in America: Employment Outcomes among Recent Immigrants</title>
<publication-date>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>carwood2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Arwood</lname>
<fname>Catherine</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Finding employment is necessary for immigrants’ self-sufficiency. This study explores factors that influence successful employment among recent immigrants in the United States. Understanding these factors helps social service providers meet the needs of foreign-born clients. Methods: Outcomes were examined for 373 Latino and Asian respondents who immigrated to the United States within five years prior to the survey, and are working (n=330) or looking for work (n=43), as reported in the National Latino and Asian American Study. Surveyors conducted interviews at respondents’ homes in the respondents’ preferred language. Analyses compared employed and unemployed workers based on English language proficiency, education, social capital, discriminatory experiences, age, gender, and race/ethnicity. Results: Unemployed immigrants reported higher levels of education and English proficiency than those who were working. Results of a chi-square test of indicated a significant relationship between gender and employment, χ2 (1, N=373)=7.271, p=0.007. Females were more likely to be unemployed (16.4%) than men (7.4%). Respondents also reported experiencing discrimination due to race, ancestry, ethnicity, or skin color. Conclusions: Based on findings education levels and English deficiency did not necessarily prevent immigrants from finding employment in the United States. However, discrimination may reduce employment chances, especially for female immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2015/socialwork/2</coverpage-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1065</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-28T08:00:40-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1065/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>7039582</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2015/socialwork/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Keywords: immigrants, refugees, employment, discrimination, gender equality, social work, self-sufficiency, Asian, Latino, English language, education&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
<supplemental-files>
<file>
<archive-name>Abstract_for_EUReCA_Presentation.docx</archive-name>
<upload-name>Abstract_for_EUReCA_Presentation.docx</upload-name>
<url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=0&amp;amp;article=1065&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;type=additional</url>
<mime-type>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</mime-type>
<description>Full Abstract</description>
</file>
</supplemental-files>
</document>
</documents>