<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Perspectives of Rural Library Managers/Directors Regarding Professional Education: A Qualitative Study in Northwest Georgia</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tracy</lname>
<fname>Christina</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Attempts have been made by several organizations, including the American Library Association (ALA), to provide greater access to professional education for library managers/directors; however, the rural environment presents unique challenges to education not addressed by many of the policies and programs currently in place. This study examined the perspectives of library managers/directors in rural Northwest Georgia about the factors that impede or facilitate professional degree attainment. Participants included twelve library managers/directors serving in rural communities. Qualitative interviews with the library managers/directors identified their experiences and issues including challenges and incentives to professional degree attainment. The principal findings include: the difference in the experiences and perspectives of degreed and non-degreed participants, regarding professional degree attainment; and the degree to which multiple financial, geographical and cultural factors are affected by demographic characteristics of participants. The results of this study can be used by organizations and agencies who seek to improve the education of rural library managers/directors.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/475</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1511&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>475</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1511</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-19T06:59:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1155444</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/475</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bharat Mehra</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>William C. Robinson, Kimberly Black</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Information Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/TracyChristina.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>