<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>n3 and n6 polyunsaturated fatty acids differentially modulate prostaglandin E secretion but not markers of lipogenesis in adipocytes</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-21T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wortman</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Miyazaki</lname>
<fname>Yuko</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>nkalupah@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kalupahana</lname>
<fname>Nishan Sudheera</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kim</lname>
<fname>Suyeon</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>phansen@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hansen-Petrik</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>asaxton@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Saxton</lname>
<fname>Arnold</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Michigan State University</institution>
<lname>Claycombe</lname>
<fname>Kate</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Voy</lname>
<fname>Brynn</fname>
<mname>H.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>jwhelan@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Whelan</lname>
<fname>Jay</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>moustaid@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Moustaid-Moussa</lname>
<fname>Naima</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;A dramatic rise in the incidence of obesity in the U.S. has accelerated the search for interventions that may impact this epidemic. One recently recognized target for such intervention is adipose tissue, which secretes a variety of bioactive substances including prostaglandins. Prostaglandin E&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;(PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) has been shown to decrease lipolysis in adipocytes, but limited studies have explored alternative mechanisms by which PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;might impact obesity, such as adipogenesis or lipogenesis. Studies conducted on &lt;em&gt;Apc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Min/+ &lt;/sup&gt;mice indicated that selective inhibition of the cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 enzyme led to significant reductions in fatty acid synthase (FAS) activity in adipose tissue suggesting lipogenic effects of PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. To further investigate whether these lipid mediators directly regulate lipogenesis, we used 3T3-L1 adipocytes to determine the impact of eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and celecoxib on PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;formation and FAS used as a lipogenic marker. Both arachidonic acid (AA) and EPA dose-dependently increased PGE secretion from adipocytes. AA was expectedly more potent and exhibiting at 150 uM dose a 5-fold increase in PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;secretion over EPA. Despite higher secretion of PGE by EPA and AA compared to control, neither PUFA significantly altered FAS activity. By contrast both AA and EPA significantly decreased FAS mRNA levels. Addition of celecoxib, a selective COX-2 inhibitor, significantly decreased PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;secretion (p &lt; 0.05) versus control, and also significantly decreased FAS activity (p &lt; 0.05). Unexpectedly, the combination of exogenous PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;and celecoxib further decreased the FAS activity compared to PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;alone or untreated controls. In conclusion, EPA-mediated inhibition of AA metabolism did not significantly alter FAS activity while both AA and EPA significantly decreased FAS mRNA expression. COX-2 inhibition significantly decreased PGE&lt;sub&gt;2 &lt;/sub&gt;production resulting in a decrease in FAS activity and expression that was not reversed with the addition of exogenous PGE&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, suggesting an additional mechanism that is independent of COX-2.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/22</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1021&amp;amp;context=utk_nutrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1021</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-10T12:06:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4302137</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Nutrition &amp; Metabolism 2009, 6:5 doi:10.1186/1743-7075-6-5</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-21T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>