<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Differentiation of Equine Mesenchymal Stromal Cells into Cells of Neural Lineage: Potential for Clinical Applications</title>
<publication-date>2014-11-24T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Villagrán</lname>
<fname>Claudia</fname>
<mname>Cruz</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Amelse</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Neilsen</lname>
<fname>Nancy</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dunlap</lname>
<fname>John</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dhar</lname>
<fname>Madhu</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>mesenchymal stromal cells</keyword>
<keyword>neural lineage</keyword>
<keyword>neural progenitor protein</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) are able to differentiate into extramesodermal lineages, including neurons. Positive outcomes were obtained after transplantation of neurally induced MSCs in laboratory animals after nerve injury, but this is unknown in horses. Our objectives were to test the ability of equine MSCs to differentiate into cells of neural lineage in vitro, to assess differences in morphology and lineage-specific protein expression, and to investigate if horse age and cell passage number affected the ability to achieve differentiation. Bone marrow-derived MSCs were obtained from young and adult horses. Following demonstration of stemness, MSCs were neurally induced and microscopically assessed at different time points. Results showed that commercially available nitrogen-coated tissue culture plates supported proliferation and differentiation. Morphological changes were immediate and all the cells displayed a neural crest-like cell phenotype. Expression of neural progenitor proteins, was assessed via western blot or immunofluorescence. In our study, MSCs generated from young and middle-aged horses did not show differences in their ability to undergo differentiation. The effect of cell passage number, however, is inconsistent and further experiments are needed. Ongoing work is aimed at transdifferentiating these cells into Schwann cells for transplantation into a peripheral nerve injury model in horses.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_largpubs/37</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=utk_largpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>37</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1036</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-06T07:47:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Large Animal Clinical Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>9238912</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_largpubs/37</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Cruz Villagrán, C., Amelse, L., Neilsen, N., Dunlap, J., &amp; Dhar, M. Differentiation of equine mesenchymal stromal cells into cells of neural lineage: potential for clinical applications. Stem cells international, 2014.
DOI: 10.1155/2014/891518</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1155/2014/891518</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-11-24T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Stem Cells International</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>