<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Federal Interventions in Private Enterprise in the United States: Their Genesis in and Effects on Corporate Finance Instruments and Transactions</title>
<publication-date>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>corporate finance</keyword>
<keyword>preferred stock</keyword>
<keyword>bankruptcy</keyword>
<keyword>mergers</keyword>
<keyword>acquisitions</keyword>
<keyword>financial crisis</keyword>
<keyword>private enterprise</keyword>
<keyword>legal practice</keyword>
<keyword>Section 363</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Antitrust and Trade Regulation</discipline>
<discipline>Banking and Finance Law</discipline>
<discipline>Bankruptcy Law</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In  response to U.S. corporate failures involved in the current global  financial crisis, traditional corporate finance vehicles and tools were  widely used in new ways and for new purposes. Of course, one object of  the U.S. government’s investment and intervention in, and exercise of  influence over, private enterprise during the crisis was to provide for  or ensure the provision of adequate capital funding. But its investment,  intervention, and influence also represented a new way to oversee and  otherwise regulate key business enterprises in the financial services  and automotive sectors. This Article reviews certain aspects of the use  of preferred stock, bankruptcy-related proceedings, and mergers and  acquisitions in connection with the government’s recent, crisis-mode  interventions in private enterprise. Further, it analyzes corporate  finance aspects of these exploits and highlights potential effects of  these activities on corporate finance instruments, transactions, and  legal practice.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/23</coverpage-url>
<label>23</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1015</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-26T10:17:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2032426</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/23</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Federal Interventions in Private Enterprise in the United States: Their Genesis in and Effects on Corporate Finance Instruments and Transactions (June 1, 2010). Seton Hall Law Review, Vol. 40, No. 4, 2010; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 138. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1752326</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1752326</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>