<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Revitalizing a 19th Century Industrial Complex into a 21st Century Research and Learning Technology Center</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jwines@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Wines</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Lawrence</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Public school</keyword>
<keyword>waterfront</keyword>
<keyword>greenway</keyword>
<keyword>revitalization</keyword>
<keyword>connectivity</keyword>
<keyword>curriculum</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architectural Technology</discipline>
<discipline>Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Cultural Resource Management and Policy Analysis</discipline>
<discipline>Curriculum and Instruction</discipline>
<discipline>Environmental Design</discipline>
<discipline>Historic Preservation and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The revitalization and repurposing of the Domino’s Sugar Plant will foster a vibrant and engaged community for the neighborhood in a distinct way differing from the recent history of growth. Williamsburg is located in a north Brooklyn, New York, community that has been struggling for its identity since the 1970’s. The reprogramming of this abandoned industrial site will include the addition of a new technological research center that will contribute to economic growth and stability for the neighborhood. The new jobs will help bring more people into the neighborhood who will be committed to both live and work there. At present, most of the new residents live there due to the neighborhood’s proximity to Manhattan. This project would activate 1,500 feet of waterfront property on the East River and create a greenway that would be a gateway for this community. The greenway will move residents through the new research center, creating an awareness of the developments taking place there. The research center will support a progressive school that will utilize distinctive architectural design coupled with an innovative educational curriculum. The school will be designed with a digital focus that is on the cutting edge of education reform as competitive schools make a neighborhood attractive to families. By bringing in new jobs, creating greenways, new opportunities in education and encouraging occupancy by residents who have a longer-term commitment to the area, the project will help foster a cohesive community that is invested in the Williamsburg neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2477</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2670&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2477</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2670</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-03-01T11:47:44-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3817639</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2477</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory Spaw</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George Dodds, Matthew Hall</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>