<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Revenue Manual for Tennessee Cities</title>
<publication-date>1985-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Finane</lname>
<fname>Jim</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>MTAS</keyword>
<keyword>AR.742</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;One of the most essential tasks that a City Recorder, Finance Officer, or City Manager performs each year is the projection of the revenues upon which next year&#39;s budget is built, and the subsequent work required to insure that those revenues are collected and accounted for properly. Estimating and tracking revenue collection is frequently a difficult job, and can be nearly impossible without a good working knowledge of all the revenue sources available to and receive d by a city. The purpose of this manual is to provide a description of the revenues most commonly collected by municipalities in Tennessee, to be use d as a tool in revenue collection and accounting. The manual can also be used as a guide for cities in preparing their own customized revenue manual.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_mtaspubs/33</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1032&amp;amp;context=utk_mtaspubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>33</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1032</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-06T12:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>MTAS Publications: Full Publications</publication-title>
<context-key>2638724</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_mtaspubs/33</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The MTAS publications provided on this website are archival documents intended for informational purposes only and should not be considered as authoritative. The content contained in these publications may be outdated, and the laws referenced therein may have changed or may not be applicable to your city or circumstances. For current information, please visit the MTAS website at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&quot;&gt;http://mtas.tennessee.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-04-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>