<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Drawing on a painted canvas identity and modernism in fin-de-siècle Westphalia</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Jackson</lname>
<fname>Megan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>History</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Drawing on a Painted Canvas: Identity and Modernism in Fin-de-Siècle Westphalia&quot; uses an analysis of local visual culture to investigate the interaction of confessional identity, provincial identity, and artistic modernism in nineteenth-century German civil society. Specifically, I approach the research by observing communal identity and its manifestation in not only the pursuits of a German regional art society (which includes the 1907 creation of a provincial museum) but also the creation of a distinct visual culture. With an analysis of local painting and architecture, I also study the particular provincial response to German modernity by gauging the local citizens&#39; perception of artistic modernism. This thesis concludes that &quot;Catholics, like Westphalians in general, appear neither anti-modern nor anti-nationalist, as their identities--like their society, their museum, and their architecture--simply comprised a combination of elements: Catholic and secular, traditional and modern, local and national.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5725</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7347&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5725</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7347</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467484</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5725</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Denise Phillips</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>History</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>