<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Regional English of the Former Inhabitants of Cades Cove in the Great Smoky Mountains</title>
<publication-date>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jones</lname>
<fname>M.</fname>
<mname>Jean</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cades Cove is the largest pastoral region in the Great Smoky Mountains. Surrounded on all sides by formidable ridges, the Cove remained isolated from the outside world for over a century. Inhabitated by a rugged group of settlers who came from farther north in the early nineteenth century, the Cove was home for a thriving and homogeneous culture until the 1940&#39;s, when the last residents were forced to leave in order that the National Park be established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two significant factors influenced the undertaking of this investigation of Cades Cove Regional English: first, the absence of comprehensive, accurate, and comparable linguistic data for the South, especially the Southern mountains; second, the fact that Cades Cove speakers, untutored and isolated during a period in which this country witnessed tremendous growth and industrialization, represent many survival forms of the English language. Furthermore, the timely and carefully-wrought formulation of &quot;Questionnaire for the Investigation of American Regional English: Based on the Work Sheets of the Linguistic Atlas of the United States and Canada&quot; by Harold Orton and Nathalia Wright allows for uniform elicitations and collation of mountain dialect, comparable with other regional surveys based on the LAUSC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cades Cover Regional English is characterized by a fairly persistent pattern of vowel fluctuation--front vowels tending primarily to be raised; back vowels tending primarily to be lowered; both front and back vowels tending to be centralized--and by the diphthonging of short vowels, particularly under stress. The dialect is further characterized by survival forms of grammar and vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present investigation was designed and completed as preliminary methodology and research for further investigation of Southern Mountain speech based on the Orton-Wright Questionnaire. It is, furthermore, a sampling investigation of Tennessee Regional English comparable with completed and current surveys based on the Work Sheets for other regions of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1622</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3048&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1622</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3048</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-06-14T11:59:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4226198</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1622</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Harold Orton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nathalia Wright, Bain Tate Stewart, Allen Yeomans</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>