<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Field Experiences with the Division of Nutrition in the Wisconsin State Board of Health</title>
<publication-date>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dow</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This report is based upon observations and experiences during a seven weeks&#39; period of field training with the Division of Nutrition in the Wisconsin State Board of Health in Madison, Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the field training was to supplement the on-campus academic education in Public Health Nutrition with practical nutrition experiences and observation. More specifically, the purpose was to help the student-nutritionist gain an understanding of the function of a state nutrition staff that works through a decentralized, district organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A varied program was planned by the Director of the Division of Nutrition to help the student accomplish these objectives. Four and one-half weeks were spent in five of the eight district health offices, and the remaining time was spent in the central office in Madison. Information was obtained on organization, history, programs, and services of the Division of Nutrition by reading state publications and reports and by having conferences with the nutrition director and the district nutritionists. The student-nutritionist observed and participated in field visits, in-service education and training classes, interdisciplinary team conferences, and the annual meeting of the Wisconsin Dietetic Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student-nutritionist gained an understanding of the function of a state nutrition staff that works through a decentralized, district organization. She also became aware of the way in which each district nutritionist develops the nutrition program to meet the needs and interests of the people in the district. The student-nutritionist gained an appreciation of how important records and reports are for a continuous nutrition program. It was possible for the student to comprehend some of the changes which have occurred in the nutrition program emphasis since the division was organized in 1938. The student feels that she has a clearer concept of a large state nutrition program than she had before her field experience, and that this experience will enable her to become a better public health nutritionist.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3943</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5431&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3943</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5431</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-09T11:31:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9098255</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3943</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Beth Duncan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Harold H. Walker, Florence L. MacCleod</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>