<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Using GIS to Identify At-Risk Populations of Military-Generated Dust</title>
<publication-date>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dayers3@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ayers</lname>
<fname>Darcy Ann</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geographic Information Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Human Geography</discipline>
<discipline>Nature and Society Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Physical and Environmental Geography</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Cultural Anthropology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;This project uses GIS and an anthropological perspective to identify local populations surrounding Pohakuloa Training Area (PTA) that are most at risk from military vehicle-generated dust. Using ArcGIS, the following data was analyzed in order to better understand impacts from dust on the local population: • Prevailing wind rose data from National Water and Climate Center under the USDA National Resources Conservation Service, • Digital Elevation Model (DEM) map of the island provided by National Elevation Dataset from USGS, and • The US Census data of the local population distribution surrounding the military base at PTA. When studying demographics, I evaluated the spatial distribution and density of the adjacent population. The resulting GIS data was a combination of my own dust dispersion estimates (from wind, topography, and distance from source) with my demographic research in order to determine the risk associated with populations on the island of Hawaii. The current populations being subjected to high levels of dust exposure were identified and quantified through a rudimentary algorithm relating the variables considered. The resulting map portrayed the spatial distribution of the generated dust across the island and identified the populations which will be experiencing significant impacts due to the dust dispersion.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2015/artsandsciences/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1087&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1087</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-05-14T11:24:18-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_eureca/article/1087/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>7104427</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2015/artsandsciences/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>Arts and Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Hyun Kim</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-13T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2015-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>