<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ranking the components of ecological resistance to biological invaders : an experimental manipulation in a southern Appalachian riparian forest.</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Von Holle</lname>
<fname>MaryBeth.</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The theory that communities can withStand introductions of non-natives is called “ecological resistance,” which was hypothesized to consist of three interdependent elements: (1) environmental resistance, which may be mediated through natural disturbances; (2) biotic resistance, which is a consequence of plant adaptive strategies; and (3) demographic resistance, which may be expressed as differential dispersal and establishment. I separated the influences of natural disturbance, biotic resistance, and demographic resistance and ranked their contributions to ecological resistance with a field experiment. This research was conducted at Big Stony Creek, a naturally flooded system within the Jefferson National Forest in southwestern Virginia. I manipulated resident diversities and functional group representation along a disturbance gradient and planted differing quantities of invaders into these manipulated plots. Success of an invasion was measured by survivorship and growth of the invader.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6326</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8278&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6326</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8278</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450434</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6326</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel Simberloff</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Hazel R. Delcourt, Louis J. Gross, Sharon H. Hermann, Wilfred M. Post III, Jake F. Weltzin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>