<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of the Development of Services, Facilities, and Professional Standards of Catholic Charities of Tennessee, Inc., 1962 - 1967</title>
<publication-date>1968-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Junod</lname>
<fname>Louis</fname>
<mname>Jules</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this paper is to study the development of the social welfare program of Catholic Charities of Tennessee, Inc., from 1962 to 1967 and to determine if development ha resulted in improved services, facilities, and professional standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material for this study was gathered by personally interviewing the top executive at each agency. Also, except in East Tennessee, the locations were visited, employees talked with, and facilities observed. In addition, the central files of the Executive Office of Catholic Charities of Tennessee, Inc., the files of the area offices, and the central files of the diocesan chancery office were utilized in the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study determines that a positive development has occurred in the services, facilities, and professional standards of the social welfare program of Catholic Charities of Tennessee, Inc., from 1962 to 1967. The development has overcome the major problems faced by the organization in 1962. The study indicates that the priests&#39; potential and the agency potential is held latent by a centralization of authority in the Executive Office. The study concludes with the recognization that the present state of growth permits greater emphasis to be placed upon the development of the priests&#39; and agencies&#39; potential.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4430</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5927&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4430</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5927</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-17T11:48:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9881037</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4430</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard Gene Vance</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roberta M. Hampton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>