<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Asymmetric Total Synthesis of Congeners of Hydramycin, an Anthraquinone-Type Antitumor Agent</title>
<publication-date>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ncostyl@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Njiojob</lname>
<fname>Costyl Ngnouomeuchi</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>asymmetric congeners of hydramycin from sharpless</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Heterocyclic Compounds</discipline>
<discipline>Organic Chemicals</discipline>
<discipline>Polycyclic Compounds</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Hydramycin is an antitumor antibiotic isolated from &lt;em&gt;Streptomyces violaceus&lt;/em&gt;.  It is a pyranoanthraquinone-type antitumor agent that has shown  broad-spectrum activity against a variety of human-derived cancer cell  lines. Among tumors evaluated at the National Cancer Institute (lung,  colon, melanoma, breast and prostate), GI&lt;sub&gt;50&lt;/sub&gt;s were &lt;10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt; M in the NCI&#39;s 60-cell-line panel. We embarked on the synthesis and  evaluation of a simplified congener 2-(1-hydroxy-1-(oxiran-2-yl)ethyl)-4&lt;em&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;-naphtho[2,3-&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;]chromene-4,7,12-trione(&lt;strong&gt;17&lt;/strong&gt;),  which would facilitate synthesis while retaining the potent activity.  Hydramycin has two chiral centers, and our goal is to design and  synthesize all the possible enantiomers (four in total) for the congener  of hydramycin &lt;strong&gt;17&lt;/strong&gt; in order to ascertain which of the  enantiomers is responsible for the observed antitumor activity.  The use  of enantiospecific techniques such as the Sharpless epoxidation was  initially tried to introduce the chiral centers at a later stage during  the multi-step synthesis and obtain the required pure enantiomers. Due  to some limitations observed with this technique and many other  asymmetric epoxidation techniques which utilize very substrate-specific  ligands, we then modified the synthetic scheme to use another procedure,  the Sharpless asymmetric dihydroxylation in order to obtain two of the  pure enantiomers of this congener of hydramycin.  The other two  enantiomers are selectively obtained using the Sharpless asymmetric  dihydroxylation procedure via cyclic sulfate intermediates, followed by a  modified irreversible Payne rearrangement procedure.  These routes then  allowed us to obtain separately all four stereoisomers, each having  more than 90% &lt;em&gt;ee&lt;/em&gt; as determined on chiral columns with HPLC. The  four stereoisomers have been fully characterized and will then be  tested separately to ascertain which of the isomers is responsible for  the observed antitumor activity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1210</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2363&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1210</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2363</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-03T19:51:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2330060</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1210</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David C. Baker</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Shawn Campagna, Ben Xue, Elizabeth Howell</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-09T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>