<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effectiveness of Coupons on the Decision to Purchase in the Full-Service Dining Segment of the Restaurant Industry</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Poisson</lname>
<fname>Donetta</fname>
<mname>Kay</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The National Restaurant Association (1999) indicates that coupons are the second most likely marketing tactic to be utilized in the restaurant industry (Hsu &amp; Powers, 2002). Coupons are a part of marketing a product because the consumer perceives savings (Lichtenstein &amp; Netemeyer, 1991). Customers are the vital driving force in the hospitality industry and it is what customers think and feel, not what the operators or corporations do that defines the &lt;em&gt;marketing&lt;/em&gt; orientation (Hsu, &amp; Powers, 2002). Whether customers are generated through creating new ones, stealing them from competitors or they are bound by loyalty, the hospitality industry requires customers for survival (Lewis, &amp; Chambers, 2000). Although they are viable marketing strategy, improperly used, the coupon promotions could have a negative impact (Hsu &amp; Powers, 2002). Coupons are often used in service companies, but little is known as to their influence. The bulk of the information provided encompasses retail couponing and may serve as a basis for better understanding how coupons affect the food service industry (Taylor, 2000). There are two consumer choices; purchase or nonpurchase (Gonul &amp; Srinivasan, 1996).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study investigates the use of coupons on the decision process to purchase, as well as the consumer’s motivations, behaviors and attitudes toward coupons in the full-service restaurant segment. A research instrument was completed by a randomized sample of 246 consumers in the Knoxville, TN market. Further a purchase or no purchase experiment as conducted with the sample and an additional population. The results from both interventions were analyzed and applied to implications effecting the full-service dining segment of the restaurant industry. Consumers report they want coupons to be available. However, the results of this study indicate coupons not be well utilized.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4444</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5955&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4444</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5955</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-31T12:44:28-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9956468</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4444</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John Antun</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Steve Morse, Carol A. Costello</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Consumer Services Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>