<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthesis of Palladium-Based Electrocatalysis—From Pure Metal to Bimetallic Nanoparticles</title>
<publication-date>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hgao4@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Gao</lname>
<fname>Haijun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Synthesis</keyword>
<keyword>Palladium</keyword>
<keyword>Electrocatalysis</keyword>
<keyword>Bimetallic Nanoparticles.</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Inorganic Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Materials Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis focuses on synthesis and characterization of palladium-based nanoparticles. Background information of the research in this thesis is provided in Chapter 1. Preparation and characterization of pure palladium nanoparticles are presented in Chapter 2. A fast and convenient method to prepare ultra small Pd nanoparticles via Pluronic P123 reduction is discussed in detail. Impregnation method and poly method are also studied in this chapter. Chapter 3 reports the studies of these methods to prepare ultra small bimetallic (bimetallic means a mixture of two metals) palladium-based nanoparticles. Oleylamine-mediated method used Pd nanoparticles prepared via P123 reduction as precursor. Ultra small palladium-based nanoparticles are prepared in this way. With the assistance of trioctylphosphine complex as precursor, tiny palladium-based bimetallic nanoparticles can be prepared with certain structure. The structure of these bimetallic nanoparticles gives a better electrochemical activity than pure palladium nanoparticles. When loaded on mesoporous carbon, these tiny trioctylphosphine-assisted palladium nanoparticles displayed good thermal stability.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1378</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2492&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1378</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2492</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-08-08T05:50:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3189466</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1378</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sheng Dai</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>George Schweitzer, Michael Sepaniak</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>