<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of Hiking Poles on Performance and Physiological Variables During Mountain Climbing</title>
<publication-date>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Duckham</lname>
<fname>Rachel</fname>
<mname>Louise</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Exercise Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of this study was to compare performance when hiking with and without poles during a maximal effort mountain ascent. In addition, the study determined if there were differences in physiological responses, such as heart rate, estimated energy expenditure, and blood lactate accumulation. 15 physically active men and women (mean age 29±6) hiked with and without walking poles up a 4-km trail ( 426-meter elevation gain). Performance was determined by the time taken to reach the top of the mountain. In addition, differences in physiological variables including heart rate (HR), estimated energy expenditure (EE), and blood lactate accumulation were measured. When hiking with or without poles, there were no significant differences found for any of the variables tested. Time-to-completion (53.24 ± 5.31 vs. 52.74 ± 4.47 min) and blood lactate (LA) accumulation (6.23 ± 2.5 vs. 7.23 ± 3.88 mmol/l) were similar with and without poles, respectively. Similarly, no differences were seen for HRmax, average HR, and estimated EE, all variables displayed by the Polar heart watch. In conclusion, performance and physiological responses do not differ when hiking with and without poles on a 4-km mountain ascent. However the subjects reported informally that the poles reduced the lower back and lower extremity pain the day following the hike. Even though no significant differences were found in the ratings of perceived exertion between the two conditions (poles vs. no poles, respectively) 14 out of 15 subjects indicated in a follow up interview that they felt the poles made the effort easier.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4466</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5996&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4466</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5996</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-11T12:15:16-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10006785</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4466</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Eugene Fitzhugh, Edward T. Howley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Exercise Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>