<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Empirical Analysis of Factors Impacting Turnover Intention and Termination Intention among Manufacturing Workers</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>yli82@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Yuting</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Job Satisfaction</keyword>
<keyword>Organizational Commitment</keyword>
<keyword>Leadership</keyword>
<keyword>Job performance</keyword>
<keyword>Work-family conflict</keyword>
<keyword>Turnover Intention</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate how turnover intention relates to job satisfaction, organizational commitment, leadership, job performance, work-family conflict among manufacturing workers in Tennessee, USA. A causal model was proposed and a turnover intention survey questionnaire was set up for manufacturing workers. The data was collected from a large manufacturing company in the East Tennessee area and was analyzed by SPSS and Structural Equation Modeling (SEM). The results of our study indicated that job satisfaction and organizational commitment have negatively and significantly affected the manufacturing worker’s turnover intention while the work-family conflict has positively and significantly affected turnover intention. Although leadership indirectly influences turnover intention, its efforts on turnover intention were fully mediated by job satisfaction and organizational commitment. No effect of job performance on turnover intention was found in this study based on the manufacturing workers. The results suggested that policies for enhancing worker job satisfaction and organizational commitment, balancing work-family conflict, and improving leadership style should be proposed to reduce turnover intention. The relationship between factors and termination intention were also investigated in this study. Moreover, the results indicated that job performance and role conflict are the determinants of the manufacturing workers’ termination intention. The results suggested that management needs to improve their worker&#39;s job performance and reduce their role conflict and then decrease the workers’ termination intention.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5470</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7006&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5470</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7006</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545516</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5470</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rapinder Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Kobza, James Simonton, Timothy Munyon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>