<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Publish in Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology – Article processing charges are only paid by those who can afford it</title>
<publication-date>2003-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>buko@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee Graduate School of Medicine</institution>
<lname>Bukovsky</lname>
<fname>Antonin</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Texas A&amp;M University</institution>
<lname>Bazer</lname>
<fname>Fuller</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Editorial&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic journals are the basis of a world of purely electronic scientific communication. Just imagine, no more bookshelves and mountains of disorganized paperwork, no more late nights organizing and searching for articles of interest. For most active research-oriented students and scientists this is already a reality, or will be in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most &#39;top ranked&#39; traditional journals now offer web access to recent publications, and to less or more of their archives, not everyone has the luxury of access through their university, or has his/her subscription paid for, or can afford to pay US $30–35 for an electronic reprint. Traditionally, journals generated their revenue from individual subscribers, private and/or state owned institutions, page charges from authors, and charges for color illustrations. Consequently, the traditional science publishing industry limited access to scientific publications to scientists in the developed countries while, in many cases, leaving the rest of the world unattended.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_biolpubs/27</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1026&amp;amp;context=utk_biolpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>27</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1026</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-15T08:03:56-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- General Biology</publication-title>
<context-key>4312448</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_biolpubs/27</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology 2003, 1:56 doi:10.1186/1477-7827-1-56</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>