<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Synthesis and Characterization of Magnetic Nanowires Prepared by Chemical Vapor Deposition</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>stang3@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tang</lname>
<fname>Siwei</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>helimagnetic</keyword>
<keyword>skyrmion</keyword>
<keyword>nanowires</keyword>
<keyword>spin density wave</keyword>
<keyword>CVD</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Condensed Matter Physics</discipline>
<discipline>Other Materials Science and Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Various metal silicide and germanide magnetic nanowires were synthesized using a home-built CVD [chemical vapor deposition] system. The morphology, composition, and magnetic properties of the nanowires were studied and correlated with growth parameters such as temperature, pressure, time, and source-substrate distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the compositions targeted for synthesis was MnSi [manganese silicide]. In bulk, this material orders helimagnetically at T&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt; [curie temperature] = 30K, with a helical pitch of about 20 nm. After extensive study, we learned that the thickness of the silicon dioxide layer on the substrate is a critical parameter for the growth of MnSi nanowires. An oxide assisted one-dimensional growth mechanism was proposed. A growth diagram was created that shows the effect of various growth parameters on the products. The nanowires were characterized magnetically in a SQUID [superconducting quantum interference device] magnetometer using AC [alternating current] susceptibility. These measurements confirmed helimagnetic ordering and skyrmion lattice formation in the nanowires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another composition targeted for synthesis was FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; [iron digermanide]. In bulk, FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; undergoes a spin density wave transition at 289 K. Nanowires of FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; have not been previously reported. We were able to grow FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowires on a Ge substrate. The FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowires were identified by selected area diffraction using a transmission electron microscope. The growth direction was determined to be [110]. FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowires were integrated into four-probe nanodevices, which were fabricated through an e-beam lithography system via beam dose correction and a double-layer geometry. The combined magnetic and electronic transport measurements show that while the antiferromagnetic spin density wave is still present along the FeGe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; nanowire long axis, ferromagnetism was identified in other directions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2777</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4130&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2777</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4130</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-04-14T13:10:39-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4130/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5479581</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2777</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David G Mandrus</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Zheng  Gai, David C Joy, Bin Hu</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Materials Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>