<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of ozone, treatment temperature, and antimicrobials on inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella spp. in apple cider and orange juice</title>
<publication-date>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>Charles</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The studies presented in this dissertation were conducted to determine the effect of ozone, treatment temperature, and antimicrobials on the inactivation of Escherichia coli O157:H7 and Salmonella spp. in apple cider and orange juice. In the first experiment, inactivation of£. coli O157:H7 and Salmonella in apple cider and orange juice treated with ozone was evaluated. A five-strain mixture of E.coli O157:H7 or Salmonella was inoculated (7 log cfu/ml) into apple cider and orange juice. Ozone (0.9 g ozone/h) was pumped into juices maintained at 4°C, ambient temperature (~20°C), and 50°C for up to 30 min (Salmonella/50°C), 75 min (E. coli/50°C), 180 min (apple cider/4°C) or 240 min (orangejuice/4°C and ambient). Samples were withdrawn, diluted in 0.1 % peptone water, neutralized with 1.0 N NaOH, and surface plated onto recovery media. Recovery of£. coli O157:H7 was compared on tryptic soy (TSA), sorbitol MacConkey (SMAC), hemorrhagic coli (HC), and modified eosin methylene blue (MEMB) agars; recovery of Salmonella was compared on TSA, bismuth sulfite (BSA), and XLT4 agars. After treatment at so·c, £. coli O157:H7 populations were reduced to the limit of detection ( 1.0 log cfu/ml) in 45, 30, 45, and 30 min in apple cider, and 75, 60, 60, and 45 min in orange juice, as determined on TSA, HC, MEMB, and SMAC, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6466</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8440&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6466</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8440</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T07:10:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>24075152</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6466</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David A. Golden</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>F. Ann Draughon, Alan G. Matthew, John R. Mount</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>