<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pharmacokinetics of orally administered tramadol in domestic rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus)</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>S</lname>
<fname>Marcy</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Greenacre</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cox</lname>
<fname>S</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE:To determine the pharmacokinetics of an orally administered dose of tramadol in domestic rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus). ANIMALS: 6 healthy adult sexually intact female New Zealand White rabbits. PROCEDURES: Physical examinations and plasma biochemical analyses were performed to ensure rabbits were healthy prior to the experiment. Rabbits were anesthetized with isoflurane, and IV catheters were placed in a medial saphenous or jugular vein for collection of blood samples. One blood sample was collected before treatment with tramadol. Rabbits were allowed to recover from anesthesia a minimum of 1 hour before treatment. Then, tramadol (11 mg/kg, PO) was administered once, and blood samples were collected at various time points up to 360 minutes after administration. Blood samples were analyzed with high-performance liquid chromatography to determine plasma concentrations of tramadol and its major metabolite (O-desmethyltramadol). RESULTS: No adverse effects were detected after oral administration of tramadol to rabbits. Mean +/- SD half-life of tramadol after administration was 145.4 +/- 81.0 minutes; mean +/- SD maximum plasma concentration was 135.3 +/- 89.1 ng/mL. CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL RELEVANCE: Although the dose of tramadol required to provide analgesia in rabbits is unknown, the dose administered in the study reported here did not reach a plasma concentration of tramadol or O-desmethyltramadol that would provide sufficient analgesia in humans for clinically acceptable periods. Many factors may influence absorption of orally administered tramadol in rabbits.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/9</coverpage-url>
<label>9</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-27T11:40:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>1288701</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/9</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Marcy J. Souza, C B. Greenacre, and S Cox. &quot;Pharmacokinetics of orally administered tramadol in domestic rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus)&quot; American journal of veterinary research 69.8 (2008): 979-982.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://avmajournals.avma.org/doi/abs/10.2460/ajvr.69.8.979?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%3dncbi.nlm.nih.gov</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>American Journal of Veterinary Research</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>