<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Use of Sodium Bicarbonate in Complete Rations for Lactating Cows</title>
<publication-date>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Bogart</lname>
<fname>Brian</fname>
<mname>C.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Sixty-two Holstein cows were assigned to respective treatments of a randomized complete block design three days postpartum. Complete rations, formulated to meet NRC requirement, were fed during the first 112 days of lactation. Diets contained, on an as-fed basis, 75% corn silage and 25% pelleted concentrate (CS:PC) or (CS:PC) + .5% feed grade sodium bicarbonate added as a percent of the total ration (CS:PC+). In addition, each cow received 5 lb of alfalfa-grass hay daily (as fed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data collected weekly included milk yield (1b/d), milk fat (percent), 4% fat corrected milk (1b/d), ration dry matter intake (percent of body weight), and total dry matter intake (percent of body weight). Least-square means values of these parameters were 62.76, 3.30, 56.26. 2.09, 2.44, and 60.91, 3.42, 55.66, 2.19, 2.55 for CS:PC and CS:PC+, respectively. Significant treatment differences were not observed between diets (P &gt; .05). Rumen fluid, blood, and additional milk samples were collected at monthly intervals from 27 cows randomly chosen from the total. Acetate-to-proportionate ratio and rumen pH values were 2.85, 6.45, and 2.66, 6.31 for CS:PC and CS:PC+, respectively. Blood serum Ca, P, Mg and Na values (mg/100 ml) were 9.44, 5.25, 2.22, 403.13, and 10.09, 5.40, 2.14 405.37 for CS:PC and CS:PC+, respectively. Least-square mean values for milk protein (percent), total solids (percent), and solids-not-fat (percent) were 3.95, 12.13, 8.87, and 3.98, 11.93, 8.53 for CS:PC and CS:PC+, respectively. No significant differences could be attributed to diets on data collection monthly (P &gt; .05).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of this study indicate that incorporation of .5% sodium bicarbonate to complete rations was neither efficacious nor detrimental to dairy cows in early lactation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3012</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4386&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3012</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4386</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-12-12T09:39:04-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6457731</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3012</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Monty J. Montgomery</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. N. Heitman, C. C. Chamberlin</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1982-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>