<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Advanced Radiation Detection Devices: 3D Diamond Detectors and KSr2I5:Eu Scintillating Crystals</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>twulz@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wulz</lname>
<fname>Thomas</fname>
<mname>Greogry</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Diamond</keyword>
<keyword>Radiation Detector</keyword>
<keyword>Semiconductor</keyword>
<keyword>CERN</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;First, the radiation detection charge collection properties have been determined for four diamonds with each diamond having received a fluence of 1 MeV neutron irradiation. Photoluminescence measurements were conducted at 150 K on the most irradiated diamond, revealing information about the energies of optically-active defect centers created by the neutron radiation. Then, two diamond plates, one single-crystal and the other polycrystalline, were processed using the bulk microstructural modification technique of femtosecond-pulsed laser machining. Deep reactive ion etching of the samples revealed that the laser-treated channels etch considerably faster than the surrounding diamond. Next, to create through-diamond vias (TDVs) in diamond plates, deep reactive ion etching techniques similar to those employed in the silicon industry for creating through-silicon vias were utilized. Two different diamonds, one optical-grade and one detector-grade, were used to establish a repeatable process for etching holes completely through diamond. A stainless steel foil was found to be an effective and robust etching mask for creating TDVs with an aspect ratio of 5.0. Electroplating was used to fill the TDVs with a highly conductive chromium metal. The TDVs were connected with interdigitated strips on the surface of the diamond, establishing for the first time a 3D diamond radiation detector with fully metal electrodes. Lastly, the spatial uniformity of the light emission produced by a relatively new scintillation crystal composed of potassium strontium iodide activated with europium has been explored.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4670</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5191&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4670</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5191</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-26T06:01:17-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/5191/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>8221755</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4670</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Eric D. Lukosi</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stefan Spanier, Maik Lang, Lawrence Heilbronn</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nuclear Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>