<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Pedometer-measured physical activity in elementary school children</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Sefchick</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to assess how many steps per day Elementary school children take. Specifically, the study sought to (a) determine the average number of steps per day that are taken in children from kindergarten through fifth grade; (b) to estimate the percentage of children who meet the President&#39;s challenge standards for step counting; and ( c) to ascertain if there is a correlation between steps per day and body mass index. Additionally, physical activity was assessed using the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES III) and these scores were compared with step counts from the pedometer. A total of 110 children (54 boys and 56 girls) between the ages of five and eleven years old were used in the final assessment of step counts from original 131 participants from baseline. Participants completed the physical activity section of the youth questionnaire (NHANES Ill) and wore a pedometer (NL-2000) for seven consecutive days except while showering, swimming or sleeping. The average number of steps per day was 11,429 for boys and 11,180 for girls. Children took significantly fewer steps per day on Sunday than on other days of the week (p&lt;0.001). When grades were put into groups of Kindergarten and first grade (Kil); second and third (2/3) grade; fourth and fifth grade (4/5) found that Kil was significantly took more steps compared to 4/5 (p=0.003). The President&#39;s Council on Physical Fitness and Sports has set a standard of=&gt; 11,000 steps/day for girls and =&gt;13,000 steps/day for boys to receive an activity award. Forty-two percent of girls met this recommendation while only 35.2% boys met this recommendation. A significant correlation (r=-0.212) was found between step counts and BMI (p&lt; 0.05). These results suggest that pedometers can be used to monitor physical activity in children over seven days, and that only a minority of children are meeting the national recommendation set forth in the President&#39;s challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5291</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6699&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5291</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6699</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847207</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5291</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David R. Bassett Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>