<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Application of fractal algorithms of coastline echo’s generation on marine radar simulator</title>
<publication-date>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ji</lname>
<fname>Shuguang</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Tangshan Maritime Safety Administration of People&#39;s Republic of China</institution>
<lname>Zhang</lname>
<fname>Zhang</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Hongbiao</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Police University of China</institution>
<lname>Liu</lname>
<fname>Dan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sawhney</lname>
<fname>Rapinder</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Marine radar simulator</keyword>
<keyword>Coastline echo</keyword>
<keyword>Fractal algorithm</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Background: Marine radar simulator is a useful approach endorsed by International Maritime Organization (IMO) to train the seafarers on how to operate marine radar equipment and use marine radar equipment for positioning and collision avoidance in laboratory. To fulfill all of the marine radar simulator training requirements, a high performance simulator is necessary. However, imperfections with currently available marine radar simulators require simulator developers to make improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case Description: In this study, improved fractal algorithms (random Koch curve, fractional Brownian motion, and Weierstrass-Mandelbrot function) are applied to generate natural-looking radar echoes on a marine radar simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion and evaluation: From the results of the simulations, we can observe that the structures of the coastline echoes generated by improved fractal algorithms, especially by fractional Brownian motion algorithm, outperform the echoes generated by conventional method in representing a natural coastline feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions: Based on evaluations from a panel of experienced mariners, we conclude that the coastline echoes simulated by fractal algorithms better represent a natural coastline feature than those generated by conventional methods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_indupubs/22</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1026&amp;amp;context=utk_indupubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>22</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1026</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-10-14T06:01:46-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Industrial &amp; Information Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>9266119</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_indupubs/22</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Ji, S., Zhang, Z., Yang, H., Liu, D., &amp; Sawhney, R. (2016). Application of fractal algorithms of coastline echo’s generation on marine radar simulator. Visualization in Engineering, 4(1), 1.
doi: 10.1186/s40327-016-0037-7</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1186/s40327-016-0037-7</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-12T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Visualization in Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>