<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Insights into archaeal evolution and symbiosis from the genomes of a nanoarchaeon and its inferred crenarchaeal host from Obsidian Pool, Yellowstone National Park</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mpodar@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Podar</lname>
<fname>Mircea</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
<lname>Makarova</lname>
<fname>Kira</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>dgraha13@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Graham</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
<lname>Wolf</lname>
<fname>Yuri</fname>
<mname>I.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>National Institutes of Health</institution>
<lname>Koonin</lname>
<fname>Eugene</fname>
<mname>V.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Portland State University</institution>
<lname>Reysenbach</lname>
<fname>Anna-Louise</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Archaea evolution</keyword>
<keyword>Single cell genomics</keyword>
<keyword>Symbiosis</keyword>
<keyword>Hyperthermophiles</keyword>
<keyword>Split genes</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Microbiology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single cultured marine organism, &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeum equitans&lt;/em&gt;, represents the &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt; branch of symbiotic Archaea, with a highly reduced genome and unusual features such as multiple split genes.  &lt;h4&gt;Results&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first terrestrial hyperthermophilic member of the &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt; was collected from Obsidian Pool, a thermal feature in Yellowstone National Park, separated by single cell isolation, and sequenced together with its putative host, a &lt;em&gt;Sulfolobales&lt;/em&gt; archaeon. Both the new &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt; (Nst1) and &lt;em&gt;N. equitans&lt;/em&gt; lack most biosynthetic capabilities, and phylogenetic analysis of ribosomal RNA and protein sequences indicates that the two form a deep-branching archaeal lineage. However, the Nst1 genome is more than 20% larger, and encodes a complete gluconeogenesis pathway as well as the full complement of archaeal flagellum proteins. With a larger genome, a smaller repertoire of split protein encoding genes and no split non-contiguous tRNAs, Nst1 appears to have experienced less severe genome reduction than &lt;em&gt;N. equitans.&lt;/em&gt; These findings imply that, rather than representing ancestral characters, the extremely compact genomes and multiple split genes of &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt; are derived characters associated with their symbiotic or parasitic lifestyle. The inferred host of Nst1 is potentially autotrophic, with a streamlined genome and simplified central and energetic metabolism as compared to other &lt;em&gt;Sulfolobales&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;h4&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparison of the &lt;em&gt;N. equitans&lt;/em&gt; and Nst1 genomes suggests that the marine and terrestrial lineages of &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt; share a common ancestor that was already a symbiont of another archaeon. The two distinct &lt;em&gt;Nanoarchaeota&lt;/em&gt;-host genomic data sets offer novel insights into the evolution of archaeal symbiosis and parasitism, enabling further studies of the cellular and molecular mechanisms of these relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/44</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>44</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1044</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-07-10T12:03:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4302175</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/44</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Biology Direct 2013, 8:9 doi:10.1186/1745-6150-8-9</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>