<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Death as a process : human decomposition in an insect-restricted environment</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Tomlinson</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
<mname>Dawn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Many view death as an event; however, the death investigator must perceive death as a process that is catalyzed by cellular breakdown and ultimately results in skeletal remains. Yet, a gap persists in the· understanding of the causal events inherent to the human decomposition process. In order to gain a clearer understanding of these causal events, research must focus on internal factors of decomposition, specifically autolysis and putrefaction. However, in order to observe the contribution of autolysis and putrefaction to the process of human decomposition, external factors proven to grossly manipulate these effects, as perceived by the senses, must be limited. One such external factor is insect activity.  While gathering data for successional analysis of insects affiliated with the decomposition of the baby pig, Sus scrofa Linnaeus, Payne ( 1965) denied insect access to a separate group of pigs. Observing that the decomposition of this group differed from the group exposed to insects, Payne designated an alternative nomenclature for the stages of decomposition specific to the unexposed pigs.  To determine if this nomenclature could be applied to humans in a similar setting, an insect-restricted environment was constructed at the Anthropology Research Facility in Knoxville, Tennessee. Four unembalmed, unautopsied human donations were involved in the study. As two members of the control group were allowed full exposure to the elements, two members of the experimental group were placed inside the structure specifically to monitor autolysis and putrefaction influenced only by environmental conditions and insects that crossed the barrier. Data collection involved observations of the visual and olfactory cues of human decomposition and notations of insects attracted to each subject, including those attempting to cross the constructed barrier. Environmental data (i.e., temperature, humidity, rainfall, sky conditions) was collected in the vicinity of each donation, with special attention attributed to temperature and humidity data collection methods. In order to contemplate each progression, all data specilic to each subject was articulated within the context of the circumstances surrounding each donation. Hence, Bass&#39;s (1997) nomenclature representative of decomposition in a natural and uncontrolled environment served as the default for all subjects, while Payne&#39;s (1965) nomenclature specific to insect-free pigs was considered when addressing the progression of the experimental group.  While the interpretations of the decomposition and insect activity data and the environmental data collection methods were supported by the literature, the ultimate goal was to access the causal events affiliated with internal decomposition. Although the results of this study indicated that the control group members followed Bass&#39;s ( 1997) nomenclature while the experimental group progressed according to Payne&#39;s (1965) nomenclature, both progressions revealed generalized sequential patterns of causal events attributed to autolysis and putrefaction. Such events involving initial indications of generalized skin discoloration, marbling, skin slippage, hair slippage, the purging of fluids, and odor occurred prior to and continued throughout bloating, while dehydration and skeletonization were noted upon deflation and beyond. Adipocere formation, desiccation, and the proliferation of fungi and/or mold were variable. In addition, these patterned events were influenced by temperature, humidity, rainfall, and sky conditions, which consequently affected the rate of decomposition.  Research contributions inherent to this study include support for regional models based on patterns of causal events. Contributions to the death scene investigation involve the recognition of both the visual/olfactory signatures attributed to decomposition and natural versus disrupted insect successional patterns, coupled with suggestions for proper environmental data collection methods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5308</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6716&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5308</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6716</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847250</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5308</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Murray Marks</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>