<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>VaaS: Visualization as a Service</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ahota@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hota</lname>
<fname>Alok</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Scientific Visualization</keyword>
<keyword>Cloud Computing</keyword>
<keyword>Microservice Architecture</keyword>
<keyword>Data Analysis</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Traditional HPC visualization applications provide scientists with scalable solutions to work with large datasets. However, computation today is moving towards cloud-hosted systems, as they present key advantages over traditional HPC cluster systems, primarily that of high availability. Computation on a cloud-hosted system can be accessed on demand without long queue times and without long resource acquisition times. Existing applications cannot be ported to the cloud as they rely on a monolithic application structure that does not flexibly distribute among virtual cloud instances.In this dissertation, I study the architectural decisions required to transition scientific data analysis and visualization into the cloud. In particular, I focus on a microservice-based architecture model, designed to use loosely couple modular components using a limited communication model. This general scheme allows scalability and flexibility on cloud-hosted systems, and provides &lt;i&gt;Visualization as a Service&lt;/i&gt; that can be deployed on-demand. I present working prototype solutions to the challenges of large data storage and working set management, loosely-coupled rendering and analysis services, and visualization records keeping and reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5444</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6980&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5444</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6980</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-14T08:42:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>16545482</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5444</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jian Huang</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jens Gregor, Mark Dean, Russell Zaretzki, Bradley Vander Zanden</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3595-3253</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Computer Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>