<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>THE LIVED RESETTLEMENT EXPERIENCE FOR SINGLE REFUGEE MOTHERS FROM THE DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF CONGO</title>
<publication-date>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>loppizzi@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mefford</lname>
<fname>Lauren</fname>
<mname>Michelle</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>single motherhood</keyword>
<keyword>motherhood</keyword>
<keyword>Congo</keyword>
<keyword>women</keyword>
<keyword>refugee</keyword>
<keyword>resettle</keyword>
<keyword>resettlement</keyword>
<keyword>resettlement experience</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Public Health and Community Nursing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;At least 72% of the 50,000 Congolese refugees resettled in the USA in the last 5 years are women and children. Many are single refugee mothers (SRM) disadvantaged by obstacles (i.e., childcare) that hinder them from becoming self-sufficient within the required timeframe post-resettlement. Published research on resettlement has focused general challenges, but an understanding of the unique needs and perspectives of SRMs is lacking. This phenomenological, qualitative study provides insight into the lived resettlement experience for SRMs from the Democratic of Congo (DRC). Participants (n=7) were recruited from a refugee resettlement agency in East Tennessee and partook in open-ended, unstructured interviews lasting from 45-60 minutes, mediated by an interpreter. A university Transdisciplinary Phenomenology Research Group verified accuracy of data analysis. Participants’ median age was 36 years, most had 3-4 children, and the length of time living in the US ranged from 1 to 5 years. The story of the lived resettlement experience for Congolese SRMs begins with life in Africa, the place they once called home and knew as “normal” before moving to the US. Life with family and friends in Africa colored their experiences postresettlement, thus, the theme “From Collective Survival to Lone Motherhood in a Precarious World” is the central theme. In essence, the meaning of the experience can be vividly seen among four interrelated figural themes within the central theme: “Powerlessness/’I Want to be in Charge of my Own Life’”; “Alone in America/Connection”; “Perpetual Loss &amp; Betrayal/Miraculous Provision”; and “Worry/’Little by Little’”. The role of resettlement agency was critical to sustaining hope. vii Practice implications surround supporting SRMs throughout resettlement to bolster their overall physical and mental health. Current resettlement policies inconsistently address SRMs’ needs, though there are precedents and provisions that organizations can implement. Research is needed to understand best practices to support SRMs post-resettlement, resettlement experiences for children of SRMs, and resettlement issues of SRMs versus other refugee women (e.g., women-at-risk, married refugee women, etc.). Overall, greater attention should be given to SRMs in practice, policy, and research in order to improve the resettlement experience and likelihood for successful integration for this population.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6175</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7355&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6175</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7355</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-09-10T12:20:43-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/7355/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>19331980</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6175</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sandra P. Thomas</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sandra Thomas, Sandra Mixer, Lisa Davenport, Solange Muñoz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nursing</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2021-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>