<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Unity in the Black Community</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-08T12:20:37-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cdzingir@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Dzingira</lname>
<fname>Cecilia Uhlezipi Shamis</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>African American Studies</discipline>
<discipline>African History</discipline>
<discipline>African Languages and Societies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Dzingira, Cecilia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black Issues Conference 2012&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unity in the Black Community&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: As an African American student who attends a pre-dominantly White Institution, I’ve found that the importance of unity is much more greater than we allow it to appear; by “We” I am referring to the African-American population that rests within the University’s community. When a new student is admitted into the University, it is not difficult that not only is there segregation between all races of students, but also within the different races lays a much deeper separation. Because of these issues that rise within communities daily, I’ve chosen to present on the topic “Unity in the Black Community”. I believe that in order for us to be united with other races that surround us, we much find unity within ourselves as a people, while working towards accepting each other’s diversity. &lt;strong&gt;Methods: &lt;/strong&gt;To present the importance of this information to my fellow peers, I’ve constructed a Demonstration through PowerPoint that entails more in depth details about what Unity is, how we can work towards implementing it within our society, and the benefits that are brought by it should we succeed in it. Along with the PowerPoint presentation, I’ve also added visual aid (videos) than can aid my audience in better understanding why unity is important and the benefits it has on us as individuals and as people together. &lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; Educating the Black Community about Unity is important for strength, prosperity, and communication within ourselves. It not only is beneficial for today’s generation, but it helps us mold better lives for generations to come. Lets be united and make bigger differences in our communities than those that take place now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“A House divided is a House that cannot Stand”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that my presentation will effectively educate the African-American people about the importance of our uniting. When people are being asked to change their ways for the goodness of humanity, 90% of the time, they ask why? And How? I have put together a presentation that includes definitions, quotes, pictures, and videos about how the Black culture can effectively work towards uniting with one another. As schools, the workplace, and communities continue to segregate, it is helpful for people to come together and be as “one” to improve our culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outline&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A). Raised Fist: the background information about the “raised fist” and what it represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B). Definition of Unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity in Schools&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A)    Do you think that there is unity on campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B)    Class socialization between Greeks, Religious Groups, Organizations, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C)    You Tube Video about “Visions of Black Schools Uniting”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity in the Workplace&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A).  Do African Americans segregate themselves in the workplace?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B). Do we uplift one another enough at work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity in the Communities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A). School zoning, Transportation, Food, and Housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B).  Make a Difference Chart: Explains the little effort that the African American youth from ages 15-25 give to make a difference in their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C). “How Can we Foster Unity in the Black Community” video: correlates all the information taught by giving more in depth examples of improvements in the Black Community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A)    Everyone will be given a notecard handout with the  “Black Child’s Pledge” typed on it and I will lead a discussion about each line or stanza and its importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B)    The Poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black Child&#39;s Pledge &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pledge allegiance to my Black People.  I pledge to develop my mind and body to the greatest extent possible.  I will learn all that I can in order to give my best to my People in their struggle for liberation.  I will keep myself physically fit, building a strong body free from drugs and other substances which weaken me and make me less capable of protecting myself, my family and my Black brothers and sisters.  I will unselfishly share my knowledge and understanding with them in order to bring about change more quickly.  I will discipline myself to direct my energies thoughtfully and constructively rather than wasting them in idle hatred.  I will train myself never to hurt or allow others to harm my Black brothers and sisters for I recognize that we need every Black Man, Woman, and Child to be physically, mentally and psychologically strong.  These principles I pledge to practice daily and to teach them to others in order to unite my People.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Black Panther, October 26, 1968  by Shirley Williams&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2012/session1/1</coverpage-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1068</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-02-02T12:21:19-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1068/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>2490463</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2012/session1/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;The following are videos i will be showing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/s0p9dHhkvpI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(stop video at 1:20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/JHWZtJA5zr4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(stop video at  1:12)&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Carolyn P. Brown   Memorial University Center</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>