<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Dynamic Ampacity Model for the Testing of Advanced Conductors</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Sooter</lname>
<fname>Matthew</fname>
<mname>Benjamin</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Electrical and Electronics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Advanced Conductors are an intriguing new technology that promises to help the utility industry increase the transmission capacity available in the United States. Manufacturers of advanced conductors promise double the current carrying capacity of normal Aluminum Clad Steel Reinforced conductor through a combination of increased thermal limits and decreased thermal elongation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thesis will outline a control developed for the Power Line Conductor Accelerated Test Facility at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. This custom facility is designed for the testing and rapid aging of advanced overhead conductors as part of a U.S. Department of Energy initiative to assist the development and deployment of new transmission technologies. The control outlined will make use of an ampacity model capable of accurately describing the current – temperature relationship of bare overhead conductor at an outdoor facility. This model will be used to maintain test conductors at specific elevated temperatures for extended periods of time. It is hoped that these tests will verify the thermal limits of the advanced conductors and encourage utilities to begin deploying them in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2361</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3789&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2361</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3789</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-18T08:28:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4737935</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2361</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leon Tolbert</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jack Lawler, Fangxing Li</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>