<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>INACTIVATION KINETICS OF &lt;i&gt;BOTRYTIS CINEREA&lt;/i&gt; INOCULATED ON STAINLESS STEEL COUPONS BY CHLORINE DIOXIDE GAS</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>malnajja@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Dhanapal</lname>
<fname>Aruna</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Botrytis cinerea&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt;) is a soil borne fungus that produces airborne spores and causes serious damage to crops. Inactivation of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; has become a difficult challenge as it has become more resistant to fungicides, disinfectants, thermal, and non-thermal inactivation techniques, such as ultraviolet light and pulsed white light. Chlorine dioxide gas (ClO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) has proven to have promising and effective antifungal properties. The aim of this study is to determine the inactivation kinetics (&lt;i&gt;D-value&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;z-value&lt;/i&gt;) of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; on stainless steel coupons (SS) using very low concentrations of chlorine dioxide gas, and to determine the survival rate of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; on stainless steel coupons. The &lt;i&gt;D-value&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;z-value&lt;/i&gt; can be used to determine the appropriate combination of gas concentration and treatment time to achieve the desired log reductions of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Botrytis cinerea&lt;/i&gt; at initial levels of ~ 6 log spores/ml on SS coupons was treated with 36, 60, and 90 ppmv (0.1, 0.17, and 0.25 mg/l respectively), of ClO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas for 15, 30, 45, and 60 min; 6, 13, 20, and 26 min and 4, 8, 16, and 24 min, respectively. The first order linear model &lt;i&gt;D-values&lt;/i&gt; for 36, 60, and 90 ppmv were 22.34 ± 2.53, 10.18 ± 0.75, and 10.65 ± 0.44 min respectively with a &lt;i&gt;z-value&lt;/i&gt; of 175.43 ± 0.19 ppmv. The &lt;i&gt;D-value&lt;/i&gt; decreased as the ClO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gas concentration increased. The survival analysis determines the efficiency of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; to survive on the surface of the SS coupons without any added nutrients. It is important to determine the survival rate of &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; during food processing or on food contact surfaces.In this study, the survival rate decreased from 60% on Day 3 to 17% on Day 4. Also, in this study, &lt;i&gt;B. cinerea&lt;/i&gt; survived on the coupons without any nutrients for 7 days, which was the limit of testing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5423</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6831&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5423</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6831</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-02-12T18:30:08-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>16528554</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5423</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mark Morgan</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Doris H. D&#39;Souza, Bonnie H. Ownley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>