<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Bridging the Divide Between Gen. X and Millennials</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:37:37-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>Realtalk1969@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Miley</lname>
<fname>Floyd</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Civic and Community Engagement</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The problems that plague the Black community are a multi-dimensional phenomenon deeply rooted in systemic racism. For 400 years, the Black experience in America has been one of subjugation, segregation, lynching, discrimination and racism. The historic Civil Rights Movement changed legislation, but it didn’t change racist attitudes or institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Donald Trump’s presidency, America has witnessed a resurgence of White supremacists’ attitudes, beliefs, values and practices towards people of color, especially Blacks. His administration supports the social, political, criminal justice and economic institutions that negatively affect the Black community. As a result, Blacks have the highest incarceration rate, poverty violence and unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the Black community is in desperate need of a social, political and economic agenda to eradicate systemic racism. The future and responsibility falls with Generation X and Millennials. The critical question is how the perceived conflicts and perspectives can be resolved to address systemic economic exploitation, political oppression and social degradation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/18</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1204&amp;amp;context=omsaconference&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>18</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1204</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-02T09:32:27-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13556555</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/18</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>