<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Status of the Blackstripe (Fundulus notatus) and Blackspotted (F. olivaceus) Topminnows in the Ozark uplands of Central Missouri</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-19T08:05:56-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>steffensmeier.8@buckeyemail.osu.edu</email>
<institution>The Ohio State University</institution>
<lname>Steffensmeier</lname>
<fname>Nathaniel</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>nrqd7@mst.edu</email>
<institution>Missouri University of Science and Technology</institution>
<lname>Remex</lname>
<fname>Naznin</fname>
<mname>Sultana</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>robert.hrabik@mdc.mo.gov</email>
<institution>Missouri Department of Conservation</institution>
<lname>Hrabik</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>duvernelld@mst.edu</email>
<institution>Missouri University of Science and Technology</institution>
<lname>Duvernell</lname>
<fname>David</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>ecoregion</keyword>
<keyword>species abundance</keyword>
<keyword>hybridization</keyword>
<keyword>species replacement</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Aquaculture and Fisheries</discipline>
<discipline>Biodiversity</discipline>
<discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Molecular Genetics</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The topminnow species &lt;em&gt;Fundulus notatus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;F. olivaceus&lt;/em&gt; have broadly overlapping geographic distributions that extend throughout much of the central and southern United States. In the northern portion of their respective ranges, in Missouri, the regional distributions of the two species coincide largely with recognized ecoregions. In the unglaciated southern half of Missouri, &lt;em&gt;F. olivaceus&lt;/em&gt; is distributed throughout Ozark upland habitats while &lt;em&gt;F. notatus&lt;/em&gt; is abundant in marginal large river and prairie habitats along the Ozark borders. An exception to this partitioning is the historical report of abundant &lt;em&gt;F. notatus&lt;/em&gt; in the Bourbeuse and upper Meramec River drainages within the Ozark uplands ecoregion. We conducted an extensive survey of the Bourbeuse and Dry Fork Meramec Rivers to determine topminnow species composition in these systems. Our surveys found abundant &lt;em&gt;F. olivaceus&lt;/em&gt; populations throughout these drainages and failed to uncover any &lt;em&gt;F. notatus&lt;/em&gt; individuals. A review of museum accessions from the 1940s and 1960s confirms the historical presence of &lt;em&gt;F. notatus&lt;/em&gt; in these river drainages, suggesting that a significant shift in topminnow species abundance has occurred in the past half century.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1292&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1292</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-23T12:14:12-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1292/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>13360793</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>We are grateful to collections managers who shared images of specimens from collections at the University of Kansas (Andy Bentley), University of Michigan (Douglas Nelson), Oregon State University (Brian Sidlauskas), Ohio State University (Mark Kibbey), Cornell University (Casey Dillman), and the Illinois Natural History Survey (Chris Taylor). We wish to thank Jacob Schaefer for discussions of this work. NS was supported by an internship provided by the National Great Rivers Research and Education Center. Funding for this project was provided by NSF grant DEB-1556778.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-11-23T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0x12fd10b0)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Status of Topminnows (Fundulus notatus and F. olivaceus) in MO</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>