<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Professional Development: A Case Study of Mrs. G</title>
<publication-date>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sgranade@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Owens</lname>
<fname>Sharilyn Kay</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>professional development</keyword>
<keyword>classroom discourse</keyword>
<keyword>levels of questioning</keyword>
<keyword>formative assessment</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Science and Mathematics Education</discipline>
<discipline>Teacher Education and Professional Development</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation is a case study of one teacher who participated in a project that investigated the effects of the Texas Instruments NavigatorTM, a wireless communication system on student algebra achievement and related pedagogy. The larger study, Classroom Connectivity in Promoting Mathematics and Science Achievement (CCMS) based at The Ohio State University (OSU), funded by the U. S. Department of Education, involved approximately 120 self-selected participants across the United States. A partial requirement for participation was agreement to attend professional development provided by the CCMS project. The professional development included a week-long summer institute at OSU prior to implementation of the TI-NavigatorTM, attendance at annual International T3 meetings, participation in the cohort listserve, and semi-annual telephone interviews. During data collection of the CCMS project, many of the participants exhibited an enthusiasm for implementation of the tool and the pedagogy supported by the CCMS project. The subject of this case study, Mrs. G, was among those perceived as high implementers. This longitudinal study attempts to verify alignment of her instruction with the pedagogy promoted in the professional development sessions provided by the project. Transcripts from professional development sessions were compared with Mrs. G’s comments about her perception of her implementation of the project. Transcribed classroom observations were then analyzed using NVivo software to quantify evidence of implementation of the pedagogy with respect to the three constructs of classroom discourse, levels of questioning and formative assessment. The results of the analyses indicated that Mrs. G implemented the pedagogy advocated by the professional development sessions of the CCMS project. According to the literature key elements were in place for successful professional development. The teacher was allowed autonomy and choice in her professional development In Mrs. G’s words, “Professional development must be relevant to my profession and support my goals… student understanding.” Implications are that pre-service programs should instill in prospective teachers the importance of life-long learning and equip them with strategies to seek out professional development opportunities that are relevant to them. In-service teachers should in turn be given autonomy and choice in determining which professional development opportunities will complement their programs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/732</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1757&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>732</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1757</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-13T08:13:55-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/1757/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1272731</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/732</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vena Long</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Charles Collins, Lynn Hodge, Blanche O&#39;Bannon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>