<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ecology of black bears in a bottomland hardwood forest in Arkansas</title>
<publication-date>1985-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Tommy</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Population characteristics, growth patterns, reproduction, mortality, food habits, denning, movements, and habitat use of black bears in bottomland hardwood forest were studied on White River National Wildlife Refuge in eastern Arkansas from June 1979 to May 1982. A total of 51 bears was captured 64 times, and 2104 telemetry locations of 28 radioinstrumented bears were obtained. Estimates of population size and density on the 457 km2 Refuge were 130 bears and 1 bear/4.5 km2, respectively. The genetically effective number of bears in the lower White River basin was estimated to be 53 to 130, indicating that the long-term fitness of this closed population is precarious. The composite ratio of males to females in the capture sample was 1.56:1; it did not differ significantly from 1:1 (P&lt;0.05). Capture data suggested a stable age structure, and that females, which reached 14 years of age, were longer-lived than males. Growth was curvilinear in both sexes. Males attained peak body weight by 5 years of age, but females added weight until 9 or 10 years old. Mean weight of adult males (102 kg) was twice that of adult females (52 kg). Approximately one-third of the females successfully bred as 3- year-olds, and all had produced cubs by 6 years of age. All males appeared to be sexually mature by 4 years of age. Mean breeding interval of radio-collared females was 2.4 years. Most litters were born in early February, and mean litter size was 2.3 cubs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6146</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8134&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6146</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8134</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-15T05:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23359371</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6146</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1985-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>