<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Aquiculture</title>
<publication-date>1937-06-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ramsey</lname>
<fname>Hugh</fname>
<mname>T.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Aquaculture and Fisheries</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;There is every evidence that the productivity of our ponds, lakes, and streams can be materially increased by the intelligent application of present scientific knowledge to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years it has been recognized that our streams and lakes are becoming more and more barren of fish, and other aquatic life, but remedial measures, until recently, have been applied to only one-half of the problem. Efficient fish hatchery systems are maintained, both state and federal, and millions of fingerlings and legal-size fish are planted each year in an effort to increase the fish population of our waters, and to add to the profit and enjoyment of an increasing army of fishermen. On the other hand, little thought has been given to the fate of these fish after they have been released, and to the ability of our streams and lakes to provide the essentials of life for an increased fish population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concurrent with the pushing back of our frontiers has been the wanton destruction of timber, the reduction of underground water tables, increased erosion and silt, increased temperature and pollution of streams, and quick run-off of surface water with consequent floods, a decrease in the volume of water in creeks and rivers during the dry seasons, as well as many other factors which have a direct bearing upon the productivity of streams and lakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of the automobile, followed by the extension of our highway system to virtually every nook and corner, there are now few streams of any size that are not accessibly to the ardent fisherman. As distance from a stream is now a negligible factor, the number of fishermen is growing each year and the sportsmen feel that they are entitled to some return for the money invested in the purchase of a privilege license. The answer to this problem apparently lies in the extension of the principles of aquiculture, heretofore more or less restricted to the hatcheries, to include our public waters.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3051</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4461&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3051</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4461</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-01-13T12:43:34-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6524178</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3051</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Edwin B. Powers</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>ARRAY(0x7f6ffe6e1588)</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1937-05-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1937-06-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>