<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Experiential Learning Experiences and Leadership Development of Students on a Study Abroad Trip to Australia</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bjarrell@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Jarrell</lname>
<fname>Baylee</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to describe student’s perceptions of a study abroad trip to Australia designed to include Kolb’s (2014) principles of experiential learning. Activities conducted were in effort to increase students’ international perspectives in the areas of leadership, education, communications, and extension. In an effort to remain true to the experiential learning process, students selected organizations from a generated list in which students learned about leadership, education, communications or extension. Six students, one male and five females, were involved in the study abroad trip to Australia for 21 days. Throughout the 21 days, interviews were conducted with the students about their experiences. Thematic analysis was used to code the transcriptions from each interview and to pinpoint nine codes that later developed into five themes. Those five themes are: (a) Experiential learning and leadership development did occur on this study abroad experience, (b) Students had personal growth while involved in the study abroad experience, (c) Cultural and global diversity impacted the student’s experiences, (d) Student’s perceptions of agriculture were enhanced through this study abroad experience, and (e) Students faced emotional challenges during the study abroad trip. Some recommendations are to have a well-designed plan for experiential learning courses, plan for varied experiences, and prepare more for emotional challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5671</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7207&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5671</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7207</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-01-24T14:00:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>21246551</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5671</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carrie Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Christopher Stripling, Tom Gill</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communications</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>