<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>PB1604 How Will Your Food Be Regulated</title>
<publication-date>2005-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Food</keyword>
<keyword>Food Safety</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;As you to prepare to enter the food business, you need to be aware of a few basic principles before making a total commitment. In UT Extension PB1399, &lt;strong&gt;Getting Started in a Food Manufacturing Business in Tennessee&lt;/strong&gt;, the obstacles are defined with regard to the mechanisms of Good Manufacturing Practices (GMPs), labeling, legal aspects, types of permits, etc. However, the &lt;strong&gt;Federal Code of Regulations&lt;/strong&gt; divides different foods into categories or classes, and they are regulated differently by the state and federal governments. Additional information is available at &lt;em&gt;www.wcmorris.com&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foods are essentially differentiated by the amount of acid present, added and/or water activity (aw) and whether the food is in a hermetically sealed container. A hermetically sealed container means a container that is designed and intended to be secure against the entry of microorganisms, thereby maintaining the commercial sterility of its contents after processing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfood/42</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1041&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfood&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>42</label>
<document-type>foodsafety</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1041</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-17T10:21:52-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Food, Nutrition and Food Safety</publication-title>
<context-key>1229214</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfood/42</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>PB1604-500-3/05 (Rep) E12-4815-00-003-0 05-03025</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-17T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>