<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Personal Facts About Executive Officers: A Proposal for Tailored Disclosures to Encourage Reasonable Investor Behavior</title>
<publication-date>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jheminwa@tennessee.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Heminway</lname>
<fname>Joan</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>disclosure</keyword>
<keyword>officer</keyword>
<keyword>executive</keyword>
<keyword>personal facts</keyword>
<keyword>securities regulation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Business Law, Public Responsibility, and Ethics</discipline>
<discipline>Business Organizations Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Law and Society</discipline>
<discipline>Legal Ethics and Professional Responsibility</discipline>
<discipline>Securities Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Required  disclosures under U.S. securities laws, whether mandated by line-item  disclosure rules, gap-filling regulations, or antifraud provisions, tend  to focus principally, although not exclusively, on corporate facts -  information about an issuer of securities or a transaction involving an  issuer of securities.  Although there are line-item disclosure rules  that require the public revelation of personal facts about executive  officers (both by the issuer and by the executive himself or herself),  these rules are limited in scope. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;However, public disclosure of  executives&#39; personal facts not covered by these line-item rules still  may be required under applicable gap-filling regulations or antifraud  provisions.  The analysis of whether and, if so, when to disclose  personal facts about an executive officer under these regulations and  provisions may be difficult.  The lynchpin in that analysis is a  decision as to whether the personal facts are material under applicable  formulations of the judge-made materiality standard.  These materiality  determinations may be complex and emotionally laden. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;This paper  argues for an enhancement of federal disclosure rules as they relate to  personal facts about executive officers of public companies.  The paper  first summarizes significant existing requirements for disclosure about  executive officers.  Then, the paper argues that the existing federal  securities law regime applicable to public company executive disclosures  of personal facts is deficient in three respects. Specifically,  existing disclosure requirements place too much discretion in the hands  of executives, cause pressure on important individual rights, and tend  to cause investors and markets to overreact.  As a response, the paper  proposes limited federal securities rule changes designed to more  effectively and efficiently manage the public release of personal facts  about public company executives.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/13</coverpage-url>
<label>13</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1025</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-05-27T09:39:57-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2035239</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/13</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Heminway, Joan MacLeod, Personal Facts About Executive Officers: A Proposal for Tailored Disclosures to Encourage Reasonable Investor Behavior. Wake Forest Law Review, Vol. 42, No. 3, 2007; University of Tennessee Legal Studies Research Paper No. 11. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=1020203</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1020203</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>