<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Two Ways Out/Back “Home”: Two Transnational and Literary Perspectives in Chinese Puzzle and Budapeste</title>
<publication-date>2018-04-06T18:10:38-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ascdtb@mail.missouri.edu</email>
<institution>University of Missouri-Columbia</institution>
<lname>Compaoré</lname>
<fname>Seth</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Transnational</keyword>
<keyword>home</keyword>
<keyword>border-crossing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Film and Media Studies</discipline>
<discipline>French and Francophone Language and Literature</discipline>
<discipline>Other Film and Media Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the current global cinematic practices, it almost becomes a natural phenomenon that filmmakers leave home to film in the spaces beyond the borders of their homelands. These films are often categorized as transnational films. According to Hamid Naficy (2003: 204), “transnational films are framed within the “national cinemas” of their host countries and established cinematic genres”. &lt;em&gt;Budapeste&lt;/em&gt; (2009) directed by Walter Carvalho and &lt;em&gt;Chinese Puzzle&lt;/em&gt; (2013) directed by Cédric Klapisch are both transnational films from two different regions: South America, Mercosul (Brazil) and the European Union (France). Because both films present transitional places (airports) and transnational spaces, the physical spaces and symbolic borders between Brazil and Hungary in &lt;em&gt;Budapeste&lt;/em&gt; are clear, as well as the physical cityscapes from France to the Unites States in &lt;em&gt;Chinese Puzzle&lt;/em&gt;. However, because these journeys are not just territorial, the displaced main characters find themselves in deeply emotional, literary, and cultural journeys. Therefore, there is a need to rethink the notion of home in these two films. In both films, the notion of an established home is never a one-and-done thing and home is never a definite possession but it follows Gilles Deleuze’s and Félix Guattari’s theory of “becoming.” In this work, I aim to explore, first, the motherland as a place of alienation resulting in the loss of faith in national institutions in &lt;em&gt;Budapeste&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Chinese Puzzle&lt;/em&gt;. Then, I analyze the juxtaposition of literary migrations in &lt;em&gt;Budapeste&lt;/em&gt; and how it contributes to a “non-established home” for Costa, and how finding a new home for him is embracing a Hungarian identity through literary creation. Finally, in &lt;em&gt;Chinese Puzzle&lt;/em&gt;, I focus on the perpetual seeking for home by Xavier, the main character, and the city of New York as a utopian space to cure the journeyer from the trauma of his lost homeland.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/vernacular/vol3/iss1/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1046&amp;amp;context=vernacular&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1046</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-12-15T17:27:46-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/vernacular/article/1046/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Vernacular: New Connections in Language, Literature, &amp; Culture</publication-title>
<context-key>11261409</context-key>
<submission-path>vernacular/vol3/iss1/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xc6f9838)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Two Ways Out/Back “Home”: Two Transnational and Literary Perspectives in Chinese Puzzle and Budapeste</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>