<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Not so Immaculately Conceived: Imagining the Protestant Madonna 1850-1910</title>
<publication-date>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Scaperoth</lname>
<fname>Deborah</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>English Language and Literature</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Pius IX in the 1854 Bull &lt;em&gt;Ineffabilis Deus&lt;/em&gt; defined the dogma of the Immaculate Conception as the belief that Mary; mother of Jesus, was from the moment of her conception free from the &quot;stain of original sin.&quot; This idea was a part of ecclesiastical tradition, but prior to this time, the church had not officially defined Mary&#39;s sinless nature in writing. The publication of this definition, along with published accounts of Marian sightings, contributed to an already heightened awareness of her in a literate, culturally aware public. As a result, Protestant writers who sought to invoke her image interpreted a &quot;new&quot; Virgin Mary to a largely Protestant public that saw her mostly as an exotic Catholic &quot;other.&quot; In my project, I explore the idea of the reconstructed Protestant Virgin Mary and examine how this type affected images of women in nineteenth century British/American literature and popular culture from 1850-1910. I establish precedence for this idea by first examining the image of the Virgin Mary in twelfth-century France, a culture which experienced economic and social upheavals similar to the ones that occurred during the nineteenth century. From there, my argument then focuses on a particular case of how Protestant male writers constructed the Virgin Mary and how a defining characteristic meant to glorify feminine divinity could be turned into a vehicle to support the &quot;eternal needs of man&#39;s heart&quot;-as the Victorian heroine evolved into a sentimental, sexless, disempowered rendition of the Virgin Mary. Why male writers? Primarily, male writers and publishers in both countries held a great amount of power in the literary world from 1850-1900, so they would have had a great deal of influence on the reading public. My work also explores the ways that religion, language, popular culture, and the media work together in determining consumer-driven images of women. In the first half of my dissertation, I discuss Charles Dickens, Wilkie Collins, Charles Kingsley, Algernon Charles Swinburne, Robert Browning, John Ruskin, and the Pre-Raphaelites. In the second half, I examine the American writers Mark Twain, Henry James, and Henry Adams. My conclusion shows how the Protestant Madonna eventually evolved into a ludicrous type, no longer useful by the end of the century.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4269</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5972&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4269</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5972</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-06T09:43:32-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9984517</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4269</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary E. Papke</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Goslee, Tom Haddox, Amy Neff</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>English</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2006-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>