<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Forestry Extension in Tennessee: Comparing Traditional and Web-Based Program Delivery Methods</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jackson</lname>
<fname>Samuel</fname>
<mname>Wayne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;As the traditional forestry Extension clientele in Tennessee changes, Extension professionals need to adapt and deliver programs in such a way as to reach the maximum audience while ensuring the educational benefit of the program and remaining within budget. The development of the Internet and associated web-based programs presents a new tool by which Extension professionals can develop and deliver educational programs to clientele.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study compared two Extension program delivery methods, web-based and traditional field-based. A series of field workshops were held and participants were surveyed. From these field workshops, a web-based program was developed and was marketed to a similar audience; these participants were also surveyed. Demographic information, learning preferences, and other measures of program preference were collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ninety-seven percent of participants in the field-based program and 68% of the web-based sample preferred a field program over a web-based program. If only a web-based program was made available to participants, at least 50% of each sample would be interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educational level was the only demographic characteristic that was significantly different between those who chose a web-based program and those who chose a field-based program. Participants with higher educational levels were more likely to choose a web-based program. Educational level was positively correlated with income level, computer ownership, and Internet access. Educational level was negatively correlated with age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge gain was significantly higher in the field-based sample. Web-based participants showed average knowledge gain of 12.2 to 28.7% whereas the knowledge gain for people attending the traditional field day program averaged 16.5 to 46.1%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level of computer ownership was high in both samples as was the use of the computer on a regular basis. Internet access was high in both groups. The web-based sample had significantly higher levels of high-speed access. Those with high-speed connections were more likely to choose a web-based program, although both groups used the computer/Internet regularly for gathering information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current forestry Extension clientele preferred a field-based program delivery method. Some clientele, though, preferred web-based programming and these types of programs should be offered when suitable. Using a variety of delivery methods, Extension can adapt programs to a wide range of learning styles to reach new audiences, including younger generations who are more comfortable with Internet learning.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/553</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1620&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>553</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1620</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-22T11:53:36-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1162358</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/553</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George M. Hopper</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Wayne K. Clatterbuck, Timothy Cross, J. Larry Wilson, Julie K. Little</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Natural Resources</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/December2008Dissertations/JacksonSamuelWayne.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>