<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The information behavior of hospice volunteer coordinators</title>
<publication-date>2012-11-12T19:06:08-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sedwards@email.wcu.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Edwards</lname>
<fname>Sheri</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study explores the information behavior of hospice volunteer coordinators employed in hospice care in Southern Appalachia.  The study is conceptualized according to Taylor&#39;s Information Use Environment (IUE) and uses a qualitative approach by employing the critical incident technique (CIT) in order to elicit emic descriptions of participants&#39; memorable episodes of information behavior and enablers of and constraints on that behavior.  Fifteen of twenty volunteer coordinators have participated.  Data analysis incorporates a dual method of grounded theory and structuration theory.  Preliminary analysis of the data reveals that company manuals and colleagues are the most widely-used sources of information, and that those and other sources act as both enablers and constraints of coordinators&#39; information behavior.  It is hoped that the research will contribute meaningfully to the emergent body of health-related information behavior research, and function as a guide for improving hospice care volunteer training and retention.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/ccisymposium/2012/poster/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1035&amp;amp;context=ccisymposium&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1035</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-12-11T15:02:17-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/ccisymposium/article/1035/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Annual Research Symposium of the College of Communication and Information</publication-title>
<context-key>2397220</context-key>
<submission-path>ccisymposium/2012/poster/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CCI Auditorium, 321 Communications Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>