<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Impact of Ultrasonication on Physicochemical Properties and Digestibility of Sorghum Starch</title>
<publication-date>2018-05-16T14:51:10-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>zwang78@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wang</lname>
<fname>Zhihong</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Science</discipline>
<discipline>Food Chemistry</discipline>
<discipline>Food Processing</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Sorghum, a highly nutritious grain, is usually not considered as a main staple in many families because it is not as easy to be digested as other grains such as rice or maize. But recent studies of ultrasonication shed a light on potential utilization of this world’s fifth important cereal other than being raw material source of biofuel or liquor. This experiment was meant to compare the differences between unsonicated and sonicated sorghum starch in terms of their physical chemical properties and digestion ability. Despite their similarities in shapes under microscopes and their thermal properties, but sonicated sorghum starch was higher than unsonicated sorghum in the results of water retention capacity, swelling power, solubility and especially digestibility. The results might provide the background for further research to broaden the practical usage of sonicated sorghum in foods.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2018/agsciences/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1176&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1176</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-04-17T10:21:48-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>11975884</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2018/agsciences/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Agricultural Sciences &amp; Natural Resources</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Dr. Vermont Dia</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2018-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>