<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A phenomenological inquiry into children&#39;s experiences and choices related to health and disease prevention</title>
<publication-date>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Chavez</lname>
<fname>Juliann</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Child and family studies</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this phenomenological study, 10 children who were diagnosed with insulin resistance and child overweight were interviewed. These interviews focused on how the children described their first experience as they learned about their risk factors for Type II diabetes and what prevention strategies they utilized. Each child interviewed, indicated that he or she experienced positive clinical outcomes, such as weight loss, weight maintenance, lower insulin levels, or decreased lipid profiles, all physiological markers for reducing risk factors for Type II diabetes. Children illustrated through narratives how they changed lifestyle habits, primarily in food selection and exercise. These changes were coping strategies that they utilized to lose weight and decrease insulin levels. Children spoke about the how changes in body composition also improved their self-confidence and self-esteem. The themes that emerged through the interviews included (a) positive lifestyle changes (b) social support and family (c) supportive friendships (d) psychosocial environment and (e) understanding self and developing resilience. The perspectives from each child have implications for future educational programming and initiatives regarding child overweight and disease and for providers who perform individual counseling.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5978</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7911&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5978</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7911</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>22467588</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5978</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Priscilla Blanton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Child and Family Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>