<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rediscovery of the Pallid Shiner, &lt;i&gt;Hybopsis amnis&lt;/i&gt;, in the Black River System of Arkansas and Missouri Including Notes on Ecology and Life History</title>
<publication-date>2021-03-23T05:14:17-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dmorrill03@gmail.com</email>
<institution>University of Central Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Morrill</lname>
<fname>Daniel</fname>
<mname>P</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>crezac1@cub.uca.edu</email>
<institution>University of Central Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Rezac</lname>
<fname>Calvin</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>gadams@uca.edu</email>
<institution>University of Central Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Adams</lname>
<fname>Ginny</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>radams@uca.edu</email>
<institution>University of Central Arkansas</institution>
<lname>Adams</lname>
<fname>S.</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>robert.hrabik@mdc.mo.gov</email>
<institution>Missouri Department of Conservation</institution>
<lname>Hrabik</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Pallid Shiner, &lt;em&gt;Hybopsis amnis&lt;/em&gt;, is a rare and understudied minnow with little information about its ecology. This species is listed as a Species of Greatest Conservation Need (SGCN) throughout much of its range and is generally considered to be declining. It had not been detected in the Black River system of Missouri and Arkansas in over 75 years, or the state of Missouri in over 60 years. We sampled over 100 sites in the Black River system between 2017 and 2020 to assess temporal trends in fish assemblage structure and to update the status of SGCN species in this drainage. We collected 226 &lt;em&gt;H. amnis&lt;/em&gt; at seven different sites in the Black River system. We measured total lengths to estimate age classes and year of spawning. Corresponding habitat and year class data indicate this species may spawn in late winter to early spring and rely on floodplain habitat for spawning and recruitment. The apparent decline of &lt;em&gt;H. amnis &lt;/em&gt;in other systems may be a result of reduced floodplain connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss61/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1307&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1307</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-10-04T14:31:29-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1307/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>19661898</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss61/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>This study was funded by an Arkansas State Wildlife Grant. Fish were handled according to University of Central Arkansas Animal Care and Use Committee Protocol 17-004. We would like to thank the Arkansas Game and Fish Commission, the Missouri Department of Conservation, David C. Hilburn, Stephen A. Winters, Michael B. Johnson, and Steve M. Bounds for providing historical survey data for the Black River system. We appreciate Dr. Thomas Buchanan for his correspondence throughout this study. We appreciate the time and effort of Dr. David Duvernell for providing length data on the Missouri specimens. Thanks to Christopher Naus for supplying H. amnis data from his collections in the Fourche LaFave River. Thanks to the University of Central Arkansas Biology Department for their assistance with this project. These data would not have been possible without the help of numerous field assistants: Jennifer Main, Geoffry Spooner, Joseph Miller, George Gavrielides, Emily Field, Danielle Braund, Chance Garrett, Jessica Rath, and Ichthyology students from Missouri University of Science and Technology. D. P. M. would like to personally thank Daniel B. Wylie of the Illinois Natural History Survey for illuminating in him a passion for ichthyology he never knew was there.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xe553b70)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Rediscovery of the Pallid Shiner, &lt;i&gt;Hybopsis amnis&lt;/i&gt;, in the Black River System</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>