<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Energy-Driven Analysis of Electronically-Interfaced Resources for Improving Power System Dynamic Performance</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>hsilvasa@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Silva Saravia</lname>
<fname>Horacio</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Power Systems</keyword>
<keyword>Inter-area oscillations</keyword>
<keyword>Solar PV</keyword>
<keyword>Wind power</keyword>
<keyword>Energy Storage</keyword>
<keyword>Stability and control</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This dissertation investigates the strengthening of power system dynamics with regard to electromechanical oscillations by using electronically-interfaced resources (EIR). The dissertation addresses (1) the modeling and control design of a flywheel energy storage system and a large-scale solar PV plant. The latest is enabled to participate in oscillation damping control without the need for power curtailment. (2) A new dynamic performance evaluation and coordination of damping controller is also developed to analyze systems with several critically low damping ratios. This is studied by using the system oscillation energy to define the total action and total action sensitivity, which allow the identification of control action that benefit exited modes, rather than fixed targeted modes. Finally, (3) this dissertation proposes a solution for the site selection of EIR-based damping controllers in a planning stage. The effect of wind power variability and correlation between geographically closed wind farms is modeled to analyze the system performance and determine the site selection that maximizes the probability of dynamic performance improvement. Mathematical description as well as simulations in different multi-machine power systems show the advantages of the methods described in this work. The findings of this thesis are expected to advance the state-of-the-art of power system control by effectively and efficiently utilizing the fast power capabilities of EIR in systems with high penetration of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5561</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7207&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5561</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7207</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T18:48:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>18911427</context-key>
<withdrawn>2020-08-16</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5561</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hector Pulgar</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Yilu Lu, Fran Li, Russell Zaretzki</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>