<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>CONTEXTUAL TYPOLOGIES: SYNTHESIZING TIMELESS ARCHITECTURE TYPOLOGICAL DETAILS IN THE CLASSICAL URBAN FABRIC OF CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>dsells2@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sells</lname>
<fname>Denver</fname>
<mname>George</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Context</keyword>
<keyword>Typology</keyword>
<keyword>Urban Fabric</keyword>
<keyword>Charleston</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Architectural History and Criticism</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this thesis project is to explore the creation of a methodology as a tool and means of making an objective analysis out of a subjective design issue. This thesis deals with public perceptions of architecture and design, specifically Clemson University School of Architecture’s new Spaulding Paolozzi Center in Charleston, South Carolina, designed by Brad Cloepfil of Allied Works Architecture, and what ultimately led to its redaction from the Board of Architectural Reviewers in Charleston. In order to do so, case studies of other classical cities will be examined and compared to the historic urban fabric of Charleston, as well as an analysis of building typologies and how these definitions impact and effect their designs in the context of Charleston. These ideas will then be broken down into their component parts, analyzed and then synthesized into a re-design of the Spaulding Paolozzi Center. Along the way, considerations for the site’s original location will be explored, and the importance of placing public institutional “palaces” in specifically important locations within the city’s urban fabric will be discussed. The end goal of this thesis project is to understand methodology of working through an architecture problem, and while an end design will be explored, it is not meant to be understood as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; solution, but rather &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;solution to the problem of objectively solving a subjective problem.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4074</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5202&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4074</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5202</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-05-16T07:51:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8605115</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4074</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hansjoerg Goeritz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Avigail Sachs, Thomas K. Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>