<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Do increases in fruit intake lead to substitutive eating patterns and decreases in overall energy intake in normal weight adults?</title>
<publication-date>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ssobhani@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sobhani</lname>
<fname>Shireen</fname>
<mname>Amanda</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>overweight</keyword>
<keyword>obesity</keyword>
<keyword>fruit and vegetable intake</keyword>
<keyword>behavioral economics</keyword>
<keyword>relative reinforcing value</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Nutrition</discipline>
<discipline>Public Health Education and Promotion</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background: &lt;/strong&gt;It is suggested that increasing intake of fruits and vegetables may lead to decreased energy intake via substitution of higher energy-dense foods, such as snack foods (SF; i.e. candy, chips, cookies). This study investigated the impact of increasing fruit (F; grapes) intake, via increased portion size, on SF (potato chips) intake during a meal and whether increases in F intake affected total meal energy intake, via reducing SF intake (substitutive eating), in normal-weight adults. A secondary objective investigated whether the relative reinforcing value (RRV) of SF was a moderator of the substitutive relationship between F and SF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods:&lt;/strong&gt; Using a 4X4 crossover design (between-subjects factor of order [1, 2, 3, 4] and a within-subjects factor of meal condition [CONTROL, INCREASE, DECREASE, INCREASE+DECREASE]), 25 healthy-weight participants (22.0 ± 3.7 years, 76% female, 64% white) completed the study. As part of a larger project, this ancillary study focused on the unidirectional substitution relationship between CONTROL and INCREASE. In addition to two sandwiches, CONTROL contained 100 grams (g) each of F and SF, while INCREASE contained 150g of F and 100g of SF. A validated computer task determined the RRV of SF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results: &lt;/strong&gt;Analyses of variance found that participants consumed significantly more F (grams and energy) in INCREASE (141.4 ± 21.8g, 65.2 ± 11.3kcal), as compared to CONTROL (94.5 ± 16.4g, 96.2 ± 16.0kcal), but there was no significant difference in SF (grams or energy) or total energy intake in INCREASE, as compared to CONTROL. Hierarchical regressions determined that increases in F intake (grams or energy) were not significantly associated with changes in SF intake (grams or energy) or changes in total energy intake from CONTROL to INCREASE. A hierarchical regression also showed that the RRV of SF did not significantly moderate the change in SF intake from CONTROL to INCREASE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion: &lt;/strong&gt;Increasing F consumption in a meal did not contribute to significant decreases in SF or total energy intake in a meal, suggesting F does not act as substitute for SF. Recommendations encouraging individuals to increase F intake in order to decrease total energy intake may not achieve desired results.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3513</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4771&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3513</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4771</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-21T16:52:40-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4771/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7016652</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3513</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Hollie A. Raynor</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sarah E. Colby, Melissa Hansen-Petrik</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>