<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Density and Distribution of White-tailed Deer (&lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) in Cades Cove, Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>1980-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kiningham</lname>
<fname>Michael</fname>
<mname>Joseph</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Three census techniques were used from June 1978 to August 1979 to estimate population densities of white-tailed deer (&lt;em&gt;Odocoileus virginianus&lt;/em&gt;) in Cades Cove, Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Tennessee. Roadside counts were conducted 3 times a week; once at dawn, dusk, and dark. Drive counts were made every 3 months and a 3-week sampling interval was used to make pellet counts. Seasonal density estimates ranged from: 0.29 to 0.58 deer/ha (dark counts) , 0.29 to 0.76 deer/ha (drive counts) , and 0.18 to 0.47 deer/ha (pellet counts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adult sex ratios obtained from dawn and dark counts made during August (44.6 bucks:100 does) and November (22.0 bucks:100 does) indicated that there were more does than bucks in the population. These uneven adult sex ratios might be due to the dispersal of bucks out of Cades Cove during rut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fawn:doe ratios made during the summer and fall roadside counts were 27.9 fawns:100 does in 1978 and 8.4 fawns: 100 does in 1979. The difference between these ratios could be the result of a delay in fawning in 1979 compared to 1978 and not an actual decrease in fawn recruitment. The similar density estimates obtained for the summer of 1978 (0.41 deer/ha) and 1979 (0.43 deer/ha) appeared to indicate that fawn recruitment in 1978 was equal to mortality and emigration among older deer in the cove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the 3 census techniques used, roadside counts were determined to be the best to estimate densities of deer in the Cove. Drive counts had 2 major disadvantages compared to roadside counts: (1) they required large amounts of manpower, and (2) they generated small sample sixes in both areas sampled and deer counted. Pellet counts were difficult to conduct during periods of leaf fall and snow cover. High rates of deterioration and/or disappearance of pellet groups in open fields made pellet counts in those areas unreliable. Pellet counts should be reserved for areas where techniques utilizing direct counts are impractical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deer population in Cades Cove has increased since a die-off in 1971. At the present time the population might be stabilizing but, at a high density, ranging from 0.29 deer/ha to 0.58 deer/ha. As a result, disease and continued habitat degradation are probable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three alternatives to the present management practices of the Cove were considered: (1) the removal of deer, (2) stopping cattle grazing and hay mowing to allow for the resumption of plant succession, and (3) developing the educational and research potentials of the Cove. Adoption of the latter alternative was recommended.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3429</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4879&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3429</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4879</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-08-07T11:49:39-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7429684</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3429</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael R. Pelton</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Boyd L. Dearden, James L. Byford, Paul C. Smith</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Wildlife and Fisheries Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1980-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1980-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>