<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Fracture Toughness: Evaluation of Testing Procedure To Simplify JIc Calculations</title>
<publication-date>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Pehrson</lname>
<fname>Brandon</fname>
<mname>Paul</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mechanical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to examine the current fracture toughness test procedure and to determine if there is an easier, less complicated method to get the J&lt;sub&gt;Ic&lt;/sub&gt; value from a test record for fracture toughness specimens. The current method for constructing J&lt;sub&gt;Ic&lt;/sub&gt; is complicated and involves a detailed computer program or spreadsheet. The objective in this study is to simplify the analysis for the determination of J&lt;sub&gt;Q&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study has shown that the load and displacement record for a fracture toughness specimen can be used to directly estimate a J&lt;sub&gt;Q&lt;/sub&gt; value, a provisional value for fracture toughness, J&lt;sub&gt;Ic&lt;/sub&gt;. The maximum load point is used along with an adjustment factor for this direct estimation of the J&lt;sub&gt;Q&lt;/sub&gt; value. This J&lt;sub&gt;Q&lt;/sub&gt; value is equivalent to that obtained from the construction procedure, when a unit-sized specimen is tested, that is, a specimen with a width of 50 millimeters (2 inches) and a thickness of 25 millimeters (1 inch). Other sizes require a size adjustment factor, which is simply a function of the specimen width relative to the unit width. The adjustment factor proposed is a square root relationship between the width of the test specimen and a unit width. This shows that the effort required for the proposed new method of constructing J&lt;sub&gt;Ic&lt;/sub&gt; is less than that required for the construction method, the new method is simple in concept and requires a minimum number of calculations, and the method appears to produce values of J&lt;sub&gt;Q&lt;/sub&gt; which are comparable to those obtained from the construction procedure and may have less inherent scatter.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2304</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3754&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2304</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3754</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-17T11:51:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4733638</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2304</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John D. Landes</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>J. A. M. Boulet, Arnold Lumsdaine</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>