<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Management and Performance of Swine at Ames Plantation</title>
<publication-date>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Carrell</lname>
<fname>Everett</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to observe management practices and evaluate performance of straightbred and crossbread swine in the swine research program of the Animal Husbandry-Veterinary Science Department at Ames Plantation, Grand Junction, Tennessee. Data from straightbred Duroc, Hampshire, and Landrace and crossbred H X D and H X P X L pigs farrowed in the fall of 1956 and sold in the spring of 1957 at Ames Plantation were used in this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author observed and assisted in all phases of management and production throughout one season. The management practices used are practical and could be adopted to the production of swine on farms in Fayette County. Application of these practices in swine production could increase income from hogs in the county. In the swine program on the Plantation, pasture and home grown grain are used. Buildings of simple structure are used. Crossbred pigs were superior to straightbred pigs from the standpoint of economical production of pork. Crossbred sows produced larger litters and faster gaining pigs than purebred sows. Performance of two groups of Duroc sows from different sources and mated to the same boar showed that sows from Source II farrowed and raised more pigs per litter than sows from Source I. Pig and litter weights from sows of Source II were heavier at birth and 154 days as compared with sows of Source I.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4342</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5782&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4342</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5782</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-02-23T09:40:47-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9737485</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4342</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles S. Hobbs</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>French Bell, H. J. Smith, Robert S. Dotson, R. J. Cooper, T. J. Whatley</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1961-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>