<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Identity Complexities of African American First-Generation Students</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:37:34-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>chandria@hirecultures.com</email>
<lname>Harris</lname>
<fname>Chandria</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Inequality and Stratification</discipline>
<discipline>Social Psychology and Interaction</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Identity Complexities of African American First-Generation Students&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;African American first generational students struggle with identifying who they are and how they are supposed to show up in their college communities socially and academically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This session will guide attendees through the thought process of an African American First-Generational Students and solutions to assist them with persisting to graduation.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/17</coverpage-url>
<label>17</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1205</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-04T20:13:59-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1205/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13572438</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/17</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;African American First-Generational Students make up over 46% of the first-generation college community. Many of these students fall within the &quot;murky middle&quot; category with little to no emotional support to assist them with persisting through college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. First-Generational students experience a great deal of psychological stress from attempting to be the savior of their family, uncontrollable financial hardship and inability to focus academically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. First- Generational students need access and exposure to the world of work and inclusivity eligibility requirements for experiential learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Overwhelmed at the complexities of the campus community, personal needs and family needs awakens a great deal of anxiety that encourages first-generation students to give up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. African American First-Generational students need strategic emotional support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. African American First-Generational students need access and exposure to the world of work that offers financial compensation for their service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. African American First-Generational students need professional development to prepare them for the world of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional Information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.forbes.com/sites/troymarkowitz/2017/08/08/the-barriers-to-success-and-upward-mobility-for-first-generation-students-and-how-to-fix-the-problem/#36cff1561cb3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.naceweb.org/career-development/special-populations/career-development-needs-of-first-generation-students/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://opensiuc.lib.siu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1098&amp;context=ojwed&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Overhead/Screen</value>
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>