<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A world-systems perspective on the role of telecommunications in global development</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Albright</lname>
<fname>Kendra</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Until recently, an economic perspective has dominated studies of the effect of telecommunications on social and economic development. There are reasons to believe, however, that this perspective unnecessarily limits our understanding of the problems of development. Theories of development and world structure converge in world-systems theory. This world-systems perspective combined with information society theory provides a theoretical basis for understanding the role of information and communication technologies (ICTs) in globalization, not only for developing countries, but for the worldsystem as a whole. This research is premised on the view that the world operates as an interconnected network with increasingly interdependent economies. Since ICTs have not yet reached a substantial level of measurability in many countries, measures of telecommunications serve as a proxy for ICT growth and measurement of the effects of information content. The world-systems approach offers an alternative perspective that can provide a richer examination of the complex relationship between telecommunications and development. The role of telecommunications in development, broadly defined as economic, political, social, and cultural change, is explored. A structural equation model is developed to examine that perspective within the context of information society theory. Results of this model suggest telecommunications plays a broader role in development than that which has typically been limited to an economic perspective. Results also suggest that policies of multilateral development organizations do not reflect this broad perspective of development and do not, therefore, collect the data that are necessary to fully understand the role of telecommunications in development.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6199</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8151&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6199</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8151</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450285</context-key>
<withdrawn>2021-06-21</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6199</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Carol Tenopir</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>