<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Use of Dead Mussel Shells by Madtom Catfishes in the Green River</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-19T08:05:39-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>Jacob.brumley228@topper.wku.edu</email>
<institution>Western Kentucky University</institution>
<lname>Brumley</lname>
<fname>Jacob</fname>
<mname>F</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>philip.lienesch@wku.edu</email>
<institution>Western Kentucky University</institution>
<lname>Lienesch</lname>
<fname>Philip</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Madtom catfishes</keyword>
<keyword>mussel shells</keyword>
<keyword>cover</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Behavior and Ethology</discipline>
<discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The Green River in Kentucky has high fish and macroinvertebrate diversity. As both fish and macroinvertebrates have evolved together in this system, relationships have developed between species. One type of relationship that has been observed is between madtom catfishes (&lt;em&gt;Noturus &lt;/em&gt;spp.) and mussels in the Green River, where madtoms use dead mussel shells as cover when not actively foraging. In the fall of 2016 and 2017, surveys were conducted to determine if madtom catfishes use dead mussel shells more than rocks of similar size. We predicted that madtoms would select mussel shells as cover more frequently than rocks due to the natural concavity of mussel shells, which would not require excavation prior to use; rocks typically require removal of underlying substrates to create a cavity prior to use as cover. Three 12-meter by 12-meter plots were sampled at four sites along the Green River, once per year, by snorkeling in an upstream direction and searching for madtoms in dead mussel shells and under the rock substrate. Equal effort was used searching for madtoms under rocks and in mussel shells. Significantly more madtoms were found under mussel shells than under rocks of similar size. These results support our prediction and demonstrate the importance of mussel shells as cover for madtom catfishes. The decline of mussel populations, and resulting decline in available mussel shells in rivers and streams, may have negative effects on madtom populations in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1289&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1289</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-07-03T01:15:00-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1289/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>12432448</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>We would like to acknowledge the WKU Department of Biology and Center for Biodiversity Studies for the resources needed to conduct this study, along with the financial support from the WKU Office of Research and Creative Activity. We would like to thank the WKU Green River Preserve for the opportunity to conduct research on its property. We would like to acknowledge John Brumley and Henry Reynolds for help in the field, as well as Mike Compton for mussel identification. We would like to thank Dr. Scott Grubbs for reading and editing the manuscript and advising the project alongside Dr. Philip Lienesch.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0x1171d3b8)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Madtom use of Shells</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>