<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Anticytomegalovirus Peptides Point to New Insights for CMV Entry Mechanisms and the Limitations of In Vitro Screenings</title>
<publication-date>2019-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Jackson</lname>
<fname>Joseph</fname>
<mname>W.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hancock</lname>
<fname>Trevor</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dogra</lname>
<fname>Pranay</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Patel</lname>
<fname>Ravi</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>
<lname>Arav-Boger</lname>
<fname>Ravit</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Angela</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Kennel</lname>
<fname>Stephen</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wall</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>tsparer@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sparer</lname>
<fname>Tim</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>HCMV</keyword>
<keyword>MCMV</keyword>
<keyword>antiviral peptides</keyword>
<keyword>cytomegalovirus</keyword>
<keyword>entry</keyword>
<keyword>heparan sulfate</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is a ubiquitous betaherpesvirus that can cause severe disease following in utero exposure, during primary infection, or la- tent virus reactivation in immunocompromised populations. These complications lead to a 1- to 2-billion-dollar economic burden, making vaccine development and/or alternative treatments a high priority. Current treatments for HCMV include nucleoside analogues such as ganciclovir (GCV), foscarnet, and cidofovir. Recently, letermovir, a terminase complex inhibitor, was approved for prophylaxis after stem cell transplantation. These treatments have unwanted side effects, and HCMV is be- coming resistant to them. Therefore, we sought to develop an alternative treatment that targets a different stage in viral infection. Currently, small antiviral peptides are being investigated as anti-influenza and anti-HIV treatments. We have developed heparan sulfate-binding peptides as tools for preventing CMV infections. These pep- tides are highly effective at stopping infection of fibroblasts with in vitro-derived HCMV and murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV). However, they do not prevent MCMV infection in vivo. Interestingly, these peptides inhibit infectivity of in vivo-derived CMVs, albeit not as well as tissue culture-grown CMVs. We further demonstrate that this class of heparan sulfate-binding peptides is incapable of inhibiting MCMV cell- to-cell spread, which is independent of heparan sulfate usage. These data indicate that inhibition of CMV infection can be achieved using synthetic polybasic peptides, but cell-to-cell spread and in vivo-grown CMVs require further investigation to de- sign appropriate anti-CMV peptides.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_micrpubs/100</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1103&amp;amp;context=utk_micrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>100</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1103</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-07-30T20:20:11-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Microbiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15023767</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_micrpubs/100</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Jackson JW, Hancock TJ, Dogra P, Patel R, Arav-Boger R, Williams AD, Kennel SJ, Wall JS, Sparer TE. 2019. Anticytomegalovirus peptides point to new insights for CMV entry mechanisms and the limitations of in vitro screenings. mSphere 4:e00586-18. https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00586-18.</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.1128/mSphere.00586-18</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>mSphere</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>