<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Double-Hinged Di-1,2,4-Triazoles for Synthesis of Breathing MOFs</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cmurdock@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Murdock</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>Ray</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>metal-organic framework</keyword>
<keyword>flexibility</keyword>
<keyword>breathing</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Inorganic Chemistry</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Employing semi-rigid di-1,2,4-triazoles as ligands has led to the formation of a plethora of Metal-Organic Framework (MOF) architectures. The ability for the ligands to exhibit multiple conformations through a “hinge” effect allows for the formation of a multitude of MOF topologies and dimensionalities. Employment of a di-triazole containing a central &lt;em&gt;trans&lt;/em&gt;-butene moiety was initially studied and led to the formation of two three-dimensional copper MOFs. The frameworks can be synthesized independently, but a reaction occurs in water wherein the kinetic product is used as a reagent to synthesize the topologically distinct thermodynamic product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional testing of reaction conditions with the butene-containing di-triazole led to the formation of a three-dimensional breathing framework by utilizing a mixed anion system. The framework structure flexes reversibly upon removal or addition of water to form semi-hydrated and dehydrated MOFs. Single crystal X-ray analysis demonstrated the 2-butene subunit of the ligand rotates between positions, causing changes in the solvent accessible volume. This double hinge within the ligand is a built-in breathing mechanism and suggests a general synthesis for breathing MOFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing the central butene moiety with a xylene moiety resulted in the di-triazole adopting a &lt;em&gt;syn&lt;/em&gt; conformation between copper chains, forming two-dimensional MOFs that resemble fused 1D metal-organic nanotubes (MONTs). The 2D sheet layers can expand or contract, or, more remarkably, the phenyl ring can rotate between positions as a function of solvation. The transformations were followed by powder X-ray diffraction and solid state NMR. Additionally, frameworks which contain extended naphthyl and biphenyl linkers have been synthesized and characterized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;syn&lt;/em&gt; conformation adopted by the di-triazoles was further exploited for the formation of a series of 1D MONTs. The di-triazole ligands bridge rigid metal chains while appropriate anion choice provides a “capping” of the metal fragments, leading to nanotube formation instead of 2D sheets. The pore size of the MONTs can be adjusted by changing the central portion of the double-hinged ligand, allowing for a general synthesis of MONTs. Adsorption studies of MONTs revealed selective uptake of carbon dioxide and methane with copper MONTs exhibiting the highest uptake.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2772</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4005&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2772</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4005</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-20T23:49:18-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/4005/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>5175482</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2772</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David M. Jenkins</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Craig E. Barnes, Brian K. Long, David Mandrus</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>