<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Study of the Perceptions of Job Satisfaction of General and Special Education Teachers in Selected Georgia Elementary Schools Implementing the Inclusion Model</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Willard</lname>
<fname>Jonathan</fname>
<mname>Edward</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Elementary Education and Teaching</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate perceptions of job satisfaction of general and special education teachers.  Full-time teachers in grades K-5 in 26 randomly selected Georgia elementary schools were surveyed.  Differences in job satisfaction were measured through the use of the Minnesota Satisfaction Questionnaire – Short Form (MSQ) and a descriptive survey accompanying it.  Differences in responses based on the descriptors were analyzed using the Mann Whitney &lt;em&gt;U &lt;/em&gt;and multivariate analysis of variance at a confidence level of .05.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General education teachers reported greater levels of satisfaction than special education teachers on the MSQ scales of Achievement, Social Status, and Variety.  These scales are all intrinsic in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No statistically significant differences (.05, two-tailed) were found between general and special education teachers’ mean responses on the MSQ intrinsic, extrinsic, or general satisfaction scales.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4565</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6288&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4565</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6288</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-09-19T07:11:19-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10764281</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4565</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Thomas W. George</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary Jane Connelly, Ted Miller, Lloyd Davis, Kathy Puckett</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Education</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Teacher Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>