<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Foundations of Minority Leadership: Creating a Leadership Course Specifically For Our Needs</title>
<publication-date>2019-11-13T08:36:52-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>braxtonm@apsu.edu</email>
<institution>Austin Peay State University</institution>
<lname>Braxton</lname>
<fname>Marcelius</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>petersl@apsu.edu</email>
<institution>Austin Peay State University</institution>
<lname>Peters</lname>
<fname>Lorneth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Leadership Studies</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This presentation provides insight into a new hybrid, service-learning course introduced at Austin Peay State University entitled “Foundations of Minority Leadership”. With respect to leadership, individuals who are minorities often face difficulties that the majority does not have to consider.  As a result, minority individuals often do not have the opportunity to address issues that would be beneficial for their mentoring/leadership needs.  This presentation will highlight the structure of a course specifically for minority individuals.  It will also provide some examples of how two instructors use contemporary readings such as, “Minority Leader: How to Lead From the Outside and Make Real Change” by Stacey Abrams to provide methods for how to discuss, identify, and incorporate mentoring/leadership qualities through a contemporary framework meant particularly for individuals in the minority.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/omsaconference/2019/BIC19/5</coverpage-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1217</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-01-11T09:57:02-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/omsaconference/article/1217/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Black Issues Conference</publication-title>
<context-key>13608363</context-key>
<submission-path>omsaconference/2019/BIC19/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is interactive.  Participants will be working together to answer actual discussion board questions, and they will participate in multiple exercises that will be done in class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 potential exercises:&lt;/p&gt;
•SWOT Analysis (Strengths, Weaknesses, Opportunities, Threats)
•Board of Advisers (Sponsor, Adviser, Situational, Peer)
•Know That you Don’t Know (and Admit It)
•Ignorance is Bliss but Knowledge is Better</value>
</field>
<field name="equipneeds" type="string" list="true">
<value>Laptop for PowerPoint Presentations</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>Alumni Memorial Building</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>