<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Liver lipid molecules induce PEPCK-C gene transcription and attenuate insulin action.</title>
<publication-date>2007-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>gchen6@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>PEPCK</keyword>
<keyword>liver lipid</keyword>
<keyword>insulin</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Cytosolic phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK-C) plays key roles in gluconeogenesis, glyceroneogenesis, and cataplerosis. Experiments were designed to examine the effects of endogenous lipid molecules from rat livers on the expression of PEPCK-C gene in primary rat hepatocytes. The lipid extracts prepared from livers of Zucker fatty, lean, and Wistar rats induced the expression levels of PEPCK-C transcripts. Insulin-mediated reduction of PEPCK-C gene expression was attenuated by the same treatment. The lipid extracts induced the relative luciferase activity of reporter gene constructs that contain a 2.2-kb 5&#39; promoter fragment of PEPCK-C gene, but not the construct that contains only the 3&#39; untranslated region (UTR) of its mRNA. The estimated half life of PEPCK-C transcripts in the presence of the lipid extract is the same as that in the absence of it. My results demonstrate for the first time that endogenous lipid molecules induce PEPCK-C gene transcription and attenuate insulin action in liver.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1001&amp;amp;context=utk_nutrpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1001</articleid>
<submission-date>2009-11-11T20:32:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1061943</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2009-11-11T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>