<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Long-Term Trends in Water Quality for a High-Elevation Stream in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park: Impacts of Acid Deposition</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Smith</lname>
<fname>Angela</fname>
<mname>Vanessa</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the Southern Appalachians, high-elevation streams with small watershed areas tend to be sensitive to acid deposition (Deviney &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2006; Cook &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 1994) because high elevations tend to have more cloud contact, leading to greater atmospheric deposition of pollutants containing sulfate and nitrate acids (Lovett and Kinsman 1990). In a recent study by Webb &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;(2004) examined the link between atmospheric acid deposition and stream water quality in brook trout (&lt;em&gt;Salvelinus Fontinalis&lt;/em&gt;) streams in western Virginia and Shenandoah National Park (SNP). The study acknowledged that water quality improvement had been seen in response to reduced sulfate deposition in northern and eastern United States (U. S.) in regions that do not share the same watershed characteristics as the high-elevation Southern and Central Appalachians, which include SNP. In the study, Webb &lt;em&gt;et al. &lt;/em&gt;concluded that soil characteristics were the factors that retained sulfate in the system and prevented proportional stream water quality improvement. This type of study is necessary to understand water quality reactions and anticipate the best conservation measures to implement.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3682</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5032&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3682</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5032</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-02-11T11:18:40-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8131975</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3682</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>John S. Schwartz</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>R. Bruce Robinson, Randall W. Gentry</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;No Abstract, used part of Introduction.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>