<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Discrete and Complementary Mechanisms of Protection of β-Cells Against Cytokine-Induced and Oxidative Damage Achieved by bcl-2 Overexpression and a Cytokine Selection Strategy</title>
<publication-date>2003-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Chen</lname>
<fname>Guoxun</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas</institution>
<lname>Tran</lname>
<fname>Veronique</fname>
<mname>Vien</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Newgard</lname>
<fname>Christopher</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Duke University</institution>
<lname>Hohmeier</lname>
<fname>Hans</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;We have been investigating the potential utility of engineered cell lines as surrogates for primary islet cells in treatment of type 1 diabetes. To this end, two strategies that have emerged for procuring cell lines with resistance to immune-mediated damage are 1) selection of cytokine-resistant cell lines by growth of INS-1 insulinoma cells in iteratively increasing concentrations of interleukin (IL)-1β + γ-interferon (IFN-γ), and 2) stable overexpression of the anti-apoptotic gene bcl-2 in INS-1 cells. Herein, we show that bcl-2−overexpressing cells are resistant to the cytotoxic effects of reactive oxygen and nitrogen species (ROS/RNS), but are only modestly protected against high concentrations of IL-1β + INF-γ, whereas the converse is true in cytokine selected cells. We also found that the combination of bcl-2 expression and cytokine selection confers a broader spectrum of resistance than either procedure alone, such that the resultant cells are highly resistant to cytokines and ROS/RNS, with no impairment in glucose-stimulated insulin secretion. INS-1−derived cells with combined bcl-2 expression and cytokine selection are also more resistant to damage induced by coculture with mitogen-activated peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Surprisingly, application of the cytokine selection procedure to bcl-2−overexpressing cells does not result in impairment of nuclear factor-κB translocation, iNOS expression, and NO production, as clearly occurs upon application of the selection procedure to cells without bcl-2 overexpression. Further investigation of the diverse pathways involved in the development of cytokine and ROS/RNS resistance may define simplified and specific strategies for preservation of β-cell mass.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nutrpubs/5</coverpage-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1010</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-07-08T07:15:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Nutrition Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1386210</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nutrpubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>*  Veronique Vien Tran,
    * Guoxun Chen,
    * Christopher B. Newgard,
    * and Hans E. Hohmeier

Discrete and Complementary Mechanisms of Protection of β-Cells Against Cytokine-Induced and Oxidative Damage Achieved by bcl-2 Overexpression and a Cytokine Selection Strategy Diabetes June 2003 52:1423-1432; doi:10.2337/diabetes.52.6.1423</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-07-08T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/content/52/6/1423.abstract</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>