<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Monographic Studies in the Genus Polyporus (Basidiomycotina)</title>
<publication-date>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Krueger</lname>
<fname>Dirk</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Aphyllophorales</keyword>
<keyword>arthroconidia</keyword>
<keyword>classification</keyword>
<keyword>dimitic construction</keyword>
<keyword>homobasidiomycetes</keyword>
<keyword>mating studies</keyword>
<keyword>phylogeny</keyword>
<keyword>poroid hymenophore</keyword>
<keyword>taxonomy</keyword>
<keyword>stipitate</keyword>
<keyword>polypores</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Botany</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The aim of this dissertation research was an examination of the homobasidiomycete genus &lt;em&gt;Polyporus &lt;/em&gt;as currently circumscribed. Emphasis was on addressing the genus by a variety of tools appropriate to modern monographic studies, without producing another worldwide monograph. In addition to morphological examination, which traditionally was the basis of all fungal systematics, mating experiments with monokaryotic cultures, and contemporary phylogenetic tools were used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;P. alveolaris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. arcularius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. badius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. brumalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. ciliatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. dictyopus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;guianensis, &lt;em&gt;P. melanopus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. tubaeformis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. tuberaster&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. tricholoma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. umbellatus&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;varius a tetrapolar mating system was confirmed. Intercollection mate recognition was tested in &lt;em&gt;P. alveolaris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. arcularius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. brumalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. ciliatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. tubaeformis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. tuberaster&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;tricholoma, and &lt;em&gt;P. varius&lt;/em&gt;. In both &lt;em&gt;P. varius &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;P. tubaeformis &lt;/em&gt;cultures from European and North American collections were found to be compatible. In &lt;em&gt;P. tricholoma&lt;/em&gt;, the existence of at least two cryptic biological species entities was found to be contained under the species epithet, whereas in &lt;em&gt;P. alveolaris &lt;/em&gt;there may also be cryptic species. The type specimen of &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;tricholoma was studied and one of the &lt;em&gt;P. tricholoma &lt;/em&gt;cryptic species selected to represent &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;tricholoma proper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sequence analyses of nuclear ribosomal DNA were utilized to elucidate relationships of &lt;em&gt;Polyporus &lt;/em&gt;and allied genera. With large subunit (nLSU) data, the genus &lt;em&gt;Polyporus &lt;/em&gt;was found to be non-inclusive under current limits. The infrageneric group &lt;em&gt;Polyporellus &lt;/em&gt;was transferred into an emended genus &lt;em&gt;Lentinus&lt;/em&gt;, which traditionally was a genus of gilled fungi. The thelephoroid-hydnoid fungus &lt;em&gt;Mycobonia flava &lt;/em&gt;was transferred into &lt;em&gt;Polyporus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigation of relationships of infrageneric groups in &lt;em&gt;Polyporus &lt;/em&gt;revealed ITS region rDNA template heterogeneity, supported groups seen in nLSU analyses, and was able to differentiate morphological or biological species. Specific primers and RFLP markers for &lt;em&gt;P. &lt;/em&gt;tricholoma were evaluated for identification of cryptic species, but were rather successful in uncovering rDNA copy heterogeneity. As a consequence of molecular data and nomenclatural considerations, a new subgenus &lt;em&gt;Favoliporus &lt;/em&gt;was proposed to absorb infrageneric groups Favolus and &lt;em&gt;Admirabilis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2135</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3588&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2135</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3588</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-03T10:52:23-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4663445</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2135</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Ronald H. Petersen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Karen W. Hughes, Dr. Randall S. Small, Dr. Arthur C. Echternacht</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Botany</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>