<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Extending the Politeness Theory to Meditation Discourse: Does Facework Make a Difference?</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Tollison</lname>
<fname>Andrew</fname>
<mname>Craig</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Previous research has failed to determine which mediator characteristics have the greatest affect on participant satisfaction during the mediation process.  The four characteristics being analyzed in this study are politeness, facework, eye contact, and trust.  The concept of politeness suggests that mediation participants have an interest in maintaining face (i.e. positive and negative) while in the mediation session.  To avoid threatening the participants’ face, the mediator has five facework strategies to choose from.  These facework strategies, when articulated by the mediator, have the potential to combat potential face-threatening acts which can occur during the mediation process.  The use of eye contact by the mediator can help regulate the flow of communication with the mediation participant.  Finally, trust in the mediator should help to ensure a successful interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study is to investigate the relationship between politeness, facework, eye contact, and trust with the satisfaction of the mediation participant.  Respondents included 91 adults who were in the process or had previously completed mediation in Tennessee.  The survey was distributed to mediation centers around the state and was also made available online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findings revealed moderate to strong correlations among politeness, facework, eye contact, trust and participant satisfaction.  To help produce satisfaction in the mediation participant, the mediator must understand the expectations of the participant, create a working relationship with the participant, and respect the participants desire to be free from constraints.  When utilized by the mediator, the use of eye contact creates feelings of acceptance for the participant, which in turn increases participant satisfaction.  Also, the ability of the mediator to eliminate face-threatening acts helps and enhance trust helps determine participant satisfaction.  Further analysis and approaches for future research are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4594</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6126&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4594</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6126</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-26T10:25:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10080003</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4594</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kenneth Levine</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Michelle Violanti, John Haas</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>