<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Deferred empathy: A construct with implications for the mental health of older adults</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Gunther</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Deferred empathy occurs when an experience provokes a memory that after reflection allows people to say, “Now I understand.” Heretofore, the concept was explored only in quantitative research; therefore, the purpose of this phenomenological study was to elicit a more detailed description of the construct of deferred empathy. For most of the participants (n = 20) triggering events involved personal challenges such as loss, loss of control, or interpersonal conflict that reminded them of, and changed, their perception of earlier relationships. Development of empathy involved reflection on past and present events, making choices, changing expectations, and learning acceptance. The process resulted in appreciative understanding of others as well as personal benefits. Findings have implications for mental health promotion in older adults in which life review promotes gerotranscendence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/27</coverpage-url>
<label>27</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1027</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-06-23T10:54:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1369414</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/27</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Gunther, M. (2008). Deferred empathy: A construct with implications for mental health of older adults. &lt;em&gt;Issues in Mental Health Nursing&lt;/em&gt;, 29 (9), 1029-1040.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>