<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Impact of Computer Use on Food Service Organizations</title>
<publication-date>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Ference</lname>
<fname>Stephanie</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;An investigation was conducted in college and university food services to assess the present situation and probable future developments in the use of computers as well as to identify and evaluate the effect of computer use on employee skill requirements and employment trends. Results were obtained by two mail questionnaires. The first questionnaire inquired about the present and future use of the computer. The second questionnaire was used to evaluate the effect of computer utilization on employee skill requirements and labor trends. Eighty-five or 40% of the college and university food service directors responded to the questionnaire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forty-seven percent, or forty of the respondents did not utilize the computer. Fifty-three percent or forty-five of the respondents did utilize the computer. Twelve of the food service facilities utilizing the computer were making use of output pertaining to accounting transactions only. Food service employees of these facilities were not directly involved with the utilization of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computer functions least utilized and showing little potential for utilization, were sophisticated decision making functions such as simulation models and menu planning. Accounting and inventory functions were utilized to the greatest extent. Functions showing the most potential for future implementation were reports pertaining to production, sales and cost analysis, purchasing, and the use of standardized recipes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correlations were made between: (1) the number of meals served per day and the use of the computer; and (2) the number of meals served per day and the number of functions utilized. results indicate that a significant correlation did not exist for either relationship at a significant level of .05.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, there was an upgrading of skill requirements for the non-supervisory, supervisory, and administrative personnel. Although overall skill levels were rated as having increased for supervisory and administrative personnel only. Results indicated that there was no routinization, and no elimination of jobs for the non-supervisory employee. Routine supervisory tasks were eliminated as a result of utilization. Supervisory employees were felt to have more free time. Job elimination did not result at the supervisory level. Administrative decision making activities were shown to have increased. Routine tasks had been eliminated due to the use of the computer and there was no indication of job elimination at this level.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3727</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5278&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3727</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5278</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-07-27T10:11:45-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8887070</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3727</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Mary Jo Hitchcock</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kevin O&#39;Kane, Michael Evans</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1983-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>