<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>WORKING AT THE WATER&#39;S EDGE: Reconnecting the people of Charleston with the Water</title>
<publication-date>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mfox26@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Fox</lname>
<fname>Maria</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>charleston</keyword>
<keyword>ferry terminal</keyword>
<keyword>water</keyword>
<keyword>urban design</keyword>
<keyword>maritime center</keyword>
<keyword>architecture</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Historic Preservation and Conservation</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Water is a chemical compound fundamental to life. When many people first think of water, it is the water used for everyday activities and drinking that may come to mind. What is frequently overlooked is the fact that 71% of the Earth’s surface is covered with water and 96.5% of Earth’s water is found in oceans and seas (U.S. Geological Survey). What may not be as clear is the importance of these bodies of water to the surrounding towns and cities. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Since it’s founding in 1670, Charleston, South Carolina has always had a strong relationship with the water. One could call Charleston an aquatic project. The city is located in southeastern South Carolina, on a peninsula between the Cooper River and the Ashley River. You cannot find yourself getting far in or around Charleston without crossing over a body of water. Although the proximity of water has not always been a pleasant situation for Charleston with the Civil War, hurricanes, and ever changing water levels, it has helped shape the city to what it is today. This project is focused on bringing back Charleston’s connection with the water. With modern technology and innovations, locals and tourists have seemed to lose touch with the water on an everyday basis. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The design of a multi-use ferryboat terminal and maritime center located at the end of one of the most popular streets in the downtown area is going to reconnect both the locals and tourists of Charleston back with the water both visually and spatially. The city has acknowledged the problems with the end of Market Street and is looking to Cooper, Robinson &amp; Partners to work with the South Carolina State Ports Authority to redevelop this area. The major aspect of Cooper, Robinson &amp; Partners proposal is the newly designed cruise ship terminal and it’s new location. I have chosen to take some aspects of this proposal into consideration and to take advantage of the newly created view corridor down Market Street. With details such as “eco-parks”, restoration of the natural shoreline, interactive pedestrian bridges, viewing towers, and ferry boat routes, my design will bring back the industrial, historic character of Union Pier Terminal while creating opportunities for locals and visitors to experience something not yet found in Charleston, South Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2812</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3988&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2812</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3988</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-28T04:05:24-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>5234971</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2812</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>George P. Dodds</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas K. Davis, John M. McRae</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>