<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Tennessee&#39;s Promise: Education for All?</title>
<publication-date>2019-07-30T19:47:38-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>thighto1@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hightower</lname>
<fname>Tristan</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Tennessee</keyword>
<keyword>Promise</keyword>
<keyword>Tennessee Promise</keyword>
<keyword>Financial Aid</keyword>
<keyword>Scholarship</keyword>
<keyword>Community College</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>American Politics</discipline>
<discipline>Education Policy</discipline>
<discipline>Higher Education</discipline>
<discipline>Political Science</discipline>
<discipline>Public Affairs, Public Policy and Public Administration</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Access to education has been at the forefront of public policy issues over the past several years. In order to combat relatively low rates of college attainment, Tennessee legislators implemented the Tennessee Promise program. It operates by providing financial aid for any direct costs not covered by students’ grants and scholarships. Notably, the program is not applicable to four-year degree programs; students wishing to utilize the funds must attend select schools that offer certificates and associate’s degrees. Community colleges are the most popular. While a boost in community college attendance has occurred, and more people will likely graduate with an associate’s degree in the years to come, this raises an interesting question. Does restricting the choice of institution the recipients of this program have actually help to solve the education deficit in Tennessee? The number of unintended consequences suggests that the answer is no. The Tennessee Promise program is shortsighted in its goal and has serious implications for the state of education in Tennessee as a whole that future scholars should consider.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/pursuit/vol9/iss1/4</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1378&amp;amp;context=pursuit&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1378</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-01-08T08:40:51-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/pursuit/article/1378/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Pursuit - The Journal of Undergraduate Research at The University of Tennessee</publication-title>
<context-key>11334683</context-key>
<submission-path>pursuit/vol9/iss1/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>I have incurred multiple debts through the completion of this article and owe many people more than I can ever offer. First, I would like to thank the administration and staff of the Honors and Scholars Programs at UT. In particular, the guidance and encouragement from Tim Hulsey, Kristina Cantin, and Rebekah Page gave me the confidence to start and finish the project. My thesis advisor, Anthony Nownes, offered valuable feedback and support throughout the entire length of the project. Without him, I would not have been able to turn my wandering thoughts into cogent ideas. I would also like to thank my wife, Emily, who commented on many drafts and was always there during successes and failures. I owe much to my family who was there to listen at all times, day or night - my parents, Jim and Toni, and my brother, Caleb. Finally, the anonymous reviewers of the article provided many helpful comments that made the article better.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2018-01-08T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xc406570)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Tennessee&#39;s Promise: Education for All?</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>