<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Design and Implementation of EEG-Based Brain Computer Interfaces for Neuroprosthetics and Neurorehabilitation</title>
<publication-date>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rabiri@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Abiri</lname>
<fname>Reza</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Brain Computer Interface (BCI) technology motivates interesting and promising results in forward/feedback control consistent with human intention. It holds great promise for advancements in patient care and applications to neuroprosthetics and neurorehabilitation. Here, as forward control in BCI neuroprosthetics, a fundamental testbed for controlling a computer cursor was designed using noninvasive Electroencephalography (EEG) technology. In order to reduce the training time for subjects, a new paradigm called “Imagined Body Kinematics” was adopted in designed experimental protocols. Twenty-eight subjects were trained (about 10 minutes) to perform the cursor control task. The subjects were asked to answer a pre- and a post-questionnaire before and after the experiment, respectively. Several confounding variables were investigated to evaluate their correlation with subjects’ performance in training and control task. Thereafter, the developed cursor control platform was applied in Brain Machine Interfaces to control different robotic devices to confirm the potential application of investigated paradigm in neuroprosthetics control. As another interesting area in BCI, a new EEG-based BCI platform was developed to evaluate attentional states in six subjects (as pilot study) and in thirty-eight subjects (as extended study) for feedback control in neurorehabilitation. For the first time, the features from whole brain were employed in two-class classification of attentional states. By introducing a new experimental paradigm for stimuli and neurofeedback, it was discussed how the platform could have the potential application in attention training of people with cognitive deficit.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4813</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6353&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4813</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6353</articleid>
<submission-date>2018-11-08T14:09:17-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>13276397</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4813</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Xiaopeng Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Anahita Khojandi, Jindong Tan, Eric R. Wade</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8975-8210&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>