<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Consumers’ Perceptions of and Responses to Green Cause-Related Marketing</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Saylor</lname>
<fname>Betsy</fname>
<mname>Suzanne</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Communication</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In the last few decades, cause-related marketing has been increasingly refined as a method for companies to go beyond meeting the material needs of consumers (Marconi, p. xi). As cause-related marketing has developed, the variety of tactics, causes, and ethical issues has become more prevalent. The nature of cause-related marketing is conducive to a growing number of approaches, further narrowing and defining target markets through the selection of more specific causes. Competing alongside the marketing campaigns supporting cancer research is cause-related marketing geared toward restoring native species in the county of a company’s headquarters. The purpose of this study is to gain a better understanding of consumer perceptions of and responses to cause-related marketing when the cause is an environmental issue (green cause-related marketing). Long interviews were conducted to obtain feedback about consumers’ perceptions of and responses to such marketing. Results included that green cause-related marketing is effective with high and low cause-involved consumers; green cause-related marketing is persuasive with high and low levels of purchase involvement; and socially concerned consumers’ skepticism does not necessarily preclude their interest in green cause-related marketed products.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2287</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3773&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2287</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3773</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-17T13:00:53-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4734014</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2287</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Candace White</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sarah Gardial, Bonnie Riechert</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Communication</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>