<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Metabolic Pathway Analysis: A Useful Tool for Characterizing Cellular Metabolism</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ctrinh@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Trinh</lname>
<fname>Cong</fname>
<mname>T</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Wlaschin</lname>
<fname>Aaron</fname>
<mname>P</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Minnesota - Twin Cities</institution>
<lname>Srienc</lname>
<fname>Friedrich</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Metabolic pathway analysis</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<disciplines><discipline>Biochemical and Biomolecular Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Elementary mode analysis is a useful metabolic pathway analysis tool to identify the structure of a metabolic network that links the cellular phenotype to the corresponding genotype. The analysis can decompose the intricate metabolic network comprised of highly interconnected reactions into uniquely organized pathways. These pathways consisting of a minimal set of enzymes that can support steady state operation of cellular metabolism represent independent cellular physiological states. Such pathway definition provides a rigorous basis to systematically characterize cellular phenotypes, metabolic network regulation, robustness, and fragility that facilitate understanding of cell physiology and implementation of metabolic engineering strategies. This mini-review aims to overview the development and application of elementary mode analysis as a metabolic pathway analysis tool in studying cell physiology and as a basis of metabolic engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<fpage>813</fpage>
<lpage>826</lpage>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_chembiopubs/91</coverpage-url>
<label>91</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1091</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-02-04T13:46:42-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering</publication-title>
<context-key>3779584</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_chembiopubs/91</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Trinh, C., Wlaschin, A., Srienc, F. (2009). Metabolic pathway analysis: a useful tool for characterizing cellular metabolism. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 81(5):813-26. doi: 10.1007/s00253-008-1770-1.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19015845</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>