<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Use of Sulfur Chloride Systems in the Digestion and Purification of Zircaloy Nuclear Fuel Cladding</title>
<publication-date>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jtravi13@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Travis</lname>
<fname>Jordan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The overarching goal of this research has been to develop and understand a low-temperature protocol for the digestion of zirconium nuclear fuel cladding. The basic goal will be to reduce the used cladding to low-level radiological waste that can be disposed of more easily and at a reduced cost. A “blue sky” goal will be to eventually recycle the cladding to be reused in industrial processes.  A hypothesis of this project is that by using various sulfur chloride compounds, the digestion of Zircaloy® can be converted to zirconium(IV) tetrachloride (ZrCl4) at low temperatures and the purification/decontamination can be accomplished through a crystallization using thionyl chloride or other sulfur chloride reagents. Three sulfur chloride reagents were investigated, thionyl chloride (SOCl2), sulfur dichloride (SCl2) and sulfur monochloride (S2Cl2). At 150 °C for each of these reactions the speed at which they digest the metal is very different. For SOCl2 (2.937 g Zr, 1.3 times of excess SOCl2), 30 – 40 hours; SCl2 (3.033 g Zr), 28 hours; and S2Cl2 (2.950 g Zr, 2.5 times excess of S2Cl2), 3 hours. Recrystallization of ZrCl4 was accomplished using SOCl2 and preliminary study of ZrCl4 in SOCl2 was conducted. A cloud point technique was used to determine the solubility. This was accomplished by dissolving ZrCl4 in SOCl2 then removing SOCl2 at a specific temperature until crystallization occurred. The solubility was high at high temperature and was very temperature dependent over the range of 0 °C to 50 °C, the solubility increased by a factor of almost 4. Understanding the solubility will aid in the development of a purification strategy due to high-temperature dependence.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5502</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6975&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5502</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6975</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-08-13T21:48:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>18914288</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5502</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Craig Barnes</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>David Jenkins, Konstantinos Vogiatzis, Stephen Chmely</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Chemistry</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>