<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Maternal Employment and Dietary Quality of Children Aged 42-60 Months</title>
<publication-date>1999-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Samson</lname>
<fname>Lynn</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From the Summary&lt;/em&gt;): Abbreviated                   Maternal employment is becoming more the usual than an exception. Employment can be beneficial for mothers, providing satisfaction and increasing self-esteem. On the other hand, it can be stressful juggling between the roles of employee and mother. Other family members might help ease some of the burden, but mothers still bear most of the responsibility of child care and household responsibilities. Working mothers have less time to spend on food and nutrition. In most cases, the diets of children whose mothers are employed do not differ from children of mothers who are not employed, but this subject has not been extensively examined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this literature review on maternal employment and dietary quality of children was to explore reasons why mothers choose or do not choose employment, how maternal employment impacts family members including children, and how the dietary quality of children whose mothers are employed compares to children of nonworking mothers. Women&#39;s participation in the workforce has steadily increased and this increase will likely affect the lives of children. The final chapter of this thesis will describe the dietary quality of children of employed and unemployed mothers over a year and a half time period. This study was designed to determine differences in nutrient intakes, dietary variety, and eating occasions away from home of children with employed mothers compared to children of unemployed mothers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3893</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5376&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3893</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5376</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-24T07:45:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9025264</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3893</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jean D. Skinner</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Betty R. Carruth, Priscilla Blanton</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1999-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1999-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>