<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Embodying Mycenaean Cultural Identity in Late Bronze Age Central Greece: A Bioarchaeological Analysis</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kstiles4@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Stiles</lname>
<fname>Kaitlyn</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Social Bioarchaeology</keyword>
<keyword>Late Bronze Age Greece</keyword>
<keyword>Greek Archaeology</keyword>
<keyword>Cultural Identity</keyword>
<keyword>Mycenaean Culture</keyword>
<keyword>Skeletal Biology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This research is a bioarchaeological examination of the biocultural manifestation of Mycenaean cultural identity in the Late Bronze Age (ca. 1600-1100 BCE) rock cut chamber tomb cemetery of Golemi Agios Georgios (“Golemi”) in central Greece. Biological correlates for Mycenaean cultural identity were identified from current archaeological narratives of Mycenean cultural identity. A biological profile including the minimum number of individuals, age, sex, cranial and dental non-metric traits, non-specific indicators of disease, activity markers, and evidence for cranial trauma was developed for each tomb. The results of these analyses were used to explore the extent to which the mortuary community of Golemi embodied the archaeologically defined Mycenaean cultural identity. Hierarchical Bayesian analysis was used to examine whether some tombs demonstrated significantly more or less of a given skeletal trait. Chi-square and Fisher’s exact tests for independence investigated possible relationships between age, sex, social status, and various indicators of health. The results of all analyses were combined to identify potential spatial relationships between tombs in the cemetery. The results of these analyses indicate that the individuals of Golemi do embody Mycenaean cultural identity, but the extent to which each tomb expresses this identity is variable. Contrary to the overt image of male dominance in Mycenaean cultural identity, females and males are equally represented in the cemetery and female individuals, on average, survived longer than did male individuals. The special treatment of some juveniles and their variable presence in tombs indicates that including juveniles was a highly individualized decision. A significant relationship between non-specific indicators of disease and status was observed suggesting a spectrum of social statuses existed among the tomb groups. The location of wealthy, healthy tomb groups next to relatively poor, less healthy groups may indicate that social networks dictated burial placement rather than familial relationships, thereby reflecting the networked nature of Mycenean culture. Finally, the persistence of Golemi throughout tumultuous periods of the Late Bronze Age suggests that the community was able to successfully adapt to the changing social climate.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5706</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7472&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5706</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7472</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419562</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5706</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dawnie Steadman, Aleydis Van de Moortel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Graciela Cabana, Stephen Collins-Elliot</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Anthropology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2020-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>