<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The relationship between aggression and work performance among temporary employees</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Wolf</lname>
<fname>Brenda</fname>
<mname>Faye</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study explored the impact of gender, race, education level, arrest record, marital status, and aggression on work performance among temporary employees over a 90-day evaluation period. The sample consisted of 144 temporary employees from a professional temporary service who were all placed in entry-level production positions in an industrial company located in the southeastern United States. Predictor data were collected from these employees during their registration process with the professional temporary service, and performance data were obtained from the industrial company following a 90-day probation period. Results from this study indicated that there was no significant difference between the temporary employees&#39; aggression scores in relation to their work performance over the 90-day evaluation period.  Findings from this study also indicated that the demographic variables had no relationship with the temporary employees&#39; work performance, aggression scores, or arrest records.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5319</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6727&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5319</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6727</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847275</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5319</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ernest W. Brewer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>