<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Public Health Nutrition Field Experience with the Chattanooga-Hamilton County, Tennessee, Health Department in 1973</title>
<publication-date>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Colvard</lname>
<fname>Charlotte</fname>
<mname>Bickford</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Nutrition</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis describes and analyzes the student&#39;s seven weeks of field training within the Nutrition Service of the Chattanooga-Hamilton County Health Department. This experience provided the student with appropriate background experience for her future role as a public health nutritionist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field experience gives the student in public health nutrition an opportunity to work with allied health personnel under supervision and to apply the theories and principles of public health learned during the academic year to the practice of public health nutrition in the community. The experience was designed to strengthen the student&#39;s philosophy and practical understanding of public health by introducing her to the practice of public health in the official health agency and the community. It provides a better understanding of the role of nutrition in the health agency, with a practical application to individuals and families. Experiences in a consultant capacity with other agencies was also offered. The student was given the opportunity to develop both her professional and personal abilities in carrying out applied nutrition programs in the health agency with community groups. Assignment to a specific area of the county provided responsibility similar to that of a new nutrition staff member in a county setting.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3836</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5317&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3836</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5317</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-10T12:52:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8959245</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3836</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Daniel Hubbard</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Roy Beauchene, Brent Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Nutrition</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1973-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>