<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Efficacy of Extending the Voluntary Waiting Period in Lactating Dairy Cows to Improve Fertility of Sex-Sorted Semen</title>
<publication-date>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>sorr6@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Orr</lname>
<fname>Sarah</fname>
<mname>E.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Voluntary Waiting Period</keyword>
<keyword>Sex-Sorted Semen</keyword>
<keyword>Lactating Dairy Cows</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Dairy Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to compare fertility of sex-sorted semen in lactating cows using a voluntary waiting period (&lt;strong&gt;VWP&lt;/strong&gt;) of approximately 55 days (&lt;strong&gt;VWP55&lt;/strong&gt;) or 85 days (&lt;strong&gt;VWP85&lt;/strong&gt;). At 21 days in milk (&lt;strong&gt;DIM&lt;/strong&gt;), cows were randomly assigned to begin estrus synchronization at 55 or 85 DIM. Only cows confirmed cyclic by 55 DIM were synchronized. At 55 or 85 DIM, cows [VWP55 (n=44); VWP85 (n=45)] having a corpus luteum (&lt;strong&gt;CL&lt;/strong&gt;) were administered PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α &lt;/sub&gt;[two alpha]. Estrus was monitored continuously by the HeatWatch® [registered sign] system (&lt;strong&gt;HW&lt;/strong&gt;) and by twice daily visual observation seven days following each PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α&lt;/sub&gt;. Cows exhibiting estrus were artificially inseminated with sex-sorted Holstein semen using one of two different bulls having similar sire conception rates. After 14 days, PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α&lt;/sub&gt; was administered to any cow that did not exhibit estrus. Cows not responding to either PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α &lt;/sub&gt;administration were administered GnRH and a controlled intravaginal drug releasing device (&lt;strong&gt;CIDR&lt;/strong&gt;). Seven days later, CIDR was removed and PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α&lt;/sub&gt; was administered. Pregnancy determination occurred 28 to 35 days after AI and was monitored at 60, 80, and 150 days. No difference in overall percentage of cows expressing estrus (79.55% and 77.78%, P = 0.8393), hours to estrus following either the first or all PGF&lt;sub&gt;2α &lt;/sub&gt;administrations (65.79 h and 72.65 h, P = 0.4908; 62.28 h and 73.00 h, P = 0.2218, respectively), number of mounts (9.05 and 10.54, P = 0.5246), average mount duration (4.59 s and 4.99 s, P = 0.2602), and total estrus length (8.16 h and 9.17 h, P = 0.6389) was observed between VWP55 and VWP85 cows. Conception rates 30 days after AI were significantly higher for VWP85 cows compared to VWP55 (51.43% vs. 22.86%, respectively; P = 0.0181). Conception rates were monitored at 60 (48.57% vs. 20.00%, respectively; P = 0.0166), 80 (42.86% vs. 20.00%, respectively; P = 0.0471), and 150 days after AI (42.86% vs. 20.00%, respectively; P = 0.0471) to monitor embryonic loss. Fertility of sex-sorted semen in lactating cows can be improved after a VWP of 85 days under specific management conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3598</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4923&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3598</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4923</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-10-09T08:36:20-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>7699342</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3598</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>J. Lannett Edwards</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>F. Neal Schrick, Justin D. Rhinehart</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Animal Science</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>