<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>A Simulation Based Approach for Determining Maintenance Strategies</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Murthi</lname>
<fname>Vasanth</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Other Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing organizations are continuously in the mode of identifying and implementing mechanisms to achieve a competitive edge. To this point manufacturers have recognized the critical role of equipment in the productivity of manufacturing operations. With the current trend of manufacturers attempting to lean out their production processes, primary and auxiliary equipment have become even more important to manufacturers as measured by productivity, quality, delivery, and cost metrics. As a result of the focus on lean manufacturing, maintenance management has found a new vigor and purpose to increase equipment capacity and capability. However, the most proactive maintenance strategy is not always the most effective utilization of resources. It is typical for manufacturers to integrate both reactive and proactive maintenance to define a cost effective maintenance strategy. A simulation-based approach is presented that allows an end user to develop such a maintenance strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2131</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3497&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2131</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3497</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-07T12:41:00-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4677305</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2131</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Rupy Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Denise Jackson, Dr. Thomas Shannon</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>