<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Glyphosate Resistant Palmer amaranth (&lt;i&gt;Amaranthus palmeri&lt;/i&gt;) management late-season and POST-harvest in corn production systems</title>
<publication-date>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>whidcrow@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Crow</lname>
<fname>Whitney</fname>
<mname>D.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The objectives of this research were to evaluate control options for glyphosate resistant (GR) Palmer amaranth (&lt;em&gt;Amaranthus palmeri&lt;/em&gt;) latelate-season in corn systems and POST-harvest for the prevention of seed production. Our results determined that the best late-season control methods were treatments tank-mixed with dicamba plus diflufenzopyr. These tank-mixtures improved control from 10 to 46% [percent] over treatments without the dicamba premix. Tankmixtures with dicamba plus diflufenzopyr that provided weed control &gt; [greater than] 96% 28 DAA included &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;-metolachlor plus glyphosate plus mesotrione and tembotrione plus thiencarbazone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the prevention of POST-harvest GR palmer amaranth seed production, our results determined that paraquat provides excellent initial control of existing vegetation but regrowth can occur from larger plants. The addition of a residual herbicide may aid in controlling regrowth as well as preventing plant germination. All treatments provided enough control for the prevention of seed production. Through implementation of POST-harvest management practices, 1200 seed per m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; [meter squared] was prevented from replenishing the soil seed bank. There were no adverse affects on wheat yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these results, we can conclude that when practicing POST only weed management strategies, application timing is vital for the prevention of corn loss and that implementation of late-season weed management programs can effectively reduce weed seed rain, therefore reducing weed seed bank densities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3143</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4212&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3143</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4212</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-10-06T08:59:09-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4212/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6208416</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3143</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Lawrence E. Steckel</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Robert M. Hayes, Thomas C. Mueller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Plant Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>