<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effect of Processing Parameters on Barrier Properties of Polymers</title>
<publication-date>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>rlhjr@icx.net</email>
<lname>Hallman</lname>
<fname>Russell</fname>
<mname>Louis</mname>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Permeation</keyword>
<keyword>Polymer</keyword>
<keyword>Degree of crystallinity</keyword>
<keyword>morphology</keyword>
<keyword>diffusion</keyword>
<keyword>solubility</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Polymer and Organic Materials</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The intent of this work was to learn if polyethylene could be made with predictable water transfer rates by control of the microstructure. A series of films were formed from three different polyethylenes with a range crystallinities using melt pressing, a controlled cooling rate, and subsequent heat treatments. The samples were tested on a novel device called the polymer characterization device that measures the water transfer flux as a function of temperature. The samples’ morphology was examined using differential gradient column, differential scanning calorimetry, Fourier transform infrared microscopy, wide-angle X-ray diffractions, small-angle X-ray scattering, and small angle light scattering, and scanning electron microscopy. When the water transfer flux was expressed as the frost point of a dry carrier gas the results showed a remarkable sensitivity that allows for analysis of subtle distinction in rates due to changes in morphology. Analysis showed that the water transfer flux is a function of the polymer, conditions of the samples preparation from the melt, and any subsequent heat treatment. Another interesting finding was that the time for the sample to reach a steady state water transfer flux is a function of morphology. A free volume model was developed to that simulates the response of the polymer as a function of morphology, presence of water, and thermal cycling. The conclusion of this work is that the water transfer flux is a function of the specific polymer, the initial formation conditions, and later heat treatments and with this knowledge the polymer could be made with a specific water transfer flux.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2430</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2480&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2430</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2480</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-03-14T06:22:05-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_graddiss/article/2480/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>2666317</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2430</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Roberto Benson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Kevin Kit, David Joy, Christopher P. Stephens</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Polymer Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>