<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Reliability and Validity of the UNIT - Gifted Screening Scale (UNIT - GSS)</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Gray</lname>
<fname>Rebecca</fname>
<mname>Grace</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The psychometric integrity of the UNIT - Gifted Screening Scale (UNIT -GSS; McCallum &amp; Bracken, in press) was explored by examining Cronbach&#39;s Alphas for each of its scales (reliabilities ranged from .95 to .98). In addition, the concurrent validity was evaluated by comparing scores from non-academically oriented UNIT-GSS scales to other instruments that measure the same constructs for 106 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; through 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; grade students, rated either by their teachers or themselves, on the UNIT-GSS, the Gifted Rated Scales (GRS; Pfeiffer &amp; Jarosewich, 2003), and a self-report instrument designed to measure emotional intelligence, the Bar-On Emotional Quotient: Youth Version Short Form (Bar-On EQ-i: YV [S]; Bar-On &amp; Parker, 2000). To assess concurrent validity of the UNIT-GSS academic scales, scores on and end-of-year achievement test, the Terra Nova Comprehensive Test of Basic Skills (CTBS; CTB, 1996) were compared (to the academically oriented UNIT-GSS scales). Coefficients for &quot;like&quot; constructs ranged from .46 to .85 (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001). Finally, providing evidence of construct validity, all UNIT-GSS scale means for 53 students who participated in a Gifted and Talented program were significantly higher (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &lt; .001) than their matched non-gifted peers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4228</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5923&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4228</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5923</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-03-27T11:54:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9930120</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4228</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>R. Steve McCallum</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tricia McClam, Sherry Bain, John W. Lounsbury</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>