<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The predictors of turnover intentions : an investigation of front-line employees in the retail industry</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Daves</lname>
<fname>Hester</fname>
<mname>Alicia</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to investigate turnover intentions among front-line retail employees. The independent variables examined were work-family conflict, family-work conflict, pay satisfaction, job satisfaction, and organizational commitment. Relationships among the independent variables were also examined. Data were collected from four mass-merchandise retailers in the southeast. The final sample consisted of 282 front-line employees, which was a 30.6 percent response rate. The survey included 45 items that measured the variables along with demographic questions and an area for additional comments. Structural equation modeling was used to evaluate ten hypotheses. The overall fit of the turnover intention structural equation model was supported by a comparative fit index (CFI) of 0.935. Positive significant relationships were found between work-family conflict and family-work conflict, pay satisfaction and job satisfaction, pay satisfaction and organizational commitment, and job satisfaction and organizational commitment. There was a positive direct impact found from family-work conflict on turnover intentions. Negative significant relationships were found between work-family conflict and job satisfaction, work-family conflict and organizational commitment, family-work conflict and pay satisfaction, and family-work conflict and organizational commitment. Negative direct impacts were found from pay satisfaction on turnover intentions and from organizational commitment on turnover intentions.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6221</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8173&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6221</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8173</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450312</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6221</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ann Fairhurst</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nancy Fair, Laura Jolly, Mary Sue Younger</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>