<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>ONE KNOXville</title>
<publication-date>2016-04-12T09:22:33-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mwill168@vols.utk.edu</email>
<lname>Williams</lname>
<fname>Mustapha A Farrankhan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;East Knoxville was once a vibrant community for many African-Americans. Stores, schools, and churches all populated the area giving the African-American community a sense of pride. Between 1964 and 1974, however, urban renewal disrupted this community with the construction of James White Parkway and the Knoxville Civic Coliseum and Auditorium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ONE KNOXville intends to bridge the gap between the two neighborhoods. Downtown Knoxville and East Knoxville can once again be connected, socially and economically. An interstate cap will be the component that connects the two neighborhoods. Along with the community aspect, Cal Johnson Park will have the ability to bring money to the city of Knoxville. With a baseball stadium, rentable soccer/football spaces, private retail areas, office and residential space, the city of Knoxville will be able to gain revenue from this development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Situated where the East Knoxville Police Precinct currently sits will be a new hockey arena. Seating about 5,000 the arena will be the new home for the Knoxville Ice Bears, as well as hosting concerts, sports events, and other large activities. There is a practice rink that shares the same zone as a public hockey rink. These two rinks can be used interchangeably among the public during the off-season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connected to the arena and adjacent to the public hockey rink is a large community center. The community center is accessible by Green Middle Magnet School located north of the site on a hill. A new greenway creates a safe, natural zone where students can leave school and go down the hill to the community center. At the west end of the community center is a media and history center of the East Knoxville area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ONE KNOXville development is to be mainly for people to engage the streets by walking, biking, or taking public transportation. Acting as the crown of the development is a 40-story residential tower. This tower, designed to be for multiple levels of income, will have astonishing views of downtown and the Great Smokey Mountains. The entire development is meant to both connect two areas of Knoxville that were separated years ago while also enticing people from around the region to come visit, and stay, in Knoxville.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_eureca/2016/architecturedesign/1</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1104&amp;amp;context=utk_eureca&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1104</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-11T10:25:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>EURēCA: Exhibition of Undergraduate Research and Creative Achievement</publication-title>
<context-key>8459106</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_eureca/2016/architecturedesign/1</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="college" type="string">
<value>College of Architecture and Design</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="faculty_mentor" type="string">
<value>Marleen Davis</value>
</field>
<field name="year" type="date">
<value>2016-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>