<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>An exploratory investigation of three NCAA division I African-American athletes&#39; aspirations of a career in professional football</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>McMaster</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to explore the possible factors related to career aspirations (dreams) of three African American male athletes with regard to their thoughts/attitudes about how cultural and social variables in life and sport have shaped them and their career aspirations. African-American male athletes from Division I-A football programs were interviewed to obtain a deeper understanding of their experience with sport socialization, academic achievement and how these may or may not have shaped their career aspirations. These interviews were transcribed and analyzed using qualitative research methods. The results revealed five themes that were poignant in the athletes&#39; experiences: 1) influences on self, 2) preparation in life; 3) emphasizing academics; 4) career choice; and 5) my thoughts on race. Conclusions and recommendations for sport researchers and coaches followed discussion of the potential of qualitative research methodology for studies of this nature.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5963</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7596&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5963</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7596</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-22T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>23467625</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5963</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Leslee A. Fisher</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Craig A. Wrisberg, Joy T. DeSensi</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Performance and Sport Studies</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>