<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>TIPS: Telephone Intervention-Problem Solving for persons with Schizophrenia</title>
<publication-date>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Beebe</lname>
<fname>Lora</fname>
<mname>Humphrey</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Florida</institution>
<lname>Tian</lname>
<fname>Lili</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A prospective experimental design was used to examine whether face-to-face meetings designed to establish rapport had an effect on the verbal responses of persons with schizophrenia in subsequent Telephone Intervention—Problem Solving (TIPS). Verbal responsiveness was operationalized as length of telephone conversation, number of feeling statements expressed, and number of one-word responses. Experimental participants met with the TIPS provider twice during hospitalization, while controls did not meet with the TIPS provider. All subjects received TIPS weekly from a psychiatric nurse for six weeks after hospital discharge. Compared to controls, experimental participants conversed longer at every measurement point, and significantly longer during weeks one through three. Experimental participants were approximately twice as likely to make a feeling statement as those in the control group. These data suggest that psychiatric nurses who would like to employ TIPS to support clients in the community should plan for at least two face-to-face interventions to establish rapport prior to initiating TIPS.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_nurspubs/134</coverpage-url>
<label>134</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1134</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-09-10T08:54:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Nursing</publication-title>
<context-key>1550308</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_nurspubs/134</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Beebe, L.H. &amp; Tian, L. (2004). TIPS: Telephone Intervention-Problem Solving for persons with Schizophrenia.
Issues in Mental Health Nursing.25 (3), 317-329.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://informahealthcare.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01612840490274804</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>