<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>From Trials to Triumph: The Influence of Service Dogs for Children with Autism in the Family and Classroom</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-11T11:15:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ariane.schratter@maryvillecollege.edu</email>
<institution>Maryville College</institution>
<lname>Schratter</lname>
<fname>Ariane</fname>
<mname>K.</mname>
<suffix>Dr.</suffix>
</author>
<author>
<email>kristy.niemeyer@my.maryvillecollege.edu</email>
<institution>Maryville College</institution>
<lname>Niemeyer</lname>
<fname>Kristy</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Animal Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Mental and Social Health</discipline>
<discipline>Psychiatry and Psychology</discipline>
<discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is one of the most common and widely known developmental disorders of public and international concern. Early studies using dogs in Animal Assisted Intervention (AAI) reported benefits in children’s physical, emotional, and social behaviors such as increased socially appropriate, responsible, and nurturing behaviors and decreased isolation (e.g., Martin &amp; Farnum, 2002). Using AAI for children with autism is noteworthy since these specially trained dogs appear to rapidly reduce the children’s impulsive running, self-harm, mood swings, night-awakenings, and social isolation through specific actions such as retrieving the child, crawling on the child to calm him/her, alerting parents, and responding to child’s verbal commands. These service dogs are unique since they are trained to interrupt perseverating or self-stimulatory behaviors by nudging the child, for example, to break the child’s concentration and redirect the child’s focus. The relationship between a child and his/her dog may also act as a bridge to meaningful human relationships. The non-threatening nature of the animal may act as a social buffer and catalyst, which has important implications for the treatment of children with autism (Burrows, 2005). Despite the success of using service dogs, several schools around the nation have not allowed service dogs for children with autism to attend school. For this presentation, we highlight the cases of two seven-year old boys with autism and their service dogs (trained by Wilderwood Service Dogs). These children represent the diversity within autism as they exhibit very different behavioral characteristics and use of language. Further, one family has been able to successfully integrate their service dog into the classroom with their child while the other child’s dog is currently not permitted into school. Using data (Pervasive Developmental Disabilities Inventory) and information provided by the families, school staff, Wilderwood Service Dogs, and video-taped observations, we will discuss the process by which the service dogs are trained to meet the children’s unique needs, the degree to which the dogs bond with their immediate and extended families, and the challenges and successes associated with integrating the dogs into the family and classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burrows, K. E. (2005). Service Dogs for Children with Autism Spectrum Disorder: Benefits, Challenges, and Welfare Implications (Unpublished Master’s Thesis). The University of Guelph, Ontario, Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin, F., &amp; Farnum, J. (2002). Animal-assisted therapy for children with pervasive developmental disorders. Western Journal of Nursing Research, 24, 657-670.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april11/19</coverpage-url>
<label>19</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1045</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-11-05T14:55:28-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3448168</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april11/19</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Dr. Ariane Schratter is an Associate Professor of Psychology at Maryville College (Maryville, Tennessee) where her research interests focus on the effects of service dogs for children with autism. Dr. Schratter earned her Ph. D. in Experimental Psychology from the University of Tennessee in 2000, her MA in Psychology from California State University, Sacramento in 1996, and her BA in Psychology from California State University, Sonoma in 1991. Dr. Schratter joined Maryville College in 2000 where she currently teaches classes regarding Child Development, Psychology of Exceptional Children, and International Child Welfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristy Niemeyer is a senior at Maryville College in Maryville, Tennessee. She will receive a BA in Psychology upon graduation in May 2012. Her areas of interest are children and adults with special needs, particularly those with autism spectrum disorders, and also the human-animal bond as it pertains to individuals with special needs. She plans to pursue a Masters Degree in Special Education upon graduation from Maryville College, and after completing the degree, follow a teaching career.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Ariane K. Schratter, 919 S. Court Street, Maryville, TN 37803, 865.680.2288&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristy B. Niemeyer, 240 Foxglove Lane, Maryville, TN 37801, 865.274.1230&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:45:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>LECONTE</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Podium: 30-minute podium presentation</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:15:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-11T11:15:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Animal assisted interactions</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>yes</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>