<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Additional Evidence Against Radio-handicapping of Northern Bobwhites</title>
<publication-date>2017-07-25T06:47:53-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>Albany Quail Project</institution>
<lname>Sisson</lname>
<fname>D.</fname>
<mname>Clay</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Georgia</institution>
<lname>Terhune</lname>
<fname>Theron</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>Auburn University</institution>
<lname>Stribling</lname>
<fname>H.</fname>
<mname>Lee</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Colinus virginianus</keyword>
<keyword>northern bobwhite</keyword>
<keyword>radio-handicapping</keyword>
<keyword>southeastern USA</keyword>
<keyword>survival</keyword>
<keyword>telemetry</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The validity of radio-telemetry to produce reliable information (e.g., survival estimates) has recently been challenged. Radio-telemetry is a widely used technique in studies of numerous species, therefore, concerns regarding potential bias in these estimates warrant further investigation. As such, and as part of a larger study, we investigated 3 aspects of potential radio-bias: 1) variation in survival distributions among treatment (newly radio-tagged) and control (previously radio-tagged) groups; 2) proportion of trapped animals censored during the traditional 7-day censor period; and 3) ramifications to cause-specific mortality through estimation of harvest rate. Kaplan-Meier survival, based on 30-day post trapping, was similar between treatment (n = 901) and control (n = 293) bobwhites for all but 1 of 8 trapping sessions during 2000-2004. In this case, treatment bobwhites (0.970, SE = 0.015) had higher survival than control birds (0.878, SE = 0.042). We determined the effect of censoring relative to sample size was inconsequential for our analysis because the proportion of bobwhites (18 out of 1,350; 0.013) meeting the criteria for censoring, i.e., dying during the first 7 days, was minimal. Censoring of these data influenced survival estimates by an average of only 0.016 (SE = 0.004; range: 0.00 - 0.04). We evaluated harvest rate by comparing first year recovery rates of banded verses radio-tagged birds during thirteen hunting seasons occurring between 1992 and 2005. Annual recovery rate was not different (P &lt; 0.05) for banded birds and radio-tagged birds where harvest averaged 6.68% (range 3.3 - 11.7) and 6.65% (range 3.4 - 11.1), respectively. These findings are consistent with previous research demonstrating that radio-telemetry can provide reliable demographic information. However, we recommend that future researchers test for these potential effects among their data before making biological inferences.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/nqsp/vol6/iss1/54</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1362&amp;amp;context=nqsp&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>54</label>
<document-type>telemetry_effects</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1362</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-07-25T05:30:08-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>National Quail Symposium Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>10472118</context-key>
<submission-path>nqsp/vol6/iss1/54</submission-path>
</document>
</documents>