<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Computer-Assisted lnstruction for Teaching Decision-Making in Food Systems Administration</title>
<publication-date>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Canter</lname>
<fname>Deborah</fname>
<mname>Dean</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Models for the inclusion, development, and implementation of computer-assisted instruction (CAI) in a dietetic education program were developed, tested, and evaluated. The models were applied to the Coordinated Undergraduate Program in Dietetics, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An assessment of competencies to be met by an entry-level generalist dietitian in food systems administration revealed that the competency concerning principles and practices of management of personnel was not being met adequately by dietetic students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participating faculty and students were introduced to CAI and oriented to the use of computer terminals. Case study simulations were presented via CAI and programmed learning booklets (for off-campus students) to 59 students enrolled in FSA 4140, Food Systems Personnel Development, taught Winter Quarter, 1977. Small-group discussions after completion of each case study helped enrich the simulation experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluation of CAI effectiveness was assessed by administration of three test instruments immediately before and after the CAI experience. The Leadership Evaluation and Development Scale (LEADS), the Leadership Opinion Questionnaire (LOQ) and the Self-Perception of Confidence (SPOC) Scale assessed managerial decision-making ability, the leadership dimensions of Consideration and Structure, and comfort (confidence) of the student when faced with a personnel management problem situation, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the inability of objective measurement devices to assess change in affective behavior, no significant change was noted in managerial decision-making ability or in the leadership dimensions of Consideration and Structure as a result of the CAI simulations. A significant increase in comfort (confidence) was noted after the CAI exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The models for inclusion, development, and implementation of CAI in a dietetic education program was determined to be feasible for use with the Coordinated Undergraduate Program in Dietetics, the University of Tennessee, Knoxville.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3804</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5462&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3804</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5462</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-24T07:51:14-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9025126</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3804</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Betty L. Beach</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Mary J. Hitchcock, Grayce E. Goertz, Eugene W. Schoch</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1977-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>