<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Culinary Biologique and Cartographic Anxiety</title>
<publication-date>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>abucha19@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Buchanan</lname>
<fname>Adam</fname>
<mname>Lamar</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>mapping</keyword>
<keyword>image</keyword>
<keyword>landscape</keyword>
<keyword>rail</keyword>
<keyword>agriculture</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Landscape Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Other Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The 21st century’s most dominant characteristic, and greatest challenge, is the explosive growth of the world’s population. Swelling at an exponential rate, the increasing physical distance between the acts of growth and consumption yields an agrarian system that is highly unsustainable… &lt;strong&gt;a crisis looms in the future!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This crisis is most easily detected in images of the Earth taken from satellites. These recently recorded pixels of reflected light taken from the cherished Icarian vantage point have been acquired and perfected over the past five decades. Ultimately, these lightning speed revelations show patterns that emerge as broken relationships that can be manipulated by the screen-printing process to yield even greater readings. The focus of this investigation is on the image that attacks from numerous angles and at various scales so as to generate roots for many unexpected architectural outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chosen site is the stretch of the Nashville and Eastern Railroad from downtown Nashville, Tennessee to Lebanon, Tennessee. The thesis explores the site through a series of images that are reformulated to emphasize relationships between individual pixels. By addressing the pixels themselves, a set of alternatives is offered that is directly related to the image and begins to reformulate our connection to the landscape. These alternatives are explored and then valued against the initial set of images.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4025</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5182&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4025</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5182</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-04-17T21:41:06-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>8487087</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4025</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Brian Ambroziak</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jennifer Ackerman, Beauvais Lyons</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2016-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>