<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Feasibility of Production and Marketing Blueberries in Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Dellachiesa</lname>
<fname>Alejandro</fname>
<mname>Enrique</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The primary objective of this research was to develop a detailed feasibility analysis for blueberry production in Tennessee. The focus of the study was to provide blueberry producers with estimates of the typical costs and returns associated with commercial production and marketing of blueberries. Secondary objectives were to provide pertinent financial information for entrepreneurs to consider when using their available resources to produce what could be a potential opportunity in Tennessee. Another secondary objective was to evaluate options for marketing fresh blueberries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of this study were accomplished by constructing cost and return budgets to determine the cost of producing blueberries; by conducting cash flow, breakeven, and sensitivity analyses. This information could be used to evaluate the income opportunities for producers, and to identify marketing options for fresh consumption of blueberries in Tennessee. Three marketing options examined were wholesale, pick-your own (PYO), and Already Picked (AP) on farm sales. Pick-your-own enable customers to select their own fresh product from the field and at a very low cost. Alternatively, the already picked option enables customers to buy freshly picked produce from the farm stall.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4617</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6142&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4617</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6142</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-05-03T09:12:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10112111</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4617</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Charles Hall</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>John Brooker, David Lockwood</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Economics</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>