<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Ground Penetrating Radar Investigations on the Relationship between Horizontal Sub-wavelength ‘Thin-layer’ Bedrock Fractures and Reflection Amplitudes</title>
<publication-date>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Burns</lname>
<fname>Kevin</fname>
<mname>E</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Geology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Several theoretical equations that predict sub-wavelength ‘thin-layer’ reflection amplitudes are compared to the results of a series of controlled ground penetrating radar surveys using 1 GHz transducers over a physical model of a horizontal bedrock fracture. Two large plastic (UHMW-PE) blocks, separated by one or more stacked inserts (polyethylene; ~0.1 mm thick) for a total of 101 surveys, generate a modeled fracture with an aperture ranging from 0-300 mm. All existing theoretical reflection coefficient equations fail to predict observed reflection amplitude oscillations in the data when the fracture aperture is less than 1/48 of a wavelength. The only theoretical formulation to properly predict any significant aspect of the fracture EM reflectivity is the Widess equation; however, the best fit only occurs where aperture sizes are less than 1/16, not 1/8 of the wavelength as predicted. Thermal expansion and temperature fluctuations do not sufficiently account for the oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The influence of salinity on a water-filled sub-wavelength constant aperture (5 mm) fracture using 1 GHz antennas is also investigated. Results indicate that at this frequency, the reflection amplitude has a slight negative correlation with changes in salinity from 0-5700 mS/m.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/364</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1371&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>364</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1371</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-15T09:25:03-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1145540</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/364</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Gregory S. Baker</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Edmund Perfect, Larry McKay</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Geology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/BurnsKevin.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>