<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>FUTURE Study: Physical Activity in Individuals with Intellectual Disability</title>
<publication-date>2013-12-17T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>withdrawn</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mwalkup1@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Walkup</lname>
<fname>Mary</fname>
<mname>K</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>FITBIT</keyword>
<keyword>Intellectual Disability</keyword>
<keyword>FUTURE</keyword>
<keyword>physical acitvity</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Medicine and Health Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;High rates of obesity and low aerobic fitness levels are related to increases in chronic disease development in the U.S. This rise in obesity is a result of a variety of factors, but one of the main one is the sedentary lifestyle that the majority of people lead, with a low percentage of Americans meeting recommended physical activity level on a daily basis. This sedentary lifestyle is especially prevalent in the special population of people with&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Intellectual Disability (ID)&lt;strong&gt;. &lt;/strong&gt;ID is a term used for an individual who shows mental limitations specifically intellectually and behaviorally (Schalock et al., 2010). Along with the mental limitations come barriers such as lack of communication and motivation that prevent these individuals from a daily active lifestyle. With a program that is led by peers and easy to maintain, individuals with ID can become more physically active and decrease their risk of becoming obese. Therefore with this study, we hope to determine if our motivation, activity awareness education, and interactive devices have a positive impact on the daily activity of students with ID&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_exerpubs/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1008&amp;amp;context=utk_exerpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>report</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1008</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-12-27T16:02:17-08:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_exerpubs/article/1008/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Kinesiology, Recreation, and Sport Studies Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>4946219</context-key>
<withdrawn>2016-11-04</withdrawn>
<submission-path>utk_exerpubs/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-12-17T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>