<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>‘Capitalism A Nuh’ Wi Frien’. The formatting of farming into an asset, from financial speculation to international aid</title>
<publication-date>2015-10-13T19:36:07-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lrussi@lrning.info</email>
<institution>University of Exeter</institution>
<lname>Russi</lname>
<fname>Luigi</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>tferrando@law.harvard.edu</email>
<institution>Harvard Institute for Global Law and Policy &amp; Sciences Po Law School</institution>
<lname>Ferrando</lname>
<fname>Tomaso</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>farming</keyword>
<keyword>commodities</keyword>
<keyword>financialisation</keyword>
<keyword>land grabbing</keyword>
<keyword>food sovereignty</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Agricultural and Resource Economics</discipline>
<discipline>Human Geography</discipline>
<discipline>International Relations</discipline>
<discipline>Political Economy</discipline>
<discipline>Politics and Social Change</discipline>
<discipline>Rural Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This paper deciphers the formatting of farming into an asset by tracking the modalities by which financial calculation is enabled across different sites of agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first focus of our analysis are commodity futures markets, which have witnessed a double spike in prices in 2008 and in 2012. In the paper, we look at these hikes as the outcome of endogenous dynamics, caused by the changing makeup of market participants after 2000, which turned futures markets into resources for hedging commodity index-linked derivative products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We subsequently analyse the increasing reliance on financial actors placed by public development agencies that channel funds through private equity initiatives to acquire and invest in farmland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complete our analysis, we finally set our contribution alongside the alternative represented by food-sovereignty, which offers the promise of heeding to the needs engendered from within the peasant milieu, as opposed to subjugating it to extrinsic quantitative metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol6/iss1/7</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1078&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>7</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1078</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-04-09T10:11:54-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/catalyst/article/1078/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>6965463</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol6/iss1/7</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>The authors would like to thank the organisers of the 2014 Annual Conference of the International Initiative for Promoting Political Economy at the University of Naples ‘L’Orientale’. We are also indebted to Paolo Ramazzotti of the University of Macerata for his encouragement and feedback. Although the paper is the outcome of joint research and thinking, the first two sections are attributable to Luigi Russi, the third section to Tomaso Ferrando, whereas the concluding one has been jointly written.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2015-04-09T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xe7480a0)</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>&#39;Capitalism A Nuh’ Wi Frien&#39;</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>