<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Rebuilding Burlington</title>
<publication-date>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Lee</lname>
<fname>Illabelle</fname>
<mname>H</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This thesis explores the extent to which architectural design contributes to the revitalization of a declining urban community. It contends that architecture is more than the building of shops and squares; it can be the building of community, pride, and hope. Buildings such as these are assembled from the visions of the local people, with respect for their history, their struggle, and their dreams. The setting for this thesis investigation is the Burlington community of Knoxville, Tennessee. Racist policies expressed in earlier years by overcrowded slums, urban renewal, and disinvestment have left Burlington in distress. Its continued decline is a shameful waste of human potential. Rebuilding Burlington cannot occur by architectural design alone-nor can it occur without it. This thesis proposes that the architectural components of a revitalization plan will create a new civic presence, a reoccupation of the public spaces, and a reinforcement of the community&#39;s defining elements. Specifically, it proposes a mixed-use building complex occupying an entire block of the business district. Included are retail shops to reestablish Burlington&#39;s main street, office space for non-profit agencies and private business, a police precinct, public library, public outdoor space and indoor public assembly space, emergency shelter, and permanent housing.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5253</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6661&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5253</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6661</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-02-19T05:36:07-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>13847118</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5253</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>David Fox</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>