<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI): Apprenticing deaf students in the construction of English text</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>kwolbers@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Wolbers</lname>
<fname>Kimberly</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>deaf education</keyword>
<keyword>writing</keyword>
<keyword>writing instruction</keyword>
<keyword>American Sign Language</keyword>
<keyword>information report</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study investigates the effects of using Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI) with deaf, middle school students who use American Sign Language as their L1 and written English as L2. Using a pretest-posttest control group design, the research explores whether students receiving SIWI made significantly greater gains compared to those not receiving SIWI on a number of variables. There are 33 total students, 16 in the treatment group and 17 in the comparison group. The intervention lasted a total of 8 weeks, during which time the treatment group collaboratively constructed two report papers using SIWI components, and the comparison group continued with their typical literacy instruction. The pre and posttest measures were scored, according to rubrics, for evidence of primary traits, contextual language, and conventions. The multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) and follow-up univariate analyses were statistically significant. Furthermore, effect sizes (d) were large to very large, ranging from 1.27 to 2.65, indicating SIWI to be an effective approach with deaf L2 writers.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_theopubs/5</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;amp;context=utk_theopubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1007</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-05-26T10:12:15-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Theory and Practice in Teacher Education Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>8654257</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_theopubs/5</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Wolbers, K. (2008). Strategic and Interactive Writing Instruction (SIWI): Apprenticing deaf students in the construction of English text. ITL International Journal of Applied Linguistics, 156, 299-326. doi:10.2143/ITL.156.0.2034441</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.2143/ITL.156.0.2034441</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>