<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>FACULTY PERCEPTIONS OF THE FACTORS ENABLING  AND FACILITATING THEIR INTEGRATION OF  INSTRUCTIONAL TECHNOLOGY IN TEACHING</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>csturgeo@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Sturgeon</lname>
<fname>Charles Michael</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Instructional Media Design</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This study employed a survey research design to identify factors that facilitate university faculty to integrate computer-based technologies into their teaching practice. The purpose of the study was to measure the practices and perceptions of higher education faculty toward instructional technology. The designed survey instrument established a series of five personal profile categories. The five categories were used as variables manipulated to enable a series of statistical analyses to examine factors that enable faculty to use technology in their teaching.  The survey was electronically administered to faculty in 36 universities in the Appalachian Region; a target population of approximately 4000 potential survey respondents.  A total of 427 faculty from 22 of these institutions responded to the survey, which was approximately 10% of the total population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings, showed statistically significant correlations between the teaching with technology subscale and personal technology use subscale.  This may suggest that personal use and personal knowledge are indicators of whether or not university faculty will use technology in their teaching.  Additionally, a statistically significant difference was found between the extent to which female faculty reported using technology compared to male faculty members.  The generational factor (age), was not shown to have any significant relationship with the frequency of faculty members’ use of technology, but results indicated generational differences on the personal requirements profile.  Lastly, one finding related to the personal requirements profile indicated that the most common requirement for using technology reported by the faculty was the knowledge that doing so would enhance students’ learning.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1030</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2055&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1030</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2055</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-01-05T15:29:57-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1719025</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1030</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael Waugh</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Trena Paulus, Barbara Thayer-Bacon, Jay Pfaffman</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>