<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>NSAID-activated gene-1 as a molecular target for capsaicin-induced apoptosis through a novel molecular mechanism involving GSK3beta, C/EBPbeta and ATF3</title>
<publication-date>2010-04-22T10:52:08-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>The University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Baek</lname>
<fname>Seung</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>capsaicin</keyword>
<keyword>apoptosis</keyword>
<keyword>NAG-1</keyword>
<keyword>cytokines</keyword>
<keyword>capsaicin treatment</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Capsaicin, a natural product of the Capsicum species of red peppers, is known to induce apoptosis and suppress growth. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug-activated gene-1 (NAG-1) is a cytokine associated with pro-apoptotic and antitumorigenic property in colorectal and lung cancer. Our data demonstrate that capsaicin leads to induction of apoptosis and up-regulates NAG-1 gene expression at the transcriptional level. Overexpression of CCAAT/enhancer binding protein beta (C/EBPbeta) caused a significant increase of basal and capsaicin-induced NAG-1 promoter activity. We subsequently identified C/EBPbeta binding sites in the NAG-1 promoter responsible for capsaicin-induced NAG-1 transactivation. Electrophoretic mobility shift assay and chromatin immunoprecipitation assay confirmed binding of C/EBPbeta to the NAG-1 promoter. Capsaicin treatment resulted in an increase of phosphorylated serine/threonine residues on C/EBPbeta, and the immunoprecipitation study showed that capsaicin enhanced binding of C/EBPbeta with glycogen synthase kinase 3beta (GSK3beta) and activating transcription factor 3 (ATF3). The phosphorylation and interaction of C/EBPbeta with GSK3beta and ATF3 are decreased by the inhibition of the GSK3beta and Protein Kinase C pathways. Knockdown of C/EBPbeta, GSK3beta or ATF3 ameliorates NAG-1 expression induced by capsaicin treatment. These data indicate that C/EBPbeta phosphorylation through GSK3beta may mediate capsaicin-induced expression of NAG-1 and apoptosis through cooperation with ATF3 in human colorectal cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_pathobiopubs/11</coverpage-url>
<label>11</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1010</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-04-22T10:50:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Pathobiology Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1284734</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_pathobiopubs/11</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Seung J. Baek. &quot;NSAID-activated gene-1 as a molecular target for capsaicin-induced apoptosis through a novel molecular mechanism involving GSK3beta, C/EBPbeta and ATF3&quot; Carcinogenesis 31.4 (2010): 719-728.</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://carcin.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/31/4/719</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Carcinogenesis</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>