<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SOCIO-ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION THROUGH BROWNFIELD RECLAMATION</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>cbreedin@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Breeding</lname>
<fname>Corrin James</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Brownfield redevelopment</keyword>
<keyword>brownfield remediation</keyword>
<keyword>bioremediation</keyword>
<keyword>phytoremediation</keyword>
<keyword>urban design</keyword>
<keyword>reclamation</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Environmental Design</discipline>
<discipline>Landscape Architecture</discipline>
<discipline>Urban, Community and Regional Planning</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Brownfields are defined as real property, the expansion, redevelopment, or reuse of which may be complicated by the presence or potential presence of hazardous substance, pollutant, or contaminant (epa.gov). Brownfield remediation is land rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many brownfield sites that exist around the world today. These locations are nuisances because of their effect on the environment. They can be eyesores, riddled with dilapidated structures and debris that put chemicals into the soil, affect local watersheds, become prime areas for violence and/or other activities viewed as unsafe, etc. The impact these areas have on the health of living organisms is a major concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This affects the neighborhoods in close proximity to a brownfield site. Many of the inhabitants of these neighborhoods live on property considered to be low in value due to the brownfields. The lack of interest in these areas keeps other citizens away thus decreasing the chance of the land being considered for reclamation. This can create a difficult situation if these people are to keep their neighborhoods clean and safe without professional assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The questions raised through this project are: can brownfield reclamation be helpful for these communities? How would it impact them? Would it have a positive or negative effect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do remediated landscapes have the potential to create attractive and functional spaces but they can also positively impact the local economy. Jobs can be created during the construction phase and after the project is completed if the context and/or needs of the surrounding neighborhoods are taken into consideration. Through this project, the end result should prove that brownfield reclamation can bring about socio-economic revitalization.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1329</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2486&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1329</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2486</articleid>
<submission-date>2012-08-02T23:48:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>3174273</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1329</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ken McCown</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Tracy Moir-McClean, Dr. Caula Beyl</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Landscape Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Landscape Architecture</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2012-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>