<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>On the evolution of codon usage bias</title>
<publication-date>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>allmaya@gmail.com</email>
<lname>Shah</lname>
<fname>Premal</fname>
<mname>R</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>codon usage bias</keyword>
<keyword>population genetics</keyword>
<keyword>translation efficiency</keyword>
<keyword>translation errors</keyword>
<keyword>RNA thermometer</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Evolution</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The genetic code is redundant, with most amino acids coded by multiple codons. In many organisms, codon usage is biased towards particular codons. A variety of adaptive and non-adaptive explanations have been proposed to explain these patterns of codon usage bias. Using mechanistic models of protein translation and population genetics, I explore the relative importance of various evolutionary forces in shaping these patterns. This work challenges one of the fundamental assumptions made in over 30 years of research: codons with higher tRNA abundances leads to lower error rates. I show that observed patterns of codon usage are inconsistent with selection for translation accuracy. I also show that almost all the variation in patterns of codon usage in &lt;em&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/em&gt; can be explained by a model taking into account the effects of mutational biases and selection for efficient ribosome usage. In addition, by sampling suboptimal mRNA secondary structures at various temperatures, I show that melting of ribosomal binding sites in a special class of mRNAs known as RNA thermometers is a more general phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/1024</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2135&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1024</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>2135</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-04-12T14:42:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1937326</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/1024</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Michael A. Gilchrist</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Sergey Gavrilets, Louis Gross, James Fordyce, Russell Zaretzki</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2011-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>