<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Frame Analysis of the Living Wage Campaign and Social Work Implications</title>
<publication-date>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>McClernon-Chaffin</lname>
<fname>Katherine</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The general aim of this study was to examine the living age movement and how frame alignment fits into social work practice. This research was developed from a limited empirical and theoretical base surrounding the living wage as a social movement. Frame alignment is becoming a tool that more and more people should know how to use. Frame alignment has been a key component in propelling social movements into society in order to effect change. This research is an examination of frame alignment, specifically the living wage movement and how it fits into effective social work practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data were obtained from a convenience sample of 487 students from a public university in middle Tennessee. Three different frames were developed and distributed to 500 college students with a 94.7 response rate. The data were collected from November 2003 to November 2004 through the use of a survey via an experimental design. Three different frameworks were distributed in order to gain insight on framing issues surrounding the living wage. Frame A was an economic justice frame, frame B was a social justice frame and frame C was a control frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding from this study indicate a strong support for the social justice frame. ANOVA and t-tests have shown a statistical significance between Frame B and support for a living wage [F (2,482) =5.301, p≤.006]. In addition it was discovered that women were not only more likely to support a living wage but they were also more likely to help organize a living wage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications for social work practice and policy indicate social justice as a strong value for change. Frame B was a social justice frame, which ties in appropriately with effective social work practice and the ideal that social workers must fight for oppressed populations in order to seek change and end social justice. Frame alignment has been in the forefront of all successful social movements including the civil rights movement, which also identified with people’s values and beliefs as a part of frame alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4696</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6281&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4696</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6281</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-08-16T05:39:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10607780</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4696</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Jenny Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Cindy Davis, Brian Bride</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science in Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Social Work</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>