<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Diffuse intestinal T cell lymphosarcoma in a yellow-naped Amazon parrot (Amazona ochrocephala auropalliata)</title>
<publication-date>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Souza</lname>
<fname>M</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee-Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Newman</lname>
<fname>Shelley</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Greenacre</lname>
<fname>C</fname>
<mname>B.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Avenell</lname>
<fname>J</fname>
<mname>S.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>avian</keyword>
<keyword>immunohistochemistry</keyword>
<keyword>lymphosarcoma</keyword>
<keyword>positron emission tomography</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A 10-year-old, intact, female yellow-naped Amazon parrot was examined because of anemia, lymphocytic leukocytosis, regurgitation, and weight loss. A positive fecal occult blood and monoclonal globulinopathy were present. A distended proventriculus and diffusely thickened loops of small intestine with irregular luminal surfaces were identified with contrast radiography and contrast computed tomography. A micro positron emission tomography scan was performed with (18)F-fluorodeoxyglucose. Diffuse intestinal T-cell lymphosarcoma was diagnosed based on histopathology and immunohistochemistry of full thickness small intestinal biopsies. The patient was treated with a multidrug chemotherapy protocol with little to no effect. Euthanasia was elected, and intestinal lymphosarcoma was confirmed on histopathology of necropsy intestinal samples; no other organs demonstrated neoplastic infiltration. To the authors&#39; knowledge, no reports are currently available detailing the clinical presentation or diagnosis of diffuse intestinal T-cell lymphosarcoma in any avian species.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_compmedpubs/62</coverpage-url>
<label>62</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1061</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-11-01T09:42:07-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Faculty Publications and Other Works -- Biomedical and Diagnostic Sciences</publication-title>
<context-key>2323840</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_compmedpubs/62</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="create_openurl" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>M J. Souza, Shelley Newman, C B. Greenacre, J S. Avenell, J S. Wall, J C. Phillips, M M. Fry, R L. Donnnell, and G B. Daniel. &quot;Diffuse intestinal T cell lymphosarcoma in a yellow-naped Amazon parrot (Amazona ochrocephala auropalliata)&quot; Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation 20.5 (2008): 656-660.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://www.jvdi.org/cgi/content/abstract/20/5/656</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Journal of Veterinary Diagnostic Investigation</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>