<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>In re Fairpoint Communications, Inc.</title>
<publication-date>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Green</lname>
<fname>Patrick</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Skelton</lname>
<fname>Todd</fname>
<mname>Blakeley</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Bankruptcy Law</discipline>
<discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;FairPoint Communications, Inc. (the “Company”) and its subsidiaries (collectively, “FairPoint”) provide communications services to rural and small business customers in eighteen states.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; As of December 2009, FairPoint had approximately 1.7 million “access line equivalents (including voice access lines and high-speed data lines, which include digital subscriber lines, or DSL, wireless broadband and cable modem) in service.”&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; Challenges presented by industry competition and innovation, the integration of acquired operations, adverse economic conditions, and changes in customer usage and spending habits contributed to FairPoint and its subsidiaries and affiliates’ filing a voluntary Chapter 11 bankruptcy petition on October 26, 2009 (the “Petition Date”).&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; United States Bankruptcy Judge Burton Lifland confirmed the Company’s plan of reorganization on January 13, 2011.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; FairPoint continues to operate today as a public company.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is divided into several parts. Parts II and III provide background on FairPoint and the events leading into its filing bankruptcy, respectively. The information in Part II refers to FairPoint as of the Petition Date, unless indicated otherwise. Part IV discusses the various “first-day motions” filed in FairPoint’s bankruptcy case.&lt;a title=&quot;&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; Next, Part V highlights selected events during the middle portion of FairPoint’s bankruptcy case. Part VI then details FairPoint’s plan of reorganization before providing a snapshot of FairPoint post-bankruptcy in Part VII. Finally, Part VIII briefly concludes.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_studlawbankruptcy/37</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=utk_studlawbankruptcy&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>37</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1036</articleid>
<submission-date>2014-05-24T08:25:27-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Chapter 11 Bankruptcy Case Studies</publication-title>
<context-key>5619255</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_studlawbankruptcy/37</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-24T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2014-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>