<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effect of Length on the Performance of Lean NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; Traps</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Prikhodko</lname>
<fname>Vitaly</fname>
<mname>Y.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Mechanical Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The effect of monolith length on the NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; performance of two different Lean NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt; Traps has been investigated using a bench flow reactor (BFR). The washcoat composition of one of the catalysts consists of Pt/K/γ-Al&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;; the major components of the other catalyst include Pt, Pd, Rh, barium, ceria and zirconia supported on γ-alumina washcoat. Samples of 2.22-cm in diameter and length of 2.54, 5.08 and 7.62-cm within each LNT were evaluated with long and short-cycle experiments at a fixed gas hourly space velocity, and results were compared between samples of different lengths. No significant difference in performance was observed in long and short-cycle experiments with full regeneration. On a contrary, significant difference was observed in short-cycle experiments with partial regeneration: the longer the sample the better the performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intra-catalyst concentration of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; measured at different axial locations in short-cycle experiments indicated higher H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; consumption in shorter samples. A series of experiments was carried out to ascertain different mechanisms of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; consumption, and results indicated different degrees of lean and rich front back-mixing for samples of different sizes. Higher back-mixing in shorter samples resulted in a higher H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; loss via its oxidation by O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and lesser H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; availability for reducing stored NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;, which in turn affected catalyst’s performance when regeneration was limited by amount of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; available.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/193</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1225&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>193</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1225</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-10T08:44:16-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1138895</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/193</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ke Nguyen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Stuart Daw, J. Roger Parsons, David K. Irick</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Mechanical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/PrikhodkoVitaly.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>