<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Data from Spectroscopic studies of size-dependent optical properties of oxide nanomaterials, molecule-based materials in extreme condition</title>
<publication-date>2020-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Musfeldt</lname>
<fname>J.</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [DMR-1707846 (JLM, UT) and DMR-1703003 (JLM, EWU)], the Petroleum Research Fund [52052-ND10 (JLM, UT)], and the Department of Energy, Office of Science, Basic Energy Sciences, Materials Sciences and Engineering Division (RF). The research at UNIST (JHL, MSK) was supported by Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning (2015R1C1A1A01055760) and Creative Materials Discovery Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT (2017M3D1A1040828). Work at the National Synchrotron Light Source at Brookhaven National Laboratory was funded by the Department of Energy (DEAC98-06CH10886). The use of the U2A beamline was supported by COMPRES under NSF Cooperative Agreement EAR 11-57758 and CDAC (DE-FC03-03N00144). This research used resources of the National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center, a DOE Office of Science User Facility supported by the Office of Science of the U.S. Department of Energy under Contract No. DE-AC02-05CH11231.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_datasets/3</coverpage-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>data</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1002</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-04-28T08:28:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Data Sets</publication-title>
<context-key>17551647</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_datasets/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.7290/qtlpnw5g3</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2020-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>https://doi.org/10.7290/qtlpnw5g3</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>