<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>What Libraries and Information Professionals Can Learn from Knowledge and Project Management</title>
<publication-date>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ecortez@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Cortez</lname>
<fname>Edwin</fname>
</author>
<author>
<lname>Colon-Aguirre</lname>
<fname>Monica</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Conference Proceedings</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>project management</keyword>
<keyword>knowledge management</keyword>
<keyword>knowledge workers</keyword>
<keyword>information professionals</keyword>
<keyword>ITC competencies</keyword>
<keyword>LIS education</keyword>
<keyword>library and information science</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Library and Information Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Few professions have seen as rapid change over the past several decades as the field of library and information science (LIS), due mainly to information technologies. Computers not only provide the backbone of today’s libraries and information agencies, but they are also changing in fundamental ways how these organizations operate. Dennis Lee et al., in their article “Critical Skills and Knowledge Requirements of IS Professionals” (1995), espouse the view that these changes in information technologies and their use create different demands on and new expectations for the jobs of information professionals in such organizations as libraries and other information environments. Employers, educators as well as students have raised concerns regarding the knowledge and skills that are required for information professionals to function effectively in these changing environments, as well as how university and corporate training must be revised to meet the changing needs. Two areas useful for building the needed skill sets are knowledge management (KM) and project management (PM). The purpose of this paper is to investigate the application of KM and PM practices best suited to meet the challenges confronting librarians and information professionals in today’s workplace. Four broad categories of critical KM and PM knowledge/skills will be examined. 1) technical knowledge; 2) administrative knowledge 3) social knowledge; and 4) system knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_infosciepubs/15</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1014&amp;amp;context=utk_infosciepubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>15</label>
<document-type>presentation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1014</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-27T10:31:05-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>School of Information Sciences -- Faculty Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>1582549</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_infosciepubs/15</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Cortez, Edwin M., Colon-Aguirre, Monica.  “What Libraries and Information Professionals Can 	 Learn from Knowledge and Project Management.” 17TH BOBCATSSS Symposium. January 28-30, 2009. Porto, Portugal.</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2009-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>17th BOBCATSSS Symposium</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>