<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>SP576 Protecting Trees during Construction</title>
<publication-date>2003-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<organization>The University of Tennessee Agricultural Extension Service</organization>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Trees</keyword>
<keyword>Construction</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Plant Sciences</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Trees add considerable value to homes and buildings. We enjoy, appreciate and need trees around our homes and places of business. They provide shade and privacy, improve and diversify the landscape, and attract wildlife. When choosing property for construction, trees can be an attractive asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, problems with trees often arise when construction begins. Most construction crews are not conditioned to notice or appreciate landscape trees and may inadvertently cause irreparable damage. Often tree injuries and their effects are not noticeable until the years following project completion. The subsequent need to remove a tree can be expensive because of newly created obstacles. Proper planning and action prior to and during construction will minimize damage to trees, allowing them to contribute to a healthy and pleasing landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To protect trees from construction damage, follow these simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. First, assess the existing trees on the construction site to determine which ones are worth retaining;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Next, design or arrange approaches to the building site that consider the trees to be to retained and protected during construction;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Finally, provide sound tree maintenance during and after construction.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_agexfores/71</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1070&amp;amp;context=utk_agexfores&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>71</label>
<document-type>treeprotect</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1070</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-03-31T10:22:55-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Forestry, Trees, and Timber</publication-title>
<context-key>1256327</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_agexfores/71</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>SP 576- 12M - 7/03   R12-4910-034-002-04</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2010-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>