<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Dynamic characteristics of an FRP deck bridge</title>
<publication-date>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>jsong12@utk.edu</email>
<lname>Song</lname>
<fname>Jing</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Dynamic</keyword>
<keyword>FRP deck</keyword>
<keyword>Bridge</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Civil Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Fiber reinforced polymer (FRP) deck has some significant advantages compared to concrete deck in use of bridges, such as light self-weight, high stiffness and strength, good durability and easy to install. FRP deck has already been used in some bridge rehabilitation and short span bridges. But for widely used in bridges, FRP deck bridges still need further research. Currently many research efforts focus on the filed tests of FRP deck bridges. Compared to field tests, Finite element analysis also has great advantages, such as low cost and convenient to conduct. Therefore, in this thesis finite element analysis is conducted by ABAQUS on the Boyer Bridge in Pennsylvania. The finite element model is verified by the static field test result. Then a simplified moving truck load is applied on the bridge model in order to analyze the dynamic responses of the FRP deck bridge, including the displacements and stress of each girder at the middle span. The dynamic effect is shown by comparing the dynamic responses and the static responses of the bridge. The connection between the FRP deck and girder is very important to the behavior of the bridge. In this thesis shear studs serve to connect the FRP deck and girder. This thesis also analyzes the effect of shear studs to the dynamic responses of the bridge by changing the number of the shear studs.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/750</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1810&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>750</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1810</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-08-04T18:48:13-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1425858</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/750</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Zhongguo John Ma</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Thomas L. Attard, Qiuhong Zhao</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Civil Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2010-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>