<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Culture of Intimidation: Power Relationships, Quiescence, and Rebellion in Oak Ridge, Tennessee</title>
<publication-date>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Durbin</lname>
<fname>Barry</fname>
<mname>R.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Sociology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Studies suggest that quiescence, or the absence of challenge from deprived groups can be explained as a function of power relationships. Power has the potential to influence the decision-making process by monopolizing decision-making arenas. Furthermore, elites that occupy positions of power have the capability to resist challenges from deprived groups by preventing certain issues or grievances from ever being raised. This study’s focus is a former nuclear weapons production facility (the former K-25 Gaseous Diffusion Plant) in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, the quiescent nature of workers there, and the subsequent rise of rebellion. I employ a historical perspective using in-depth interviews and secondary data sources to investigate the perceptions of workers on power relationships. I explore the consequences of unequal power relationships on workers. K-25 was the first site built for the Manhattan Project in 1943. Findings indicate that the quiescent nature of K-25 workers cannot be explained by worker apathy or consensus with the status quo. In fact, the perception of quiescence can be explained by power relationships between dominant and subordinate groups. Generalized grievances were present, but were controlled and contained by the Department of Energy (DOE) and its corporate contractors. Even as rebellion emerged, traces of quiescence can still be found among workers in Oak Ridge.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2055</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3414&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2055</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3414</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-01T11:17:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4652961</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2055</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Sherry Cable</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Virginia Seitz, Robert Jones</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Sociology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>