<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Self-Efficacy on Transfer of Cross-Cultural Training and Expatriate Performance</title>
<publication-date>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Drewry</lname>
<fname>Anne</fname>
<mname>Wang</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Human Resources Management</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The presented study focused on the effect of self-efficacy, as well as other selected demographic variables, on the transfer of cross-cultural training and expatriate performance. Selected independent variables include self-efficacy, expatriate tenure, level of education, gender, age, marital status, level of foreign language competency and level of formal cross-cultural experience. Expatriates employed by multinational company that were on their current assignments were selected to be the studied sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design of this study employed a quantitative research method. A survey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;instrument crafted specifically for this study was digitized and was made accessible for participants via the Internet. After the data was automatically collected, appropriate statistical analysis tools such as descriptive statistics, correlations of means, Analysis of Variance, and a reliability test such as Cronbach’s alpha were used for data analysis purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expatriate’s perceived self-efficacy was found to interactive with the transfer of cross-cultural training (CCT). While demographic variables such as expatriate tenure, level of education, gender, age, martial status, level of foreign language competency, and level of formal cross-cultural experience were found having no correlation with the transfer of CCT, the test results show self-efficacy to have strong impact on expatriate’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the conclusions, a set of recommendations has been made for future researchers. Implications for HRD practitioners and multinational organizations have also been explored.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/1937</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3296&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>1937</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3296</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-23T13:38:36-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4615515</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/1937</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Vickie Johnson Stout</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Virginia W. Kupritz, Robert T. Ladd</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Resource Management</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2003-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>