<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>First Report of a Population of Western Blacknose Dace (&lt;i&gt;Rhinichthys obtusus&lt;/i&gt;) in the Brushy Creek System of the Black Warrior River Drainage, Alabama</title>
<publication-date>2017-09-20T12:59:37-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>efb0005@tigermail.auburn.edu</email>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Bauer</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>malorie.hayes@gmail.com</email>
<institution>Auburn University Main Campus</institution>
<lname>Hayes</lname>
<fname>Malorie</fname>
<mname>M</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Freshwater</keyword>
<keyword>Fish</keyword>
<keyword>Distribution</keyword>
<keyword>New occurrence</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biodiversity</discipline>
<discipline>Population Biology</discipline>
<discipline>Zoology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Alabama is home to the southernmost populations of &lt;em&gt;Rhinichthys obtusus&lt;/em&gt;, the Western Blacknose Dace. Within Alabama, &lt;em&gt;R. obtusus&lt;/em&gt; is found in the Tennessee, Coosa, and Black Warrior River basins, but its presence in the Black Warrior River drainage has been limited. Until now, &lt;em&gt;R. obtusus&lt;/em&gt; in the Black Warrior drainage has only been reported as collections of 1 to 4 specimens at a time in the Sipsey Fork drainage. Herein, we report two novel occurrences of &lt;em&gt;R. obtusus&lt;/em&gt; in the headwaters of the Brushy Creek system in the Black Warrior River drainage including a singleton and a large population. The population observed in Collier Creek is located over 21 km from the Tennessee River divide, on the divide between the Brushy Creek system and the Sipsey Fork drainage, and is in close proximity to an artificial lake, any of which may be the origin of this population. The presence of a population of &lt;em&gt;R. obtusus&lt;/em&gt; in the system necessitates further sampling of the headwaters of the Black Warrior River drainage to understand its natural prevalence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss57/2</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1274&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2</label>
<document-type>notes</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1274</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-03-25T10:08:31-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1274/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>8383601</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss57/2</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>The authors would like to acknowledge the EPA Wetland Program Development Grant 104(b)(3) for partial funding. Many thanks to Brian Helms, David Werneke, and Thomas Hess for assistance in the field. We would especially like to thank C. Keith Ray for his expertise and comments regarding this paper. We would also like to thank Jonathan Armbruster for his comments on this manuscript. Collection of specimens was done under Alabama Permit #2014000124068680, and Animal Care Protocol was approved by Auburn University PRN 2014-2451. This paper is contribution No. 735 of the Auburn University Museum of Natural History.</value>
</field>
<field name="distribution_license" type="string">
<value>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2016-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xdcb04a8)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>&lt;i&gt;Rhinichthys&lt;/i&gt; in Black Warrior River Drainage</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>