<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Impact of Organizational Attributes on Project Performance as Measured by On-Time Delivery and Budget</title>
<publication-date>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>El-Akkad</lname>
<fname>Zeid</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Industrial Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Before we determine what lean tools are suitable for an office environment and how to modify those tools to make them more suitable and in order to develop a lean office, it is important to understand the different processes and aspects within an office. For this reason, better understanding of office processes and aspects helps facilitate the deployment and implementation and modification of different lean techniques to better suit the office environment. The purpose of this paper is to identify seven different factors to compare against one another and against project performance in terms of on-time delivery and budget. The seven factors are as follows: business sector, size of the organization, office layout, information processing, data flow, location, and interaction or lack of interaction among various departments within an organization. A hypothesis will be developed regarding each of these factors, and subsequently a survey will be created and conducted. A statistical analysis of this survey will be done using primarily a Chi Square test to determine whether our hypotheses can be validated by the data.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/122</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1154&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>122</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1154</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-08T12:03:29-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>1136174</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/122</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Rupy Sawhney</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Xuipeng Li, Denise Jackson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Industrial Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2007/ElAkkadZeid.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>