<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Relationship Between Self-Directed Learning and Learning Styles</title>
<publication-date>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Canipe</lname>
<fname>James</fname>
<mname>Boyd</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship between self-directed learning readiness and learning styles. A cluster sample of 260 graduate students enrolled in classes in the College of Education and Behavioral Sciences at Morehead State University at Morehead, Kentucky was utilized in this research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Self-Directed Learning Readiness Scale (SDLRS), developed by L. M. Guglielmino (1977), and the Learning Style Inventory (LSI) developed by D. A. Kolb (1984), were administered to the sample as a means of exploring the relationship between the two variables. In addition, a demographic questionnaire was used to describe the characteristics of the sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of this research suggest that there are no significant differences between self-directed learning readiness and the four learning styles as defined by the LSI (p &gt; .05). Thus, self-directed learning readiness in this study appears to occur across all learning styles, instead of being identified with a particular learning style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the results of this study indicate that there are significant correlations between self-directed learning readiness and two of the modes of learning at an alpha level of .05--one positive and one negative. However, these correlations are very weak. Therefore, for the most part, self-directed learning readiness appears to occur across all modes of learning, and this relationship between the SDLRS and the modes of learning of the LSI can be described as an amalgamation. Furthermore, this relationship could perhaps be described as &quot;apples and oranges.&quot; Yet, the lack of strong relationships and the lack of a part of all learning styles and all the modes of learning and does not relate to one particular learning style or mode of leaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations for further research include studies that consider different socioeconomic, ethnic, and racial groups among graduate students. Also, the use of different instruments to measure the variables of self-directed learning and learning styles, as well as exploration of various conceptualizations of self-directed learning and learning styles, may bring further insight into these relationships. Finally, it is recommended that a different target population should be studied, such as those who are GED recipients.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2094</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3538&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2094</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3538</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-09-30T13:09:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4648413</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2094</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ralph G. Brockett</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Luther Kindall, Donald J. Dessart, Michael Johnson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2001-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>