<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Do Judges Systematically Favor the Interests of the Legal Profession?</title>
<publication-date>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>bbarton@utk.edu</email>
<institution>The University of Tennessee College of Law</institution>
<lname>Barton</lname>
<fname>Benjamin</fname>
<mname>H</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<subject-areas>
<subject-area>Torts</subject-area>
<subject-area>Courts</subject-area>
<subject-area>Law and Economics</subject-area>
<subject-area>Constitutional Law</subject-area>
<subject-area>Professional Ethics</subject-area>
<subject-area>Legal Profession</subject-area>
<subject-area>Jurisprudence</subject-area>
<subject-area>Judges</subject-area>
</subject-areas>
<keywords>
<keyword>judges</keyword>
<keyword>legal profession</keyword>
<keyword>legal malpractice</keyword>
<keyword>rules of professional conduct</keyword>
<keyword>miranda</keyword>
<keyword>lawyer-client privilege</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Law</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;This Article answers this question with the following jurisprudential hypothesis: many legal outcomes can be explained, and future cases predicted, by asking a very simple question, is there a plausible legal result in this case that will significantly affect the interests of the legal profession (positively or negatively)?  If so, the case will be decided in the way that offers the best result for the legal profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article presents theoretical support from the new institutionalism, cognitive psychology and economic theory.  The Article then gathers and analyzes supporting cases from areas as diverse as constitutional law, torts, professional responsibility, employment law, evidence, and criminal procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The questions considered include: why are lawyers the only American profession to be truly and completely self-regulated?  Why is it that the attorney-client privilege is the oldest and most jealously protected professional privilege?  Why is it that the Supreme Court has repeatedly struck down bans on commercial speech, except for bans on in-person lawyer solicitations and some types of lawyer advertising?  Why is it that the Miranda right to consult with an attorney is more protected than the right to remain silent?  Why is legal malpractice so much harder to prove than medical malpractice?  The Article finishes with some of the ramifications of the lawyer-judge hypothesis, including brief consideration of whether our judiciary should be staffed by lawyer-judges at all.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_lawpubl/37</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1038&amp;amp;context=utk_lawpubl&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>37</label>
<document-type>unpublished_paper</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1038</articleid>
<submission-date>2007-05-01T11:57:35-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_lawpubl/article/1038/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>College of Law Faculty Scholarship</publication-title>
<context-key>2241443</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_lawpubl/37</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="bp_categories" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xf1a52b8)</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2007-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>ExpressO</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>