<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Assessment of Psychopathic Traits and Risk-Taking Using Balloon Analog Risk Task (BART)</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Hunt</lname>
<fname>Melissa</fname>
<mname>Kathryn</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Continuing a program of research assessing the utility of the Behavioral Analog Risk Task (BART, Lejuez et al, 2002) as a measure of risk taking, the BART was administered to a non-forensic sample of individuals high and low in self-reported psychopathy. Inter-relations of BART performance with measures of psychopathy and impulsivity were examined, with an emphasis on exploring the predictive validity of self-report measures on overt risk-taking behavior. Following completion of the &lt;em&gt;Self-Report Psychopathy Scale&lt;/em&gt; (SRP-II; Hare, 1991), &lt;em&gt;Barratt Impulsiveness Scale&lt;/em&gt; (BIS; Barratt, 1985), and the &lt;em&gt;Authority Problems&lt;/em&gt; subscale (Pd2) of the &lt;em&gt;MMPI-2&lt;/em&gt; (Harris &amp; Lingoes, 1955), physiological data were collected while participants completed the BART. Results supported the primary hypothesis that higher self-reported psychopathy (SRP-II Factor II: Antisocial Behavior) is predictive of increased risk-taking behavior on the BART. Findings also supported the notion of behavioral symmetry across forensic and nonclinical samples of individuals high in psychopathic traits, revealed interesting gender differences in self-reported psychopathy, and provided psychometric support for both the BART and SRP-II assessment strategies. Future research directions are presented.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4633</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6189&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4633</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6189</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-14T09:53:37-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10299905</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4633</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Derek Hopko</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Deborah Welsh, Lowell Gaertner</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>