<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Assessing the Impact of a Geospatial Data Collection App on Student Engagement in Environmental Education</title>
<publication-date>2019-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Norton</lname>
<fname>Evan</fname>
</author>
<author>
<email>yli32@utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Li</lname>
<fname>Yingkui</fname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mason</lname>
<fname>Lisa</fname>
<mname>Reyes</mname>
</author>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville, University of Nevada, Reno</institution>
<lname>Washington-Allen</lname>
<fname>Robert</fname>
<mname>A</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>geographic information systems</keyword>
<keyword>environmental education</keyword>
<keyword>data collection app</keyword>
<keyword>student engagement</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;A critical component of environmental education is to ensure student understanding and use of available technologies to better experience and analyze spatially distributed features of the environment. Combining mobile technologies with geographic information systems in field data collection may provide a unique opportunity for students to feel engaged in what they are learning and take ownership of their learning process. We customized an open access data collection application using Collector for ArcGIS and investigated its impacts on student engagement and perception of the incorporation of technology within an environmental science curriculum. Analyses of pre- and post-surveys indicate that the inclusion of geospatial technologies as a part of environmental curricula allows students to take the lead on their own research, view field data interactively as opposed to looking at a database in hindsight and analyze multiscale data as it is presented during field data collection. The findings of this study are consistent with previous studies, suggesting a strong association between the inclusion of geospatial technologies as a part of curricula and student engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_geogpubs/21</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1022&amp;amp;context=utk_geogpubs&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>21</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1022</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-07-31T04:59:41-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Geography Publications and Other Works</publication-title>
<context-key>15026309</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_geogpubs/21</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This article was published openly thanks to the University of Tennessee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.utk.edu/scholar/services/opsf/&quot;&gt;Open Publishing Support Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="custom_citation" type="string">
<value>Norton, E.; Li, Y.; Mason, L.R.; Washington-Allen, R.A. Assessing the Impact of a Geospatial Data Collection App on Student Engagement in Environmental Education. Education Science 2019, 9, 118. https://doi.org/10.3390/educsci9020118</value>
</field>
<field name="doi" type="string">
<value>10.3390/educsci9020118</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_publication" type="string">
<value>Education Sciences</value>
</field>
<field name="submission_type" type="string">
<value>Publisher&#39;s Version</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>