<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Race, Memory, and Historical Responsibility: What Do Southerners Do with a Difficult Past?</title>
<publication-date>2012-08-27T21:16:03-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>ljgriffin@georgiasouthern.edu</email>
<institution>Georgia Southern University</institution>
<lname>Griffin</lname>
<fname>Larry</fname>
<mname>J.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>har_agga@georgiasouthern.edu</email>
<institution>Georgia Southern University</institution>
<lname>Hargis</lname>
<fname>Peggy</fname>
<mname>G.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Race/Race Relations; Collective Memory; Transitional Justice; U.S. South; Reconciliation; Jim Crow; Inequality; Reprarations; Memorialization; Trials</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>African American Studies</discipline>
<discipline>American Studies</discipline>
<discipline>History</discipline>
<discipline>Politics and Social Change</discipline>
<discipline>Race and Ethnicity</discipline>
<discipline>Regional Sociology</discipline>
<discipline>United States History</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Newly emerging, transitional societies –– that is, societies that traded dictatorial or authoritarian rule for some form of open or liberal polity –– face at least three interdependent problems of what is called in legal scholarship and social science “transitional justice”: the first is how (if at all) to hold the old regime’s autocratic, often violence-laden leadership responsible for its wrongdoings while in power; the second is what (if anything) to do with thousands upon thousands of ordinary folk whose participation in, or compliance with, the old regime helped legitimate and thus perpetuate the wrongdoing; and the third task how (if at all) to deal with the victims of the old regime. By situating the American South in the global context of the need of newly democratizing societies for transitional justice, we explore how the South’s similarities with and differences from other such societies have shaped the timing and character of its peoples’ post-Jim Crow era restorative justice and racial reconciliation projects, paying particular attention to criminal trials for perpetrators of past crimes, apology, truth and reconciliation-type commissions, and memorialization. We then document the extent of racial inequalities in employment, income, poverty status, and morbidity and mortality, arguing both that past racial injustices result in contemporary racial inequalities and that restorative justice points forward in time--and thus must deal with current inequities –– as well as backward.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/catalyst/vol2/iss1/3</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1023&amp;amp;context=catalyst&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3</label>
<document-type>article</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1023</articleid>
<submission-date>2011-07-19T12:15:05-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/context/catalyst/article/1023/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Catalyst: A Social Justice Forum</publication-title>
<context-key>2106716</context-key>
<submission-path>catalyst/vol2/iss1/3</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>Much of the material in this paper was presented to audiences at Centenary College, Delta State University, Jackson State University, North Carolina A&amp;T University, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the Southern Sociological Society, and St. George Tucker Society. We are indebted David Cunningham and two anonymous Catalyst reviewers for their helpful remarks on an earlier version of this article, Robin Gary and Colin Campbell for their research assistance, and Thomas Craemer for generously sharing his public opinion data on racial reparations. This research was supported by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xafb9980)</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Race, Memory, and Historical Responsibility</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>