<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Effects of Cooking Method, Fat Level, and Days on Feed on the Objective and Sensory Characteristics of Restructured Steaks</title>
<publication-date>1984-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Costello</lname>
<fname>Carol</fname>
<mname>A.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Home Economics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Top rounds from steers fed grain 0, 28, 56, or 84 days were removed and flaked in a Urschel Comitrol containing a plate with 1.9-cm openings. Fat (beef plates approximately 55% fat) from animals fed grain was finely ground. Flaked meat and fat were mixed and formed into 227-g restructured steaks with 15%, 20%, or 25% fat. Steaks were cooked in a microwave oven on a preheated browning dish or broiled in a conventional oven to an internal temperature of 73&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C ± 2&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C or 73&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greater cooking losses were exhibited for steaks heated in a microwave oven than were found with conventional heating. Objective measurements of tenderness indicated conventionally heated steaks were more tender than microwave-heated steaks. As the level of fat increased, tenderness, as determined by objective methods, generally increased. Generally, as the number of days an animal was on grain increased, Warner-Bratzler shear values decreased. Total microbial destruction was exhibited by both cooking methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 10-member experienced panel evaluated the steaks for various characteristics using an unstructured, 150-mm descriptive scale. Steaks cooked in the microwave oven were less tender, had less moisture released, and appeared to be more well-done than steaks broiled in the conventional oven. As fat level increased in the steaks, tenderness, moisture released, greasiness, and acceptability also increased while off-flavor of the steaks decreased. Cooking method, fat level, or number of days on feed did not affect acceptability as judged by a 36-member consumer panel. It appeared that the use of fat from grain-fed animals minimized tenderness, juiciness, and off-flavor problems reported to be associated with meat from grass-fed animals. This study indicated that it would be feasible to utilize meat from grass-fed animals in the formation of restructured steaks. An increase in fat level was shown to positively affect the characteristics of the steaks.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/3987</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5525&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3987</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5525</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-09-22T09:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>9172084</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/3987</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Marjorie P. Penfield</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Frances A. Draughon, Roy E. Beauchene, Nina R. Marable</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1984-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1984-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>