<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Phonological Process Use in the Speech of Children Fitted With Cochlear Implants</title>
<publication-date>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Parker</lname>
<fname>Rhonda</fname>
<mname>Gale</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Rehabilitation and Therapy</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Objective:  The purpose of this study was to examine the use of both developmental and non-developmental phonological processes in a group of young children using cochlear implants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants: 6 preschool children with severe to profound binaural hearing loss with cochlear implants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Method:  15-25 minute conversational speech samples from six children were collected at three-month intervals over a period of 12-21 months for a prior study.  These samples were then transcribed and analyzed using Natural Phonological Analysis (NPA) and a data collection form created solely for the purpose of this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Analysis:  Pearson correlations were used to determine relationships among the variables.  Z-scores were also used to make comparisons with the available normative data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results:  Possible explanations for the use of developmental as well as non-developmental processes in this population are discussed.  These results have implications for the assessment and clinical treatment of phonological errors in the speech of children with cochlear implants.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/4536</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6066&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4536</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6066</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-04-21T11:24:58-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>10058622</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/4536</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Peter Flipsen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Ilsa Schwartz, Lori Swanson</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Speech Pathology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2005-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>