<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Moderating effect of intimate exchange on the reciprocal relation between best friend delinquency and child externalizing behavior</title>
<publication-date>2008-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Gaertner</lname>
<fname>Alden</fname>
<mname>Elizabeth</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Psychology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Research indicates both peer selection (choosing behaviorally similar individuals as friends) and peer socialization (mutual regulation of behavior) processes impact the development of problem behavior in childhood and adolescence. Differential association theory explains these processes by suggesting children and adolescents elect to participate in peer groups that conform to a commonly accepted set of group norms. Moreover, deviant peer groups ascribe to unconventional norms characterized by a higher proportion of pro-deviance messages learned in the context of intimate personal groups. Consistent with differential association theory, the current study examined the moderating effect of intimate exchange, or relational closeness, on the reciprocal relation between externalizing behavior (aggressive and rule breaking behavior) and best friend delinquency (rule breaking behavior). Participants included 65 children (67% male), ranging from 10-13 years of age at baseline (M = 11.95 years, SD = 1.30), and their primary caregivers. Contrary to hypotheses, peer delinquency did not predict increases in child externalizing behavior over time and intimate exchange did not moderate this effect. Moreover, intimate exchange moderated the relation between child externalizing behavior and best friend delinquency, but not in the expected direction. At high levels of intimate exchange, best friend delinquency predicted decreases in child externalizing behavior whereas at low levels of intimate exchange, best friend delinquency predicted increases in child externalizing behavior. Implications and future directions of these findings are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/5749</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7371&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5749</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7371</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-04-13T13:18:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>22467512</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/5749</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Paula J. Fite</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>