<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Design and Implementation of a Low‐Power Wireless Respiration Monitoring Sensor</title>
<publication-date>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>imahbub@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>Univeristy of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Mahbub</lname>
<fname>Ifana</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Pyroelectric transducer</keyword>
<keyword>front-end amplifier</keyword>
<keyword>IR-UWB transmitter</keyword>
<keyword>low-power</keyword>
<keyword>CMOS</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Biomedical</discipline>
<discipline>Electrical and Electronics</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Wireless devices for monitoring of respiration activities can play a major role in advancing modern home-based health care applications. Existing methods for respiration monitoring require special algorithms and high precision filters to eliminate noise and other motion artifacts. These necessitate additional power consuming circuitry for further signal conditioning. This dissertation is particularly focused on a novel approach of respiration monitoring based on a PVDF-based pyroelectric transducer. Low-power, low-noise, and fully integrated charge amplifiers are designed to serve as the front-end amplifier of the sensor to efficiently convert the charge generated by the transducer into a proportional voltage signal. To transmit the respiration data wirelessly, a lowpower transmitter design is crucial. This energy constraint motivates the exploration of the design of a duty-cycled transmitter, where the radio is designed to be turned off most of the time and turned on only for a short duration of time. Due to its inherent duty-cycled nature, impulse radio ultra-wideband (IR-UWB) transmitter is an ideal candidate for the implementation of a duty-cycled radio. To achieve better energy efficiency and longer battery lifetime a low-power low-complexity OOK (on-off keying) based impulse radio ultra-wideband (IR-UWB) transmitter is designed and implemented using standard CMOS process. Initial simulation and test results exhibit a promising advancement towards the development of an energy-efficient wireless sensor for monitoring of respiration activities.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/4639</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6115&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>4639</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>6115</articleid>
<submission-date>2017-06-09T14:21:42-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>10276593</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/4639</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Syed K. Islam</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Nicole McFarlane, Aly Fathy, Mohamed R. Mahfouz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Electrical Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2017-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>