<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Yield, Cost, and Acceptability of Beef Sirloin Roasted by Forced Convection at Two Oven Temperatures</title>
<publication-date>1968-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Davenport</lname>
<fname>Marilyn</fname>
<mname>McCammon</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Food Science</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;em&gt;From the Introduction&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The relationship of numerous factors to yield and palatability of meat has been under investigation for many years. Since meat is the most costly menu item for institutional food, establishments, factors which affect yield, cost, and palatability are of primary concern to food service managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the development of forced convection ovens a relatively new approach to meat cookery was introduced to the food service industry. Borsenik and Newcomer (1959) pioneered in the development of forced convection cookery by installing a blower in a conventional oven. They found that cooking time was reduced and fuel consumption was decreased with forced convectiion. In 1961, Scheman and Ball reported that time for roasting meat was decreased and yield was increased by the use of an oven designed to be operated with increased pressure and forced air circulation. In a recent investigation Funk et al. (1966) also reported that forced convection shortened cooking time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally beef is roasted at approximately 300° F. for both home and institutional uses. However, some evidence has been acquired that lower oven temperatures have a tendering effect on meat without impairment of other sensory properties. Cover (1943) was one of the first to report that slow rates of heat penetration had a tendering effect on beef. Further evidence that lower oven temperatures, under some conditions, produced more tender meat was reported by Griswold (1955), Bramblett et al. (1959), Bramblett and Vail (1964), Simmers (1965), Nielsen and Hall (1965), and Fugate (1967).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since forced convection shortens the cooking time due to faster heat penetration whereas slow heat penetration seems to favor the tendering of meat, the question can be raised of whether lower oven temperature would be advantageous when roasting by forced convection. The purpose of this study was to compare acceptability, cooking losses, cooking time, shear values, yield of usable meat, and raw food cost per serving for pairs of beef sirloin butts roasted at 200 and 300° F. in gas forced convection ovens. Eight pairs of roasts were tested. Data were analyzed by a t-test to determine significance of differences associated with oven temperature.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3920</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=5405&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3920</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>5405</articleid>
<submission-date>2016-08-31T08:44:47-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>9056066</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3920</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bernadine Meyer</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Jane R. Savage, Grayce E. Goertz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Food Science and Technology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>1968-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1968-03-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>