<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Moderating Effect of Negative Peer Group Climate on the Relation Between Men’s Locus of Control and Aggression Towards Intimate Partners</title>
<publication-date>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>mschmi13@vols.utk.edu</email>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Schmidt</lname>
<fname>Megan</fname>
<mname>Ryan</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Intimate Partner Aggression</keyword>
<keyword>External Locus of Control</keyword>
<keyword>Negative Peer Group Climate</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Clinical Psychology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The present study sought to examine the interactive effects of an external locus of control and interaction in a negative peer group climate on men’s perpetration of physical aggression and infliction of injury towards their female intimate partners. Participants were 206 heterosexual males recruited from the metro-Atlanta community who completed self-report measures of external locus of control, involvement in a negative peer group climate, and physical aggression and infliction of injury against intimate partners during the past 12 months. Negative peer group climate was conceptualized as a peer group that displays behavior which may instigate aggressive norms, attitudes, and behaviors. Results indicated that men with an external locus of control were more likely to perpetrate physical aggression toward and inflict injury on their intimate partners if they reported high, but not low, involvement in a negative peer group climate. These results extend current research suggesting external locus of control as a risk factor for intimate partner aggression by highlighting the impact of negative peer groups. Implications and future intervention research are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/3405</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4727&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>3405</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>4727</articleid>
<submission-date>2015-03-31T14:24:41-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/utk_gradthes/article/4727/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>6926494</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/3405</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Todd M. Moore</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Deborah P. Welsh, Gregory L. Stuart</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;This work was previously published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Interpersonal Violence&lt;/em&gt;. [Schmidt, M. R., Lisco, C. G., Parrott, D. J., &amp; Tharp, A. T. (2016). Moderating effect of negative peer group climate on the relation between men’s locus of control and aggression toward intimate partners. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 31&lt;/em&gt;(5), 755-773. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/&lt;/a&gt;0886260514556761.] © 2014 The Authors. Reprinted by permission of Sage Publications.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Arts</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Psychology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2017-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="instruct" type="string">
<value>1</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2015-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>