<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Experiences and Ethical Issues Across the Spectrum of Veterinary Social Work Services at Michigan State University</title>
<publication-date>2013-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>lawren45@msu.edu</email>
<institution>Michigan State University</institution>
<lname>Lawrence</lname>
<fname>Linda</fname>
<mname>L</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Social and Behavioral Sciences</discipline>
<discipline>Social Work</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The six years of experience at the Michigan State University Veterinary Social Work Services (VSWS) has presented a wide variety of ethical issues. Issues are now addressed in the Policies and Procedures manual for the VSWS. The ethical issues discussed here do not only refer to the education of the MSW Interns. These issues are related to the entire staff of the hospital, medical and support staff. Also included are suggestions for client care, boundary setting to lower the chances of liability and inappropriate relationships. Again, this is not just for the students; this is for the hospital staff as well. Another action in which the VSWS has become involved is with the Mortality and Morbidity debriefing sessions that are held and include all members of the medical team, supervisors, administration, and support and care staff. These are chaired by the Hospital Director and the VSWS is considered an equal member.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>http://trace.tennessee.edu/utvswsummit/Third/april12/4</coverpage-url>
<label>4</label>
<document-type>event</document-type>
<type>event</type>
<articleid>1076</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-01-25T06:45:51-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>International Veterinary Social Work Summit</publication-title>
<context-key>3615741</context-key>
<submission-path>utvswsummit/Third/april12/4</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="abstract_identification" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linda L Lawrence, MSW, LMSW,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate Academic Advisor – School of Social Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice Sequence Clinical Instructor – School of Social Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordinator Veterinary Social Work Services (VSWS)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michigan State University Veterinary Teaching Hospital&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clinical social work services for clients of the VTH and the staff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facilitate Support Groups for the Loss of a Companion Animal, These groups are open to the “public.” In addition groups for the staff of the VTH due to the compassion fatigue experienced, and the lack of appreciation shown for work well done, therefore seeking ways to improve the work environment.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="contact_info" type="string">
<value>&lt;p&gt;Linda L Lawrence, 2201 Quentin Avenue, Lansing, MI 48910&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;phone 517-881-0930&lt;/p&gt;</value>
</field>
<field name="end_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T13:30:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="location" type="string">
<value>CARRIAGE/CRYSTAL ROOM</value>
</field>
<field name="multimedia_format" type="string">
<value>flash_audio</value>
</field>
<field name="presentation_format" type="string">
<value>Table Topic: Facilitated conversation at meal time</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="start_date" type="date">
<value>2013-04-12T12:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="track_select" type="string">
<value>Ethical dilemmas in social work and animals</value>
</field>
<field name="will_other_format" type="string">
<value>no</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>