<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Size Selective Parasitism of Rainbow Trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) by Chestnut Lampreys (Ichthyomyzon castaneus) in an Artificial Setting</title>
<publication-date>2020-05-21T12:19:08-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<email>salingj4692@uapb.edu</email>
<institution>University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff</institution>
<lname>Salinger</lname>
<fname>Jeremiah</fname>
<mname>M.</mname>
</author>
<author>
<email>rlj@astate.edu</email>
<institution>Arkansas State University</institution>
<lname>Johnson</lname>
<fname>Ronald</fname>
<mname>L.</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>Chestnut Lamprey</keyword>
<keyword>parasitism</keyword>
<keyword>optimal resource utilization</keyword>
<keyword>relative weight</keyword>
<keyword>Rainbow Trout</keyword>
</keywords>
<disciplines><discipline>Aquaculture and Fisheries</discipline>
<discipline>Behavior and Ethology</discipline>
<discipline>Parasitology</discipline>
<discipline>Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Paradigms of optimal resource utilization by animals, both classical and more recent, were not originally developed in the context of parasitism. Though this oversight has slowly been reversed, little attention has been paid to optimal resource utilization by parasitic fishes, such as lampreys. Multiple explanations for host size selection by parasitic lampreys may be plausible, but results from previous studies have been inconsistent. We studied host size selection by Chestnut Lampreys (&lt;em&gt;Ichthyomyzon castaneus&lt;/em&gt;) parasitizing Rainbow Trout (&lt;em&gt;Oncorhynchus mykiss&lt;/em&gt;) in fish hatchery raceways in north central Arkansas during the late winter and early spring of 2013. Parasitized Rainbow Trout were significantly shorter than non-parasitized conspecifics. Using the relative weight metric of condition, evidence was found that parasitized Rainbow Trout were in better condition than non-parasitized Rainbow Trout. Our findings are not consistent with previous studies of parasitic lamprey host size selection, but do suggest that Chestnut Lampreys are capable of determining a fish’s suitability as a host based on their plumpness even in a setting with low host size heterogeneity and high host density.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/6</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1299&amp;amp;context=sfcproceedings&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6</label>
<document-type>research</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1299</articleid>
<submission-date>2019-05-02T07:28:27-07:00</submission-date>
<native-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/context/sfcproceedings/article/1299/type/native/viewcontent</native-url>
<publication-title>Southeastern Fishes Council Proceedings</publication-title>
<context-key>14413409</context-key>
<submission-path>sfcproceedings/vol1/iss59/6</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="acknowledgements" type="string">
<value>We would like to thank the staff of the United States Fish &amp; Wildlife Service’s Norfork National Fish Hatchery for permission to conduct this study in their facility with their fish. Further gratitude is extended to M. Jirka of the Friends of the Norfork National Fish Hatchery for his insights regarding historical mechanisms of lamprey access to the hatchery. Discussions with the late P. Cochran regarding parasitic lamprey feeding biology were indispensable. Field and laboratory assistance was provided by C. Allison, T. Mackey, J. Moore, L. Renoux, J. Royal, S. Shourd, D. Trotter, J. Wagner, and B. Williams. D. Gilmore and S. Trauth provided access to laboratory equipment necessary for specimen processing. This research was funded by a Conservation Grant from the North Arkansas Fly Fishers to the lead author.</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2019-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="letters_to_reviewers" type="special">
<value>ARRAY(0xe9e4820)</value>
</field>
<field name="peer_reviewed" type="boolean">
<value>true</value>
</field>
<field name="short_title" type="string">
<value>Size Selective Parasitism Chestnut Lampreys</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>