<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Grade A milk producers in Henry County, Tennessee : problem A: Characteristics of Henry County Grade A milk producers and their farms : problem B: Management practices of Henry County Grade A milk producers : problem C: Factors influencing dairy management practice adoption by Henry County Grade A milk producers : three related special problems in lieu of thesis /</title>
<publication-date>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Shearon</lname>
<fname>George</fname>
<mname>Curtis</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Statewide, dairying usually ranks about fourth in importance as a source of agricultural income in Tennessee (19:1).* Annual receipts averaged about 85 million dollars for the five-year period 1959-1963. There were about 476,000 dairy cows in Tennessee in 1963. Average milk production per Tennessee cow that year was 4,700 pounds, while the average American cow produced 7,545 pounds. Research has suggested that production per cow of less than 6,000 pounds is unprofitable, and that cows producing below that amount ought to be culled and replaced. Henry County is located in the northwest corner of the Western Division of Tennessee. It is bordered by the state of Kentucky to the north and the Tennessee River to the east. The agriculture of the county is rather diversified, a little more than one-half of the agricultural income coming from the sale of livestock and livestock products and a little under-one-half coming from the sale of crops. Dairying ranks second in importance and is exceeded only in dollar value by the sale of cattle and calves (5:217).&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/6057</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7696&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6057</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7696</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-07-29T06:24:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>24074436</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/6057</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Robert S. Dotson</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Lewis H. Dickson, Don O. Richardson, William M. Miller</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Agricultural Extension</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>1965-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>