<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>The Effects of a Constructivist Intervention On Pre-Service Teachers’ Confidence and Perceptions of the Experience</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>DiPietro</lname>
<fname>Kathryn</fname>
<mname>Ann</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Education</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was, first, to determine the effect of a constructivist intervention supported by technology on pre-service teachers’ confidence in their own ability to plan and create six constructivist learning activities supported by technology and, second, to understand their perceptions of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants were 23 pre-service teachers accepted into the College of Education’s Masters program at the University of Tennessee Knoxville and enrolled in an introduction to instructional computing course during the summer of 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey was used to assess pre-intervention confidence levels and experience with six constructivist learning activities supported by technology. Students were then situated in a class that employed constructivist methodology supported by technology to facilitate their own exploration of constructivist pedagogy supported by technology. Once students completed the class, they were asked to re-take the portion of the survey that focused on their confidence to plan and create constructivist learning activities supported by technology. A paired samples t-tested was used to compared pre-intervention confidence levels with post-intervention confidence levels. The results revealed a significant difference, p &lt; .001, in each of the six areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journals, focus groups, and interviews were used to gain insight into the participants’ perceptions of the experience and suggested a reflective process. Participants engaged in thinking about, comparing, and adapting their constructs of teaching, learning, and the use of technology. They were self-motivated to analyze how their constructs of teaching and learning might work in future classes, the processes they used while situated in a constructivist learning environment, the instructor’s role in their learning, their collaborative/collegial relationships with peers, how specific materials supported learning, and their technology skills.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/2118</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3561&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2118</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3561</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-01T11:12:02-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>4652874</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/2118</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Dr. Edward L. Counts, Jr.</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Dr. Mary Jane Connelly, Dr. Ronald E. Taylor, Dr. Norma T. Mertz</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Education</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>