<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Characterization of an Estrogen-degrading Culture, &lt;em&gt;Novosphingobium tardaugens&lt;/em&gt; ARI-1</title>
<publication-date>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<lname>Yang</lname>
<fname>Yuechauan</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Engineering</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;In this study, experiments were conducted to characterize the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Novosphingobium spp&lt;/em&gt; ARI-1, which is the only known estradiol-degrading strain. The kinetic parameters, the effects of acetone on cell growth, and the effects of starvation on estrogen degradation have been measured. A quantitative fingerprinting molecular technique, called real-time-t-RFLP, was used to characterize microbial communities of activated sludge samples collected from six wastewater treatment plants in east Tennessee. The experimental data showed that ARI-1 was capable of growing on estrogens in the presence and absence of acetone. In the absence of acetone, ARI-1 grew on 17α-estradiol, 17β-estradiol, and estrone with cell yields Y=0.05-0.13 (mg VSS/mg estrogen). The half-velocity constant (K&lt;sub&gt;m&lt;/sub&gt;) was 7.8±2.3mg/L for 17β-estradiol and 5.1±1.5mg/L for estrone. The maximum specific substrate utilization rate ( qˆ , mg estrogen/mg VSS-day) was 14.0±4.5d&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; for 17β-estradiol and 14.0±4.4d&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; for estrone. Degradation rates decreased when ARI-1 was deprived of estrogen for 1, 3, and 7 days. After growing in LB (nutrient-rich) medium without exposure to 17β-estradiol for 7 days, ARI-1 degraded 17β-estradiol at a much slower rate and failed to degrade estrone for more than 10 days. The results of microbial community analysis of activated samples suggested but not confirmed the presence of ARI-1. The results of this study, including the kinetic parameters of estrogen degradation by ARI-1, starvation effects, and prevalence of ARI-1 in various activated sludge system, are valuable for engineers to design a biological treatment system for enhanced estrogen removal.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_gradthes/2222</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3600&amp;amp;context=utk_gradthes&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>2222</label>
<document-type>thesis</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>3600</articleid>
<submission-date>2013-10-10T10:09:04-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Masters Theses</publication-title>
<context-key>4692490</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_gradthes/2222</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Kung-Hui Chu</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Chris D. Cox, Paul D. Frymier</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Master of Science</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Environmental Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2004-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>