<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Forest Responses to Rising Atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;: Causes and Consequences of Increased Fine-Root Production in a CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-Enriched Sweetgum Plantation</title>
<publication-date>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee - Knoxville</institution>
<lname>Iversen</lname>
<fname>Colleen</fname>
<mname>Marie</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<disciplines><discipline>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</discipline>
</disciplines><abstract>&lt;p&gt;Increased forest growth in response to rising atmospheric concentrations of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; may mitigate a portion of fossil fuel emissions, especially if carbon is sequestered in longlived biomass or soil pools. Greater carbon uptake under elevated atmospheric [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] in forested ecosystems may facilitate the production of small diameter (i.e. “fine”) roots used for nutrient acquisition. Increased fine-root production in forested ecosystems may affect soil carbon storage and nitrogen cycling because fine roots live and die in the span of a year. My dissertation research took advantage of a long-term, on-going Free-Air CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-Enrichment experiment in a sweetgum (&lt;em&gt;Liquidambar styraciflua&lt;/em&gt; L.) forest stand at Oak Ridge National Laboratory to investigate the &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;consequences&lt;/em&gt; of increased fine-root production under elevated [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]. To examine the premise that N limitation was the cause of increased fine-root production in the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-enriched sweetgum stand, I fertilized plots in an adjacent sweetgum plantation with 200 kg ha&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; of N as urea. The relative C flux to wood production that I observed in the fertilized treatment is consistent with the premise that increased root production in the adjacent FACE experiment is in response to N limitation. To examine the &lt;em&gt;consequences&lt;/em&gt;of increased fine-root production under elevated [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;], I: (1) quantified fine-root biomass and N inputs at several soil depths using a long-term minirhizotron data set combined with continuous, root-specific measurements of root mass per unit length and [N], and (2) allowed fine roots grown under current and elevated [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;] to decompose in a common garden experiment by modifying existing litterbag methodology. I found that C and N inputs via root mortality were doubled under elevated [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;], and half of the inputs were below 30 cm soil depth. However, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-enrichment had no effect on fine-root chemistry or decomposition rate, and therefore more root detritus may be incorporated into long-lived soil organic matter under elevated [CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]. Quantification of the effects of elevated CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; on the fate of a greater quantity of fine-root detritus, especially at depth in the soil, will provide critical information needed for predicting processes such as long-term soil C storage and N cycling in response to environmental change.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/456</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1517&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>456</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>1517</articleid>
<submission-date>2010-02-18T11:46:10-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>1154029</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/456</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Richard J. Norby, Aimée T. Classen</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>James A. Fordyce, Louis J. Gross, Jennifer A. Schweitzer</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Ecology and Evolutionary Biology</value>
</field>
<field name="embargo_date" type="date">
<value>2011-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2008-08-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
<field name="source_fulltext_url" type="string">
<value>http://etd.utk.edu/2008/August2008Dissertations/IversenColleen.pdf</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>