<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>Workers&#39; compensation injuries/illnesses : an analysis of selected Knox County government employee claims</title>
<publication-date>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Hamilton</lname>
<fname>Theda</fname>
<mname>Carol</mname>
</author>
</authors>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this study was to identity major Worker Compensation problem areas and through this analysis, develop an action plan to affectively reduce the causes of these occupational injury and illness claims through specific training. The examination of previous injuries/illness data serve as an effective way to provide information about risk factors and are the first steps in construct future programs to reduce accident and illnesses and their related costs. The analysis of these Knox County Worker Compensation accident reports assist in identifying unsafe conditions, needed employee training, successful interventions programs and in guiding the allocation of resources. Research studies analyzing previous injuries and illnesses have helped target the significant risk factors and generate measure to control specific risks. The study design was a retrospective study of those Knox County employees that reported a Worker Compensation injury or illness during the period of 1995 through 2000. This was a Risk Management assessment of Workers&#39; Compensation claims for Knox County Government population compared across department, age, gender and length of service for the period of 1995 through 2000. An action plan was developed to reduce Worker Compensation claims in Knox County Government. The Sheriff department reported 732 claims (42.8 percent) and Engineering was the second highest with 362 claims (21.2 per cent). These two departments studied had significantly higher incidence rates and costs associated with injury/illness events than the other five departments. The age group 22 to 31 had the most reported claims with 600 injury/illness cases (35.1 per cent) and the group that had the second highest injury/illness rate was the age interval 32 - 41 (29. 7 per cent) with 508 claims. The average work population was 2500 per year and had more females in clerical positions. The reported rate of injury for the female group was 461 claims (27 per cent) and the males group was 1248 claims (73 per cent). The Sheriff department injury/illness group accounted for 173 female cases (37.5 per cent) and 559 male cases (44.8 per cent). The length of employment up to three years was an important period as 493 males (39.5 per cent) and 185 females (40.1 per cent) reported injury and illness claims. The unanticipated discovery of excessive hand and arm injury in all departments identify the need for ergonomic engineering of the work areas as well as safety training on upper muscle skeletal disorder and their prevention. The finding that employees working less than three years and between the ages of 22 to 31 have the most injury and illness stresses the need for intensified safety training following OSHA guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/6238</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=8190&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>6238</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>8190</articleid>
<submission-date>2021-06-21T05:06:03-07:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>23450333</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/6238</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Bill C. Wallace</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Human Ecology</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2002-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>