<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' ?>
<documents><document>
<title>High-throughput multifunctional materials characterization with real-time analytics and feedback</title>
<publication-date>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</publication-date>
<state>published</state>
<authors>
<author>
<institution>University of Tennessee</institution>
<lname>Muckley</lname>
<fname>Eric</fname>
</author>
</authors>
<keywords>
<keyword>QCM</keyword>
<keyword>humidity</keyword>
<keyword>materials</keyword>
<keyword>adsorption</keyword>
<keyword>sensing</keyword>
<keyword>analytics</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>&lt;p&gt;Novel functional materials are enabling transformational breakthroughs in energy, electronics, manufacturing and medicine. Development of new materials is being fueled by advances in high-performance computing, robotics, and high-throughput methods for materials synthesis and processing. To close the feedback loop between materials design, synthesis and functionality, novel materials must be rapidly screened for stability and functionality under a broad range of ambient environment conditions. We developed an automated system for simultaneous probing of electrical, optical, gravimetric, and viscoelastic properties of materials under controlled environments, enabling characterization of material response to temperature, pressure, humidity, light intensity, and ambient gas/vapor composition. Control of environmental conditions, experimental procedures, and data acquisition is achieved using custom integrated software which performs on-the-fly data processing, analytics and modeling. Results from real-time analysis are used as feedback for iterative optimization of experiment settings, which allows automated initiation and termination of experimental procedures and reduces the need for input from human researchers. Integration of analytics in the experimental control software enables high-throughput sample processing and rapid interpretability of experimental results. The system has been used to characterize environmental response and sensing performance of a broad range of materials including polymers, metal oxides, organic small molecules, biomolecules, perovskites, nanotubes and two-dimensional materials.Here, we describe details of the multifunctional characterization system, show examples of functional materials characterized by the system, and describe potential future improvements to the system. Future opportunities for development include (i) integration of combinatorial synthesis methods to close the feedback loop between synthesis and characterization, (ii) integration of computational modeling for real-time feedback between experiment and simulation, (iii) database integration for creation of a materials expert system, and (iv) in situ diagnostics on X-ray and/or neutron beamlines for probing structure-function relationships under dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</abstract>
<coverpage-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/utk_graddiss/5782</coverpage-url>
<fulltext-url>https://trace.tennessee.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=7548&amp;amp;context=utk_graddiss&amp;amp;unstamped=1</fulltext-url>
<label>5782</label>
<document-type>dissertation</document-type>
<type>article</type>
<articleid>7548</articleid>
<submission-date>2020-12-04T22:54:05-08:00</submission-date>
<publication-title>Doctoral Dissertations</publication-title>
<context-key>20419683</context-key>
<submission-path>utk_graddiss/5782</submission-path>
<fields>
<field name="advisor1" type="string">
<value>Ilia Ivanov</value>
</field>
<field name="advisor2" type="string">
<value>Phil Rack, Wim Bras, Bin Hu, Bobby Sumpter, Natalie Stingelin</value>
</field>
<field name="author1_orcid" type="string">
<value>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7114-5424</value>
</field>
<field name="comments" type="string">
<value>Portions of this document were previously published in ACS Nano, ACS Applied Materials and Interfaces, RSC Nanoscale, Nature Scientific Reports, SPIE Journal of Photonics for Energy, and Elsevier Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical.</value>
</field>
<field name="degree_name" type="string">
<value>Doctor of Philosophy</value>
</field>
<field name="department" type="string">
<value>Energy Science and Engineering</value>
</field>
<field name="publication_date" type="date">
<value>2019-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</value>
</field>
</fields>
</document>
</documents>